<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Environ Health Perspect</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Environ. Health Perspect</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Environmental Health Perspectives</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0091-6765</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1552-9924</issn><publisher><publisher-name>National Institue of Environmental Health Sciences</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15598610</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1247656</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1289/txg.7345</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ehp0112-001589</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Toxicogenomics</subject><subj-group><subject>Articles</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Phenotypic Anchoring of Gene Expression Changes during Estrogen-Induced Uterine Growth</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Moggs</surname><given-names>Jonathan G.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ehp0112-001589"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tinwell</surname><given-names>Helen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ehp0112-001589"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Spurway</surname><given-names>Tracey</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ehp0112-001589"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Hur-Song</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-ehp0112-001589"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref rid="fn2-ehp0112-001589"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pate</surname><given-names>Ian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ehp0112-001589"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>Fei Ling</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ehp0112-001589"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>David J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ehp0112-001589"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Soames</surname><given-names>Anthony</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ehp0112-001589"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Stuckey</surname><given-names>Ruth</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ehp0112-001589"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Currie</surname><given-names>Richard</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ehp0112-001589"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Tong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-ehp0112-001589"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kimber</surname><given-names>Ian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ehp0112-001589"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ashby</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ehp0112-001589"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Orphanides</surname><given-names>George</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ehp0112-001589"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af1-ehp0112-001589"><sup>1</sup>Syngenta Central Toxicology Laboratory, Alderley Park, Cheshire, United Kingdom</aff><aff id="af2-ehp0112-001589"><sup>2</sup>Syngenta Biotechnology Inc., Research Triangle Park, North Carolina, USA</aff><author-notes><corresp id="fn1-ehp0112-001589">Address correspondence to G. Orphanides, Syngenta CTL, Alderley Park, Cheshire, SK10 4TJ, UK. Telephone: 44-1625-510803. Fax: 44-1625-585715. E-mail:
george.orphanides@syngenta.com</corresp><fn id="fn2-ehp0112-001589" fn-type="present-address"><p>*Present address: Diversa Corporation, 4955 Directors Place, San Diego, CA 92121 USA.</p></fn><fn><p>Supplemental data is available online (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ehp.niehs.nih.gov/txg/members/2004/7345/supplemental.pdf">http://ehp.niehs.nih.gov/txg/members/2004/7345/supplemental.pdf</ext-link>)</p></fn><fn><p>We thank M.G. Parker, D.G. Deavall, N. Wallis, and T. Barlow for critical comments on the manuscript; P. Lefevre and J. Odum for technical assistance; and I. Kupershmidt and E. Hunter (Silicon Genetics) for advice on statistical analysis of microarray data.</p></fn><fn><p>This work was partially supported by the UK Food Standards Agency.</p></fn><fn><p>The authors declare they have no competing financial interests.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>11</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>7</day><month>10</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><volume>112</volume><issue>16</issue><fpage>1589</fpage><lpage>1606</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>6</month><year>2004</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>7</day><month>10</month><year>2004</year></date></history><permissions><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/" license-type="public-domain"><license-p>Publication of EHP lies in the public domain and is therefore without copyright. All text from EHP may be reprinted freely. Use of materials published in EHP should be acknowledged (for example, ?Reproduced with permission from Environmental Health Perspectives?); pertinent reference information should be provided for the article from which the material was reproduced. Articles from EHP, especially the News section, may contain photographs or illustrations copyrighted by other commercial organizations or individuals that may not be used without obtaining prior approval from the holder of the copyright. </license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>A major challenge in the emerging field of toxicogenomics is to define the relationships between chemically induced changes in gene expression and alterations in conventional toxicologic parameters such as clinical chemistry and histopathology. We have explored these relationships in detail using the rodent uterotrophic assay as a model system. Gene expression levels, uterine weights, and histologic parameters were analyzed 1, 2, 4, 8, 24, 48, and 72 hr after exposure to the reference physiologic estrogen 17&#x003b2;-estradiol (E<sub>2</sub>). A multistep analysis method, involving unsupervised hierarchical clustering followed by supervised gene ontology&#x02013;driven clustering, was used to define the transcriptional program associated with E<sub>2</sub>-induced uterine growth and to identify groups of genes that may drive specific histologic changes in the uterus. This revealed that uterine growth and maturation are preceded and accompanied by a complex, multistage molecular program. The program begins with the induction of genes involved in transcriptional regulation and signal transduction and is followed, sequentially, by the regulation of genes involved in protein biosynthesis, cell proliferation, and epithelial cell differentiation. Furthermore, we have identified genes with common molecular functions that may drive fluid uptake, coordinated cell division, and remodeling of luminal epithelial cells. These data define the mechanism by which an estrogen induces organ growth and tissue maturation, and demonstrate that comparison of temporal changes in gene expression and conventional toxicology end points can facilitate the phenotypic anchoring of toxicogenomic data.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>estrogen</kwd><kwd>gene expression</kwd><kwd>microarray</kwd><kwd>phenotypic anchoring</kwd><kwd>uterus</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Gene expression profiling, used within the existing framework of toxicologic assessment, promises to advance significantly the mechanistic understanding and prediction of adverse effects. To benefit fully from the opportunities offered by gene expression profiling, we must first understand the relationships between changes in gene expression and alterations in traditional toxicology parameters. The process by which gene expression changes are linked to changes in phenotype has been termed &#x0201c;phenotypic anchoring&#x0201d; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8-ehp0112-001589">Cunningham et al. 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b42-ehp0112-001589">Paules 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b47-ehp0112-001589">Schmidt 2003</xref>). This approach has been used successfully to identify groups of genes whose expression correlates with specific pathologic changes during griseofulvin-induced chronic liver injury (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11-ehp0112-001589">Gant et al. 2003</xref>), renal toxicity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2-ehp0112-001589">Amin et al. 2004</xref>), furan-mediated hepatotoxicity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14-ehp0112-001589">Hamadeh et al. 2004</xref>), and aceta-minophen-induced hepatotoxicity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16-ehp0112-001589">Heinloth et al. 2004</xref>). In the present study we used phenotypic anchoring, in conjunction with gene ontology analysis, to define the transcriptional program associated with the response of the rodent uterus to a reference estrogen and to identify groups of genes that may drive specific histologic changes.</p><p>The immature mouse uterus is a major estrogen-responsive organ and forms the basis for a reference assay of estrogenic activity of chemicals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b39-ehp0112-001589">Owens and Ashby 2002</xref>). The physiologic response of the uterus to exogenous estrogens has been documented in detail (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6-ehp0112-001589">Clark and Mani 1994</xref>). The immature mouse uterus is sensitive to elevations in endogenous levels of 17&#x003b2; -estradiol (E<sub>2</sub>) that occur during puberty. E<sub>2</sub> releases the immature uterus from quiescence and promotes cell proliferation and differentiation. The initial effects of E<sub>2</sub> are rapid (4&#x02013;6 hr) and involve the uptake of fluid resulting from hyperemia and vasodilation of uterine capillaries, which causes the uterus to swell. This phenomenon is termed &#x0201c;water imbibition&#x0201d; and increases the availability of substrates and ions required for growth. Another early event is an increase in overall levels of mRNA and protein synthesis. The uterus then enters a proliferative phase that is responsible, at least in part, for the large increase in uterine weight that occurs 16&#x02013;30 hr after E<sub>2</sub> exposure. Later responses mimic the changes in uterine physiology that accompany the onset of puberty and include alterations in the surface of the luminal epithelia.</p><p>Although the events described above have been characterized at the physiologic level, little is known about how E<sub>2</sub>, acting through the estrogen receptors ER-&#x003b1;and ER-&#x003b2;, coordinates at the molecular level the myriad cellular processes involved, despite significant progress in elucidating the molecular mechanisms by which ERs regulate gene expression <italic>in vitro</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13-ehp0112-001589">Hall et al. 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27-ehp0112-001589">McKenna and O&#x02019;Malley 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28-ehp0112-001589">Metivier et al. 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31-ehp0112-001589">Moggs and Orphanides 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30-ehp0112-001589">Moggs et al. 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b54-ehp0112-001589">Tremblay and Giguere 2002</xref>). Our data reveal the transcriptional program associated with E<sub>2</sub>-induced uterine growth. We show that E<sub>2</sub> induces a tightly coordinated transcriptional program that regulates successive and interlinked cellular processes during the uterotrophic response. Moreover, by comparing changes in gene expression with alterations in uterine weight and histology, we have identified classes of genes that may drive specific histologic changes in the uterus, including fluid uptake, coordinated cell division, and remodeling of the luminal epithelial cell layer in preparation for embryo implantation. Our data also provide novel insights into how E<sub>2</sub> initiates paracrine signaling events, recruits immune and inflammatory cells, increases mRNA and protein synthesis, and suppresses apoptosis.</p><p>These data describe, at an unprecedented level of detail, how E<sub>2</sub> induces organ growth and maturation and provide a paradigm for understanding the mechanisms of action of other nuclear receptors. Furthermore, this study demonstrates that analysis of the temporal associations between a chemically induced transcriptional program and the accompanying histologic changes can provide valuable insight into the relationships between gene expression changes and phenotypic alterations.</p><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Animals</title><p>Female Alpk:Ap<sub>f</sub>CD-1 mice (19&#x02013;20 days old), weighing no more than 14 g on arrival in the laboratory, were obtained from a barriered animal breeding unit (AstraZeneca, Macclesfield, Cheshire, UK). The animals were housed five per cage in solid-bottom cages and allowed to acclimatize for 24 hr. They were allowed RM1 diet (Rat and Mouse No. 1; Special Diet Services Ltd., Witham, Essex, UK) and water ad libitum for the duration of the study. All animal experimentation described in this article was conducted in accord with accepted standards (local and national regulations) of humane animal care. Group sizes of 10 animals were used for the first two of the three replicate studies. Five animals per group were used in the third replicate study.</p></sec><sec><title>Uterotrophic Assays</title><p>The mice were given a single subcutaneous injection of E<sub>2</sub> (400 &#x003bc;g/kg) or arachis oil (AO; vehicle control) using a dosing volume of 5 mL/kg body weight. A single dose of E<sub>2</sub> was used to avoid the complex transcriptional program that may result from the standard uterotrophic assay exposure regime (i.e., repeated administration on 3 consecutive days; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b35-ehp0112-001589">Odum et al. 1997</xref>). The relatively high dose level of 400 &#x003bc;g/kg was chosen to ensure a sustained and significant increase in blotted uterine weight during the 72-hr sampling period (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplemental Data, Figure 1</xref>). No overt toxicity was observed during the 72-hr exposure to E<sub>2</sub> (400 &#x003bc;g/kg). All animals were terminated at the appropriate time using an overdose of halothane (Concord Pharmaceuticals Ltd., Essex, UK) followed by cervical dislocation. Vaginal opening was recorded, and the uterus was then removed, trimmed free of fat, gently blotted, and weighed. Blotted uterine weights were analyzed by covariance with terminal body weights (SAS <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b46-ehp0112-001589">Institute Inc. 1999</xref>). Half of each left uterine horn was fixed in 10% formol saline and processed to paraffin wax for histologic analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b35-ehp0112-001589">Odum et al. 1997</xref>). The mean thickness of the endometrial and epithelial cell layers, indicators of cellular hypertrophy, were calculated based on the assessment of 10 locations on hemotoxylin- and eosin-stained longitudinal uterine sections for each animal. All hypertrophy data were assessed for statistical significance by analysis of variance (ANOVA). The remainder of the uterus was snap frozen in liquid nitrogen and stored at &#x02212;70&#x000b0;C for RNA extraction.</p></sec><sec><title>Mitotic Index</title><p>The total number of mitotic figures in each uterus section was counted, noting the tissue location, and the area of the section was measured using a KS400 image analysis system (Imaging Associates, Bicester, UK). The number of mitotic figures per square millimeter was calculated, and the frequency after administration of E<sub>2</sub> was compared with the frequency seen after the administration of AO using an appropriate statistical procedure. The number of mitoses per square millimeter was considered by a fixed-effects ANOVA allowing for treatment, time, and the treatment by time interaction. Analyses were carried out using the MIXED procedure in SAS, version 8.2 (SAS <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b46-ehp0112-001589">Institute Inc. 1999</xref>). Contrasts within the treatment by time interaction provided estimates of differences in E<sub>2</sub> and control response at each time point. These were compared statistically using a two-sided Student <italic>t</italic>-test based on the error mean square in the ANOVA.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Transcript Profiling and Data Analysis</title><p>Three independent biologic replicates of the entire time course study for E<sub>2</sub>-treated and time-matched AO-treated groups of animals were used to generate transcript profiling data and for subsequent statistical analysis. To minimize the effect of any interanimal variability, total RNA was isolated from the pooled uteri for each treatment group (<italic>n</italic> = 10 in the first two studies; reduced to <italic>n</italic> = 5 for the last study because of highly similar transcriptional responses being obtained in replicate studies 1 and 2) using RNeasy Midi kits (Qiagen Ltd., Crawley, West Sussex, UK). Biotin-labeled complementary RNAs were synthesized using the Enzo Bioarray HighYield RNA transcript labeling kit and hybridized to Affymetrix murine U74-Av2 GeneChips as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b60-ehp0112-001589">Zhu et al. 2001</xref>) and in the Affymetrix GeneChip expression analysis technical manual (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1-ehp0112-001589">Affymetrix, Inc. 2002</xref>). Probe arrays were scanned and the intensities were averaged using Microarray Analysis Suite 5.0 (Affymetrix, High Wycombe, UK). The mean signal intensity of each array was globally scaled to a target signal value of 500. To select E<sub>2</sub>-responsive genes, each gene was subjected to a mixed-model ANOVA allowing for treatment, time, and the treatment by time interaction as fixed effects and replicate study as a random effect. The use of mixed ANOVA models for the analysis of differential gene expression in microarray experiments has been previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5-ehp0112-001589">Churchill 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7-ehp0112-001589">Cui and Churchill 2003</xref>). Analyses were carried out using the MIXED procedure in SAS, version 8.2 (SAS <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b46-ehp0112-001589">Institute Inc. 1999</xref>). Contrasts within the treatment by time interaction provided estimates of differences in E<sub>2</sub> and control response at each time point. These were compared statistically using a two-sided Student <italic>t</italic>-test based on the error mean square in the ANOVA [<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplemental Data, Table 1</xref> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ehp.niehs.nih.gov/txg/members/2004/7345/supplemental.pdf">http://ehp.niehs.nih.gov/txg/members/2004/7345/supplemental.pdf</ext-link>)]. Data for genes exhibiting significant changes in expression (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01, two-sided) at one or more time points were then exported into GeneSpring 6.0 (SiliconGenetics, Redwood City, CA, USA), and a data transformation (values &#x0003c; 0.01 set to 0.01) and per-chip normalization (to the 50th percentile) were applied. Genes that did not have a <italic>Present</italic> detection call (Affymetrix) in any of the 14 treatment groups were removed from further analysis. Ratios of changes in gene expression were then calculated by normalizing each E<sub>2</sub>-treated sample to its corresponding time-matched vehicle (AO)-treated control. GeneChip data sets for the three independent biologic replicates were interpreted in log of ratio analysis mode, with biologic replicates being selected as a noncontinuous parameter. A total of 3,538 E<sub>2</sub>-responsive genes exhibiting a minimum of 1.5-fold up- or down-regulation in at least one time point were then subjected to gene tree&#x02013;based hierarchical clustering (Pearson correlation). To identify genes that function in specific biologic pathways, these 3,538 genes were further filtered using functional annotations derived from the NetAffx database&#x0201a; Analysis Center (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22-ehp0112-001589">Liu et al. 2003</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.affymetrix.com/analysis/index.affx">http://www.affymetrix.com/analysis/index.affx</ext-link>), together with manual annotations from published literature, before hierarchical clustering using GeneSpring. Gene names used in this article (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="ta1-ehp0112-001589">Appendix</xref>) were derived by homology searching of nucleotide sequence databases (BLASTn; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nih.gov/BLAST/">http://www.ncbi.nih.gov/BLAST/</ext-link>) using Affymetrix probe target sequences and the interrogation of NetAffx (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22-ehp0112-001589">Liu et al. 2003</xref>) database. All genes described in the figures and text showed statistically significant alterations in expression in all three replicate studies. MIAME (Minimum Information About a Microarray Experiment)-compliant microarray data for the three independent replicate studies are available as supplementary information and have been submitted to the Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO) database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec><title>Quantitative Real-Time Polymerase Chain Reaction</title><p>Uterine RNA was isolated and purified from all E<sub>2</sub>-treated and time-matched vehicle control groups (each consisting of pooled uteri) in all three replicate time course studies using the Qiagen RNeasy Midi kit (Qiagen). Before reverse transcription, RNA was treated with Dnase I (DNA-free kit; Ambion, Huntington, UK) to remove any contaminating genomic DNA. For each pool, 2 &#x003bc;g total RNA was reverse transcribed in a 25-&#x003bc;L reaction using SuperScript II (Invitrogen, Paisley, UK) and oligo-dT primer according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. Polymerase chain reaction (PCR; 25 &#x003bc;L) containing 2 &#x003bc;L first-strand cDNA (1:10 dilution), 12.5 &#x003bc;L of SYBR Green PCR Master Mix (Applied Biosystems, Warrington, UK), and 0.3 &#x003bc;M each of forward and reverse primers were run for 40 amplification cycles in an ABI PRISM 7700 Sequence Detection System (Applied Biosystems). Cycling conditions were 50&#x000b0;C for 2 min, 9&#x000b0;C for 10 min, 95&#x000b0;C for 15 sec, and 60&#x000b0;C for 1 min. All reactions were run in triplicate. Real-time (RT) PCR primers for <italic>FOS</italic> (5&#x02032;-CTGTGGCCTCCCTGGATTTG-3&#x02032;and 5&#x02032;-TGAGAAGGGGCAGGGTGAAG-3&#x02032;), <italic>LTF</italic> (5&#x02032;-CGGGGGCCTTCAGACCATC-3&#x02032;and 5&#x02032;-CTAAAGTGACAGCAGGG AGTG-3&#x02032;), and the control gene <italic>RPB1</italic> (5&#x02032; - GTTCTGGACCCCATTTTTGATAGGC-3&#x02032; and 5&#x02032;-CAGGGGACTGGCAGGGTAACAA-3&#x02032;) were designed using Primer Express software (version 1.5; Applied Biosystems) to generate amplicons within their corresponding Affymetrix probe set target sequences.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Histologic Changes and Increases in Uterine Weight</title><p>Our aim was to identify the genes and molecular networks associated with the uterotrophic response and to define the relationships between gene expression changes and histologic alterations. To this end, we gave immature female mice a single subcutaneous injection of E <sub>2</sub> (400 &#x003bc;g/kg) or vehicle and used DNA microarrays to measure uterine gene expression profiles at seven different times (1, 2, 4, 8, 24, 48, and 72 hr) after exposure. To facilitate the phenotypic anchoring of expression changes, we also measured blotted uterine weights and determined the average heights of the luminal epithelium and stromal endometrium for each animal. Three independent replicate experiments were carried out to allow a rigorous statistical analysis of the gene expression data (see &#x0201c;Materials and Methods&#x0201d;). We chose to use a single dose of E<sub>2</sub> to avoid the complex transcriptional program that may result from the standard uterotrophic assay exposure regime in which test compound is dosed by repeated administration on 3 consecutive days (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b35-ehp0112-001589">Odum et al. 1997</xref>). This dose induced a sustained increase in blotted uterine weight that was similar in the three replicate experiments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1-ehp0112-001589">Figure 1A</xref>). In each replicate experiment, a significant increase (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01) in uterine weight was observed 4 hr after exposure to E<sub>2</sub> and reached maximal levels between 24 and 72 hr (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1-ehp0112-001589">Figure 1A</xref>).</p><p>Histologic analysis of uterine sections revealed the cellular changes associated with the increase in uterine weight between 1 and 72 hr (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2-ehp0112-001589">Figure 2A</xref>). Consistent with previous reports (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6-ehp0112-001589">Clark and Mani 1994</xref>), the weight increase that occurred within 4 hr of exposure (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1-ehp0112-001589">Figure 1A</xref>) was associated with thickening of the stromal endometrium (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2-ehp0112-001589">Figure 2B</xref>) resulting from the uptake of fluid. The larger increase in uterine weight that occurred between 8 and 24 hr was due to hypertrophy and cell proliferation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19-ehp0112-001589">Kaye et al. 1971</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b45-ehp0112-001589">Quarmby and Korach 1984</xref>), which caused an increase in thickness of the luminal epithelium between 8 and 24 hr (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2-ehp0112-001589">Figure 2C</xref>). We conclude that the single dose of E <sub>2</sub> used induced a conventional uterotrophic response. Furthermore, the expression profiles of two classical E<sub>2</sub>-responsive genes, lactotransferrin (<italic>LTF</italic> ; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23-ehp0112-001589">Liu and Teng 1992</xref>) and the proto-oncogene <italic>C-FOS</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b58-ehp0112-001589">Weisz and Bresciani 1988</xref>), demonstrate that E<sub>2</sub> elicited a robust transcriptional response that was similar in the three replicate experiments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1-ehp0112-001589">Figure 1B</xref>).</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Multistep Method for Analysis of Gene Expression Changes</title><p>Uterine RNA from the seven time points for each of the E<sub>2</sub>-treated and time-matched vehicle control groups was analyzed using Affymetrix MG-U74Av2 GeneChips. A total of 42 microarray data sets were collected for the three replicate experiments. We used a multistep method to analyze the microarray gene expression data (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3-ehp0112-001589">Figure 3A</xref>). First, data were filtered and subjected to statistical analyses to identify the 3,538 genes with altered expression in E<sub>2</sub>-treated mice (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01 and &#x0003e; 1.5-fold) during at least one time point (see &#x0201c;Materials and Methods&#x0201d;). Unsupervised hierarchical clustering was then used to group these genes into co-regulated clusters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b44-ehp0112-001589">Quackenbush 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3-ehp0112-001589">Figure 3B</xref>), revealing a complex multistage transcriptional response to E<sub>2</sub> in the uterus (gene clusters A&#x02013;I in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3-ehp0112-001589">Figure 3B</xref>). To gain an overview of the predominant molecular functions and biologic pathways that were regulated at the transcriptional level during the uterotrophic response to E<sub>2</sub>, we interrogated the 3,538 E<sub>2</sub>-responsive genes using the GOStat gene ontology mining tool (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gostat.wehi.edu.au">http://gostat.wehi.edu.au</ext-link>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3-ehp0112-001589">Beissbarth and Speed 2004</xref>). This approach revealed that E<sub>2</sub> targets predominantly genes involved in protein metabolism, cell cycle, cell proliferation, DNA replication, RNA metabolism, mRNA transcription, and blood vessel development [<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplemental Data, Table 2</xref> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ehp.niehs.nih.gov/txg/members/2004/7345/supplemental.pdf">http://ehp.niehs.nih.gov/txg/members/2004/7345/supplemental.pdf</ext-link>)]. Next, we used a supervised clustering approach using customized gene ontology definitions (see &#x0201c;Materials and Methods&#x0201d;) to identify gene functions that were predominant in each co-regulated cluster in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3-ehp0112-001589">Figure 3B</xref>. This revealed that E<sub>2</sub> regulates each class of gene during a narrow window of time and suggests that E<sub>2</sub> induces uterine growth and maturation by regulating successively the activities of different biologic pathways (described below). Finally, we analyzed the temporal associations between the gene expression program and alterations in uterine weight and histology to anchor the gene expression changes to alterations in uterine phenotype. These associations are described below.</p></sec><sec><title>Phase 1: Rapid Induction of Transcriptional Regulators and Signaling Components by E<sub>2</sub></title><p>The first 4 hr of the uterotrophic response is characterized by the influx into the uterus of fluid that provides the nutrients and ions required for growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6-ehp0112-001589">Clark and Mani 1994</xref>). This leads to decompaction of stromal cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4-ehp0112-001589">Figure 4A</xref>) and thickening of the stromal endometrial layer at 4 hr (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2-ehp0112-001589">Figure 2B</xref>). This first phase of the uterotrophic response is accompanied by the rapid and transient regulation of genes encoding components of intra- and inter-cellular signaling pathways (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4-ehp0112-001589">Figure 4B</xref>) and sequence-specific transcriptional regulators (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4-ehp0112-001589">Figure 4C</xref>). Most of these genes show maximal expression between 1 and 4 hr, suggesting that the transcriptional effects of E <sub>2</sub>, mediated via ER- &#x003b1;and ER-&#x003b2;, are amplified rapidly through the induction or modulation of multiple transcriptional and nontranscriptional signaling pathways.</p></sec><sec><title>Signaling Genes</title><p>The signaling genes rapidly up-regulated by E<sub>2</sub> function in a broad array of signal transduction pathways (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4-ehp0112-001589">Figure 4B</xref>). These genes include protein kinases (<italic>AKT, MEK1, PIM3</italic>), growth factors (<italic>VEGF</italic>, <italic>PLGF</italic>), GTPases (<italic>RHOC, RAB11A, DEXRAS1</italic>), cytokine signaling proteins (<italic>MCP1, SOCS1, SOCS3</italic>, <italic>WSB1, IL17R</italic>), and a Wnt signaling factor (<italic>WNT4</italic>). Several E <sub>2</sub> -induced genes may act to attenuate initial signaling events (e.g., the protein phosphatase <italic>MKP1</italic> negatively modulates MAP kinase activity). Strikingly, many of the signaling genes induced within 4 hr of E<sub>2</sub> exposure have roles in the regulation of vascular permeability in other tissues, suggesting that they may be involved directly in initiating the influx of fluid into the uterus at this time (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4-ehp0112-001589">Figure 4B</xref>). These genes include angiogenic/vascular cell growth factors (<italic>VEGF, PLGF, ADM, ANGPT2, TGFB2</italic>), vasoactive serine proteases (<italic>KLK2, KLK6, KLK9, KLK22</italic>), and vascular endothelial receptors (<italic>IL17R, BDKRB1, ENG, GNA13</italic>). Furthermore, the vascular growth factor receptors <italic>TIE1</italic> and <italic>TIE2</italic> are rapidly down-regulated in response to E<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4-ehp0112-001589">Figure 4B</xref>), which may serve to attenuate the uptake of fluid after 4 hr. Collectively, these genes shed light on the mechanism by which E<sub>2</sub> promotes fluid uptake in the uterus and provide a clear link between gene expression changes and histologic changes occurring at this time.</p></sec><sec><title>Transcriptional Regulators</title><p>The sequence-specific transcription factors induced during the first 4 hr of the response can be divided into four main classes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4-ehp0112-001589">Figure 4C</xref>). The first contains members of the Jun, Fos, and ATF subgroups of transcription factors (<italic>C-FOS, FOSB, C-JUN, JUNB, ATF3, ATF4, ATF5</italic>) that form AP-1 dimers implicated in the regulation of cell proliferation and survival (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b48-ehp0112-001589">Shaulian and Karin 2001</xref>). The second class contains genes that control cell differentiation during the development of a number of tissues (<italic>SOX11, SOX18, HEY1, CART1, PRX2, SMAD7, ID1</italic>). The early induction of members of this class suggests that E<sub>2</sub> deploys a diverse range of gene expression networks to control cell growth and differentiation in the uterus. The third class contains two genes that encode co-regulators for nuclear receptors (<italic>RIP140</italic>, <italic>NCOR2</italic>), suggesting that these may act to modulate ER-mediated responses to E<sub>2</sub> in the uterus. The fourth class of genes encodes presumed transcriptional regulators of unknown function (e.g., <italic>GIF</italic>).</p><p>We conclude that the initial response to E<sub>2</sub> serves to <italic>a</italic>) modulate the activities of intra- and intercellular signaling pathways that, among other functions, promote vascular permeability and fluid uptake and <italic>b</italic>) up-regulate the expression levels of transcription factors that promote growth and differentiation. These early gene expression changes facilitate the amplification of the originating hormonal signal and set into motion the series of events that result in uterine growth and differentiation.</p></sec><sec><title>Phase 2: Coordinated Induction of Genes Required for mRNA and Protein Synthesis</title><p>No increase in uterine weight or obvious changes in uterine histology occur between 4 and 8 hr (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1-ehp0112-001589">Figures 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2-ehp0112-001589">2</xref>). Nevertheless, our data reveal that this phase is associated with the induction of a large cluster of genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5-ehp0112-001589">Figure 5</xref>). Most are induced 2 hr after E<sub>2</sub> administration, reach maximal expression at 4 or 8 hr, and return to control or subcontrol levels by 48 hr (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5-ehp0112-001589">Figure 5B</xref>). Most of these genes play roles in mRNA and protein synthesis, demonstrating that the bulk of transcriptional activity occurring at this time functions to increase the capacity of the uterus for new protein synthesis. This is consistent with earlier observations that exposure to E<sub>2</sub> results in a rapid increase in the mRNA and protein content of the uterus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6-ehp0112-001589">Clark and Mani 1994</xref>). Our data define the molecular basis for these prior observations and identify the genes targeted by ERs to induce these effects.</p><p>In a broad sense, protein synthesis includes the interlinked processes of transcription, mRNA processing, mRNA export into the cytoplasm, protein translation, and protein folding (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b38-ehp0112-001589">Orphanides and Reinberg 2002</xref>, and references therein; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5-ehp0112-001589">Figure 5G</xref>). Our data reveal the coordinated induction of genes involved in each of these processes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5-ehp0112-001589">Figure 5A</xref>&#x02013;F). These genes include <italic>a</italic>) components of the RNAP II general transcription machinery (<italic>RPB8</italic>, <italic>RPB10, TAF10</italic>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5-ehp0112-001589">Figure 5A</xref>); <italic>b</italic>) transcription termination and polyadenylation factors (<italic>NSAP1</italic>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5-ehp0112-001589">Figure 5A</xref>); <italic>c</italic>) mRNA splicing factors (<italic>SFPQ, U2AF1, RNPS1</italic>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5-ehp0112-001589">Figure 5A</xref>); <italic>d</italic>) mRNA export proteins (<italic>NXF1</italic>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5-ehp0112-001589">Figure 5C</xref>); <italic>e</italic>) protein translation factors (<italic>EIF1A, EIF2A, EIF2B, EIF3</italic>; ribosomal proteins <italic>RPL11, RPL12, RPL20, RPL52</italic>, <italic>RPS18b</italic>, and tRNA synthetases <italic>VALRS</italic>, <italic>GLURS, PHERS</italic>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5-ehp0112-001589">Figure 5D</xref>), and <italic>f</italic> ) protein folding factors (<italic>FKBP4</italic>, <italic>CCT3, CCT6a, CCT7, CCT8</italic>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5-ehp0112-001589">Figure 5E</xref>). The down-regulation of several genes associated with transcriptional repression (<italic>HDA1, TGIF, MAD4, EZH1</italic>) and mRNA degradation (<italic>AUH</italic>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5-ehp0112-001589">Figure 5B</xref>) may also contribute to the general elevation of mRNA synthesis. We also note a concurrent increase in the expression of components of the ubiquitin&#x02013;proteasome proteolytic pathway (<italic>PAD1, SUG1</italic>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5-ehp0112-001589">Figure 5F</xref>) and genes whose products are required for the nuclear import and export of proteins (<italic>IMPORTIN</italic>&#x003b1;<italic>2, IMPORTIN</italic>&#x003b1;<italic>3</italic>, <italic>RAE1, G3BP2</italic>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5-ehp0112-001589">Figure 5C</xref>), indicating that E<sub>2</sub> additionally elevates proteasome levels and nuclear-cytoplasmic protein transport activity at this time. We conclude that E<sub>2</sub> is able to increase protein synthesis activity in the uterus by altering the expression of genes involved in all aspects of the protein biosynthesis pathway.</p><p>Therefore, during the first two phases of the transcriptional program, E<sub>2</sub> induces the expression of a battery of sequence-specific transcriptional regulators (phase 1; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4-ehp0112-001589">Figure 4C</xref>) and then induces the expression of genes in the protein synthesis pathway (phase 2; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5-ehp0112-001589">Figure 5</xref>). It appears, therefore, that, during phase 1, E<sub>2</sub> specifies the gene expression networks that will be active, and then ensures during phase 2 that these networks have sufficient mRNA and protein synthesis capacity to operate. In addition the increased expression of components of the RNA and protein synthesis machinery is likely to be a prerequisite for proliferation in the uterus because cells must increase their mass before division to provide sufficient cellular components required for survival of the daughter cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b34-ehp0112-001589">Norbury and Nurse 1992</xref>). Consistent with this, we note that induction of protein synthesis components immediately precedes the up-regulation of genes required for proliferation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f6-ehp0112-001589">Figure 6</xref>; see below). An additional function of the increased uterine capacity for protein synthesis may be to facilitate the production of the abundant cytoarchitectural and secreted proteins induced at the end of the uterotrophic response (see below).</p></sec><sec sec-type="background"><title>Phase 3: Coordinated Regulation of Genes Controlling Chromosome Replication and the Cell Cycle</title><p>The next phase in the uterotrophic response occurs between 8 and 24 hr and involves an approximate doubling in uterine weight (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1-ehp0112-001589">Figure 1A</xref>) and a large increase in the thickness of the luminal epithelium (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2-ehp0112-001589">Figures 2C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f6-ehp0112-001589">6A</xref>). A quantitative histologic analysis of mitotic figures in the uterine cells (&#x0201c;Materials and Methods&#x0201d;) revealed a clear and statistically significant (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01) increase with E <sub>2</sub> at 24 hr, whereas no E<sub>2</sub>-dependent increase was observed at 8, 48, or 72 hr (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t1-ehp0112-001589">Table 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f6-ehp0112-001589">Figure 6A</xref>). These observations are consistent with previous studies showing that most cells in the immature rodent uterus are stimulated to leave their quiescent state and divide synchronously under the influence of E<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19-ehp0112-001589">Kaye et al. 1971</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b45-ehp0112-001589">Quarmby and Korach 1984</xref>).</p><p>We found that genes required for the replication of chromosomal DNA (<italic>PCNA</italic>, <italic>FEN1, CDC6, MCM2, MCM3, MCM4, MCM5, ORC1, ORC6, RRM1, RRM2</italic>) and genes required for postreplicative phases of the cell division cycle (e.g., <italic>CCNB1, PLK1</italic>) are coordinately induced and reach maximal expression levels between 8 and 24 hr (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f6-ehp0112-001589">Figure 6B</xref>), consistent with the timing of the histologic changes observed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f6-ehp0112-001589">Figure 6A</xref>. Genes required for maintaining genome integrity (<italic>CHK1, CKS1, GEMININ</italic>) and the epigenetic status of newly replicated DNA (<italic>CAF-1 p60, AHCY</italic>) are also up-regulated at 8 and/or 24 hr (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f6-ehp0112-001589">Figure 6B</xref>). It is striking that after their induction during the proliferative phase (8&#x02013;24 hr), the expression levels of most genes that regulate chromosome replication and cell division are reduced to levels well below those of control animals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f6-ehp0112-001589">Figure 6B</xref>). This suggests that mechanisms exist for the active repression of these genes to prevent further rounds of proliferation. Declining E<sub>2</sub> levels in mice 48 hr after a single subcutaneous injection may also contribute to the cessation of proliferation. Together, these data provide a molecular explanation for the changes in uterine weight and histology that occur between 8 and 24 hr (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1-ehp0112-001589">Figures 1A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2-ehp0112-001589">2</xref>, and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f6-ehp0112-001589">6A</xref>) and support the assertion that the early increase in weight seen at 4 hr is due to fluid uptake. Furthermore, these gene expression changes demonstrate that cell proliferation is restricted to a narrow window of time between 8 and 24 hr by the coordinated regulation of chromosome replication and cell division genes.</p></sec><sec sec-type="background"><title>Regulation of Cell Division</title><p>Our data also provide insight into the mechanisms by which E<sub>2</sub> releases cells of the immature uterus from quiescence and promotes cell division. The E<sub>2</sub>-induced expression profile of <italic>E2F1</italic>, a key transcriptional regulator of DNA replication genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b36-ehp0112-001589">Ohtani 1999</xref>), closely parallels the induction of the chromosome replication genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f6-ehp0112-001589">Figure 6B</xref>), consistent with the proposal that <italic>E2F1</italic> regulates the expression of components of the DNA replication fork in human breast cancer cell lines exposed to E<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24-ehp0112-001589">Lobenhofer et al. 2002</xref>). Our data indicate that release from quiescence also involves the E<sub>2</sub>-induced down-regulation of genes that maintain cells in a growth-arrested state (<italic>KIP1</italic>, <italic>CCNG2, CCNG1</italic>). The principle way in which mitogens induce proliferation of quiescent cells involves a reduction in levels of the Kip1 protein, which inhibits the activities of cyclin&#x02013;cdk complexes and induces cell cycle arrest (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b37-ehp0112-001589">Olashaw and Pledger 2002</xref>). We found that <italic>KIP1</italic> was down-regulated within 1 hr of E<sub>2</sub> exposure and remains repressed over a period of at least 24 hr, only reaching control levels when cell proliferation has ceased (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f6-ehp0112-001589">Figure 6C</xref>). Furthermore, E<sub>2</sub> may promote degradation of the Kip1 protein via the induction of <italic>CDC34</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f6-ehp0112-001589">Figure 6C</xref>), a gene that has been implicated in the ubiquitin-mediated degradation of Kip1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20-ehp0112-001589">Koepp et al. 1999</xref>). These data suggest that E<sub>2</sub> promotes cell proliferation by coordinately reducing Kip1 mRNA and protein levels. It is not clear whether <italic>KIP1</italic> is a direct or indirect target of the activated ERs. However, <italic>KIP1</italic> gene expression is controlled by ras-mediated PI3K signaling pathways (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b37-ehp0112-001589">Olashaw and Pledger 2002</xref>), components of which are up-regulated rapidly in response to E<sub>2</sub> (e.g., <italic>DEXRAS1</italic>, <italic>RASSF1</italic>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4-ehp0112-001589">Figure 4B</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Suppression of Apoptosis</title><p>E<sub>2</sub> protects against apoptosis in a number of tissues, including brain, testes, and uterus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b53-ehp0112-001589">Thompson 1994</xref>). Although the anti-apoptotic activity of estrogen in the uterus is thought to play a crucial role in the maintenance of uterine homeostasis, the mechanistic basis for this action has not been defined. Our data reveal that E<sub>2</sub> induces the expression of anti-apoptotic genes (<italic>BAG2, BAG3, DAD1</italic>) while simultaneously down-regulating the expression of pro-apoptotic genes (<italic>CASP2</italic>, <italic>NIX</italic>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f6-ehp0112-001589">Figure 6D</xref>). Thus, apoptosis appears to be suppressed through transcriptional mechanisms during E<sub>2</sub>-induced uterine growth. Consistent with these observations, E<sub>2</sub> also induces the apoptotic regulators <italic>BCL2</italic> and <italic>BAG1</italic> in cultured breast cancer cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b43-ehp0112-001589">Perillo et al. 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b50-ehp0112-001589">Soulez and Parker 2001</xref>). It will be important to determine whether estrogens elicit similar changes in the expression of apoptosis-regulating genes in other tissues.</p></sec><sec><title>Phase 4: Induction of Genes Involved in Uterine Cell Differentiation and Defense Responses</title><p>The period from 24 to 72 hr after E <sub>2</sub> exposure is associated with remodeling of the luminal epithelial cell layer, including the formation of secretory epithelial cells and a glycocalyx layer consisting of glycoproteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b40-ehp0112-001589">Paria et al. 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b59-ehp0112-001589">Weitlauf 1994</xref>). These changes result in the formation of a highly differentiated epithelial layer that is primed for cell recognition and adhesion events necessary for embryo attachment and implantation.</p></sec><sec><title>Changes in Cytoarchitecture</title><p>The final phase of the uterotrophic response coincides with the induction of a battery of genes involved in the cytoarchitectural remodeling of proliferating uterine cells, thus providing a further link between phenotypic and gene expression changes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f7-ehp0112-001589">Figure 7A</xref>). These genes encode components of desmosomes (<italic>DSG2</italic>), gap junctions (<italic>CX26</italic>), tight junctions (<italic>CLDN4, CLDN7</italic>), the cornified envelope (<italic>SPRR1A, 2A, 2B, 2E, 2F, 2G, 2I, 2J</italic>), intermediate filaments (<italic>KRT19</italic>), and a variety of cell-surface and extracellular-matrix glycoproteins (<italic>SPP1, BGP1, BGP2, MUC1, TROP2, CLU</italic>). The latter class of genes is likely to contribute to the formation of the glycocalyx layer present on differentiated uterine epithelium (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b59-ehp0112-001589">Weitlauf 1994</xref>). The concomitant E<sub>2</sub>-dependent induction of a number of enzymes required for carbohydrate metabolism (<italic>MAN2B1, GALNT3</italic>) may provide the increase in sugar metabolism necessary for the production of these glycoproteins. E<sub>2</sub> also induces genes encoding ion channels that regulate the balance of Na<sup>+</sup> absorption and Cl<sup>&#x02212;</sup> secretion across the endometrial epithelium to maintain a luminal fluid microenvironment suitable for implantation (<italic>CFTR, CLCA3, MAT8</italic>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f7-ehp0112-001589">Figure 7A</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Defense Responses</title><p>A number of genes involved in host defense processes or detoxification are first regulated between 24 and 72 hr (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f7-ehp0112-001589">Figure 7B</xref>). We speculate that the products of these genes may provide an environment that is protective of, and facilitates, embryo implantation and development. These include genes encoding lysosomal enzymes (<italic>LYZP, LYZM, CTSH CTSL, CTSS, LGMN</italic>), genes involved in detoxification and clearance of xenobiotics (<italic>GSTO1, GSTT2, UGT1A1</italic>), and genes involved in immune and inflammatory responses (<italic>CD14, MX1, PIGR</italic>). The up-regulation of genes encoding chemoattractant cytokines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f7-ehp0112-001589">Figure 7C</xref>) for infiltrating eosinophils (<italic>EOTAXIN</italic>) and monocytes (<italic>MCP1</italic>/<italic>3</italic>) is consistent with previous observations of immune cell infiltration into the uterus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12-ehp0112-001589">Gouon-Evans and Pollard 2001</xref>, and references therein). Another E<sub>2</sub>-regulated defense response may be provided by the induction of LTF (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23-ehp0112-001589">Liu and Teng 1992</xref>), an iron-binding protein with bacteriostatic activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b49-ehp0112-001589">Singh et al. 2002</xref>). Our data reveal the induction of two additional iron metabolism genes at this time (<italic>CP, LCN2</italic>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f7-ehp0112-001589">Figure 7E</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18-ehp0112-001589">Kaplan 2002</xref>), suggesting a role for iron homeostasis in the uterotrophic response to E<sub>2</sub>.</p><p>Several components of the complement system are also induced 48&#x02013;72 hr after exposure to E <sub>2</sub>. These include <italic>C1QA, C1QB, C1QC, C2, C3, C4, CFH,</italic> and <italic>CFI</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f7-ehp0112-001589">Figure 7D</xref>). Although many complement components have been identified in female reproductive epithelium, only <italic>C3</italic> has previously been established as an E<sub>2</sub>-responsive gene (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b51-ehp0112-001589">Sundstrom et al. 1989</xref>). In addition to participating in immune and inflammatory responses and host resistance, there is increasing evidence that complement functions in tissue remodeling and organ regeneration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26-ehp0112-001589">Mastellos and Lambris 2002</xref>). Intriguingly, complement also influences mammalian reproduction and particularly the integrity of maternofetal interfaces during pregnancy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4-ehp0112-001589">Caucheteux et al. 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26-ehp0112-001589">Mastellos and Lambris 2002</xref>). Therefore, it is possible that the complement system may play a noninflammatory role in the uterotrophic response.</p></sec><sec><title>Evidence for a Transcriptional Cascade in the Uterus</title><p>It is striking that many different induction profiles can be seen in the genes regulated by E<sub>2</sub>: some genes are induced within 1 hr of exposure, whereas others are not induced until 48 hr (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3-ehp0112-001589">Figure 3B</xref>). The induction of a large number of sequence-specific transcription factors during the first phase of the response suggests that a transcriptional cascade may operate in the uterus, with the products of genes induced at the beginning of the program regulating the transcription of those toward the end. The regulation of the SPRR genes provides evidence for the existence of such a cascade (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f8-ehp0112-001589">Figure 8</xref>). The mouse SPRR genes are located in a tandem array at the same chromosomal locus, and their transcription is regulated by the AP-1 and Ets transcription factors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b41-ehp0112-001589">Patel et al. 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f8-ehp0112-001589">Figure 8A</xref>). Eight members of the SPRR gene family are induced between 4 and 72 hr, with maximal induction occurring between 24 and 48 hr (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f8-ehp0112-001589">Figure 8B</xref>). Intriguingly, the mRNAs encoding Ets2 and components of AP-1 (c-Jun, JunB, c-Fos, FosB, and Atf3, Atf4, Atf5) are maximally induced during the first phase of the uterotrophic response, between 1 and 4 hr (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f8-ehp0112-001589">Figure 8B</xref>). We speculate, therefore, that a transcriptional cascade operates, in which ER-&#x003b1;or ER-&#x003b2;induces the expression of Ets2 and AP-1 components, which in turn regulate the transcription of the SPRR genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f8-ehp0112-001589">Figure 8C</xref>). Alternatively, it is possible that ER-&#x003b1;or ER-&#x003b2;cooperates with Ets2 and AP-1 to regulate the expression of the SPRR genes. In this way, transcription of the SPRR genes would not begin until sufficient levels of Ets2 and AP-1 were present. Consistent with this model, feed-forward loops (in which a transcriptional regulator controls a second transcription factor that then functions in concert with the initial regulator on a common downstream target gene) are emerging as common mechanisms in eukaryotes for transcriptional networks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21-ehp0112-001589">Lee et al. 2002</xref>). It is likely that analysis of the regulatory regions of other E<sub>2</sub>-responsive genes during the uterotrophic response will suggest the existence of additional transcriptional networks.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Our data describe at an unprecedented level of detail the molecular events that initiate and drive uterine physiologic changes upon exposure to the sex steroid hormone E <sub>2</sub> in the immature mouse uterus. Gene expression profiling reveals that E<sub>2</sub> induces a multistage and tightly coordinated transcriptional program that regulates successive and functionally interlinked cellular processes during the uterotrophic response (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f9-ehp0112-001589">Figure 9</xref>). The temporal patterns of gene expression we have identified for E<sub>2</sub> are consistent with, and extend, those reported recently for the uterotrophic response of immature, ovariectomized mice after exposure to 17&#x003b1;-ethynylestradiol (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10-ehp0112-001589">Fertuck et al. 2003</xref>), in which concordant temporal responses were seen for genes involved in several functional categories in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f9-ehp0112-001589">Figure 9</xref>. These include RNA and protein metabolism, cell cycle regulation, immune responses, and complement components. Furthermore, many of the genes regulated by exogenous E<sub>2</sub> in our study are also differentially regulated in response to endogenous hormones (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b52-ehp0112-001589">Tan et al. 2003</xref>).</p><p>Comparison of gene expression changes with alterations in uterine weight and histologic alterations, and analysis of gene expression data according to gene function allowed us to implicate specific groups of genes in driving water imbibition in the stromal endothelium, synchronous cell proliferation, and cytoarchitectural changes associated with luminal epithelial cell differentiation. These data thus provide a detailed mechanistic view of the relationships between the uterotrophic response and the underlying transcriptional program. Furthermore, this work demonstrates that comparison of temporal changes in gene expression and conventional toxicology parameters (uterine weight and histologic changes) can provide an understanding of the relationships between gene expression patterns and phenotypic change.</p><p>E<sub>2</sub> can regulate transcription through a combination of at least two distinct signaling pathways: <italic>a</italic>) via activation of the nuclear transcription factors ER-&#x003b1;and ER-&#x003b2;(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13-ehp0112-001589">Hall et al. 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27-ehp0112-001589">McKenna and O&#x02019;Malley 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31-ehp0112-001589">Moggs and Orphanides 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b54-ehp0112-001589">Tremblay and Giguere 2002</xref>) and <italic>b</italic>) via extranuclear or &#x0201c;nongenomic&#x0201d; signaling events (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9-ehp0112-001589">Falkenstein et al. 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15-ehp0112-001589">Hammes 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30-ehp0112-001589">Moggs et al. 2003</xref>). The transcriptional responses to E<sub>2</sub> that we have defined here are likely to involve a combination of direct gene regulation by nuclear ERs and indirect gene regulation via extranuclear signaling pathways. Although the uterus of the immature mouse expresses both ER subtypes (&#x003b1;and &#x003b2;) at comparable levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b57-ehp0112-001589">Weihua et al. 2000</xref>), recent transcript profiling studies using ovariectomized ER-knockout mice revealed a predominant role for ER-&#x003b1;in the regulation of estrogen-responsive genes in the uterus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17-ehp0112-001589">Hewitt et al. 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b55-ehp0112-001589">Watanabe et al. 2003</xref>) consistent with the observation that only a partial uterotrophic response occurs in ER-&#x003b1;knockout mice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25-ehp0112-001589">Lubahn et al. 1993</xref>). Therefore, it is likely that most E<sub>2</sub>-responsive genes we have identified are regulated by ER-&#x003b1;. However, identification of the direct gene targets for each ER subtype will ultimately require the development of methods for measuring the occupancy of receptor subtypes at promoters <italic>in vivo</italic>. Nevertheless, our temporal analysis of E<sub>2</sub>-responsive genes provides novel insights into the transcriptional cascades that are initiated through E<sub>2</sub>-responsive transcription factors.</p><p>The molecular events described here for the reference natural estrogen E<sub>2</sub> provide the basis for understanding how other estrogenic chemicals, including synthetic estrogens and phytoestrogens, induce their effects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29-ehp0112-001589">Moggs et al. 2004</xref>). Increasing attention is being paid to the use of gene expression changes in the uterus for the identification of surrogate markers for short-term rodent estrogenicity assays (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32-ehp0112-001589">Naciff et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b33-ehp0112-001589">2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b39-ehp0112-001589">Owens and Ashby 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b56-ehp0112-001589">Watanabe et al. 2002</xref>), and our data reveal a large number of novel candidate marker genes. The insights provided by these data, into how an ER ligand coordinates transcriptional regulatory networks that result in proliferation and differentiation in a complex organ, provide a paradigm for understanding the modes of action of other nuclear receptors.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><label>Supplemental Figures and Tables</label><media xlink:href="ehp0112-001589s1.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:type="simple" id="N0x8b5a838.0x9616568" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="b1-ehp0112-001589"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Affymetrix, Inc</collab> 2002. GeneChip Expression Analysis: Technical Manual. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http//www.affymetrix.com/support/technical/manual/expression.manual.affx">http//www.affymetrix.com/support/technical/manual/expression.manual.affx</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b2-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Amin</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Vickers</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Sistare</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Roman</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawton</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Identification of putative gene based markers of renal toxicity</article-title><source>Environ Health Perspect</source><volume>112</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>465</fpage><lpage>479</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15033597</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b3-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Beissbarth</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Speed</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>GOstat: find statistically overrepresented gene ontologies within a group of genes</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>20</volume><fpage>1464</fpage><lpage>1465</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14962934</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b4-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Caucheteux</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kannellopoulos-Langevin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ojcius</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>At the innate frontiers between mother and fetus: linking abortion with complement activation</article-title><source>Immunity</source><volume>18</volume><fpage>169</fpage><lpage>172</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12594944</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b5-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Churchill</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Using ANOVA to analyze microarray data</article-title><source>Biotechniques</source><volume>37</volume><fpage>173</fpage><lpage>175</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15335204</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b6-ehp0112-001589"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Mani</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group> 1994. Actions of ovarian steroid hormones. In: The Physiology of Reproduction (Knobil E, Neill J, eds). Vol 1, 2nd ed. New York:Raven Press, 1011&#x02013;1059.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b7-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Churchill</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Statistical tests for differential expression in cDNA microarray experiments</article-title><source>Genome Biol</source><volume>4</volume><fpage>210.1</fpage><lpage>210.10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12702200</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b8-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Irwin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Boorman</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Tox/path team takes on differential gene expression</article-title><source>Environ Health Perspect</source><volume>111</volume><fpage>A814</fpage><lpage>A815</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14630520</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b9-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Falkenstein</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Tillmann</surname><given-names>H-C</given-names></name><name><surname>Christ</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Feuring</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wehling</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Multiple actions of steroid hormones&#x02014;a focus on rapid, non-genomic effects</article-title><source>Pharmacol Rev</source><volume>52</volume><fpage>513</fpage><lpage>555</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11121509</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b10-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Fertuck</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Eckel</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Gennings</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Zacharewski</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Identification of temporal patterns of gene expression in the uteri of immature, ovariectomized mice following exposure to ethynylestradiol</article-title><source>Physiol Genomics</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>141</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12915738</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b11-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Gant</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name><surname>Baus</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Clothier</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Riley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Judah</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Gene expression profiles associated with inflammation, fibrosis, and cholestasis in mouse liver after griseofulvin</article-title><source>Environ Health Perspect</source><volume>111</volume><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>43</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b12-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Gouon-Evans</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Pollard</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Eotaxin is required for eosinophil homing into the stroma of the pubertal and cycling uterus</article-title><source>Endocrinology</source><volume>142</volume><fpage>4515</fpage><lpage>4521</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11564717</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b13-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Couse</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Korach</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>The multifaceted mechanisms of estradiol and estrogen receptor signaling</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>276</volume><fpage>36869</fpage><lpage>36872</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11459850</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b14-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Hamadeh</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Jayadev</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaillard</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Stoll</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Blanchard</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Integration of clinical and gene expression endpoints to explore furan-mediated hepatotoxicity</article-title><source>Mutat Res</source><volume>549</volume><fpage>169</fpage><lpage>183</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15120969</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b15-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Hammes</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>The further redefining of steroid-mediated signaling</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>100</volume><fpage>2168</fpage><lpage>2170</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12606724</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b16-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Heinloth</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Irwin</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Boorman</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Nettesheim</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Fannin</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Sieber</surname><given-names>SO</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Gene expression profiling of rat livers reveals indicators of potential adverse effects</article-title><source>Toxicol Sci</source><volume>80</volume><fpage>193</fpage><lpage>202</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15084756</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b17-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Hewitt</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Deroo</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Grissom</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Afshari</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Estrogen receptor-dependent genomic responses in the uterus mirror the biphasic physiological response to estrogen</article-title><source>Mol Endocrinol</source><volume>17</volume><fpage>2070</fpage><lpage>2083</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12893882</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b18-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Mechanisms of cellular iron acquisition: another iron in the fire</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>111</volume><fpage>603</fpage><lpage>606</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12464171</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b19-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Kaye</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheratzky</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindner</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name></person-group><year>1971</year><article-title>Kinetics of DNA synthesis in immature rat uterus: age dependence and estradiol stimulation</article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><volume>261</volume><fpage>475</fpage><lpage>486</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4335548</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b20-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Koepp</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Harper</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Elledge</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>How the cyclin became a cyclin: regulated proteolysis in the cell cycle</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>97</volume><fpage>431</fpage><lpage>434</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10338207</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b21-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>TI</given-names></name><name><surname>Rinaldi</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Robert</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Odom</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Bar-Joseph</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerber</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Transcriptional regulatory networks in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic></article-title><source>Science</source><volume>298</volume><fpage>799</fpage><lpage>804</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12399584</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b22-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Loraine</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Shigeta</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Cline</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Valmeekam</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>NetAffx: Affymetrix probesets and annotations</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><volume>31</volume><fpage>82</fpage><lpage>86</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12519953</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b23-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Teng</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name></person-group><year>1992</year><article-title>Estrogen response module of the mouse lactoferrin gene contains overlapping chicken ovalbumin upstream promoter transcription factor and estrogen receptor-binding elements</article-title><source>Mol Endocrinol</source><volume>6</volume><fpage>355</fpage><lpage>364</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1584212</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b24-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Lobenhofer</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Cable</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bushel</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Afshari</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Regulation of DNA replication fork genes by 17beta-estradiol</article-title><source>Mol Endocrinol</source><volume>16</volume><fpage>1215</fpage><lpage>1229</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12040010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b25-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Lubahn</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Moyer</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Golding</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Couse</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Korach</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Smithies</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><year>1993</year><article-title>Alteration of reproductive function but not prenatal sexual development after insertional disruption of the mouse estrogen receptor gene</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>90</volume><fpage>11162</fpage><lpage>11166</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8248223</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b26-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Mastellos</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lambris</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Complement: more than a &#x02018;guard&#x02019; against invading pathogens?</article-title><source>Trends Immunol</source><volume>23</volume><fpage>485</fpage><lpage>491</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12297420</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b27-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>McKenna</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Malley</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Combinatorial control of gene expression by nuclear receptors and coregulators</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>108</volume><fpage>465</fpage><lpage>474</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11909518</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b28-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Metivier</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Penot</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Hubner</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Brand</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kos</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Estrogen receptor-alpha directs ordered, cyclical, and combinatorial recruitment of cofactors on a natural target promoter</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>115</volume><fpage>751</fpage><lpage>763</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14675539</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b29-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Moggs</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashby</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tinwell</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>F-L</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimber</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>The need to decide if all estrogens are intrinsically similar</article-title><source>Environ Health Perspect</source><volume>112</volume><fpage>1137</fpage><lpage>1142</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15289156</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b30-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Moggs</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Deavall</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Orphanides</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Sex steroids, ANGELS and osteoporosis</article-title><source>Bioessays</source><volume>25</volume><fpage>195</fpage><lpage>199</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12596222</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b31-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Moggs</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Orphanides</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Estrogen receptors: orchestrators of pleiotropic cellular responses</article-title><source>EMBO Rep</source><volume>2</volume><fpage>775</fpage><lpage>781</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11559590</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b32-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Naciff</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jump</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Torontali</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Carr</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Tiesman</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Overmann</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Gene expression profile induced by 17alpha-ethynyl estradiol, bisphenol A, and genistein in the developing female reproductive system of the rat</article-title><source>Toxicol Sci</source><volume>68</volume><fpage>184</fpage><lpage>199</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12075121</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b33-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Naciff</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Overmann</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Torontali</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Carr</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Tiesman</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Gene expression profile induced by 17 alpha-ethynyl estradiol in the prepubertal female reproductive system of the rat</article-title><source>Toxicol Sci</source><volume>72</volume><fpage>314</fpage><lpage>330</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12655037</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b34-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Norbury</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Nurse</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year>1992</year><article-title>Animal cell cycles and their control</article-title><source>Annu Rev Biochem</source><volume>61</volume><fpage>441</fpage><lpage>470</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1497317</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b35-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Odum</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lefevre</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Tittensor</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Paton</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Routledge</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Beresford</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>The rodent uterotrophic assay: critical protocol features, studies with nonyl phenols, and comparison with a yeast estrogenicity assay</article-title><source>Regul Toxicol Pharmacol</source><volume>26</volume><fpage>176</fpage><lpage>188</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9185893</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b36-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Ohtani</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>Implication of transcription factor E2F in regulation of DNA replication</article-title><source>Front Biosci</source><volume>4</volume><fpage>D793</fpage><lpage>D804</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10577392</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b37-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Olashaw</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Pledger</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Paradigms of growth control: relation to Cdk activation</article-title><source>Sci STKE</source><volume>134</volume><fpage>RE7</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12034920</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b38-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Orphanides</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Reinberg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>A unified theory of gene expression</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>108</volume><fpage>439</fpage><lpage>451</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11909516</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b39-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Owens</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashby</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Critical review and evaluation of the uterotrophic bioassay for the identification of possible estrogen agonists and antagonists: in support of the validation of the OECD uterotrophic protocols for the laboratory rodent. Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development</article-title><source>Crit Rev Toxicol</source><volume>32</volume><fpage>445</fpage><lpage>520</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12487363</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b40-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Paria</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Reese</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Dey</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Deciphering the cross-talk of implantation: advances and challenges</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>296</volume><fpage>2185</fpage><lpage>2188</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12077405</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b41-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kartasova</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Segre</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Mouse SPRR locus: a tandem array of coordinately regulated genes</article-title><source>Mamm Genome</source><volume>14</volume><fpage>140</fpage><lpage>148</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12584609</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b42-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Paules</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Phenotypic anchoring: linking cause and effect</article-title><source>Environ Health Perspect</source><volume>111</volume><fpage>A338</fpage><lpage>A339</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12760838</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b43-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Perillo</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasso</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Abbondanza</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Palumbo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>17beta-Estradiol inhibits apoptosis in MCF-7 cells, inducing bcl-2 expression via two estrogen-responsive elements present in the coding sequence</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><volume>20</volume><fpage>2890</fpage><lpage>2901</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10733592</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b44-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Quackenbush</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Microarray data normalization and transformation</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><volume>32</volume><issue>suppl</issue><fpage>496</fpage><lpage>501</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12454644</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b45-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Quarmby</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name><name><surname>Korach</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name></person-group><year>1984</year><article-title>Differential regulation of protein synthesis by estradiol in uterine component tissues</article-title><source>Endocrinology</source><volume>114</volume><fpage>694</fpage><lpage>702</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6697957</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b46-ehp0112-001589"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>SAS Institute Inc.</collab> 1999. SAS/STAT User&#x02019;s Guide, Version 8. Cary, NC:SAS Institute Inc.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b47-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Toxicogenomics</article-title><source>Environ Health Perspect</source><volume>111</volume><fpage>A20</fpage><lpage>A25</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b48-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Shaulian</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Karin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>AP-1 in cell proliferation and survival</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><volume>20</volume><fpage>2390</fpage><lpage>2400</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11402335</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b49-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Parsek</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><name><surname>Welsh</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>A component of innate immunity prevents bacterial biofilm development</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>417</volume><fpage>552</fpage><lpage>555</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12037568</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b50-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Soulez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Identification of novel oestrogen receptor target genes in human ZR75-1 breast cancer cells by expression profiling</article-title><source>J Mol Endocrinol</source><volume>27</volume><fpage>259</fpage><lpage>274</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11719280</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b51-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Sundstrom</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Komm</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ponce-de-Leon</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Teuscher</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyttle</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group><year>1989</year><article-title>Estrogen regulation of tissue-specific expression of complement C3</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>264</volume><fpage>16941</fpage><lpage>16947</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2674144</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b52-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>FX</given-names></name><name><surname>Piao</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Global gene profiling analysis of mouse uterus during the oestrous cycle</article-title><source>Reproduction</source><volume>126</volume><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>182</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12887274</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b53-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name></person-group><year>1994</year><article-title>Apoptosis and steroid hormones</article-title><source>Mol Endocrinol</source><volume>8</volume><fpage>665</fpage><lpage>671</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7935482</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b54-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Tremblay</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><name><surname>Giguere</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Coregulators of estrogen receptor action</article-title><source>Crit Rev Eukaryot Gene Expr</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12433063</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b55-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Itamoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lubahn</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Analysis of temporal changes in the expression of estrogen-regulated genes in the uterus</article-title><source>J Mol Endocrinol</source><volume>30</volume><fpage>347</fpage><lpage>358</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12790804</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b56-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mizutani</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Khono</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lubahn</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Handa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Genome-wide analysis of changes in early gene expression induced by oestrogen</article-title><source>Genes Cells</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>497</fpage><lpage>507</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12047351</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b57-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Weihua</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Saji</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Makinen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name><name><surname>Warner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Estrogen receptor (ER) beta, a modulator of ERalpha in the uterus</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>97</volume><fpage>5936</fpage><lpage>5941</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10823946</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b58-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Weisz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bresciani</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year>1988</year><article-title>Estrogen induces expression of c-fos and c-myc protooncogenes in rat uterus</article-title><source>Mol Endocrinol</source><volume>2</volume><fpage>816</fpage><lpage>824</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3173352</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b59-ehp0112-001589"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group><name><surname>Weitlauf</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name></person-group> 1994. Biology of implantation. In: The Physiology of Reproduction (Knobil E, Neill J, eds). Vol 1, 2nd ed. New York:Raven Press, 391&#x02013;440.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b60-ehp0112-001589"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Budworth</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Toward elucidating the global gene expression patterns of developing <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>: parallel analysis of 8300 genes by high-density oligonucleotide probe array</article-title><source>Plant Physiol Biochem</source><volume>39</volume><fpage>221</fpage><lpage>242</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="f1-ehp0112-001589" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Uterotrophic response to a single dose of E<sub>2</sub>. (<italic>A</italic>) Uterine blotted weight. Data for replicate studies A and B are mean &#x000b1; SD from 10 immature female mice in each treatment group. Five animals per group were used in replicate study C. (<italic>B</italic>) Temporal expression profile of the estrogen-responsive genes complement component C3 and C-FOS. Quantitative RT-PCR analysis of <italic>FOS</italic> and <italic>LTF</italic> gene expression from three independent time-course studies (<italic>A&#x02013;C</italic>) and comparison with microarray data. Each RT-PCR data point represents a fold value, obtained using the comparative <italic>C</italic><italic><sub>t</sub></italic> (threshold cycle) method, for E<sub>2</sub>-induced change in gene expression relative to time-matched vehicle controls. The fold induction value is relative to the endogenous control gene <italic>RPB1</italic> and to treatment, that is, estrogen/untreated. Microarray data are ratios (E<sub>2</sub>:time-matched vehicle control) of normalized Affymetrix GeneChip signal intensities (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3-ehp0112-001589">Figure 3A</xref> and &#x0201c;Materials and Methods&#x0201d;).
<break/>*<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05;
<break/>**<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="ehp0112-001589f1"/></fig><fig id="f2-ehp0112-001589" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Histologic analysis of uterotrophic response to a single dose of E<sub>2</sub>. (<italic>A)</italic> Panels show longitudinal 0.3-&#x003bc;m&#x02013;thick paraffin sections of uteri stained with hematoxylin and eosin; bar = 50 &#x003bc;m. Luminal space (L), luminal epithelium (LE), stromal endothelium (SE), and glandular epithelium (GE) are indicated. (<italic>B</italic>) Height of stromal endothelial cell layer. (<italic>C</italic>) Height of luminal epithelial cell layer. Data in <italic>B</italic> and <italic>C</italic> are mean &#x000b1; SD from 10 immature female mice in each treatment group. Solid bars, E<sub>2</sub>; open bars, AO.
<break/>*<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05;
<break/>**<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="ehp0112-001589f2"/></fig><fig id="f3-ehp0112-001589" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>(<italic>A</italic>) Experimental strategy for phenotypic anchoring of E<sub>2</sub>-responsive genes during uterotrophic response. Three independent biologic replicate studies were performed in which we analyzed seven different time points for E<sub>2</sub>-treated animals and the equivalent time points for vehicle-treated animals. (<italic>B</italic>) Staged transcriptional response of the immature mouse uterus to E<sub>2</sub>. Gene tree generated by hierarchical clustering of 3,538 E<sub>2</sub>-responsive genes showing clusters (labeled A&#x02013;I) of temporally co-regulated genes. The genes clustered in groups A&#x02013;I are further annotated using gene ontology analyses in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4-ehp0112-001589">Figures 4</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f7-ehp0112-001589">7</xref>. The color scale indicates the mean fold change of E<sub>2</sub>-induced gene expression relative to time-matched AO-treated control samples (based on the three independent studies shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1-ehp0112-001589">Figure 1A</xref>).</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="ehp0112-001589f3"/></fig><fig id="f4-ehp0112-001589" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Phase 1: rapid induction of transcriptional regulators and signaling components by E<sub>2</sub>. (<italic>A</italic>) Water imbibition and increased vascular activity in stromal endothelium (SE) 2 and 4 hr after a single dose of E<sub>2</sub>. Longitudinal 0.3-&#x003bc;m&#x02013;thick paraffin sections of uteri stained with hematoxylin and eosin are shown. Scale bar, 50 &#x003bc;m. (<italic>B</italic>) Coordinate expression of genes encoding signaling components. Genes marked with a red circle have functions associated with altered vascular permeability and may drive the water imbibition seen at this time. (<italic>C</italic>) Coordinate expression of genes encoding transcription factors. Detailed quantitative data for genes encoding AP-1 transcription factors are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f8-ehp0112-001589">Figure 8B</xref>. Gene trees were generated by supervised hierarchical clustering; genes with related functions were selected from clusters of temporally co-regulated E<sub>2</sub>-responsive genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3-ehp0112-001589">Figure 3B</xref>) using universal gene ontology descriptions. The color scale for fold change in expression is identical to that used in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3-ehp0112-001589">Figure 3B</xref>. Data derived from independent Affymetrix probe sets are shown for <italic>GIF</italic> and <italic>SOX18</italic>. See <xref ref-type="table" rid="ta1-ehp0112-001589">Appendix</xref> for gene nomenclature and Affymetrix probe sets.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="ehp0112-001589f4"/></fig><fig id="f5-ehp0112-001589" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Phase 2: coordinated induction of genes required for mRNA and protein synthesis. Coordinated expression of genes involved in (<italic>A</italic>) RNA synthesis, (<italic>B</italic>) transcriptional repression, (<italic>C</italic>) nuclear import/export, (<italic>D</italic>) protein translation, (<italic>E</italic>) protein folding, and (<italic>F</italic>) protein degradation. Gene trees were generated as described in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4-ehp0112-001589">Figure 4</xref>. Data derived from independent Affymetrix probe sets are shown for <italic>eIF1A</italic>, <italic>eRF1</italic>, and <italic>CCT3</italic>. See <xref ref-type="table" rid="ta1-ehp0112-001589">Appendix</xref> for gene nomenclature and Affymetrix probe sets. (<italic>G</italic>) Schematic overview of RNA and protein synthesis in eukaryotes, showing machinery involved in each step of the process. Reprinted from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b38-ehp0112-001589">Orphanides and Reinberg (2002)</xref>, with permission from Elsevier.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="ehp0112-001589f5"/></fig><fig id="f6-ehp0112-001589" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Phase 3: coordinated regulation of genes controlling chromosome replication and the cell cycle. (<italic>A</italic>) Thickening of luminal (LE) and glandular epithelium (GE) and increased number of mitotic cells (indicated by arrowheads) between 8 and 24 hr after a single dose of E<sub>2</sub>. Longitudinal 0.3-&#x003bc;m&#x02013;thick paraffin sections of uteri were stained with hematoxylin and eosin. Scale bar, 50 &#x003bc;m. Coordinated expression of genes involved in (<italic>B</italic>) chromosome replication and cell division, (<italic>C</italic>) cell-cycle regulation, (<italic>D</italic>) and apoptosis. Gene trees were generated as described in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4-ehp0112-001589">Figure 4</xref>. Data derived from independent Affymetrix probe sets are shown for <italic>MCM3</italic>. See <xref ref-type="table" rid="ta1-ehp0112-001589">Appendix</xref> for gene nomenclature and Affymetrix probe sets.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="ehp0112-001589f6"/></fig><fig id="f7-ehp0112-001589" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title>Phase 4: induction of genes involved in uterine cell differentiation and defense responses. (<italic>A</italic>) Cytoarchitecture; (<italic>B</italic>) defense responses; (<italic>C</italic>) chemoattractant cytokines; (<italic>D</italic>) complement; and (<italic>E</italic>) iron homeostasis. Gene trees were generated as described in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4-ehp0112-001589">Figure 4</xref>. Data derived from independent Affymetrix probe sets are shown for <italic>SPRR2A</italic>, <italic>CD133</italic>, <italic>TROP2</italic>, <italic>BGP1</italic>, <italic>CLU</italic>, <italic>KRT19</italic>, and <italic>CFH</italic>. Detailed quantitative data for the SPRR gene family are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f8-ehp0112-001589">Figure 8B</xref>. See <xref ref-type="table" rid="ta1-ehp0112-001589">Appendix</xref> for gene nomenclature and Affymetrix probe sets.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="ehp0112-001589f7"/></fig><fig id="f8-ehp0112-001589" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><title>Evidence for a transcriptional regulatory network during the uterotrophic response. (<italic>A</italic>) Organization of mouse SPRR genomic locus that is coordinately regulated by the transcription factors AP-1 and Ets. (<italic>B</italic>) E<sub>2</sub>-induced expression (mean + SD) of genes encoding AP-1 and Ets transcription factors temporally precedes the coordinate regulation of the tandem array of SPRR genes. (<italic>C</italic>) Feed-forward model for an ER-dependent transcriptional cascade in the uterus. Transcriptional regulators are represented by blue circles. Gene promoters are represented by white rectangles. See <xref ref-type="table" rid="ta1-ehp0112-001589">Appendix</xref> for gene nomenclature and Affymetrix probe sets.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="ehp0112-001589f8"/></fig><fig id="f9-ehp0112-001589" position="float"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><title>Summary of the transcriptional program associated with E<sub>2</sub>-induced uterine growth showing the successive regulation of genes with distinct molecular functions.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="ehp0112-001589f9"/></fig><table-wrap id="t1-ehp0112-001589" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Quantitative histologic analysis of mitotic figures in uterine cells after exposure to E<sub>2</sub> for 8, 24, 48, and 72 hr.<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tfn2-ehp0112-001589"><italic><sup>a</sup></italic></xref></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr valign="bottom"><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">Mitosis/mm<sup>2</sup> (mean &#x000b1; SD)
<hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Time (hr)</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AO (5 mL)</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">E<sub>2</sub> (400 &#x003bc;g)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.36 &#x000b1; 1.81</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.51 &#x000b1; 0.41</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.86 &#x000b1; 5.05</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.15 &#x000b1; 6.37<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tfn3-ehp0112-001589">**</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">48</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.81 &#x000b1; 0.83</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.46 &#x000b1; 3.26</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">72</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.88 &#x000b1; 2.28</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.67 &#x000b1; 1.77</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn1-ehp0112-001589"><p>Quantitative mitotic index data were derived from four animals per group.</p></fn><fn id="tfn2-ehp0112-001589"><label>a</label><p>Data were assessed for statistical significance using ANOVA and a two-sided Student <italic>t</italic>-test (see &#x0201c;Materials and Methods&#x0201d;).</p></fn><fn id="tfn3-ehp0112-001589"><label>**</label><p><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="ta1-ehp0112-001589" position="float"><caption><p><bold>Appendix.</bold> Gene nomenclature and Affymetrix probe sets for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4-ehp0112-001589">Figures 4</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f8-ehp0112-001589">8</xref>.<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tfn4-ehp0112-001589"><italic><sup>a</sup></italic></xref></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr valign="bottom"><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gene symbol</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Affymetrix Probe Set</th><th align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gene description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4-ehp0112-001589">Figure 4B</xref> &#x02014;Signaling components</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">IL17R</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99992_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">interleukin 17 receptor</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RAP1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">160822_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rap1, GTPase-activating protein 1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">DEXRAS1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99032_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RAS, dexamethasone-induced 1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MKP1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">104598_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">dual specificity phosphatase 1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">WNT4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">103238_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">wingless-related MMTV integration site 4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">IGFBP10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92777_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">cysteine rich protein 61</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PIP92</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99109_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">immediate early response 2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PIM3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">96841_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">similar to serine/threonine-protein kinase pim-3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ARHU</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">96747_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ras homolog gene family, member U</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CISH3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">162206_f_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">cytokine inducible SH2-containing protein 3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NAB2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100962_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ngfi-A binding protein 2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SOCS3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92232_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">cytokine inducible SH2-containing protein 3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">EPLG2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">98407_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ligand for receptor tyrosine kinase ELK</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">IL17R</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99991_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">interleukin 17 receptor</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CDKN1A</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">98067_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">cyclin-dependent kinase inhibitor 1A (P21)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CDKN1A</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94881_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">cyclin-dependent kinase inhibitor 1A (P21)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">WSB1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">98946_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">WD-40-repeat-containing protein with a SOCS box</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">VEGF</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">103520_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">vascular endothelial growth factor A</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GADD45</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">102292_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">growth arrest and DNA-damage-inducible 45</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SYT</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99610_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">synovial sarcoma translocation, chromosome 18</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SOCS1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92832_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">cytokine inducible SH2-containing protein 1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GADD45g</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">101979_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">growth arrest and DNA-damage-inducible 45 gamma</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GLY96</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94384_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">immediate early response 3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAPKAP2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">160353_i_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAP kinase-activated protein kinase 2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">KLK22</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">101289_f_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">epidermal growth factor binding protein type 1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TROB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99532_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">tob family</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RGS3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">160747_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">regulator of G-protein signaling 3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GNA13</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100514_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">guanine nucleotide binding protein, alpha 13</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RAB11A</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">96238_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RAB11a, member RAS oncogene family</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PLGF</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92909_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">placental growth factor</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">BDKRB1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">101748_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">bradykinin B1 subtype receptor</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CF3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">97689_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">coagulation factor III</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PDK4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">102049_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pyruvate dehydrogenase kinase, isoenzyme 4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HERPUD1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95057_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">homocysteine-inducible, endoplasmic reticulum stress-inducible, ubiquitin-like domain member 1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MYD116</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">160463_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">myeloid differentiation primary response gene 116</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NORE1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">102028_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ras association (RalGDS/AF-6) domain family 5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NET1A</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94223_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">neuroepithelial cell transforming gene 1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GEM</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92534_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GTP binding protein (gene overexpressed in skeletal muscle)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SNRK</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">97429_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SNF related kinase</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ALASH</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">93500_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">aminolevulinic acid synthase 1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NTTP1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">161171_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">dual specificity phosphatase 8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAPKAP2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95721_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAP kinase-activated protein kinase 2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MEK1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92585_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">mitogen activated protein kinase kinase 1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RGSr</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94378_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">regulator of G-protein signaling 16</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RASSF1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">102379_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ras association (RalGDS/AF-6) domain family 1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NGEF</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">93178_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">neuronal guanine nucleotide exchange factor</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">C-KIT</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99956_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">kit oncogene</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NOTCH1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">97497_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Notch gene homolog 1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">BTG3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">96146_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B-cell translocation gene 3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PC4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">160092_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">interferon-related developmental regulator 1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SGK</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">97890_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">serum/glucocorticoid regulated kinase</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ADM</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">102798_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">adrenomedullin</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ANGPT2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92210_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">angiopoietin 2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">UBQLN1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95601_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ubiquilin 1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">THBS1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">160469_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">thrombospondin</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ROCK2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">98504_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">rho-associated coiled-coil forming kinase 2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SNK</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92310_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">serum-inducible kinase</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAP2K3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">93315_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">mitogen activated protein kinase kinase 3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ENG</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100134_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">endoglin</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PTDSR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95486_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">phosphatidylserine receptor</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SWIP2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">160296_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">WD-40-repeat-containing protein with a SOCS box</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AKT</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100970_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">thymoma viral proto-oncogene 1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RHOC</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">96056_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ras homolog gene family, member C</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TGFB2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">93300_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">transforming growth factor, beta 2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">EPCR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">98018_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">protein C receptor, endothelial</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">KLK6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100061_f_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">kallikrein 6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GALN</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100407_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">galanin</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NEDD4B</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">103907_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">neural precursor cell expressed, developmentally down-regulated gene 4-like</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">KLK22</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95775_f_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">kallikrein 22</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">KLK9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94716_f_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">kallikrein 9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MCP1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">102736_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">platelet-derived growth factor-inducible protein JE</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TIE1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99936_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">tyrosine kinase receptor 1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RAMP1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">104680_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">receptor (calcitonin) activity modifying protein 1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PGF</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">97769_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">prostaglandin F receptor</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PDGF&#x003b1;RA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95079_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">platelet derived growth factor receptor, alpha polypeptide</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">OB-RGRP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">93600_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">leptin receptor</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ERK1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">101834_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">mitogen activated protein kinase 3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GRB7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">103095_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">growth factor receptor bound protein 7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ADCY6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">102321_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">adenylate cyclase 6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TIE1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">161184_f_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">tyrosine kinase receptor 1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GNAI1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">104412_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">guanine nucleotide binding protein, alpha inhibiting 1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ADCY7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">103392_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">adenylate cyclase 7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TIE2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">102720_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">endothelial-specific receptor tyrosine kinase</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GPCR26</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100435_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">endothelial differentiation, lysophosphatidic acid G-protein-coupled receptor, 2</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4-ehp0112-001589">Figure 4C</xref>&#x02014;Transcription factors</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GIF</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99603_g_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TGFB inducible early growth response</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GIF</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99602_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TGFB inducible early growth response</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ETS2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94246_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">E26 avian leukemia oncogene 2, 3&#x02019; domain</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ID1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100050_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">inhibitor of DNA binding 1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SMAD7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92216_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAD homolog 7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">C-JUN</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100130_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Jun oncogene</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">BRF2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">160273_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">zinc finger protein 36, C3H type-like 2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">IRF8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">98002_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">interferon concensus sequence binding protein</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AGP/EBP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92925_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CCAAT/enhancer binding protein (C/EBP), beta</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">C-FOS</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">160901_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">c-fos oncogene</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">KROX24</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">98579_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">zinc finger protein Krox-24</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FOSB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">103990_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FBJ osteosarcoma oncogene B</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NR4A1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">102371_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N10 nuclear hormonal binding receptor</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SOX18</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">161025_f_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SRY-box containing gene 18</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SOX18</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">104408_s_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SRY-box containing gene 18</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">KROX20</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">102661_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Early growth response 2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ESG</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">104623_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">transducin-like enhancer of split 3, homolog of Drosophila E(spl)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FOG</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">97974_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">zinc finger protein, multitype 1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NCOR2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95129_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nuclear receptor co-repressor 2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SOX11</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">101631_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SRY-box containing gene 11</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">C/EBP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94466_f_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CCAAT/enhancer binding protein alpha (C/EBP), related sequence 1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PRX2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">103327_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">paired related homeobox 2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ATF4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100599_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">activating transcription factor 4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">STAT5B</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100422_i_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">signal transducer and activation of transcription 5A</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HEY1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95671_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hairy/enhancer-of-split related with YRPW motif 1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ATF5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">103006_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">activating transcription factor 5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">C/EBP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">98447_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CCAAT/enhancer binding protein</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RIP140</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">103288_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nuclear receptor interacting protein 1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CRTR1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">103761_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tcfcp2-related transcriptional repressor 1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MEF2A</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">93852_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">myocyte enhancer factor 2A</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TIS11</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92830_s_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">zinc finger protein 36</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">STAT5B</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100423_f_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">signal transducer and activation of transcription 5A</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ATF3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">104155_f_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">activating transcription factor 3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CART1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100005_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TNF receptor associated factor 4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">JUNB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">102362_i_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">transcription factor junB</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5-ehp0112-001589">Figure 5A</xref>&#x02014;RNA synthesis</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SFPQ</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99621_s_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">splicing factor proline/glutamine rich (polypyrimidine tract binding protein associated)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">U2AF1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">97486_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">U2 small nuclear ribonucleoprotein auxiliary factor (U2AF), 35 kDa</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RBMXP1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">160192_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RNA binding motif protein, X chromosome retrogene</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">DDX21</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94361_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">DEAD/H (Asp-Glu-Ala-Asp/His) box polypeptide 21 (RNA helicase II/Gu)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">DDX3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">101542_f_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">DEAD (aspartate-glutamate-alanine-aspartate) box polypeptide 3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NSAP1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94985_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NS1-associated protein 1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MKI67 bp</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">93342_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mki67 (FHA domain) interacting nucleolar phosphoprotein</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ELAVL1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94001_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ELAV (embryonic lethal, abnormal vision, Drosophila)-like 1 (Hu antigen R)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PSP1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">103393_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">paraspeckle protein 1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SRP20</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">101003_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">splicing factor, arginine/serine-rich 3 (SRp20)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">JKTBP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">96084_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">heterogeneous nuclear ribonucleoprotein D-like</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RPA2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92225_f_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RNA polymerase 1&#x02013;2 (128 kDa subunit)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RALY</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">98511_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">hnRNP-associated with lethal yellow</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SFRS10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95791_s_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">splicing factor, arginine/serine-rich 10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FBL</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">160503_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">fibrillarin</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SNRPA1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">101506_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">small nuclear ribonucleoprotein polypeptide A&#x02019;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TASR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">98048_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">neural-salient serine/arginine-rich</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RPB10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">93551_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RNA polymerase II subunit 10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AUF1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94303_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">heterogeneous nuclear ribonucleoprotein D</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HRMT1L2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">96696_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">heterogeneous nuclear ribonucleoproteins methyltransferase-like 2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CGI-110</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95714_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">pre-mRNA branch site protein p14</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SMN</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">103620_s_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">survival motor neuron</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RPB8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">97254_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RNA binding motif protein</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RNPS1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">93518_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ribonucleic acid binding protein S1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NCL</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">160521_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nucleolin</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RPA1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">93620_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RNA polymerase 1&#x02013;4 (194 kDa subunit)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HNRPA2B1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">93118_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">heterogeneous nuclear ribonucleoprotein A2/B1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SNRPD1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100577_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">small nuclear ribonucleoprotein D1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">H/ALAsnRNP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">97824_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nucleolar protein family A, member 2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TAF10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">103910_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TAFII30</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">DDX24</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99096_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">DEAD/H (Asp-Glu-Ala-Asp/His) box polypeptide 13 (RNA helicase A)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5-ehp0112-001589">Figure 5B</xref></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAD4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99024_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Max dimerization protein 4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">EZH1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100486_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">enhancer of zeste homolog 1 (Drosophila)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HDA1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">104376_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">histone deacetylase 5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AUH</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">96650_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AU RNA binding protein/enoyl-coenzyme A hydratase</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TGIF</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">101502_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TG interacting factor</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5-ehp0112-001589">Figure 5C</xref>&#x02014;Nuclear import/export</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">POM121</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">96174_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nuclear pore membrane protein 121</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NXF1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">101079_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nuclear RNA export factor 1 homolog (<italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">IMPORTINa3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">96010_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">karyopherin (importin) alpha 3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RAE1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">160466_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RNA export 1 homolog (S. pombe)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">IMPORTINa2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92790_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">karyopherin (importin) alpha 2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">G3BP2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94913_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ras-GTPase-activating protein (GAP120) SH3-domain binding protein 2</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5-ehp0112-001589">Figure 5D</xref>&#x02014;Protein translation</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">eIF3S7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99101_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">eukaryotic translation initiation factor 3, subunit 7 (zeta, 66/67kDa)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">eIF2B</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">160365_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">eukaryotic translation initiation factor 2, subunit 2 (beta, 38kDa)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">eIF3S4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">96883_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">eukaryotic translation initiation factor 3, subunit 4 (delta, 44kDa)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">EBNA1-bp2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">96297_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">EBNA1 binding protein 2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GLNRS</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">96628_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">glutamyl-prolyl-tRNA synthetase</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NAT1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100535_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">eukaryotic translation initiation factor 4, gamma 2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">eIF3S9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">93973_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">eukaryotic translation initiation factor 3, subunit 9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RPS18b</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95159_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ribosomal protein S18b</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">VALRS</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">97894_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">valyl-tRNA synthetase 2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RPL12</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">160431_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">mitochondrial ribosomal protein L12</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">eIF1A</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">93058_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">eukaryotic translation initiation factor 1A</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">eRF1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">160451_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">translation releasing factor eRF1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">eIF1A</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">103708_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">eukaryotic translation initiation factor 1A</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">eIF6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94826_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">integrin beta 4 binding protein</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">eRF1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">98608_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">translation releasing factor eRF1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RPL20</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94875_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">mitochondrial ribosomal protein L20</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PHERS</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94494_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">phenylalanine-tRNA synthetase-like</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ASNS</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95133_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">asparagine synthetase</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">eIF3S10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94250_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">eukaryotic translation initiation factor 3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NOP56</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95109_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nucleolar protein 5A</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">eIF2AS1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94253_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">eukaryotic translation initiation factor 2A</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RRS1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">96778_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">regulator for ribosome resistance homolog (S. cerevisiae)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">eRF1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">96755_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">translation releasing factor eRF1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">eRF1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">96754_s_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">translation releasing factor eRF1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SUI1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92855_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">suppressor of initiator codon mutations, related sequence 1 (<italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RPL11</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">98876_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">mitochondrial ribosomal protein L11</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RPL52</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">97443_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">mitochondrial ribosomal protein L52</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5-ehp0112-001589">Figure 5E</xref>&#x02014;Protein folding</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CCT3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">98153_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">chaperonin subunit 3 (gamma)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FKBP4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92808_f_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FK506 binding protein 4 (59 kDa)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CCT7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">160562_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">chaperonin subunit 7 (eta)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PPID</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">97445_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">peptidylprolyl isomerase D (cyclophilin D)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CCT10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92829_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">heat shock 10 kDa protein 1 (chaperonin 10)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CCT8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">160102_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">chaperonin subunit 8 (theta)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CCT6A</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">162279_f_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">chaperonin subunit 6a (zeta)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CCT3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">161238_f_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">chaperonin subunit 3 (gamma)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5-ehp0112-001589">Figure 5F</xref>&#x02014;Protein degradation</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PAD1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">97274_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26S proteasome-associated pad1 homolog</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PSMB5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">101558_s_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">proteasome (prosome, macropain) subunit, beta type 5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PSMD4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94302_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">proteasome (prosome, macropain) 26S subunit, non-ATPase, 4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PSMB3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94025_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">proteasome (prosome, macropain) subunit, beta type 3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SUG1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">160534_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">protease (prosome, macropain) 26S subunit, ATPase 5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PSMB6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">101992_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">proteasome (prosome, macropain) subunit, beta type 6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PSMB2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94219_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">proteasome (prosome, macropain) subunit, beta type 2</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f6-ehp0112-001589">Figure 6B</xref>&#x02014;DNA replication and cell division</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SAKB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">98996_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">serine/threonine kinase 18</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RRM2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">102001_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ribonucleotide reductase M2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CAF1 p60</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100890_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">chromatin assembly factor, p60 subunit</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ORC6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95712_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">origin recognition complex, subunit 6-like (S. cerevisiae)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PCNA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">101065_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">proliferating cell nuclear antigen</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MCM2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">93112_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">mini chromosome maintenance deficient 2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CDC6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">103821_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">cell division cycle 6 homolog (S. cerevisiae)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MCM4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">93041_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">mini chromosome maintenance deficient 4 homolog</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MCM3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">160496_s_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">mini chromosome maintenance deficient (S. cerevisiae)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MCM3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100062_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">mini chromosome maintenance deficient (S. cerevisiae)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TOPB1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">103071_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">topoisomerase (DNA) II binding protein</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CHK1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">103064_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">checkpoint kinase 1 homolog (S. pombe)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MCM5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100156_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">mini chromosome maintenance deficient 5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CKS1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">97468_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CDC28 protein kinase 1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ORC1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92458_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">origin recognition complex, subunit 1-like (S. cerevisiae)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RRM1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100612_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ribonucleotide reductase M1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FEN1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">97327_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">flap structure specific endonuclease 1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GEMININ</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">160069_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">geminin</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">E2F1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">102963_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">E2F transcription factor 1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PLK1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">93099_f_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">polo-like kinase homolog (Drosophila)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CCNB1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">160159_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">cyclin B1, related sequence 1</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f6-ehp0112-001589">Figure 6C</xref>&#x02014;Cell-cycle regulators</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CCND1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94232_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">cyclin D1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CDC34</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94048_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">cell division cycle 34 homolog</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">KIP2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95471_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">cyclin-dependent kinase inhibitor 1C (P57)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CCNG2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">98478_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">cyclin G2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">KIP1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">161010_r_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">cyclin-dependent kinase inhibitor (p27)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CCNI</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94819_f_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">cyclin I</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f6-ehp0112-001589">Figure 6D</xref>&#x02014;Apoptosis</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CASP2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99049_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">caspase 2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NIX</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">96255_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">BCL2/adenovirus E1B 19 kDa-interacting protein 3-like</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">APR3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">160271_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">apoptosis related protein APR3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TNFSF12</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">93917_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">tumor necrosis factor (ligand) superfamily, member 12</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PDCD4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">103029_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">programmed cell death 4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MIAP2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">102734_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">baculoviral IAP repeat-containing 3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MTD</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">98031_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bcl-2-related ovarian killer protein</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SDNSF</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">97451_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">neural stem cell derived neuronal survival protein</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">DAD1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">96008_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">defender against Apoptotic Death 1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AAC11</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">101035_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">apoptosis inhibitor 5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">BAG3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">96167_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bcl2-associated athanogene 3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">BAG2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">161129_r_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">similar to BAG-family molecular chaperone regulator-2</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f7-ehp0112-001589">Figure 7A</xref>&#x02014;Cytoarchitecture</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MDEG2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99910_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">amiloride-sensitive cation channel 1, neuronal (degenerin)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAT8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">103059_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FXYD domain-containing ion transport regulator 3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CLCA3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">162287_r_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">chloride channel calcium activated 3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CD133</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">93389_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">prominin</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CD133</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">93390_g_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">prominin</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PIGF</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">104725_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ras-like protein</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">DSG2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">104480_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">desmoglein 2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAN2B1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99562_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">mannosidase 2, alpha B1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CLDN4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">101410_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">claudin 4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CLDN7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99561_f_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">claudin 7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SPRR2E</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100723_f_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">small proline-rich protein 2E</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SPRR2J</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">101755_f_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">small proline-rich protein 2J</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SPRR2A</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">101025_f_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">small proline-rich protein 2A</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TROP2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">103648_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">tumor-associated calcium signal transducer 2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SPRR2I</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95794_f_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">small proline-rich protein 2I</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SPRR2C</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">101761_f_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">small proline-rich protein 2C</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SPRR2A</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">101024_i_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">small proline-rich protein 2A</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">LRG</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">97420_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">leucine-rich alpha-2-glycoprotein</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TROP2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">160651_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">tumor-associated calcium signal transducer 2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SPRR2G</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">101754_f_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">small proline-rich protein 2G</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SPRR2F</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94120_s_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">small proline-rich protein 2F</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">BGP1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">102805_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CEA-related cell adhesion molecule 1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">BGP1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">102804_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CEA-related cell adhesion molecule 1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">BGP1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">102806_g_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CEA-related cell adhesion molecule 1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">BGP2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">101908_s_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CEA-related cell adhesion molecule 2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CX26</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">98423_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">connexin 26</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MUC1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">102918_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">mucin 1, transmembrane</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SPP1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">97519_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">secreted phosphoprotein 1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CLU</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">161294_f_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">clusterin</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CLU</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95286_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">clusterin</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CFTR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94757_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">cystic fibrosis transmembrane conductance regulator homolog</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">KRT19</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92550_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">keratin complex 1, acidic, gene 19</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">KRT19</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">102121_f_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">keratin complex 1, acidic, gene 19</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SPRR1A</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">160909_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">small proline-rich protein 1A</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GALNT3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">162313_f_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">UDP-N-acetyl-alpha-D-galactosamine:polypeptide N-acetylgalactosaminyltransferase 3</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f7-ehp0112-001589">Figure 7B</xref>&#x02014;Defense responses</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PLGR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99926_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">polyimmunoglobulin receptor</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CTSL</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">101963_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">cathepsin L</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">LAMP1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100136_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">lysosomal membrane glycoprotein 2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CTSS</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">98543_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">cathepsin S</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GSTO1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">97819_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">glutathione S-transferase omega 1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GSTT2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">104603_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">glutathione S-transferase, theta 2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CTSH</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94834_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">cathepsin H</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">UGT1A1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99580_s_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">UDP glycosyltransferase 1 family, polypeptide A6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CD14</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">98088_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CD14 antigen</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">LGALS3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95706_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">lectin, galactose binding, soluble 3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PGLYRP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">104099_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">peptidoglycan recognition protein</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">LGMN</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">93261_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">legumain</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GARG16</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100981_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">interferon-induced protein with tetratricopeptide repeats</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">H2Q1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99378_f_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MHC beta-2-microglobulin</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ISGFG3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">103634_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">interferon dependent positive acting transcription factor 3 gamma</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">H2D1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">101886_f_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">histocompatibility 2, D region locus 1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">LYZP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">101753_s_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P lysozyme structural</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">LYZM</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100611_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">lysozyme M</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MLGP85</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">101389_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">scavenger receptor class B, member 2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">H2D1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">97540_f_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">histocompatibility 2, D region locus 1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CD68</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">103016_s_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CD68 antigen</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">LY6A</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">93078_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">lymphocyte antigen 6 complex, locus A</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MX1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">98417_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">myxovirus (influenza virus) resistance 1</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f7-ehp0112-001589">Figure 7C</xref>&#x02014;Chemoattractant cytokines</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MCP3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94761_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">monocyte chemoattractant protein 3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MCP1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">102736_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">platelet-derived growth factor-inducible protein JE</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">EOTAXIN</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92742_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">small inducible cytokine a11</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f7-ehp0112-001589">Figure 7D</xref>&#x02014;Complement</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CFI</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99927_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">complement component factor i</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">C3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">93497_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">complement component 3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CFH-related</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92291_f_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">complement component factor-related</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">C2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">103673_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">complement component 2 (within H-2S)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CFH-related</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">101853_f_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">complement component factor h</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">C1QA</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">98562_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">complement component 1, q subcomponent, alpha polypeptide</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">C1QB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">96020_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">complement component 1, q subcomponent, beta polypeptide</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">C4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">103033_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">complement component 4 (within H-2S)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">C1QC</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92223_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">complement component 1, q subcomponent, c polypeptide</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CFH-related</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94743_f_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">complement component factor-related</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f7-ehp0112-001589">Figure 7E</xref>&#x02014;Iron homeostasis</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92851_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ceruloplasmin</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">LTF</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">101115_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">lactotransferrin</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">LCN2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">160564_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">lipocalin 2/24p3 gene.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f8-ehp0112-001589">Figure 8B</xref></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ETS2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94246_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">E26 avian leukemia oncogene 2, 3&#x02019; domain</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ATF3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">104155_f_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">activating transcription factor 3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">JUN</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100130_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Jun oncogene</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">JUNB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">102362_i_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">transcription factor junB</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FOS</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">160901_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">c-fos oncogene</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FOSB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">103990_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FBJ osteosarcoma oncogene B</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ATF5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">103006_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">activating transcription factor 5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ATF4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100599_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">activating transcription factor 4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SPRR2I</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95794_f_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">small proline-rich protein 2I</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SPRR2C</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">101761_f_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">small proline-rich protein 2C</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SPRR2G</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">101754_f_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">small proline-rich protein 2G</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SPRR2J</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">101755_f_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">small proline-rich protein 2J</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SPRR2A</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">101025_f_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">small proline-rich protein 2A</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SPRR2F</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">94120_s_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">small proline-rich protein 2F</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SPRR2E</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100723_f_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">small proline-rich protein 2E</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SPRR1A</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">160909_at</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">small proline-rich protein 1A</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn4-ehp0112-001589"><label>a</label><p>Gene annotations were derived by interrogation of the NetAffx (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22-ehp0112-001589">Liu et al. 2003</xref>) database; http://www.affymetrix.com/analysis/index.affx and by homology searching of nucleotide sequence databases (BLASTn; http://www.ncbi.nih.gov/BLAST/) using Affymetrix probe target sequences.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></floats-group></article>
