<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Ecol</journal-id><journal-title>BMC Ecology</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1472-6785</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15987507</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1185528</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1472-6785-5-5</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1472-6785-5-5</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Genetic diversity in populations of asexual and sexual bag worm moths (Lepidoptera: Psychidae)</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Grapputo</surname><given-names>Alessandro</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>grapputo@cc.jyu.fi</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kumpulainen</surname><given-names>Tomi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>Tokumpul@bytl.jyu.fi</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mappes</surname><given-names>Johanna</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>Mappes@bytl.jyu.fi</email></contrib><contrib id="A4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Parri</surname><given-names>Silja</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>silja.parri@valpuri.net</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Biological and Environmental Science, University of Jyv&#x000e4;skyl&#x000e4;, P.O. Box 35, FI-40014 Jyv&#x000e4;skyl&#x000e4;, Finland</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2005</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>29</day><month>6</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1472-6785/5/5"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>17</day><month>9</month><year>2004</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>29</day><month>6</month><year>2005</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2005 Grapputo et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2005</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Grapputo et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>
               Grapputo
               Alessandro
               
               grapputo@cc.jyu.fi
            </dc:author><dc:title>
            Genetic diversity in populations of asexual and sexual bag worm moths (Lepidoptera: Psychidae)
         </dc:title><dc:date>2005</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>BMC Ecology 5(1): 5-. (2005)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1472-6785(2005)5:1&#x0003c;5&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1472-6785</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Despite the two-fold cost of sex, most of the higher animals reproduce sexually. The advantage of sex has been suggested to be its ability, through recombination, to generate greater genetic diversity than asexuality, thus enhancing adaptation in a changing environment. We studied the genetic diversity and the population structure of three closely related species of bag worm moths: two strictly sexual (<italic>Dahlica charlottae </italic>and <italic>Siederia rupicolella</italic>) and one strictly asexual (<italic>D. fennicella</italic>). These species compete for the same resources and share the same parasitoids.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Allelic richness was comparable between the sexual species but it was higher than in the asexual species. All species showed high heterozygote deficiency and a large variation was observed among <italic>F</italic><sub>IS </sub>values across loci and populations. Large genetic differentiation was observed between populations confirming the poor dispersal ability of these species. The asexual species showed lower genotype diversity than the sexual species. Nevertheless, genotype diversity was high in all asexual populations.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>The three different species show a similar population structure characterised by high genetic differentiation among populations and low dispersal. Most of the populations showed high heterozygote deficiency likely due to the presence of null alleles at most of the loci and/or to the Wahlund effect. Although the parthenogenetic <italic>D. fennicella </italic>shows reduced genetic diversity compared to the sexual species, it still shows surprisingly high genotype diversity. While we can not totally rule out the presence of cryptic sex, would explain this high genotype diversity, we never observed sex in the parthenogenetic <italic>D. fennicella</italic>, nor was there any other evidence of this. Alternatively, a non-clonal parthenogenetic reproduction, such as automictic thelytoky, could explain the high genotypic diversity observed in <italic>D. fennicella</italic>.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Parthenogenetic females have a two-fold advantage over sexual females because they produce only the fecund sex while sexual females produce also males. The elimination of sex is predicted whenever the two strategies compete unless there are factors that overcome this disadvantage. Nevertheless, most of the higher animals reproduce sexually[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. This leads to a fundamental question which continues to puzzle evolutionary biologists: how is sex maintained? A large body of theories seek to explain the maintenance of sex [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>].</p><p>Advantages of sexual reproduction arise from genetic recombination in cross-fertilisation, which purges deleterious mutation and increases genetic variability in the population [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>], enhancing adaptation in a changing environment. The idea that sexual reproduction and recombination may be favoured in changing environments has been the subject of several papers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. If a trait is subjected to stabilising selection, genetic variability introduces a genetic load as a consequence of the produced phenotypes that deviate from the optimum [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. However, in a varying environment that exerts directional selection on a trait, genetic variability is essential because the response to selection will be proportional to the additive genetic variance in the population [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. Under the mutation accumulation theory, the persistence of asexual lineages is more problematic unless asexuals are able to minimise the competition with sexuals through high dispersal rates [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>].</p><p>Under the Red Queen hypothesis for sex [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>], we should expect that heavy directional selection exerted by parasites can favour greater genetic variability in host populations. Parasites are more likely to infect the most common genotypes while rare genotypes, produced by sexual females, may escape infection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>]. Asexual reproduction is expected to be an unstable long term strategy since asexual females can only generate offspring with new genotypes through mutation.</p><p>The parasite hypothesis relies on several critical assumptions: the all-else-equal assumption and assumptions about the population structure and the genetic diversity of sexual and asexual populations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>]. The all-else-equal assumption (e.g. production of equal number and viability of offspring) depends on: how the asexuals originate, the type of parthenogenesis, and the degree of polyploidy of the asexuals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. The difference in population genetic structure between competing sexuals and asexuals may determine difference in the parasite infection load. Asexual hosts can persist in the long term, even in the presence of parasites, if they out-disperse their parasites [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]. The parasite hypothesis also assumes that sexual populations harbour higher levels of genetic diversity than asexual populations. The parasite hypothesis does not select for sex per se, but for diversity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>]. Thus, high clonal diversity could erode any advantage of sex. Howard and Lively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>] theoretically showed that host-parasite coevolution could lead to the accumulation of clones with different resistance genotypes and, in turn, to the elimination of sexual populations.</p><p>Few systems with coexisting sexual and asexual competitors are known. So, comparisons of genetic diversity between coexisting sexual and asexual populations are scarce: e.g. the freshwater snails, <italic>Potamopyrgus antipodarum </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>] and genus <italic>Campeloma </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>] and the aphid <italic>Rhopalosiphum padi </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>]. Additional comparisons are needed to further evaluate the parasite hypothesis for sex.</p><p>Bag worm moths (Lepidoptera: Psychidae) provide an attractive case for investigating the coexistence of sexual and asexual reproduction in the same locations. In Lepidoptera, parthenogenetic reproduction is very rare. However, in the family Psychidae and especially among <italic>Dahlica </italic>species, parthenogenesis seems to have evolved several times [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>]. A parthenogenetic (<italic>Dahlica fennicella</italic>, Suomalainen 1980) and two sexual species (<italic>Siederia rupicolella</italic>, Sauter 1954 and <italic>D</italic>. <italic>charlottae</italic>, Meier 1957) are common in Finland and often coexist in the same habitat. In these small insects (3&#x02013;6 mm), adult females are always wingless, sessile and incapable of dispersing. Males are always winged but their dispersing ability is very limited and they can only fly short distances (between 10 and 100 m). Life cycle from egg to adult takes from one to two years, but the adults only live 3&#x02013;6 days [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>]. <italic>S. rupicolella </italic>and <italic>D. fennicella </italic>are very difficult to separate from each other and the only distinctive characters are their reproductive mode and genetic markers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]. In central Finland, these bag worm moth species occur patchily in wooded habitats. The proportion of sexually and parthenogenetically reproducing species varies between locales from the total absence of the sexual species to only their presence.</p><p>Psychid larvae are often infected by at least two common species of Hymenopteran parasitoids, e.g. <italic>Orthizema </italic>spp. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]. Kumpulainen <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>] found a strong positive correlation between parasite prevalence and the occurrence of sexual reproduction in Finnish bag worm moth populations for three consecutive years. <italic>S. rupicolella </italic>(sexual) was more abundant where parasitoids were more common, whereas <italic>D. fennicella </italic>(asexual) was more common in localities where parasitoids were scarce or absent. This result could argue in favour of the parasite hypothesis for the maintenance of sex. In light of this previous result, we investigated the genetic variability and the population structure of three closely related species of bag worm moths, two strictly sexual (<italic>Siederia rupicolella </italic>and <italic>Dahlica charlottae</italic>) and one parthenogenetic (<italic>D. fennicella</italic>) using isozyme variation.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>Genetic variability</title><p>Thirteen loci from ten isozymes were detected (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). All were polymorphic in the two sexual species whereas twelve were polymorphic in the asexual species, with only fumaric acid (<italic>FUM</italic>) being monomorphic. No more than two bands were observed at all loci in the asexual <italic>D. fennicella</italic>, thus it is possible that this species is not tetraploid as are its relatives <italic>D. lichenella </italic>and <italic>D. triquetrella </italic>(tetraploid race) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>]. Ewens-Watterson [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>] and Chakraborty's [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>] test of neutrality indicated that the polymorphism observed, at the scale investigated, can confidently be assumed to be neutral.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Isoenzymatic loci scored for <italic>Siederia rupicolella</italic>, <italic>Dahlica charlottae</italic> and <italic>D. fennicella</italic>. Recipes for buffers used are found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cladocera.uoguelph.ca/tools/default.htm"/></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="left">Enzyme</td><td align="left">E.C.*</td><td align="left">Locus</td><td align="left">Buffer</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">- Isocitrate Dehydrogenase</td><td align="left">1.1.1.42</td><td align="left"><italic>IDH</italic></td><td align="left">Phosphate 0.02 M pH 7.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">- Diaphorase</td><td align="left">1.1.1.40</td><td align="left"><italic>DIA</italic></td><td align="left">Phosphate 0.02 M pH 7.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">- Glucose-6-Phosphate Dehydrogenase</td><td align="left">1.1.1.49</td><td align="left"><italic>G6PDH</italic></td><td align="left">Tris-Maleate-EDTA- MgCl<sub>2 </sub>0.2 M pH 7.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">- 6-Phosphogluconate Dehydrogenase</td><td align="left">1.1.1.44</td><td align="left"><italic>6PGDH</italic></td><td align="left">Tris-Maleate-EDTA- MgCl<sub>2 </sub>0.2 M pH 7.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">- Aspartate Aminotransferase</td><td align="left">2.6.1.1</td><td align="left"><italic>GOT</italic></td><td align="left">Citrate Phosphate 0.04 M pH 6.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left">- Phosphoglucomutase</td><td align="left">5.4.2.2</td><td align="left"><italic>PGM</italic></td><td align="left">Tris-Maleate-EDTA- MgCl<sub>2 </sub>0.2 M pH 7.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">- Malate Dehydrogenase NADP+</td><td align="left">1.1.1.40</td><td align="left"><italic>ME1</italic><break/><italic>ME2</italic><break/><italic>ME3</italic></td><td align="left">Tris Maleate 0.1 M pH 5.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">- Malate Dehydrogenase</td><td align="left">1.1.1.37</td><td align="left"><italic>MDH MDH2</italic></td><td align="left">Tris-Maleate-EDTA- MgCl<sub>2 </sub>0.2 M pH 7.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">- Glucose-6-Phosphate Isomerase</td><td align="left">5.3.1.9</td><td align="left"><italic>GPI</italic></td><td align="left">Tris-Maleate-EDTA- MgCl<sub>2 </sub>0.2 M pH 7.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">- Fumarate Hydratase</td><td align="left">4.2.1.2</td><td align="left"><italic>FUM</italic></td><td align="left">Tris Maleate 0.1 M pH 5.3</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>* Enzyme Commission Number</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The estimates of genetic variability are shown in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>. Sufficient sampling of all three species in each population for population genetic analyses was not possible. There were two reasons for this; 1) although all three species were present to some extent in each location, they were not all abundant, particularly <italic>D. fennicella</italic>, and 2) females of the sexual species <italic>S. rupicolella </italic>are difficult to separate from <italic>D. fennicella </italic>without observing their mating behaviour. While sexual females secrete pheromones to attract males and do not lay eggs before mating, parthenogenetic females lay eggs in their larval case immediately after hatching from pupa. Species determination for sexual females was performed by experimental mating with a male. Because the adults are very short lived, females can mated with males hatching only few days apart restricting the sample size.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Sample sizes, average number of alleles per locus, allelic richness, proportion of different genotypes (k), Simpson's index (D) and Evenness (E) (D and E calculated for asexual <italic>D. fennicella </italic>only), observed heterozygosity (H<sub>o</sub>), gene diversity (H<sub>s</sub>), and <italic>F</italic><sub>IS </sub>are presented for each population of each sexual species. In the last column are presented the averaged values per species and the <italic>F</italic><sub>ST </sub>values among populations.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td></td><td align="center" colspan="15"><bold>Jyv&#x000e4;skyl&#x000e4;</bold></td><td align="center" colspan="6"><bold>Orimattila</bold></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center"><italic>D. charlottae</italic></td><td align="center"><bold>K&#x000f6;</bold></td><td></td><td align="center"><bold>Lv1</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Lv2</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Lv3</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Lv4</bold></td><td></td><td align="center"><bold>Muu</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Hj</bold></td><td></td><td align="center"><bold>Pih</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Isa</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Sip1</bold></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center"><bold>Sal</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Tuk</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Vilj</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Vill</bold></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="22"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="center">N</td><td align="center">18</td><td></td><td align="center">11</td><td align="center">9</td><td align="center">14</td><td align="center">10</td><td></td><td align="center">12</td><td align="center">16</td><td></td><td align="center">14</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">7</td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">14</td><td align="center">9</td><td align="center">13</td><td align="center">11</td><td></td><td align="center">11.786</td></tr><tr><td align="center">N. alleles &#x000b1; (S.E.)</td><td align="center">3.846 (1.039)</td><td></td><td align="center">3.077 (0.485)</td><td align="center">2.692 (0.537)</td><td align="center">2.923 (0.611)</td><td align="center">3.000 (0.553)</td><td></td><td align="center">3.154 (0.761)</td><td align="center">3.692 (0.888)</td><td></td><td align="center">3.077 (0.564)</td><td align="center">2.154 (0.281)</td><td align="center">2.692 (0.511)</td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">3.462 (0.719)</td><td align="center">3.000 (0.707)</td><td align="center">3.231 (0.649)</td><td align="center">3.538 (0.860)</td><td></td><td align="center">5.6154 (1.4485)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Allelic richness</td><td align="center">3.029</td><td></td><td align="center">2.871</td><td align="center">2.543</td><td align="center">2.593</td><td align="center">2.765</td><td></td><td align="center">2.790</td><td align="center">3.049</td><td></td><td align="center">2.702</td><td align="center">2.119</td><td align="center">2.582</td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">2.877</td><td align="center">2.804</td><td align="center">2.884</td><td align="center">3.114</td><td></td><td align="center">2.766</td></tr><tr><td align="center">k</td><td align="center">1.000</td><td></td><td align="center">1.000</td><td align="center">0.889</td><td align="center">0.929</td><td align="center">1.000</td><td></td><td align="center">1.000</td><td align="center">1.000</td><td></td><td align="center">0.786</td><td align="center">1.000</td><td align="center">1.000</td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">1.000</td><td align="center">1.000</td><td align="center">1.000</td><td align="center">1.000</td><td></td><td align="center">0.972</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Ho &#x000b1; (S.E.)</td><td align="center">0.297 (0.077)</td><td></td><td align="center">0.307 (0.093)</td><td align="center">0.249 (0.087)</td><td align="center">0.295 (0.095)</td><td align="center">0.308 (0.081)</td><td></td><td align="center">0.245 (0.075)</td><td align="center">0.266 (0.070)</td><td></td><td align="center">0.251 (0.070)</td><td align="center">0.374 (0.109)</td><td align="center">0.393 (0.112)</td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">0.248 (0.063)</td><td align="center">0.274 (0.065)</td><td align="center">0.284 (0.087)</td><td align="center">0.285 (0.076)</td><td></td><td align="center">0.2955 (0.1046)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Hs &#x000b1; (S.E.)</td><td align="center">0.469 (0.107)</td><td></td><td align="center">0.548 (0.086)</td><td align="center">0.451 (0.102)</td><td align="center">0.437 (0.114)</td><td align="center">0.508 (0.110)</td><td></td><td align="center">0.447 (0.107)</td><td align="center">0.505 (0.127)</td><td></td><td align="center">0.502 (0.093)</td><td align="center">0.405 (0.087)</td><td align="center">0.425 (0.102)</td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">0.524 (0.080)</td><td align="center">0.468 (0.121)</td><td align="center">0.528 (0.099)</td><td align="center">0.558 (0.093)</td><td></td><td align="center">0.4851 (0.0841)</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><italic>F</italic><sub>ST </sub>(P)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">0.168 (&#x0003c;0.001)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">0.154 (&#x0003c;0.001)</td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">0.1530 (&#x0003c;0.001)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="22"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="center"><italic>S. rupicolella</italic></td><td></td><td align="center"><bold>Kv</bold></td><td></td><td align="center"><bold>Lv2</bold></td><td></td><td align="center"><bold>Lv4</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Lv5</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Muu</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Hj</bold></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center"><bold>Sip1</bold></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center"><bold>Vill</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Pen</bold></td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="22"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="center">N</td><td></td><td align="center">10</td><td></td><td align="center">14</td><td></td><td align="center">10</td><td align="center">9</td><td align="center">14</td><td align="center">17</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">26</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">11</td><td align="center">11</td><td align="center">13.556</td></tr><tr><td align="center">N. alleles &#x000b1; (S.E.)</td><td></td><td align="center">2.846 (0.337)</td><td></td><td align="center">3.000 (0.358)</td><td></td><td align="center">3.000 (0.340)</td><td align="center">2.385 (0.368)</td><td align="center">3.231 (0.426)</td><td align="center">3.385 (0.549)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">3.692 (0.634)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">2.538 (0.332)</td><td align="center">2.308 (0.208)</td><td align="center">2.932 (0.815)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Allelic richness</td><td></td><td align="center">2.742</td><td></td><td align="center">2.794</td><td></td><td align="center">2.783</td><td align="center">2.275</td><td align="center">2.914</td><td align="center">2.988</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">3.001</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">2.480</td><td align="center">2.198</td><td align="center">2.686</td></tr><tr><td align="center">k</td><td></td><td align="center">1.000</td><td></td><td align="center">0.929</td><td></td><td align="center">1.000</td><td align="center">1.000</td><td align="center">0.929</td><td align="center">1.000</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">1.000</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">0.909</td><td align="center">0.909</td><td align="center">0.964</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Ho &#x000b1; (S.E.)</td><td></td><td align="center">0.364 (0.084)</td><td></td><td align="center">0.327 (0.086)</td><td></td><td align="center">0.247 (0.063)</td><td align="center">0.253 (0.071)</td><td align="center">0.312 (0.084)</td><td align="center">0.343 (0.092)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">0.266 (0.068)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">0.303 (0.096)</td><td align="center">0.192 (0.073)</td><td align="center">0.290 (0.072)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Hs &#x000b1; (S.E.)</td><td></td><td align="center">0.534 (0.057)</td><td></td><td align="center">0.512 (0.072)</td><td></td><td align="center">0.507 (0.057)</td><td align="center">0.380 (0.073)</td><td align="center">0.492 (0.062)</td><td align="center">0.526 (0.069)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">0.501 (0.066)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">0.477 (0.058)</td><td align="center">0.399 (0.066)</td><td align="center">0.481 (0.049)</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><italic>F</italic><sub>ST </sub>(P)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">0.114 (&#x0003c;0.001)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">0.116 (&#x0003c;0.001)</td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">0.101 (&#x0003e;0.001)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="22"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="center"><italic>D. fennicella</italic></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center"><bold>Hn</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Pih</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Isa</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Sip1</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Sip2</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Sip3</bold></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="22"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="center">N</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">9</td><td align="center">13</td><td align="center">17</td><td align="center">18</td><td align="center">21</td><td align="center">8</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">14.333</td></tr><tr><td align="center">N. alleles &#x000b1; (S.E.)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">1.923 (0.211)</td><td align="center">2.692 (0.365)</td><td align="center">2.615 (0.241)</td><td align="center">2.385 (0.350)</td><td align="center">2.769 (0.411)</td><td align="center">1.692 (0.208)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">3.615 (0.488)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Allelic richness</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">1.692</td><td align="center">2.123</td><td align="center">2.126</td><td align="center">1.955</td><td align="center">2.125</td><td align="center">1.611</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">1.939</td></tr><tr><td align="center">k</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">0.824</td><td align="center">0.778</td><td align="center">0.667</td><td align="center">0.500</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">0.795</td></tr><tr><td align="center">D</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">9</td><td align="center">13</td><td align="center">9.966</td><td align="center">11.571</td><td align="center">10.756</td><td align="center">3.556</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">9.642</td></tr><tr><td align="center">E</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">0.712</td><td align="center">0.827</td><td align="center">0.964</td><td align="center">0.889</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">0.899</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Ho &#x000b1; (S.E.)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">0.376 (0.117)</td><td align="center">0.383 (0.115)</td><td align="center">0.363 (0.122)</td><td align="center">0.443 (0.122)</td><td align="center">0.436 (0.133)</td><td align="center">0.375 (0.130)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">0.397 (0.116)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Hs &#x000b1; (S.E.)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">0.308 (0.069)</td><td align="center">0.458 (0.067)</td><td align="center">0.448 (0.058)</td><td align="center">0.379 (0.0793)</td><td align="center">0.466 (0.066)</td><td align="center">0.279 (0.076)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">0.390 (0.033)</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><italic>F</italic><sub>ST </sub>(P)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">0.213 (&#x0003c;0.001)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">0.213 (&#x0003c;0.001)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Allelic richness ranged from 1.61 in <italic>D. fennicella </italic>to 3.11 in <italic>D. charlottae</italic>. The expected heterozygosity (Hs) ranged from 0.279 in <italic>D. fennicella </italic>to 0.558 in <italic>D. charlottae</italic>. Allele richness and gene diversity (Hs) were similar in the two sexual species (1000 permutation: P = 0.488 and P = 1.00, respectively). Both sexual species harbour significantly higher allele richness and Hs than the asexual species (permutation tests: <italic>D. charlottae </italic>vs. <italic>D. fennicella </italic>P = 0.002 and P = 0.007, respectively and <italic>S. rupicolella </italic>vs. <italic>D. fennicella </italic>P = 0.012 and P = 0.012, respectively). As expected, the proportion of different genotypes (k) was close to 1 in the sexual populations and no differences were observed between the two species (Mann-Whitney test U<sub>14,9 </sub>= 50.5, P = 0.439). The proportion of different clones (k) was also high in the asexual species, ranging from 0.5 to 1 in the different populations; however it was significantly lower than in <italic>D. charlottae </italic>and almost significantly lower than in <italic>S. rupicolella </italic>(Mann-Whitney test U<sub>14,6 </sub>= 18, P = 0.020 and U<sub>9,6 </sub>= 13, P = 0.082). Evenness was very similar among asexual populations and it was very close to 1 because of the high genotype diversity. Significant deviation from the Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium was observed in most of the loci in all three species. In the sexual species, this deviation was due to heterozygote deficiency. The <italic>F</italic><sub>IS </sub>values, over all loci indicated a significant deficiency of heterozygotes in all populations of both sexual species with the exception of Isosaari (Isa) and Sippulanniemi 1 (Sip 1) populations of <italic>D. charlottae </italic>(Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>). In <italic>D. fennicella</italic>, instead, only two populations showed heterozygosity deficiency (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>). A large variation in <italic>F</italic><sub>IS </sub>values was observed across all loci and populations in all three species with the exception of MDH2 for which no heterozygote individuals were ever observed (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>). The exclusion of this locus, however, did not change any of our results.</p><p>Null alleles might cause deviation from H-W proportion. The presence of null alleles at many of the loci analysed is strongly suggested by the significant correlation of the <italic>F</italic><sub>IS </sub>values between the two sexual species (r<sub>s </sub>= 0.93, n = 12, P &#x0003c; 0.001) and between <italic>D. charlottae </italic>and <italic>D. fennicella </italic>(r<sub>s </sub>= 0.774, n= 11, P = 0.005). Calculation of the frequency of null alleles with the methods of Brookfield [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>] indicate that null alleles are present in high frequencies in most of the loci in all three species (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p><italic>F</italic><sub>IS </sub>values and frequency of null alleles for each population of the three species at each locus. Null alleles frequencies (a*) were calculated with the method of Brookfield [38].</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="right"><italic>DIA</italic></td><td align="right"><italic>FUM</italic></td><td align="right"><italic>G6PDH</italic></td><td align="right"><italic>GOT</italic></td><td align="right"><italic>GPI</italic></td><td align="right"><italic>IDH</italic></td><td align="right"><italic>MDH</italic></td><td align="right"><italic>MDH2</italic></td><td align="right"><italic>ME1</italic></td><td align="right"><italic>ME2</italic></td><td align="right"><italic>ME3</italic></td><td align="right"><italic>6PGDH</italic></td><td align="right"><italic>PGM</italic></td><td align="right">All</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" colspan="3"><bold><italic>D. charlottae</italic></bold></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="17"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="center"><bold>Jyv&#x000e4;skyl&#x000e4;</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>K&#x000f6;1</bold></td><td align="left"><italic>F</italic><sub>IS</sub></td><td align="right">-0.278</td><td align="right">NA</td><td align="right">0.141</td><td align="right">0.721</td><td align="right">0.619</td><td align="right">0.115</td><td align="right">0.256</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">0.368</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">0.211</td><td align="right">0.011</td><td align="right">0.367</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">a*</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.027</td><td align="right">0.257</td><td align="right">0.215</td><td align="right">0.038</td><td align="right">0.092</td><td align="right">0.363</td><td align="right">0.116</td><td align="right">0.172</td><td align="right">0.095</td><td align="right">0.042</td><td align="right">0</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left"><bold>Lv1</bold></td><td align="left"><italic>F</italic><sub>IS</sub></td><td align="right">-0.653</td><td align="right">NA</td><td align="right">-0.297</td><td align="right">0.773</td><td align="right">0.828</td><td align="right">-0.071</td><td align="right">0.877</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">0.429</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">0.100</td><td align="right">0.279</td><td align="right">0.441</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">a*</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.202</td><td align="right">0.265</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.348</td><td align="right">0.410</td><td align="right">0.145</td><td align="right">0.346</td><td align="right">0.284</td><td align="right">0.014</td><td align="right">0.094</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left"><bold>Lv2</bold></td><td align="left"><italic>F</italic><sub>IS</sub></td><td align="right">-0.556</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">0.276</td><td align="right">0.000</td><td align="right">0.636</td><td align="right">-0.297</td><td align="right">0.429</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">NA</td><td align="right">-0.143</td><td align="right">0.689</td><td align="right">0.448</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">a*</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.165</td><td align="right">0.069</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.130</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.133</td><td align="right">0.331</td><td align="right">0.308</td><td align="right">0.417</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.258</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left"><bold>Lv3</bold></td><td align="left"><italic>F</italic><sub>IS</sub></td><td align="right">0.034</td><td align="right">NA</td><td align="right">-1</td><td align="right">0.840</td><td align="right">0.576</td><td align="right">-0.243</td><td align="right">0.425</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">NA</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">NA</td><td align="right">0.407</td><td align="right">0.278</td><td align="right">0.326</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">a*</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.243</td><td align="right">0.214</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.146</td><td align="right">0.252</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.417</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.092</td><td align="right">0.097</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left"><bold>Lv4</bold></td><td align="left"><italic>F</italic><sub>IS</sub></td><td align="right">-0.292</td><td align="right">NA</td><td align="right">-0.125</td><td align="right">0.385</td><td align="right">0.717</td><td align="right">-0.021</td><td align="right">0.217</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">0.509</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">0.223</td><td align="right">0.393</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">a*</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.128</td><td align="right">0.271</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.070</td><td align="right">0.383</td><td align="right">0.153</td><td align="right">0.169</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.319</td><td align="right">0.067</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left"><bold>Muu</bold></td><td align="left"><italic>F</italic><sub>IS</sub></td><td align="right">0.165</td><td align="right">NA</td><td align="right">-0.100</td><td align="right">0.681</td><td align="right">0.701</td><td align="right">0.079</td><td align="right">0.133</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">0.429</td><td align="right">0.471</td><td align="right">0.481</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">a*</td><td align="right">0.044</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.215</td><td align="right">0.231</td><td align="right">0.014</td><td align="right">0.038</td><td align="right">0.379</td><td align="right">0.133</td><td align="right">0.217</td><td align="right">0.133</td><td align="right">0.089</td><td align="right">0.186</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left"><bold>Hj</bold></td><td align="left"><italic>F</italic><sub>IS</sub></td><td align="right">0.167</td><td align="right">NA</td><td align="right">-0.189</td><td align="right">0.605</td><td align="right">0.683</td><td align="right">0.025</td><td align="right">0.534</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">0.659</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.556</td><td align="right">0.544</td><td align="right">0.474</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">a*</td><td align="right">0.045</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.220</td><td align="right">0.285</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.221</td><td align="right">0.418</td><td align="right">0.095</td><td align="right">0.105</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.173</td><td align="right">0.229</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left"><bold>Pih</bold></td><td align="left"><italic>F</italic><sub>IS</sub></td><td align="right">-0.241</td><td align="right">NA</td><td align="right">0.226</td><td align="right">0.658</td><td align="right">0.506</td><td align="right">0.158</td><td align="right">0.477</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">0.871</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">-0.294</td><td align="right">0.577</td><td align="right">0.501</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">a*</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.049</td><td align="right">0.105</td><td align="right">0.139</td><td align="right">0.052</td><td align="right">0.195</td><td align="right">0.384</td><td align="right">0.294</td><td align="right">0.290</td><td align="right">0.333</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.223</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left"><bold>Isa</bold></td><td align="left"><italic>F</italic><sub>IS</sub></td><td align="right">-1</td><td align="right">NA</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.091</td><td align="right">-1</td><td align="right">0.143</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">-0.200</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">0.750</td><td align="right">-1</td><td align="right">-0.714</td><td align="right">-0.113</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">a*</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.006</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.021</td><td align="right">0.2899</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.1967</td><td align="right">0.238</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left"><bold>Sip1</bold></td><td align="left"><italic>F</italic><sub>IS</sub></td><td align="right">0.615</td><td align="right">NA</td><td align="right">-0.091</td><td align="right">-0.333</td><td align="right">-0.161</td><td align="right">-0.333</td><td align="right">0.300</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">0.647</td><td align="right">NA</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">-0.667</td><td align="right">-0.448</td><td align="right">0.076</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">a*</td><td align="right">0.152</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.059</td><td align="right">0.3725</td><td align="right">0.158</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.197</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="17"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="center"><bold>Orimattila</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>Sal</bold></td><td align="left"><italic>F</italic><sub>IS</sub></td><td align="right">0.393</td><td align="right">-0.040</td><td align="right">0.189</td><td align="right">0.589</td><td align="right">0.482</td><td align="right">-0.026</td><td align="right">0.816</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">0.662</td><td align="right">0.769</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">0.154</td><td align="right">0.564</td><td align="right">0.527</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">a*</td><td align="right">0.121</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.047</td><td align="right">0.223</td><td align="right">0.179</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.338</td><td align="right">0.351</td><td align="right">0.191</td><td align="right">0.178</td><td align="right">0.332</td><td align="right">0.030</td><td align="right">0.133</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left"><bold>Tuk</bold></td><td align="left"><italic>F</italic><sub>IS</sub></td><td align="right">-0.333</td><td align="right">NA</td><td align="right">-0.200</td><td align="right">0.632</td><td align="right">0.575</td><td align="right">0.127</td><td align="right">0.744</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">-0.067</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">NA</td><td align="right">-0.091</td><td align="right">0.571</td><td align="right">0.415</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">a*</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.211</td><td align="right">0.223</td><td align="right">0.029</td><td align="right">0.315</td><td align="right">0.331</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.165</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.220</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left"><bold>Vilj</bold></td><td align="left"><italic>F</italic><sub>IS</sub></td><td align="right">0.208</td><td align="right">NA</td><td align="right">0.294</td><td align="right">0.222</td><td align="right">0.177</td><td align="right">-0.200</td><td align="right">0.866</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">0.353</td><td align="right">0.392</td><td align="right">0.463</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">a*</td><td align="right">0.066</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.061</td><td align="right">0.073</td><td align="right">0.048</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.311</td><td align="right">0.362</td><td align="right">0.327</td><td align="right">0.321</td><td align="right">0.124</td><td align="right">0.103</td><td align="right">0.155</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left"><bold>Vill</bold></td><td align="left"><italic>F</italic><sub>IS</sub></td><td align="right">-0.135</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">0.438</td><td align="right">0.615</td><td align="right">0.870</td><td align="right">0.067</td><td align="right">0.512</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">0.043</td><td align="right">0.681</td><td align="right">0.489</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">a*</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.142</td><td align="right">0.130</td><td align="right">0.232</td><td align="right">0.335</td><td align="right">0.009</td><td align="right">0.195</td><td align="right">0.284</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.142</td><td align="right">0.332</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.289</td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="17"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="3"><bold><italic>S. rupicolella</italic></bold></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="17"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="center"><bold>Jyv&#x000e4;skyl&#x000e4;</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>Kv</bold></td><td align="left"><italic>F</italic><sub>IS</sub></td><td align="right">-0.800</td><td align="right">NA</td><td align="right">0.250</td><td align="right">0.554</td><td align="right">0.419</td><td align="right">-0.268</td><td align="right">0.534</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">0.442</td><td align="right">0.852</td><td align="right">0.542</td><td align="right">0.351</td><td align="right">-0.184</td><td align="right">0.318</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">a*</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.067</td><td align="right">0.198</td><td align="right">0.091</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.185</td><td align="right">0.296</td><td align="right">0.159</td><td align="right">0.319</td><td align="right">0.190</td><td align="right">0.096</td><td align="right">0</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left"><bold>Lv2</bold></td><td align="left"><italic>F</italic><sub>IS</sub></td><td align="right">-0.307</td><td align="right">NA</td><td align="right">0.559</td><td align="right">0.458</td><td align="right">0.780</td><td align="right">-0.279</td><td align="right">-0.078</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">0.579</td><td align="right">0.882</td><td align="right">NA</td><td align="right">0.100</td><td align="right">0.242</td><td align="right">0.361</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">a*</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.192</td><td align="right">0.165</td><td align="right">0.178</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.413</td><td align="right">0.216</td><td align="right">0.330</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.014</td><td align="right">0.080</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left"><bold>Lv4</bold></td><td align="left"><italic>F</italic><sub>IS</sub></td><td align="right">-0.091</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.617</td><td align="right">0.664</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">0.338</td><td align="right">0.820</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">0.471</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">-0.207</td><td align="right">-0.154</td><td align="right">0.513</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">a*</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.189</td><td align="right">0.223</td><td align="right">0.390</td><td align="right">0.120</td><td align="right">0.269</td><td align="right">0.398</td><td align="right">0.148</td><td align="right">0.296</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left"><bold>Lv5</bold></td><td align="left"><italic>F</italic><sub>IS</sub></td><td align="right">0.067</td><td align="right">NA</td><td align="right">0.368</td><td align="right">-0.091</td><td align="right">0.573</td><td align="right">-0.085</td><td align="right">-0.067</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">0.818</td><td align="right">NA</td><td align="right">NA</td><td align="right">0.478</td><td align="right">0.190</td><td align="right">0.333</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">a*</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.087</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.172</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.257</td><td align="right">0.283</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.137</td><td align="right">0.045</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left"><bold>Muu</bold></td><td align="left"><italic>F</italic><sub>IS</sub></td><td align="right">0.007</td><td align="right">NA</td><td align="right">-0.132</td><td align="right">0.480</td><td align="right">0.623</td><td align="right">-0.226</td><td align="right">0.182</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">0.196</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">-0.176</td><td align="right">0.507</td><td align="right">0.367</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">a*</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.178</td><td align="right">0.158</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.063</td><td align="right">0.364</td><td align="right">0.033</td><td align="right">0.333</td><td align="right">0.290</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.170</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left"><bold>Hj</bold></td><td align="left"><italic>F</italic><sub>IS</sub></td><td align="right">-0.333</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">0.364</td><td align="right">0.202</td><td align="right">0.615</td><td align="right">-0.200</td><td align="right">0.813</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">0.509</td><td align="right">0.652</td><td align="right">NA</td><td align="right">0.336</td><td align="right">-0.049</td><td align="right">0.347</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">a*</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.172</td><td align="right">0.111</td><td align="right">0.072</td><td align="right">0.251</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.299</td><td align="right">0.386</td><td align="right">0.177</td><td align="right">0.088</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.096</td><td align="right">0</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left"><bold>Sip1</bold></td><td align="left"><italic>F</italic><sub>IS</sub></td><td align="right">-0.090</td><td align="right">NA</td><td align="right">-0.154</td><td align="right">0.301</td><td align="right">0.788</td><td align="right">0.001</td><td align="right">0.708</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">0.091</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">0.928</td><td align="right">-0.091</td><td align="right">0.358</td><td align="right">0.468</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">a*</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.085</td><td align="right">0.321</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.303</td><td align="right">0.393</td><td align="right">0.018</td><td align="right">0.316</td><td align="right">0.316</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.132</td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="17"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="center"><bold>Orimattila</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>Vill</bold></td><td align="left"><italic>F</italic><sub>IS</sub></td><td align="right">-0.800</td><td align="right">NA</td><td align="right">-0.047</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">-0.125</td><td align="right">0.612</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">-0.296</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">-0.2000</td><td align="right">0.474</td><td align="right">0.366</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">a*</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.339</td><td align="right">0.316</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.240</td><td align="right">0.316</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.153</td><td align="right">0.316</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.142</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left"><bold>Pen</bold></td><td align="left"><italic>F</italic><sub>IS</sub></td><td align="right">0.438</td><td align="right">NA</td><td align="right">0.217</td><td align="right">0.091</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">-0.524</td><td align="right">0.680</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">NA</td><td align="right">-0.026</td><td align="right">0.518</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">a*</td><td align="right">0.130</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.054</td><td align="right">0.014</td><td align="right">0.332</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.225</td><td align="right">0.373</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.301</td><td align="right">0.332</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="17"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="3"><bold><italic>D. fennicella</italic></bold></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="17"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="center"><bold>Jyv&#x000e4;skyl&#x000e4;</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>Hn</bold></td><td align="left"><italic>F</italic><sub>IS</sub></td><td align="right">0.304</td><td align="right">NA</td><td align="right">-1</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">-0.600</td><td align="right">-0.091</td><td align="right">0.448</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">NA</td><td align="right">NA</td><td align="right">NA</td><td align="right">-1</td><td align="right">-1</td><td align="right">-0.222</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">a*</td><td align="right">0.093</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.108</td><td align="right">0.331</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">NA</td><td align="right">0</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left"><bold>Pih</bold></td><td align="left"><italic>F</italic><sub>IS</sub></td><td align="right">0.268</td><td align="right">NA</td><td align="right">-1</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">0.200</td><td align="right">0.050</td><td align="right">0.553</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">0.351</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">-1</td><td align="right">-0.581</td><td align="right">0.145</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">a*</td><td align="right">0.110</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.321</td><td align="right">0.000</td><td align="right">0.058</td><td align="right">0.301</td><td align="right">0.381</td><td align="right">0.256</td><td align="right">0.299</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left"><bold>Isa</bold></td><td align="left"><italic>F</italic><sub>IS</sub></td><td align="right">0.657</td><td align="right">NA</td><td align="right">-1</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">-0.333</td><td align="right">0.185</td><td align="right">0.780</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">0.840</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">NA</td><td align="right">-0.800</td><td align="right">-1</td><td align="right">0.208</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">a*</td><td align="right">0.058</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.333</td><td align="right">0.067</td><td align="right">0.008</td><td align="right">0.205</td><td align="right">0.279</td><td align="right">0.067</td><td align="right">0.233</td><td align="right">0.172</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left"><bold>Sip1</bold></td><td align="left"><italic>F</italic><sub>IS</sub></td><td align="right">-0.732</td><td align="right">NA</td><td align="right">-1</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">-0.308</td><td align="right">-0.244</td><td align="right">0.532</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">NA</td><td align="right">-0.097</td><td align="right">NA</td><td align="right">-0.846</td><td align="right">-1</td><td align="right">-0.168</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">a*</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.095</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.207</td><td align="right">0.436</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left"><bold>Sip2</bold></td><td align="left"><italic>F</italic><sub>IS</sub></td><td align="right">0.650</td><td align="right">NA</td><td align="right">-1</td><td align="right">0.840</td><td align="right">-0.772</td><td align="right">-0.159</td><td align="right">0.162</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">NA</td><td align="right">-1</td><td align="right">-1</td><td align="right">0.057</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">a*</td><td align="right">0.218</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.185</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.052</td><td align="right">0.393</td><td align="right">0.329</td><td align="right">0.329</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left"><bold>Sip3</bold></td><td align="left"><italic>F</italic><sub>IS</sub></td><td align="right">0.391</td><td align="right">NA</td><td align="right">-1</td><td align="right">NA</td><td align="right">NA</td><td align="right">-1</td><td align="right">-0.029</td><td align="right">1</td><td align="right">NA</td><td align="right">NA</td><td align="right">NA</td><td align="right">-1</td><td align="right">-1</td><td align="right">-0.345</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">a*</td><td align="right">0.091</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0.347</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td align="right">0</td><td></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Population differentiation</title><p>The overall differentiation among populations, <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub>, was high and significantly different from zero in all three species (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>), which is an indication of strong population structure. Mean <italic>F</italic><sub>ST </sub>values across loci and the 95% confidence interval (bootstrap over loci) are shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>. The overall differentiation was significantly different in the three species. While the mean <italic>F</italic><sub>ST </sub>value of <italic>D. fennicella </italic>was not different from that of <italic>D. charlottae</italic>, it was significantly higher than that of <italic>S. rupicolella</italic>. Hierarchical analyses of molecular variance (AMOVA) indicated that the two areas, Jyv&#x000e4;skyl&#x000e4; and Orimattila, did not differ from each other for both sexual species. In <italic>D. charlottae </italic>the percentage of variance among sites was 1.61, P = 0.12, while it was 16.07, P &#x0003c; 0.001 among populations within sites. In <italic>S. rupicolella </italic>the percentage of variance among sites was 0.85, P = 0.27, while it was 11.45, P &#x0003c; 0.001 among populations within sites. We did not observe isolation by distance (Mantel test between <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub>/(1-<italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub>) and the natural logarithm of the geographical distance) in any species at either of the sites: <italic>D. charlottae </italic>(Jyv&#x000e4;skyl&#x000e4; R = -0.257, P = 0.089; Orimattila R = 0.353, P = 0.512), <italic>S. rupicolella </italic>(R = 0.222, P = 0.338) and <italic>D. fennicella </italic>(R = - 0.300, P = 0.277).</p><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Mean <italic>F</italic><sub>ST </sub>of each species and its 95% confidence interval obtained with bootstrap over loci. Asterisk indicates 5% significant level.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1472-6785-5-5-2"/></fig><p>Sixty five different genotypes were detected among the 86 samples of <italic>D. fennicella</italic>. Only two of them were shared among different populations. One genotype was shared between Sippulanniemi 1 (Sip1) and Huviniemi (Hn) while the other was shared between Sippulanniemi 3 (Sip3) and Pihta (Pih). In both cases the two populations are geographically distant, and three populations in the same area (Sip1, 2 and 3 and Hn, Pih and Isa, respectively) did not share any genotypes.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>Analysis of isozyme variation in three species of psychid moths revealed that the genetic diversity of the sexual species <italic>D. charlottae </italic>and <italic>S. rupicolella </italic>is higher than that of the asexual species <italic>D. fennicella</italic>. Allele richness, gene and genotypic diversity were also higher in the sexual species than in the asexual species. Higher genotype diversity in sexual than in asexual populations is most likely the logical result of recombination and was an expected result. The sexual populations also showed higher allele diversity, which is a more intriguing outcome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>]. One possible explanation for this difference is that the asexual lineage retained only a portion of the diversity of its sexual ancestor. Alternatively, a lower per locus diversity in the asexual species could reflect lower population sizes compared to the sexual species. Asexual <italic>D. fennicella </italic>is, in general, rarer than the sexual species, although it was the most abundant species in some locations. A lower population size is also suggested by the higher differentiation (<italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub>) among <italic>D. fennicella </italic>populations than among sexual populations.</p><p>Surprisingly, parthenogenetic <italic>D. fennicella </italic>showed a considerable amount of genotype diversity, with 65 different genotypes detected among 86 individuals. This was in contrast with a previous analysis with allozyme markers which found limited diversity among samples of <italic>D. fennicella </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>]. This amount of genotype diversity was higher than that recently observed in <italic>Potamopyrgus </italic>snails [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>] and that reported in animals (reviewed in[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>]) and in plants (reviewed in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>]) in the previous allozymes literature. Interestingly, clonal lineages of <italic>D. fennicella </italic>were mostly restricted to single populations. Only two genotypes were shared among distant populations. The lack of a common broadly adapted haplotype spread over different populations is in conflict with the hypothesis of the general-purpose-genotype [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>]. Instead, adaptation to different microclimates or other specific environmental conditions of these locales could explain the presence of many different genotypes, as suggested by Vrijenhoek's [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>] frozen niche variation hypothesis. However, we found no significant differences in morphology, size and life-history characters between two different <italic>D. fennicella </italic>populations that would reflect ecological specialisation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]. Although several studies have reported allozymes as not neutral (reviewed in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>]), in our study there were no indications that they deviate from neutrality, thus these markers are expected to be subjected more to drift than to selection. High genotypic diversity could indicate the presence of cryptic sex in the parthenogenetic species. Although we cannot completely rule out this hypothesis, we never observed sex in the species. All parthenogenetic females lay eggs immediately after hatching from pupa and never show the characteristic behaviour of sexual females when they secrete pheromones to attract potential mates (Kumpulainen et al. 2004). Moreover, mitochondrial sequences from sexual and asexual females clearly indicate these are two different species (Grapputo et al. 2005). This high genotypic diversity could also be explained by alternative types of parthenogenesis involving recombination, such as the automictic thelytoky [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>].</p><p>High clonal diversity and the observed distribution of different clones could be the result of a restricted dispersal capacity and the fragmentation of suitable habitats for these psychid moths. Large differentiation was also observed among populations of diploid parthenogenetic <italic>D. triquetrella </italic>in the Alps but not among tetraploid populations of the same species in Finland [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>]. The same pattern, however, could be explained by an extinction-colonisation process associated with a long persistence of the populations, which would explain the high intrapopulation diversity. Large genetic differentiation among populations was also observed in both the sexual species, <italic>D. charlottae </italic>and <italic>S. rupicolella</italic>, which is consistent with their extremely low ability for active dispersal (see also [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>]) and the patchy distribution of suitable habitats. Nevertheless, psychid moths sometimes colonise new areas as suggested by the absence of <italic>D. charlottae </italic>in the Isosaari population in 1999 and its presence in 2000 (T. Kumpulainen, personal observation). Most probably, dispersal between different populations is a relatively rare event taking place as passive aerial dispersal of very small larvae [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>]. The large genetic differentiation among <italic>D. charlottae </italic>and <italic>S. rupicolella </italic>populations is in contrast with the data obtained for populations of sexual <italic>D. triquetrella </italic>in the Alps by Lokki <italic>et al</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>], where allelic frequencies were described as homogeneous among populations, although rigorous tests of population differentiation were not carried out.</p><p>The observed proportion of heterozygotes was not different between the two sexual species <italic>D. charlottae </italic>and <italic>S. rupicolella </italic>(0.29) and was very similar to that previously observed in another sexual species <italic>D</italic>. <italic>triquetrella </italic>(0.23) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>]. The level of heterozygosity was also highly similar among populations in both sexual species. <italic>D. charlottae </italic>and <italic>S. rupicolella</italic>, in contrast to <italic>D. triquetrella</italic>, were not in HW equilibrium for most of the loci and populations. Heterozygote deficiency has been widely reported in allozyme surveys of natural populations of marine invertebrates (reviewed in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>]) and also in fishes (e.g. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>]), amphibians and reptiles (reviewed in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>]). Alternative hypotheses have been advanced to explain such heterozygote deficiencies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">53</xref>]. The high heterozygosity deficiency in all three species of bag worm moths could be explained by null alleles. The high variation across loci in <italic>F</italic><sub>IS </sub>values correlate among species and the methods of Brookfield [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>] for the calculation of null alleles frequencies strongly suggest that most of the loci in the three species are affected by null alleles. Most populations of sexual psychid moths are small, consisting of just 30 to 100 individuals. Suitable forest patches are also small and isolated. Moreover, females are apterous and unable to disperse. When sexual females emerge from pupae they quickly start to secrete pheromones to attract males. Once emerged, males respond promptly to the female pheromones because they have a very short adult life span (about 10 hours). Therefore, copulation most likely occurs between emerging adults that are both spatially and temporally close. This could create substructured populations and a Wahlund effect, both spatial and temporal, which could maintain a high number of alleles in the population but increase the homozygosity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">54</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>In summary, the three different moth species show a similar population structure characterised by high genetic differentiation among populations and low dispersal. The parthenogenetic <italic>D. fennicella </italic>shows reduced genetic diversity compared to the sexual species but still shows high genotype diversity that could indicate the presence of cryptic sex. All species show a very high heterozygote deficiency due to the presence of null alleles at most of the loci or to the Wahlund effect. DNA markers certainly need to be investigated to determine the causes of such heterozygote deficiency shown by the allozymes.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Source populations</title><p>Two sexual species, <italic>Siederia rupicolella </italic>and <italic>Dahlica charlottae</italic>, and an asexual species, <italic>D. fennicella </italic>were sampled to study their genetic variability and population structure. Samples were collected in April 2000 from 20 different study areas of suitable forest type [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]. All areas were situated in central Finland, 15 of them around the city of Jyv&#x000e4;skyl&#x000e4; (62 &#x000b0;15 N', 25&#x000b0;43 E') and five close to the town of Orimattila (60 &#x000b0;49 N', 25 &#x000b0;40 E') (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). Study areas consisted of old forest patches, separated by meadows and fields and sometimes by human settlements. All study areas were dominated by mixed forests of Norwegian spruce (<italic>Picea abies</italic>) and silver birch (<italic>Betula pendula</italic>), many of them also contained Scotch pine (<italic>Pinus sylvestris</italic>). Final instar larvae of all three moth species climb on tree trunks to pupate and they can easily be caught by setting tape traps on tree trunks. Larvae remain stuck on the tape and they can later be collected. Each collected larva was taken to the laboratory and kept individually until hatching to adult, allowing us to determine the reproduction mode and identify the species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]. Samples were subsequently frozen at -80&#x000b0;C until analysis.</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Map of the sampling sites in central Finland.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1472-6785-5-5-1"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Electrophoresis</title><p>Frozen samples were squashed in 20 &#x003bc;l of grinding buffer (Tris-HCl 0.1 M pH = 8.0) and then applied to Titan<sup>&#x000ae; </sup>III cellulose acetate plates (76 mm &#x000d7; 76 mm) using the Super Z-12 applicator Kit (Helena laboratories) following the method of Hebert and Beaton [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">55</xref>]. Electrophoresis was carried out at room temperature at 200 volts for 20&#x02013;25 minutes in the appropriate buffer for each enzyme as indicated in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>. Of twenty-three enzymes tested, ten were polymorphic (listed in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>) from which a total of thirteen loci could be scored. Enzymes excluded from the analysis because they were monomorphic or unreadable were: <italic>ACON </italic>(EC 4.2.1.3), <italic>AK </italic>(EC 2.7.4.3), <italic>ADH </italic>(EC 1.1.1.1), <italic>ALP </italic>(EC 3.1.3.1), <italic>ATT </italic>(EC 2.6.1.1), <italic>EST </italic>(EC 3.1.1.1), HEX (EC 2.7.1.1), <italic>LDH </italic>(EC 1.1.1.27), <italic>LAP </italic>(EC 3.4.11.1), <italic>MPI </italic>(EC 5.3.1.8), <italic>SOD </italic>(EC 1.15.1.1), <italic>&#x003b1;, &#x003b1;-Trehalase </italic>(EC 3.2.1.28) and <italic>SKDH </italic>(EC 1.1.1.25).</p></sec><sec><title>Data analysis</title><p>Tests of neutrality for each locus, population and species were carried out using the Ewens-Watterson test [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>] with the software package Popgene [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>]. The genetic diversity and population structure of each species were analysed using Fstat [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">57</xref>]. We tested the Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium (HW) for each locus and population by randomisation of alleles among individuals within populations. Significance levels were adjusted using the sequential Bonferroni correction for multiple comparisons [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">58</xref>]. For each population we estimated the number of alleles per locus, allelic richness [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">59</xref>], gene diversity (Hs) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60">60</xref>], observed heterozygosity (Ho) and <italic>F</italic><sub>IS </sub>value. Frequency of null alleles per locus and population was estimated with the method of Brookfield [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>] as implemented in Micro-Checker v.2.2.3 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">61</xref>], which does not require detecting null allele homozygotes. Genotypic diversity (or clonal diversity in asexuals) within populations was determined simply as the proportion of different genotypes in the population <italic>k </italic>= <italic>G</italic>/<italic>N</italic>, where G is number of genotypes and N is the number of individuals in the population. For the asexual species, we also measured clonal diversity using Simpson's diversity index D = <italic>1/&#x02211;p</italic><sub>i</sub>, where <italic>pi </italic>is the frequency of the i-th clone (Simpson, 1949). D varies from 1 (monoclonal population) to N if each individual carries a different genotype. This measure takes into account the frequency of clones, but it depends on the sample size, so we also calculated the evenness (E) of Simpson's index E = D/D<sub>max</sub>, which is constrained between 0 and 1. Population structure was assessed by calculating <italic>F</italic><sub>ST </sub>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B62">62</xref>] between populations and tested by permuting genotypes among samples because most of the populations were not in HW (as suggested in Fstat). Hierarchical analysis of molecular variance (AMOVA, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">63</xref>]) including all populations and populations within the two areas (Jyv&#x000e4;skyl&#x000e4; and Orimattila) was performed with Arlequin ver. 2.000 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B64">64</xref>]. If the differentiation between populations is due to isolation by distance, a positive correlation between genetic distance and geographical distance is expected. Isolation by distance was tested as suggested by Rousset [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B65">65</xref>] and a Mantel test was performed between populations in each site using Fstat.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>List of abbreviations</title><p><italic>ACON </italic>= Aconitate Hydratase, <italic>AK </italic>= Adenylate Kinase, <italic>ADH </italic>= Alcohol Dehydrogenase, <italic>ALP </italic>= Alkaline Phosphatase, <italic>AAT </italic>= Amino Aspartate Transferase, <italic>EST </italic>= Carboxylesterase, HEX = Hexokinase, <italic>LDH </italic>= Lactate Dehydrogenase, <italic>LAP </italic>= Leucine Aminopeptidase, <italic>MPI </italic>= Mannose-6-Phosphate Isomerase, <italic>SOD </italic>= Superoxide Dismutase and <italic>SKDH </italic>= shikimate dehydrogenase.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>TK collected samples and performed most of the laboratory procedure with SP. AG and JM performed the analysis of the data and wrote the manuscript. All the authors contributed to the study.</p></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We want to acknowledge K. Kulmala for assisting in the field work and in the insect laboratory. We thank M. Hietanen and M. Myllyl&#x000e4; for their assistance in the genetic laboratory, P. Halme, V. Heino, T. Hiltunen, I. Kananen and A. Kolehmainen, for assisting in the field work, K. E. Knott and A. Veijanen for help in scoring allozyme gels. Finally, we acknowledge K. E. Knott, M. Bj&#x000f6;rklund, P. Mutikainen and four anonymous reviewers for their valuable comments on previous versions of the manuscript. This study was carried out at the University of Jyv&#x000e4;skyl&#x000e4; and was financially supported by the Academy of Finland, project number 779874, and by the Centre of Excellence in Evolutionary Ecology.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>West-Eberhard</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The maintenance of sex as a developmental trap due to sexual selection</article-title><source>Q Rev Biol</source><year>2005</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15884735</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/431024</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name></person-group><source>Sex and evolution</source><year>1975</year><publisher-name>Princeton (NJ), Princeton Univ. Press</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maynard Smith</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><source>The evolution of sex</source><year>1978</year><publisher-name>Cambridge, Cambridge Univ. Press</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><source>The masterpiece of nature: the evolution and genetics of sexuality</source><year>1982</year><publisher-name>Berkeley, Univ. of California Press</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kondrashov</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Classification of hypotheses on the advantage of amphimixis</article-title><source>J Hered</source><year>1993</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>372</fpage><lpage>387</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8409359</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sex, recombination, and the efficacy of selection - Was Weismann right?</article-title><source>Evolution</source><year>2000</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>337</fpage><lpage>351</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10937212</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jokela</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lively</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Dybdahl</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic variation in sexual and clonal lineages of a freshwater snail</article-title><source>Biol J Linn Soc</source><year>2003</year><volume>79</volume><fpage>165</fpage><lpage>181</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1095-8312.2003.00181.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The relation of recombination to mutational advance</article-title><source>Mutat Res</source><year>1964</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>2</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14195748</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kondrashov</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Deleterious mutations and the evolution of sexual reproduction</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1988</year><volume>336</volume><fpage>435</fpage><lpage>440</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3057385</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/336435a0</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Experimental tests of the adaptive significance of sexual recombination</article-title><source>Nat Rev Genet</source><year>2002</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>241</fpage><lpage>251</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11967549</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrg760</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maynard Smith</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Selection for recombination in a polygenic model - the mechanism</article-title><source>Genet Res</source><year>1988</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3366381</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crow</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An advantage of sexual reproduction in a rapidly changing environment</article-title><source>J Hered</source><year>1992</year><volume>83</volume><fpage>169</fpage><lpage>173</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1624761</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Charlesworth</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The evolution of sex and recombination in a varying environment</article-title><source>J Hered</source><year>1993</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>345</fpage><lpage>350</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8409356</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kondrashov</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Yampolsky</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolution of amphimixis and recombination under fluctuating selection in one and many traits</article-title><source>Genet Res</source><year>1996</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>165</fpage><lpage>173</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>B&#x000fc;rger</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolution of genetic variability and the advantage of sex and recombination in changing environments</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>1999</year><volume>153</volume><fpage>1055</fpage><lpage>1069</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10511578</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mather</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Polygenic inheritance and natural selection</article-title><source>Biol Rev</source><year>1943</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>32</fpage><lpage>64</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Population structure, parasitism, and the survivorship of sexual and autoploid parthenogenetic Campeloma limum</article-title><source>Evolution</source><year>2000</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>167</fpage><lpage>175</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10937193</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Valen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new evolutionary law</article-title><source>Evol Theor</source><year>1973</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>30</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sex versus non-sex versus parasite</article-title><source>Oikos</source><year>1980</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>282</fpage><lpage>290</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dybdahl</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Jokela</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lively</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic structure of coexisting sexual and clonal subpopulations in a freshwater snail (Potamopyrgus antipodarum)</article-title><source>Evolution</source><year>1996</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>1541</fpage><lpage>1548</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Howard</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lively</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The maintenance of sex by parasitism and mutation accumulation under epistatic fitness functions</article-title><source>Evolution</source><year>1998</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>604</fpage><lpage>610</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ooi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yahara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic variation of geminiviruses: comparison between sexual and asexual host plant populations</article-title><source>Mol Ecol</source><year>1999</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>97</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-294X.1999.00537.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lively</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Dybdahl</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Parasite adaptation to locally common host genotypes</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2000</year><volume>405</volume><fpage>679</fpage><lpage>681</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10864323</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35015069</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Leefe</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clonal diversity and polyphyletic origins of hybrid and spontaneous parthenogenetic Campeloma (Gastropoda: Viviparidae) from the south-eastern United States</article-title><source>J Evol Biol</source><year>1999</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1056</fpage><lpage>1068</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1420-9101.1999.00099.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vrijenhoek</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Factors affecting clonal diversity and coexistence</article-title><source>Am Zool</source><year>1979</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>787</fpage><lpage>797</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ladle</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnstone</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Judson</surname><given-names>OP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coevolutionary dynamics of sex in a metapopulation: escaping the Red Queen</article-title><source>P Roy Soc Lond B Bio</source><year>1993</year><volume>253</volume><fpage>155</fpage><lpage>160</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Judson</surname><given-names>OP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preserving genes: a model of the maintenance of genetic variation in a metapopulation under frequency-dependent selection</article-title><source>Genet Res</source><year>1995</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>175</fpage><lpage>191</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lively</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Howard</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Selection by parasites for clonal diversity and mixed mating</article-title><source>Philos T Roy Soc B</source><year>1994</year><volume>346</volume><fpage>271</fpage><lpage>281</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Howard</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lively</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Parasitism, mutation accumulation and the maintenance of sex</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1994</year><volume>367</volume><fpage>554</fpage><lpage>557</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8107824</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/367554a0</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Delmotte</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Leterme</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Gauthier</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Rispe</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic architecture of sexual and asexual populations of the aphid Rhopalosiphum padi based on allozyme and microsatellite markers</article-title><source>Mol Ecol</source><year>2002</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>711</fpage><lpage>723</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11972759</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-294X.2002.01478.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B31"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>H&#x000e4;ttenschwiler</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Die Sacktr&#x000e4;ger der Schweiz (Lepidoptera, Psychidae)</article-title><source>Schmetterlinge und ihre Lebensr&#x000e4;ume Arten - Gef&#x000e4;hrdung - Schutz Band 2</source><year>1997</year><publisher-name>Basel, Switzerland, Pro Natura</publisher-name><fpage>165</fpage><lpage>308</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B32"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumpulainen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>S&#x000e4;rkk&#x000e4; J, Olsbo P and Tynkkynen ML</surname></name></person-group><source>The evolution and maintenance of reproductive strategies in bag worm moths (Lepidoptera: Psychidae)</source><series>Jyv&#x000e4;skyl&#x000e4; Studies in Biological and Environmental Science</series><year>2004</year><publisher-name>Jyv&#x000e4;skyl&#x000e4;, University of Jyv&#x000e4;skyl&#x000e4;</publisher-name><fpage>0</fpage><lpage>42</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suomalainen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Solenobiinae species of Finland (Lepidoptera: Psychidae), with a description of a new species</article-title><source>Ent Scand</source><year>1980</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>458</fpage><lpage>466</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumpulainen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Grapputo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mappes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Parasites and sexual reproduction in psychid moths</article-title><source>Evolution</source><year>2004</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>1511</fpage><lpage>1520</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15341153</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Narbel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>La Cytologie de la Parth&#x000e9;nog&#x000e9;n&#x000e8;se chez Solenobia s p. (Lepidopteres Psychides)</article-title><source>Chromosoma</source><year>1950</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>56</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14812634</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00325767</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Watterson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The homozygosity test of neutrality</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>1978</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>405</fpage><lpage>417</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17248803</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chakraborty</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mitochondrial DNA polymorphism reveals hidden heterogeneity within some Asian populations</article-title><source>Am J Hum Genet</source><year>1990</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>87</fpage><lpage>94</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2349953</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brookfield</surname><given-names>JFY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A simple new method for estimating null allele frequency from heterozygote deficiency</article-title><source>Mol Ecol</source><year>1996</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>453</fpage><lpage>455</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8688964</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-294X.1996.00098.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B39"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suomalainen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Lokki</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Saura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic polymorphism and evolution in parthenogenetic animals. X. Solenobia species (Lepidoptera: Psychidae)</article-title><source>Hereditas</source><year>1981</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>35</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B40"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ecological implications of clonal diversity in parthenogenetic morphospecies</article-title><source>Am Zool</source><year>1979</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>753</fpage><lpage>762</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B41"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ellstrand</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Roose</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Patterns of genotypic diversity in clonal plant species</article-title><source>Am J Bot</source><year>1987</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>131</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B42"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Destabilizing hybridization, general-purpose genotypes and geographic parthenogenesis</article-title><source>Q Rev Biol</source><year>1984</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>257</fpage><lpage>290</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/413902</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B43"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vrijenhoek</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>W&#x000f6;hrmann K and Loeschcke V</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Ecological differentiation among clones: the frozen niche variation model</article-title><source>Population biology and evolution</source><year>1984</year><publisher-name>Berlin, Springer-Verlag</publisher-name><fpage>217</fpage><lpage>231</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B44"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gillespie</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><source>The causes of molecular evolution</source><year>1991</year><publisher-name>New York, Oxford University Press</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B45"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mitton</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group><source>Selection in natural populations</source><year>1997</year><publisher-name>New York, Oxford University Press</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B46"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suomalainen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Significance of parthenogenesis in the evolution of insects</article-title><source>Annu Rev Entomol</source><year>1962</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>349</fpage><lpage>365</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.en.07.010162.002025</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B47"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lokki</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Suomalainen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Saura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lankinen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic polymorphism and evolution in parthenogenetic animals. II. Diploid and polyploid Solenobia triquetrella (Lepidoptera: Psychidae)</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>1975</year><volume>79</volume><fpage>513</fpage><lpage>525</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1126629</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B48"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zouros</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Foltz</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Possible explanations of heterozygote deficiency in bivalve molluscs</article-title><source>Malacologia</source><year>1984</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>583</fpage><lpage>591</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B49"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Excess of allozyme homozygosity in marine molluscs and its possible biological significance</article-title><source>Malacologia</source><year>1984</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>569</fpage><lpage>581</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B50"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Allegrucci</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Fortunato</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sbordoni</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic structure and allozyme variation of sea bass (Dicentrarchus labrax and D. punctatus) in the Mediterranean Sea</article-title><source>Marine Biology</source><year>1997</year><volume>128</volume><fpage>347</fpage><lpage>358</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s002270050100</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B51"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Castric</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonney</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernatchez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Landscape structure and hierarchical genetic diversity in the brook charr Salvelinus fontinalis</article-title><source>Evolution</source><year>2001</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>1016</fpage><lpage>1028</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11430638</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B52"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Waldman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>McKinnon</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Thornhill NW</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Inbreeding and outbreeding in fishes, amphibians and reptiles</article-title><source>The natural history of inbreeding and outbreeding: theoretical and empirical perspectives</source><year>1993</year><publisher-name>Chicago, University of Chicago Press</publisher-name><fpage>250</fpage><lpage>283</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B53"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Castric</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernatchez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Belkhir</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonhomme</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Heterozygote deficiencies in small lacustrine populations of brook charr Salvelinus fontinalis Mitchill (Pisces, Salmonidae): a test of alternative hypotheses</article-title><source>Heredity</source><year>2002</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>35</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12080367</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.hdy.6800089</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B54"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hartl</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name></person-group><source>Principles of population genetics</source><year>1997</year><edition>3</edition><publisher-name>Sunderland, MA, Sinauer Associates</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B55"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hebert</surname><given-names>PDN</given-names></name><name><surname>Beaton</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><source>Methodologies for allozyme analysis using cellulose acetate electrophoresis</source><year>1993</year><publisher-name>Beaumont, Texas, Helena Laboratories</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B56"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yeh</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyle</surname><given-names>TJB</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>ZH</given-names></name><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>JX</given-names></name></person-group><source>POPGENE, the user-friendly shareware for population genetic analysis</source><year>1997</year><publisher-name>University of Alberta, Canada, Molecular Biology and Biotechnology Centre</publisher-name><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ualberta.ca/~fyeh/"/></citation></ref><ref id="B57"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goudet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>FSTAT (vers. 1.2): a computer program to calculate F-statistics</article-title><source>J Hered</source><year>1995</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>485</fpage><lpage>486</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B58"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysing tables of statistical tests</article-title><source>Evolution</source><year>1989</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>223</fpage><lpage>225</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B59"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petit</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>El Mousadik</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pons</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identifying populations for conservation on the basis of genetic markers</article-title><source>Conser Biol</source><year>1998</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>844</fpage><lpage>855</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1523-1739.1998.96489.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B60"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><source>Molecular Evolutionary Genetics</source><year>1987</year><publisher-name>New York, Columbia University Press</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B61"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Oosterhout</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hutchinson</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name><name><surname>Wills</surname><given-names>DPM</given-names></name><name><surname>Shipley</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MICRO-CHECKER: software for identifying and correcting genotyping errors in microsatellite data</article-title><source>Mol Ecol Notes</source><year>2004</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>535</fpage><lpage>538</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1471-8286.2004.00684.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B62"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weir</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Cockerham</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimating F-statistics for the analysis of population structure</article-title><source>Evolution</source><year>1984</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>1358</fpage><lpage>1370</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B63"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Excoffier</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Smouse</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Quattro</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of molecular variance inferred from metric distances among DNA haplotypes - Application to human mitochondrial-DNA restriction data</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>1992</year><volume>131</volume><fpage>479</fpage><lpage>491</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1644282</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B64"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Roessli</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Excoffier</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><source>Arlequin ver. 2.000: A software for population genetic data analysis.</source><year>2000</year><publisher-name>University of Geneva, Switzerland, Genetics and Biometry Laboratory</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B65"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rousset</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic differentiation and estimation of gene flow from F-statistics under isolation by distance</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>1997</year><volume>145</volume><fpage>1219</fpage><lpage>1228</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9093870</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>



