<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Genomics</journal-id><journal-title>BMC Genomics</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2164</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15833139</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1097725</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1471-2164-6-53</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-6-53</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Microarray karyotyping of commercial wine yeast strains reveals shared, as well as unique, genomic signatures</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>Barbara</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>bdunn@genome.stanford.edu</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>R Paul</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>plevine@stanford.edu</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sherlock</surname><given-names>Gavin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>sherlock@genome.stanford.edu</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Dept. of Genetics, Stanford University Medical Ctr., Stanford, CA 94305-5120, USA</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Dept. of Biological Sciences, Stanford University, Stanford, CA 94305-5020, USA</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2005</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>4</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2164/6/53"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>8</day><month>10</month><year>2004</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>4</month><year>2005</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2005 Dunn et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2005</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Dunn et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>
               Dunn
               Barbara
               
               bdunn@genome.stanford.edu
            </dc:author><dc:title>
            Microarray karyotyping of commercial wine yeast strains reveals shared, as well as unique, genomic signatures
         </dc:title><dc:date>2005</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>BMC Genomics 6(1): 53-. (2005)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1471-2164(2005)6:1&#x0003c;53&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1471-2164</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Genetic differences between yeast strains used in wine-making may account for some of the variation seen in their fermentation properties and may also produce differing sensory characteristics in the final wine product itself. To investigate this, we have determined genomic differences among several <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae </italic>wine strains by using a "microarray karyotyping" (also known as "array-CGH" or "aCGH") technique.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>We have studied four commonly used commercial wine yeast strains, assaying three independent isolates from each strain. All four wine strains showed common differences with respect to the laboratory <italic>S. cerevisiae </italic>strain S288C, some of which may be specific to commercial wine yeasts. We observed very little intra-strain variation; i.e., the genomic karyotypes of different commercial isolates of the same strain looked very similar, although an exception to this was seen among the Montrachet isolates. A moderate amount of inter-strain genomic variation between the four wine strains was observed, mostly in the form of depletions or amplifications of single genes; these differences allowed unique identification of each strain. Many of the inter-strain differences appear to be in transporter genes, especially hexose transporters (HXT genes), metal ion sensors/transporters (CUP1, ZRT1, ENA genes), members of the major facilitator superfamily, and in genes involved in drug response (PDR3, SNQ1, QDR1, RDS1, AYT1, YAR068W). We therefore used halo assays to investigate the response of these strains to three different fungicidal drugs (cycloheximide, clotrimazole, sulfomethuron methyl). Strains with fewer copies of the <italic>CUP1 </italic>loci showed hypersensitivity to sulfomethuron methyl.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Microarray karyotyping is a useful tool for analyzing the genome structures of wine yeasts. Despite only small to moderate variations in gene copy numbers between different wine yeast strains and within different isolates of a given strain, there was enough variation to allow unique identification of strains; additionally, some of the variation correlated with drug sensitivity. The relatively small number of differences seen by microarray karyotyping between the strains suggests that the differences in fermentative and organoleptic properties ascribed to these different strains may arise from a small number of genetic changes, making it possible to test whether the observed differences do indeed confer different sensory properties in the finished wine.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Winemakers have long noted that different strains of wine yeasts, even when used to ferment the same juice under identical conditions, can yield very different wines in terms of sensory characteristics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>], presumably as a result of variations in the strains' fermentative properties [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. Previous studies have demonstrated genetic diversity among both commercial [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>] and wild [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]<italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae </italic>wine yeast strains, and it has been hypothesized that this genetic diversity may, at least in part, be a root cause of their differing fermentative and sensory qualities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. In addition to a large amount of diversity in mitochondrial DNA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>], some wine yeast strains have been shown to be genetically unstable [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>], with varying ploidy levels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>], multiple chromosomal aneuploidies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>], and chromosome length polymorphisms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]. In addition, the genomes of a few wine yeast strains appear to have arisen from a hybridization event between two species, <italic>S. cerevisiae </italic>and <italic>S. bayanus</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>], similar to that of the lager yeast <italic>S. pastorianus </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>].</p><p>Many studies have shown that extensive genome rearrangements occur in organisms during adaptation to changing environments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>]. It is also likely that any source of cellular stress, such as an environmental insult, may trigger a "genome shock" response [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>], leading to genome rearrangements. Although some genome changes observed in yeast populations are on a small scale (one to a few nucleotides), many changes appear to be on the scale of entire genes or even whole chromosomes, resulting in alterations of their copy numbers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]. These features may be a result of uneven mitotic crossing over [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>], gene conversion or break-induced replication [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>], or Ty transposon-mediated chromosomal translocations[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>].</p><p>Wine-making has been an ongoing human activity for several millennia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>]. Although the wine strains we have examined in this paper are commercial strains that have been propagated industrially for only the last ~40 years, each of their progenitors were distinct wild strains that had presumably been selected for many hundreds, perhaps thousands, of years to confer specific organoleptic traits. Likewise the laboratory S288C strain has been propagated as a pure culture for ~70 years; while its exact background is unknown and may include both wild and baking yeasts, it is almost certain that S288C did not derive from any commonly-used wine yeast strains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>]. At a generation time of 1.5 hours, however, 70 years can represent thousands (possibly hundreds of thousands) of generations of divergence between commercial wine yeasts and their laboratory "cousins". The genomic differences that exist among these different wine yeast strains, and between wine and laboratory yeasts, may have arisen in response to the unique selective pressures that each has encountered during its propagation. Detailed characterization of these differences may thus shed light on which biochemical pathways and cellular processes play important roles in determining the specific fermentative qualities (and the resultant wine sensory characteristics) of a particular wine yeast strain.</p><p>The recent development of DNA microarrays has enabled an unprecedented level of genome-scale research on both gene expression patterns [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>], and also on genomic DNA copy number changes and genome rearrangements through the "array-CGH" ("aCGH") technique [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>], which we will refer to as "microarray karyotyping" or "array karyotyping". This technique can be used to determine copy number changes for every gene of a given species (whose genome has been sequenced) in relation to any other strain of that species, giving information on whole or partial chromosome aneuploidies, non-reciprocal translocations and isolated gene deletions or amplifications. Using human cDNA microarrays, this technique has helped elucidate genomic copy number changes in cancer cells during tumor progression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>]; using <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>-based microarrays, it has also been employed to discover non-reciprocal chromosomal translocations that occurred in yeasts evolved to tolerate low glucose concentrations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>]. A number of previous papers have demonstrated that aCGH data accurately reflects genome changes. For example, Pollack et al.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>], using human cDNA microarrays, demonstrated good correlation of copy number of known human X-chromosome aneuploid lines (from 0 to 5 X chromosomes per diploid genome) with aCGH data. Likewise for yeast microarrays, standard PCR [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>] or quantitative real-time PCR [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>] has been used to validate either deletions or amplifications predicted by aCGH data. Also, Dunham et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>] and Winzeler et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>] have used DNA sequencing to validate rearrangements (with associated copy number changes) or single-nucleotide polymorphisms, respectively, to corroborate their aCGH results.</p><p>Until recently, studies of the genetic diversity and instability of wine yeasts (reviewed by [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>]) were performed using either classical genetic means, pulsed-field gel analysis, or by molecular techniques such as PCR, Southern blotting and restriction-fragment length polymorphisms. These studies did not, however, utilize whole-genome platforms such as microarrays, and thus the results were confined to only certain regions of the genome. Global gene expression patterns in wine yeast strains, deduced by microarray analysis, have been recently reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">53</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">55</xref>], but these studies did not include microarray karyotyping of the wine yeasts.</p><p>Microarray karyotyping has also been used to explore the genomic diversity of different <italic>S. cerevisiae </italic>strains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">58</xref>] as well as the genomic architectures (relative to <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>) of the hybrid organism <italic>S. pastorianus </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>] and the <italic>sensu stricto </italic>group of closely-related <italic>Saccharomyces </italic>species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">59</xref>]. However, none of these studies have utilized microarray karyotyping to assay the genomes of commercially-used wine yeasts for both copy number increases and decreases relative to the sequenced S288c laboratory strain. As part of larger gene expression studies, Lashkari et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">57</xref>] and Primig et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">58</xref>] generated array karyotype data, relative to S288C, for the non-S288C-derived laboratory <italic>S. cerevisiae </italic>strains Y55 and SK1 respectively; however these authors did not analyze any wine strains by array karyotyping. Filter-based whole-ORF genome arrays have also been used to investigate global gene expression patterns in a wine yeast [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60">60</xref>]. These authors also re-hybridized a filter array using labeled genomic DNA to obtain gene copy numbers changes in the wine strain relative to the laboratory strain, but the data as presented did not show many interpretable changes in the wine strain other than a decrease in Ty1 copy number relative to the laboratory strain; a small amount of the same data generated by [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60">60</xref>], restricted to chromosome VIII, was also presented in a separate paper [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>].</p><p>Winzeler et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>] performed a type of array karyotyping on the Y55 strain, as well as on a wine strain, by using high-density short (25-mer) oligo arrays; however, their technique only allowed the detection of complete deletions at the whole gene or chromosome level, i.e., they could not detect amplification or hemizygous depletion of genes or chromosomes (e.g., the increase or decrease of just one copy of a gene or chromosome in a diploid cell, giving either three or one copies, respectively). It is important to note that whole-ORF arrays allow hybridization of even a fairly diverged gene (20 &#x02013; 25% nucleotide divergence) to the target ORF on the microarray due to the long length of the target. Such divergence is much more likely to occur in non-S288C strains such as wine strains. 25-mer oligo arrays, however, are exquisitely sensitive to single-nucleotide changes; this is useful in some regards, but less so when widely-diverged strains are being analyzed. Infante et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>] performed a very detailed microarray karyotyping study of the genomic differences between two "flor" yeasts used in the production of sherry wines; however, they only compared the two "flor" yeasts to each other, and not to the sequenced S288C laboratory strain. Finally, both Edwards-Ingram et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">59</xref>] and Bond et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>] used <italic>S. cerevisiae </italic>spotted ORF microarrays to look at the whole genome organization of other species that are closely related to <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>, but did not assess the genomes of wine yeasts.</p><p>We describe here the use of microarray karyotyping to explore global changes in the genomic DNA of four commonly-used commercial wine <italic>S. cerevisiae </italic>strains relative to each other and to the sequenced <italic>S. cerevisiae </italic>laboratory strain (S288C), including the analysis of three independent isolates of each of the four wine strains. We report on the characterization of genomic similarities and differences between the wine strains and the S288C laboratory strain, as well as between the different wine strains themselves and between different independent isolates of the same strain.</p></sec><sec><title>Results and discussion</title><sec><title>Microarray-based karyotyping</title><p>In the microarray karyotyping protocol employed here, genomic DNA from an experimental strain (i.e., a commercial wine yeast strain) was labeled with the fluorescent dye Cy5 (red), while genomic DNA from a wild-type (WT) reference strain (the sequenced haploid laboratory <italic>S. cerevisiae </italic>strain S288C) was labeled with the fluorescent Cy3 dye (green). The two labeled samples were mixed, then competitively hybridized to a spotted DNA microarray in which each spot is composed of PCR-amplified DNA corresponding to one gene of the reference S288C yeast <italic>S. cerevisiae </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">61</xref>]. Under standard conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">61</xref>], hybridization to the microarray spots will generally occur between DNA molecules with 75% or more sequence identity. All experiments were performed in duplicate, i.e., the labeled DNA was hybridized to two separate microarrays. Note that the raw data for all microarray hybridizations reported in this paper can be downloaded from the website <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://microarray-pubs.stanford.edu/wine_yeast/"/> as well as from the Stanford Microarray Database [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B62">62</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">63</xref>].</p><p>Assuming that the experimental strain's genome has not experienced significant sequence divergence (i.e., greater than 25%) from that of the laboratory reference strain &#x02013; a supposition which appears to be true for most <italic>S. cerevisiae </italic>wine yeast strains, which have an average of greater than 99% identity to the S288C strain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B64">64</xref>] &#x02013; any DNA copy number change in a single gene within the experimental strain will be detected by a deviation of the R/G ratio for that gene from the expected 1:1 ratio. If there are proportionally more copies of the gene in the experimental strain relative to the reference strain, the R/G ratio will thus be higher than 1:1 (ideally, it will be 2:1 for a duplication event, 3:1 for a triplication, etc.). Likewise, if there has been a deletion of the gene in the experimental strain relative to the reference strain, or if there are more copies of the gene in the reference strain than in the experimental strain (i.e., the experimental strain has experienced a "depletion" of the gene in terms of copy number), the R/G ratio will be less than 1:1 (ideally, it will be 1:2 for a single duplication in the reference strain relative to the wine strain, or for a deletion in the experimental strain of a single-copy gene in the reference strain, and so on). Thus, with only one hybridization, the DNA copy number of all 6,000 genes of a given strain can be determined relative to the reference strain.</p><p>Because microarray karyotyping detects proportional changes in DNA copy number relative to a reference strain, genome rearrangements that result in net copy number alterations can be easily detected with this method, including gene duplications or deletions, as well as larger-scale rearrangements such as non-reciprocal translocations, loss or amplification of large chromosomal regions, and ploidy changes for a single entire chromosome (aneuploidy). These large-scale rearrangements are seen as large regions of the chromosomes for which a similar bias in the ratios exists for all the genes in the region. Thus, despite the fact that complete genomic sequencing of every wine yeast strain is impractical, a great deal of information about the genomic structure of wine strains relative to laboratory strains and to each other can be achieved by microarray karyotyping.</p></sec><sec><title>Strains used for analysis</title><p>We chose four different commercial wine yeast strains for this study, using independent isolates from each of three different commercial and/or academic sources as shown in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>. The four yeast strains used were Montrachet, Pasteur Red, Pasteur Champagne, and Prise de Mousse (see Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref> and Methods for complete list). These are among the most commonly used commercially-produced yeast strains in winemaking. Each strain has distinct fermentative qualities, and each is thought to bring unique flavor and other sensory components to the finished wine product [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B65">65</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B66">66</xref>]. Independent isolates of each strain were obtained from two major wine yeast producers, Lalvin and Red Star, as well as from the wine yeast strain collection at Univ. of Calif., Davis (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Wine Yeast Strains used in Study</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="left"><bold><italic>Wine Yeast Type </italic><sup><italic>a</italic></sup></bold></td><td align="left"><bold><italic>Lab Name </italic><sup><italic>b</italic></sup></bold></td><td align="left"><bold><italic>Product Name </italic><sup><italic>c</italic></sup></bold></td><td align="left"><bold><italic>Source </italic><sup><italic>d</italic></sup></bold></td><td align="left"><bold><italic>Wine Use </italic><sup><italic>e</italic></sup></bold></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1. Montrachet</td><td align="left">GSY1</td><td align="left">Montrachet</td><td align="left">Lalvin</td><td align="left">White, Red</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">GSY2</td><td align="left">Montrachet</td><td align="left">Red Star</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">GSY3</td><td align="left">Montrachet (UCD522)</td><td align="left">U.C. Davis</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">2. French Red</td><td align="left">GSY4</td><td align="left">Pasteur Red</td><td align="left">Lalvin</td><td align="left">Red</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">GSY5</td><td align="left">French Red (UCD725)</td><td align="left">U.C. Davis</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">GSY6</td><td align="left">French Red (UCD904)</td><td align="left">U.C. Davis</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">3. Past. Champagne</td><td align="left">GSY7</td><td align="left">Champagne</td><td align="left">Lalvin</td><td align="left">Sparkling</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">GSY8</td><td align="left">Past. Champ.</td><td align="left">Red Star</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">GSY9</td><td align="left">Past. Champ. (UCD595)</td><td align="left">U.C. Davis</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">4. Prise de Mousse</td><td align="left">GSY10</td><td align="left">EC1118</td><td align="left">Lalvin</td><td align="left">White, Red</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">GSY11</td><td align="left">Premier Cuvee</td><td align="left">Red Star</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">GSY12</td><td align="left">Prise de Mousse (UCD819)</td><td align="left">U.C. Davis</td><td></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup><italic>a</italic></sup><italic>General category of wine yeast. <sup>b</sup>Name used in laboratory collection. <sup>c</sup>Name used by source (manufacturer); numbers in parentheses indicate the U.C. Davis strain collection name. <sup>d</sup>Commercial source of strain; see Methods for contact information. <sup>e</sup>General type(s) of wines for which strains are used</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>The genomes of all four wine yeast strains are highly similar to that of <italic>S. cerevisiae </italic>S288C</title><p>We performed microarray karyotyping, as described in Methods, on each of the wine yeast strains. Because some of the strains are listed by suppliers as either <italic>S. bayanus </italic>or <italic>S. cerevisiae/S. bayanus</italic>, we also performed microarray karyotyping experiments using genomic DNA from a known type strain of <italic>S. bayanus </italic>to determine what possible signal may be generated when hybridizing <italic>S. bayanus </italic>genomic DNA to <italic>S. cerevisiae </italic>microarrays. We performed a similar experiment using <italic>S. cerevisiae </italic>DNA as a control (a "self-self" hybridization).</p><p>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref> shows a graphical representation of the microarray karyotyping data for the <italic>S. cerevisiae </italic>and <italic>S. bayanus </italic>strains presented as "karyoscope" diagrams, made using the Java TreeView program [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B67">67</xref>]. To make a karyoscope diagram the hybridization ratio for each gene is mapped onto its corresponding position on each chromosome of the reference strain of <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>. The height of each red or green vertical bar is proportional to the log<sub>2 </sub>of the red:green (R/G) ratio for a gene; if the ratio is greater than 1 (i.e., a positive log<sub>2 </sub>value), the bar will be red and drawn above the chromosome; a red bar thus represents an over-representation (amplification) of that gene in the wine strain relative to S288C. For R/G ratios less than 1 (i.e., a negative log<sub>2 </sub>value), the bar will be green and drawn below the chromosome; a green bar thus represents an under-representation (deletion or depletion, i.e., lower copy number) of that gene in the wine strain relative to S288C.</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Karyoscope views of S288C-S288C and <italic>S. bayanus</italic>-S288C microarray hybridizations. </bold>Microarray hybridizations were performed as described in the text. In both panels the <italic>S. cerevisiae </italic>laboratory strain S288C was used as a reference sample, labeled with Cy3 dye (green). In panel A, the Cy5-labeled (red) DNA was also S288C, giving a self-self hybridization. In panel B, the Cy-5 labeled DNA was <italic>S. bayanus</italic>. The labeled DNAs were competitively hybridized to spotted microarrays bearing full-length ORFs from the S288C <italic>S. cerevisiae </italic>strain; the data thus obtained is displayed here in graphical form as a karyoscope. Red bars indicate red:green ratios above 1.0 and are graphed on a log scale; green bars indicate red:green ratios below 1.0, also graphed on a log scale. The chromosomes are shown in each panel in numerical order with chromosome 1 at the top and chromosome 16 at the bottom, and are aligned by their centromeres, with their left arms extending to the left. Both karyoscopes are drawn to the same scale, i.e., the bar heights in panels A and B proportionally represent the same amplitude of change.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2164-6-53-1"/></fig><p>In the "self-self" hybridization control, the genomic DNA from the reference <italic>S. cerevisiae </italic>laboratory strain was labeled independently with Cy3 and Cy5 and then competitively hybridized against itself. We observed robust hybridization across the entire array, and after a global mean normalization (see Methods) there were equal red and green hybridization signals (R/G ratios of 1), with no obvious deviations for any particular gene, as expected (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>). We found, however, that the <italic>S. bayanus </italic>DNA did not hybridize to the arrays in the same manner as did the <italic>S. cerevisiae </italic>genomic DNA. The <italic>S. bayanus </italic>hybridization signals (Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref>) were significantly weaker and much more variable across the array, as compared to the <italic>S. cerevisiae </italic>self-self hybridization (Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>).</p><p>For all 12 of the wine yeast isolates, we observed hybridization patterns much more similar to that of the "self-self" experiment, i.e., with robust signals across most of the array, and the majority of ratios near a value of 1.0. This indicates that each of the wine strains possesses an essentially complete complement of the <italic>S. cerevisiae </italic>genome, with no observed aneuploidy. Note that we cannot rule out that there may be additional genomic DNA in these wine strains that comes from other <italic>Saccharomyces </italic>species (i.e., if the strain is a hybrid organism) whose hybridization signal would be overshadowed by the signal generated by the <italic>S. cerevisiae </italic>genomic complement. However, we do not think this is likely, as control spots on the microarrays containing <italic>S. bayanus </italic>genomic DNA did not show a hybridization signal, which we consistently observe when using known <italic>S. cerevisiae &#x02013; S. bayanus </italic>hybrid yeasts (B. Dunn, unpublished). Thus, we do not expect any potential non <italic>cerevisiae </italic>DNA in any of these wine strains to have any great effect on our observed ratios.</p></sec><sec><title>Genomic differences between wine yeast strains and the laboratory strain</title><p>We observed a distinct set of genomic variations that occur in every wine strain relative to the laboratory strain; these are shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>, and an abbreviated list of these variations is given in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>. Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> represents a consensus karyoscope-type plot generated by the program CGH-Miner [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B68">68</xref>], where the data from the 4 wine strains (taken as averages of the data for the 3 isolates of each strain) have been consolidated into statistically-significant amplifications or depletions relative to multiple self-self hybridizations of the laboratory S288C strain.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>"Commercial Wine Strain Signature" Gene List<sup><italic>a</italic></sup></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="left"><bold>Sig. amplified in at least 3 strains</bold></td><td></td><td align="center"><bold>Montrachet</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>French Red</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Champagne</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Prise de Mousse</bold></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">YAR066W</td><td></td><td align="right"><bold>0.84</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>1.43</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>0.62</bold></td><td align="right"><italic>0.19</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">YAR068W</td><td></td><td align="right"><bold>1.05</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>1.67</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>0.91</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>0.52</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">YAR069C</td><td></td><td align="right"><bold>1.11</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>1.57</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>1.09</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>0.59</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">YAR070C</td><td></td><td align="right"><bold>1.14</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>1.62</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>1.16</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>0.63</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">YAR071W</td><td align="left">PHO11</td><td align="right"><bold>1.01</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>1.37</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>1.26</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>0.57</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">YAR073W</td><td align="left">IMD1</td><td align="right"><bold>0.99</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>1.41</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>1.34</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>0.56</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">YAR075W</td><td></td><td align="right"><bold>0.98</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>1.47</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>1.46</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>0.56</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">YPL276W</td><td></td><td align="right"><italic>0.59</italic></td><td align="right"><bold>1.36</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>1.64</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>0.75</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">YPL275W</td><td align="left">FDH2</td><td align="right"><italic>0.63</italic></td><td align="right"><bold>1.39</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>1.68</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>0.78</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">YPL274W</td><td align="left">SAM3</td><td align="right"><italic>0.58</italic></td><td align="right"><bold>1.06</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>1.31</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>0.66</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">YPL273W</td><td align="left">SAM4</td><td align="right"><italic>0.52</italic></td><td align="right"><bold>0.81</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>1.04</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>0.57</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">YPL272C</td><td></td><td align="right"><italic>0.49</italic></td><td align="right"><bold>0.59</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>0.79</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>0.47</bold></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Sig. depleted in at least 3 strains</bold></td><td></td><td align="center"><bold>Montrachet</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>French Red</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Champagne</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Prise de Mousse</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">YAR007C</td><td align="left">RFA1</td><td align="right"><bold>-0.44</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.73</bold></td><td align="right"><italic>-0.80</italic></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.31</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">YAR008W</td><td align="left">SEN34</td><td align="right"><bold>-1.05</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-1.53</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-1.31</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.69</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">YAR014C</td><td align="left">BUD14</td><td align="right"><bold>-1.03</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-1.25</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.99</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.65</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">YAR015W</td><td align="left">ADE1</td><td align="right"><bold>-0.54</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.63</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.64</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.38</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">YBL007C</td><td align="left">SLA1</td><td align="right"><bold>-0.51</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.61</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.81</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.39</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">YBL006C</td><td align="left">LDB7</td><td align="right"><bold>-0.86</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.99</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-1.02</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.66</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">YBL005W</td><td align="left">PDR3</td><td align="right"><bold>-0.88</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-1.07</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-1.10</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.67</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">YBR013C</td><td></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.97</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-1.58</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-1.04</bold></td><td align="right"><italic>-0.45</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">YHR052W</td><td align="left">CIC1</td><td align="right"><italic>-0.39</italic></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.89</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-1.40</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.78</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">YHR053C</td><td align="left">CUP1-1</td><td align="right"><italic>-0.46</italic></td><td align="right"><bold>-1.32</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-1.91</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-1.07</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">YHR054C</td><td></td><td align="right"><italic>-0.56</italic></td><td align="right"><bold>-1.65</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-2.16</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-1.29</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">YHR055C</td><td align="left">CUP1-2</td><td align="right"><italic>-0.56</italic></td><td align="right"><bold>-1.43</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-1.98</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-1.26</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">YHR056C</td><td align="left">RSC30</td><td align="right"><italic>-0.49</italic></td><td align="right"><bold>-1.10</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-1.52</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.96</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">YJR024C</td><td></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.59</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.62</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.49</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.30</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">YJR025C</td><td align="left">BNA1</td><td align="right"><bold>-0.91</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-1.13</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.84</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.53</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">YJR026W</td><td></td><td align="right"><bold>-1.47</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-1.92</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-1.41</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.90</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">YJR030C</td><td></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.95</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-1.65</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-1.32</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.67</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">YJR031C</td><td align="left">GEA1</td><td align="right"><bold>-0.41</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.90</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.78</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.32</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">YJR032W</td><td align="left">CPR7</td><td align="right"><bold>-0.16</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.31</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.39</bold></td><td align="right"><italic>-0.15</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">YJR033C</td><td align="left">RAV1</td><td align="right"><bold>-0.14</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.32</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.39</bold></td><td align="right"><italic>-0.11</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">YML047C</td><td align="left">PRM6</td><td align="right"><bold>-0.46</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.89</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.91</bold></td><td align="right"><italic>-0.25</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">YML046W</td><td align="left">PRP39</td><td align="right"><bold>-0.51</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-1.16</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-1.19</bold></td><td align="right"><italic>-0.31</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">YML043C</td><td align="left">RRN11</td><td align="right"><bold>-0.49</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.99</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-1.05</bold></td><td align="right"><italic>-0.33</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">YML042W</td><td align="left">CAT2</td><td align="right"><bold>-0.83</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-1.33</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-1.16</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.51</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">YML041C</td><td align="left">VPS71</td><td align="right"><bold>-0.93</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-1.35</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-1.18</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.58</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">YML038C</td><td align="left">YMD8</td><td align="right"><bold>-0.84</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-1.39</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-1.16</bold></td><td align="right"><italic>-0.46</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">YML037C</td><td></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.47</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.97</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.93</bold></td><td align="right"><italic>-0.23</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">YMR043W</td><td align="left">MCM1</td><td align="right"><bold>-0.30</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.28</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.30</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.23</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">YMR044W</td><td align="left">IOC4</td><td align="right"><bold>-0.81</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.98</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.82</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.59</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">YMR046W-A</td><td></td><td align="right"><bold>-1.14</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-1.58</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-1.29</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.78</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">YMR047C</td><td align="left">NUP116</td><td align="right"><bold>-0.70</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.96</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.88</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.56</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">YMR048W</td><td align="left">CSM3</td><td align="right"><bold>-0.69</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.89</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.75</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.46</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">YMR049C</td><td align="left">ERB1</td><td align="right"><bold>-1.07</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-1.45</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-1.03</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.66</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">YMR052W</td><td align="left">FAR3</td><td align="right"><bold>-1.17</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-1.87</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-1.28</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.63</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">YMR052C-A</td><td></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.69</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-1.26</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.89</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.36</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">YOL165C</td><td align="left">AAD15</td><td align="right"><bold>-1.09</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-1.03</bold></td><td align="right"><italic>-0.74</italic></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.80</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">YOL164W</td><td></td><td align="right"><bold>-1.33</bold></td><td align="right"><bold>-1.24</bold></td><td align="right"><italic>-0.96</italic></td><td align="right"><bold>-0.80</bold></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup><italic>a </italic></sup><italic>The data shown in this table are the actual mean log<sub>2</sub>(R/G) ratios for each gene, calculated by averaging the values from the six arrays (duplicate arrays of each of the three isolates of each strain) hybridized per wine strain. This list represents the wine-specific subset of the total set of genes with significant copy number changes, as described in the text. Values shown in bold text were determined by the CGH-Miner program to be significantly depleted or amplified as indicated. Values not significantly depleted or amplified are shown in non-bold italicized text</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>Changes in Gene Copy Number Shared by all Wine Strains: the "Commercial Wine Yeast Signature"</bold>. A consensus plot pooling the results of all the wine strains relative to the lab strain S288C was generated by the program CGH-Miner [68]. This plot is similar to a karyoscope in that it displays values along each chromosome, and the chromosomes are shown in numerical order from top to bottom. However, in this plot, a determination of which regions were statistically significantly altered in copy number for each wine strain (i.e., averaged array values for each of the three isolates within a strain) relative to the laboratory S288C strain were determined. For each of these regions the number of wine strains showing a significant change were then added together to give a metric of how well-shared among the wine strains that particular change was. This is shown as tall red bars for significantly amplified regions among all wine yeast strains relative to the laboratory strain, and as tall green bars for significantly depleted regions in all the wine strains relative to the laboratory strain. Each gray "shadow line" above or below the chromosome represents 20% of the number of wine strains showing a significant change in that region (see legend). The group of changes comprising the tallest (&#x0003e;75%) red and green bars represents the "commercial wine strain signature"; these are listed in Table 2.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2164-6-53-2"/></fig><p>The most distinctive genomic variations seen in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> are the many prominent green bars which are seen on most of the chromosomes. These shared green bars represent genes or regions in the wine strains, taken together as a whole, that are depleted in copy number relative to the laboratory strain. In most cases these shared depleted regions consist of genes that are moderately or highly repeated in the laboratory strain, with the majority representing Ty1 elements (a yeast retrotransposon family). Also depleted are the tandemly-repeated <italic>ASP3 </italic>(asparaginase) genes on chromosome 12, and the tandemly-repeated <italic>ENA </italic>(sodium transport) genes on chromosome 4; note: general descriptions and functions for genes described in this paper were obtained from the <italic>Saccharomyces </italic>Genome Database (SGD) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B69">69</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B70">70</xref>]. The <italic>CUP1 </italic>(copper binding) tandemly-repeated genes are also significantly depleted in 3 of the 4 strains (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>, Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>) and additionally show some intra-strain variation in copy number (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>); depletion of the <italic>CUP1 </italic>genes has been observed previously in a wine strain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>]. Because these sequences are all moderately repetitive and highly conserved, we can only interpret these results to indicate that in all of the wine strains we investigated, there are either fewer or no copies of these repeated genes relative to the laboratory strain.</p><p>Because the CGH-Miner program utilizes a moving-average method for calculating significance, copy number changes of single isolated genes are not detected. However, inspection of clustered data and karyoscopes allowed us to identify single genes whose copy numbers are highly altered relative to the reference strain. Among these, we found that the single-copy drug response genes <italic>SNQ2 </italic>and <italic>PDR15 </italic>are depleted in all of the wine strains we examined (Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>). In addition, <italic>PDR3</italic>, a single-copy zinc-finger transcription factor involved in pleiotropic resistance to drugs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B71">71</xref>], appears to be entirely deleted in all four wine strains due to the very low R/G ratios it exhibits (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>, Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>). This gene resides adjacent to one of the Ty1 elements that is depleted in the wine strains. Additional altered-copy number genes identified by inspection of karyoscopes are listed in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>.</p><p>In addition to the shared depleted regions, there are shared regions that appear to be slightly, but consistently, amplified in all four wine yeast strains; the most prominent is located at the right end of chromosomes 1; other regions are on the right arms of chromosomes 2 and 12, and the left end of chromosome 16 (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>, Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). These shared amplified regions contain some genes that are members of homologous gene families in the reference strain, such as the <italic>IMD </italic>genes (involved in GMP production) and <italic>PHO </italic>genes (acid phosphatases), but they also include unique genes such as <italic>SAM3 </italic>and <italic>SAM4 </italic>(S-adenosyl methionine transport and S-AM metabolism, respectively), <italic>PET8 </italic>(mitochondrial S-AM transport), <italic>RDS1 </italic>(response to xenobiotic drugs, including fungicides, herbicides, and pesticides), <italic>TPO1 </italic>(multidrug and polyamine transporter and drug detoxification), <italic>AAD3 </italic>(aryl-alcohol dehydrogenase), <italic>ADH7 </italic>(alcohol dehydrogenase), and <italic>FDH1 </italic>and <italic>FDH2 </italic>(formate dehydrogenase) (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>, Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>). Also occurring in an amplified region is the un-named and uncharacterized gene <italic>YAR068W </italic>(Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>, Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>). This gene codes for a membrane protein which when overexpressed results in resistance to the drug ketoconazole [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B72">72</xref>]; additionally, it has been found to have one of the most elevated K<sub>a</sub>/K<sub>s </sub>ratios among the genomes of the <italic>Saccharomyces sensu stricto </italic>group [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B73">73</xref>], signifying that it may be a gene that is actively undergoing positive selection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B74">74</xref>]. A homologue to this gene, <italic>YHR214W-A</italic>, is also amplified in most of the wine yeast strains.</p><p>These results indicate that all of the wine strains that we examined have experienced a characteristic increase or decrease in copy number, relative to that of the laboratory strain, of the genes listed in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>. Although some of these changes, particularly the low copy number (or absence) of the <italic>ENA </italic>and <italic>ASP3 </italic>genes and of Ty1 elements, are consistently observed in other industrial and non-S288C laboratory yeast strains ([<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">57</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60">60</xref>], B. Dunn, unpublished), most of the other changes, particularly the amplifications, are novel and thus far appear to be unique to commercial wine yeasts.</p></sec><sec><title>Genes whose copy number changes are shared by all wine strains</title><p>Interestingly, there are many transporter and permease genes, including some involved in drug response, that show altered copy numbers in the all the wine strains relative to the laboratory strain. As described above, <italic>PDR3, PDR15, RDS1</italic>, <italic>SNQ2, TPO1</italic>, and <italic>YAR068W </italic>show alterations in their copy numbers that are shared by all the wine strains. In addition, <italic>HXT9 </italic>and <italic>HXT11 </italic>are depleted in three of the four strains (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>), and <italic>AYT1 </italic>is depleted in 2 strains and amplified in the other two. All of these genes are involved in some aspect of drug response [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B71">71</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B72">72</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B75">75</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B78">78</xref>].</p><p>It thus appears that a major group of shared genomic differences found among all the wine strains is composed of genes, especially transporters and permeases, involved in drug resistance pathways. Since vineyards are often treated with herbicides, pesticides, and fungicides, wine yeasts may be exposed to these agents on a routine basis and their genomes may have evolved to better tolerate such exposure. Alternatively &#x02013; and perhaps more likely given the fact that these commercial strains may have been isolated prior to the widespread use of herbicides, pesticides and fungicides &#x02013; the variations in transporter gene copy number seen here may have arisen to fine-tune the fermentation properties of the wine yeasts by altering the types and amounts of fermentable substrates that are taken up. These variations may also reflect an increased tolerance to, or excretion of, plant phenolic compounds. Thus, any changes in drug response pathways in these strains may be a secondary effect and not due to direct selection for drug resistance or sensitivity. This view is supported by reports that alterations in <italic>PDR1 </italic>and <italic>PDR3 </italic>gene expression, as well as mutations in the ABC transporter genes that they regulate, result in better fermentation performance by sake yeasts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B79">79</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B80">80</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Inter-strain variation</title><p>We also observed inter-strain genomic variations that are specific to each wine strain. Examples of such inter-strain genomic variation are highlighted as regions circled in black on the Karyoscopes in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A&#x02013;D</xref>. For an idea of scale in these karyoscopes, the tallest bars on the figure represent ratios of approximately 2:1 (2-fold enhanced) for red, and 1:16 (16-fold depleted) for green. Each panel in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref> represents the average of the hybridization log ratios for all three independent isolates of the given strain; since each isolate's DNA was hybridized in duplicate, each panel thus represents the average of six arrays, making the data very robust. Some examples of inter-strain variation are also shown in more detail in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref>, in which the hybridization data are represented as colored boxes, with the most intense green representing severe depletion (R/G ratios much less than 1), black representing no change in copy number (R/G ratio of approximately 1), and the most intense red representing significant amplification (R/G ratios greater than 1).</p><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>Wine strain karyoscopes. </bold>Microarray ratios from each of the three isolates of a given wine strain were averaged to yield an "average" microarray karyotype for each wine strain. Chromosomes 9 through 16 for the 4 strains are shown in panels A &#x02013; D as follows: A. "Mont" = Montrachet (average of strains GSY1-3). B. "PDM" = Prise de Mousse (average of strains GSY10-12). C. "Champ" = Pasteur Champagne (average of strains GSY7-9). D. "Red" = French Red (average of strains GSY4-6). Circled regions highlight areas that vary in characteristic ways between the different wine strains. All karyoscopes are drawn to the same scale.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2164-6-53-3"/></fig><p>One distinct inter-strain variation is seen in the copy numbers of <italic>HXT </italic>(hexose transporter) genes. As shown by the black-circled regions on chromosomes 9 and 10 in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A&#x02013;D</xref>, and in the top panel of Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref>, the Prise de Mousse isolates show no depletion of the <italic>HXT9</italic>, <italic>HXT11</italic>, and <italic>HXT12 </italic>genes, whereas the Pasteur Red isolates show a slight depletion of these genes. On the other hand, the Montrachet and Champagne isolates show extreme depletion of these genes. Since these three <italic>HXT </italic>genes are all virtually identical to each other and can cross-hybridize, this result is most likely explained by a loss of one or more of the three genes in the depleted strains. It is impossible, however, to know which particular gene(s) are missing without further investigation.</p><p>Another class of inter-strain differences is of particular interest because the differences are seen in genes that are single-copy in the laboratory strain. Depletions of these genes in a given wine strain as measured by array karyotyping may thus reflect a true deletion of that gene relative to the other wine strains, rather than just a decrease in copy number. Three instances of this type of inter-strain variation were found: the <italic>AYT1 </italic>gene (chromosome 12), the <italic>ENB1 </italic>gene (chromosome 15), and the un-characterized ORF <italic>YPL257W </italic>(chromosome 16). The circled regions on the relevant chromosomes in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A&#x02013;D</xref> highlight these single-gene strain differences, while Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref> shows the data in more detail for these three genes. <italic>AYT1 </italic>encodes an acetyltransferase that was first characterized in <italic>Fusarium </italic>and subsequently identified in <italic>S. cerevisiae </italic>by homology [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B75">75</xref>]. It plays a role in de-toxifying endotoxins of the tricothecene family in <italic>Fusarium</italic>, but its function in <italic>S. cerevisiae </italic>is unknown. Although it has been shown that the <italic>S. cerevisiae AYT1 </italic>gene product can acetylate tricothecene <italic>in vivo</italic>, cells that are deficient for this gene show no increased sensitivity to the compound, and in fact show no phenotype at all [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B75">75</xref>]. <italic>ENB1 </italic>encodes an enterobactin transporter of the major facilitator superfamily involved in iron uptake [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B81">81</xref>], while <italic>YPL257W </italic>has no known function, although its predicted product has homology to membrane proteins.</p></sec><sec><title>Intra-strain variation</title><p>We observed relatively little genomic variation between independent isolates of each of the different strains. A major exception to this was seen, however, among the three different isolates of Montrachet. As shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>, the Montrachet isolate obtained from Lalvin (GSY1) has a fairly extensive region near the left end of chromosome 7 that exhibits copy-number depletion (relative to the S288C reference strain), seen as a distinct cluster of green bars (a thick black line underlines this region). This region spans approximately 37 contiguous genes, all of which show a ratio lower than 1 (shown as green bars). This is in contrast to the other two Montrachet isolates (GSY2 and GSY3 from Red Star and UCD, respectively), which show no copy-number depletion in this region (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). Because so many contiguous genes are involved in this block of genes, and because almost all of the genes exhibit a similar direction and magnitude of deviation, we believe that this region has been lost from either one or both copies of chromosome 7 in the (presumably diploid) Lalvin isolate, yielding a net depletion in the copy numbers of these genes relative to the reference strain. It is formally possible that sequence divergence in the region caused the decreased hybridization to the reference strain, but this is unlikely because sequence divergence rarely, if ever, occurs in such a dense and homogeneous pattern, nor is it ever constrained to only one region of the genome. Since there are at least two essential genes in this region (see below), it is most likely that only one of the chromosomes in this presumably diploid strain has lost this region.</p><p>It is likely that the region of depletion extends out to the end of the chromosome, despite the fact that the two distal-most genes appear as red (amplified) bars; both genes are sub-telomeric genes that are repeated in the genome and it is thus not possible to determine whether the chromosome 7 copies are specifically present or not. Therefore, the event that caused the depletion of this large region of chromosome 7 in the Lalvin isolate could have been a non-reciprocal translocation resulting in the net loss of the distal end of chromosome 7. This is supported by the fact that the inner (proximal) boundary of the depleted region occurs exactly at a tRNA (tV(AAC)G3). It has been shown that non-reciprocal translocations and other types of gross chromosomal rearrangement events that result in better-adapted genotypes occur frequently during adaptive evolutionary growth, and that these rearrangements are almost always bounded by tRNAs or Ty1 elements [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B82">82</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B84">84</xref>].</p><fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><bold>Karyoscopes of Chromosome 7 from individual Montrachet isolates</bold>. The larger black bar on the left, placed under the left end of chromosome 7 from the Lalvin Montrachet isolate (GSY1), shows a 37-ORF region that has been depleted (or deleted) with respect to the S288C laboratory strain and with respect to the chromosome 7's of each of the other two Montrachet isolates. The smaller black bar on the right, under the UCD522 (GSY3) chromosome, indicates a region of 3 ORFs (including <italic>MAL11 </italic>and <italic>MAL13</italic>) that are present at "wild-type" (S288C) copy number in the UCD522 strain but are depleted or deleted in the other two Montrachet strains. Note that this same <italic>MAL </italic>region is also present at "wild-type" copy number in UCD725, but is depleted or deleted in all remaining wine yeast strains. Again, all karyoscopes are drawn to the same scale.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2164-6-53-4"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><bold>Unique combinations of genomic differences between different strains. </bold>Panel A: Selected portions of the averaged data shown in Karyoscope form in Figure 3 are shown here in color-block form. To generate this figure the averaged data for all four wine strains were sorted for the Montrachet strain from highest green values (greatest negative number) to highest red values (greatest postitive number) and visualized as a "clustergram" using Java TreeView (note that the data were sorted, but however, were not clustered). The topmost (most green) 25 genes are shown in the top panel; the lower two panels show the sorted data surrounding two of the genes (<italic>AYT1 </italic>in the middle panel, <italic>YPL257W </italic>in the lowest panel) whose copy number varies greatly on a strain-to-strain basis. Red asterisks mark the genes whose copy numbers vary in unique combinations between the different strains. Panel B shows a matrix of gene copy number changes for each of the 12 wine strain isolates, along with the drug response profiles of each strain isolate at the bottom. Within the copy number data portion, a dark red cell with a "++" symbol indicates a red:green log ratio greater than 0.8, light red with "+" indicates a ratio between 0.2 and 0.8, and gray with "+/-" indicates a ratio between 0.2 and -0.2. Likewise dark green with "--" indicates a red:green log ratio less than -0.8, light green with "-" indicates a ratio between -0.2 and -0.8.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2164-6-53-5"/></fig><p>The depleted region of Chromosome 7 in the Lalvin Montrachet isolate extends from Open Reading Frame ("ORF") <italic>YGL226W </italic>through <italic>YGL261W</italic>. Included in this region are three genes, two essential and one non-essential, involved in protein-nucleus export (<italic>BRR6</italic>, <italic>CSE1</italic>, <italic>KAP114</italic>), two genes involved in cell cycle control (<italic>SAP4</italic>, <italic>DOC1</italic>), as well as genes involved in secretion (<italic>SEC15</italic>), and respiratory growth (<italic>HAP2</italic>, <italic>MTO1</italic>). Also included in this region is a transporter protein for zinc uptake (<italic>ZRT1</italic>). Of possible significance in terms of winemaking are genes that are involved in glucose/fructose (<italic>HXK2</italic>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">55</xref>] and alcohol (<italic>ADH4</italic>) metabolism [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B85">85</xref>], as well as one gene (<italic>YGL258W</italic>) involved in velum formation in a flor (Sherry) yeast strain. Interestingly, <italic>YGL258W </italic>and <italic>ADH4 </italic>are both induced under zinc-deficient conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B86">86</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B87">87</xref>], which may have significance with respect to the associated depletion of <italic>ZRT1</italic>. If significant fermentative or organoleptic differences exist between the Lalvin Montrachet isolate and the other two Montrachet isolates, it would be interesting to determine whether adding back genes from the depleted region (e.g. on a stable single-copy CEN plasmid) to the Lalvin isolate would cause its fermentative and/or organoleptic characteristics to now mimic those of the other two isolates.</p><p>A second intra-strain difference we observed is a depletion of four genes near the right end of chromosome 7 that is seen in both the Lalvin and Red Star Montrachet isolates but not in the UCD522 Montrachet isolate (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>, shorter black bar underlining the region at the right telomere). This group of four genes includes a maltose permease gene (<italic>MAL11</italic>) and a maltose-activator protein (<italic>MAL13</italic>); loss of these genes usually indicates a defect in maltose fermentation, but they also appear to be involved in drug response pathways since deletions of <italic>MAL11 </italic>lead to nystatin sensitivity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B88">88</xref>]. We observed that this same group of <italic>MAL </italic>genes is depleted in all of the other strain isolates except in the French Red isolate UCD725 (GSY5). In other words, of all 12 isolates that we studied, only UCD522 (GSY3) Montrachet and UCD725 (GSY5) French Red do not show a depletion of this <italic>MAL </italic>region relative to the reference S288C strain (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A&#x02013;D</xref>, Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>).</p><p>Finally, two genomic differences were seen in the UCD725 French Red isolate (GSY5) when compared to the other two French Red strains (GSY4 and GSY6). First, as mentioned just above, the same group of <italic>MAL </italic>genes that is present at wild-type copy number in the UCD522 Montrachet isolate is also present in this UCD725 isolate, but is depleted in the other two French Red isolates. Secondly, <italic>YPL257W </italic>is depleted in the French Red strains GSY4 and GSY6, but is present at wild-type copy number in GSY5 (data not shown). This gene, encoding a putative membrane protein, is one of the set of genes that exhibit a characteristic copy number genotype between the different wine yeast strains (see below), but it apparently varies in its genotype among the French Red isolates. Overall, however, aside from the fairly small differences among the Montrachet and French Red strains, there is remarkably little intra-strain genomic variation among the strains we studied, indicating that these wine strains are relatively stable genetically, at least as assayed by microarray karyotyping.</p></sec><sec><title>Transporters and permeases are part of the shared group of copy number differences, and also show inter- and intra-strain differences</title><p>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref> shows a matrix of relative copy numbers for each of the 12 individual wine strain isolates. The first group of genes shown in the matrix represents all of the Major Facilitator Superfamily (MFS) transporter genes for which a large copy number deviation relative to the reference strain (defined as log<sub>2 </sub>(R/G) value greater than 0.8 or less than -0.8, corresponding to a 1.74 fold change) was seen for at least one isolate. A "-" or "--" sign indicates moderate or large depletion of the gene's copy number, respectively; assuming that these are diploid strains, a "-" would indicate a loss of one of the two copies and a "--" would indicate loss of both copies. Likewise, "+" or "++" indicates moderate or large amplification of the gene, respectively, which would indicate an increase from 2 to 3 copies for "+" and to 4 or more copies for "++". Remarkably, of the total of 27 MFS transporter genes annotated as such in the <italic>Saccharomyces </italic>Genome Database [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B69">69</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B70">70</xref>], almost half (13) show large deviations (as defined above) in copy number among the wine strain isolates; all 13 are shown in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>. Most MFS transporters show a depletion in copy number relative to the wild-type strain; <italic>TPO1</italic>, which can transport cycloheximide and other drugs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B78">78</xref>], is the major exception, showing amplification in all strains.</p><p>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref> also shows copy number data for known permeases and other transporters, as well as any genes annotated as having a role in drug response that show a large deviation in at least one isolate. Finally, genes which do not fall into a transporter/membrane protein class, but which nonetheless stood out in the clustered data as being significantly altered in copy number relative to S288C are included (e.g., the <italic>CUP1 </italic>locus and members of the S-adenosylmethione metabolism pathway). At the bottom of the figure are shown the results of the drug halo assays for each of the isolates (see below).</p></sec><sec><title>Drug resistance/sensitivity phenotypes in wine strains</title><p>The prevalence of genes involved in drug response and drug resistance occurring in both the shared group of copy number changes, as well as in inter- and intra-strain differences, directed us to investigate the drug response profiles of the wine yeast strains. We chose three different drugs with which to assay the cells, representing three different general classes of drugs: cycloheximide, "CYH" (a protein synthesis inhibitor); clotrimazole, "CTZ" (member of the azole class of antifungal agents which inhibit ergosterol synthesis); and sulfomethuron methyl, "SMM" (a sulfonylurea herbicide). As described in Methods, halo assays were performed on all 12 wine strains listed in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref> as well as on six other control yeast strains mentioned in Methods. These additional six strains represent either control wild-type strains (FY1679, S288C, RW2802) or strains with single-gene deletions of various drug resistance genes whose copy numbers had been observed to be altered in the wine yeast strains: an <italic>AYT1 </italic>deletion strain (ScAYT1&#x00394;; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B75">75</xref>]), a <italic>PDR5 </italic>deletion strain (JG436; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B75">75</xref>]), and a <italic>YPL257W </italic>deletion strain (GSY28).</p><p>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6B</xref> show the actual halos on the plates, while Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6C</xref> tabulates the halo results in chart form. The most notable feature of the chart is that the majority of the 12 wine strain isolates (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6A, 6C</xref>) are very sensitive to SMM compared to the WT diploid laboratory strain. However, there are three exceptions to the SMM sensitivity, with two of the three Montrachet isolates, Lalvin Montrachet (GSY1) and Red Star Montrachet (GSY2), as well as the UCD725 French Red isolate (GSY5), showing much less sensitivity or even low resistance to SMM.</p><fig position="float" id="F6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><bold>Drug resistance phenotypes of wine strains</bold>. Halo assays were performed as described in the text to test the response of the wine strains to various drugs. Panels A and B show photographs of the halos; on the far left of each panel are shown the halo assays for the WT-diploid (FY1679, a S288C-based diploid, see Methods), against which all other strains were compared. CYH = 500 ng cycloheximide; CTZ = 5 &#x003bc;g clotrimazole; SMM = 20 &#x003bc;g sulfomethuron methyl. <bold>Panel A: </bold>strains are as described in Methods and Table 1; "WT-Dip" refers to FY1679. <bold>Panel B: </bold>Strains are as described in Methods; "WT-Dip" refers to FY1679; "YPL257 &#x00394;" to GSY28; "ayt1 &#x00394;" to ScAYT1&#x00394;, "pdr5<sup>-</sup>" to JG436; and "WT-Hap" to S288C. <bold>Panel C: </bold>Graphical results of halo assays. Annular area (i.e., area of total halo minus area of disc) was calculated for each halo, then expressed as log<sub>2 </sub>of the ratio of the annular area to that of the WT-Dip (FY1679) annular area.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2164-6-53-6"/></fig><p>It can also be seen in Figs. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6C</xref> that the individual isolates of Champagne (GSY7-9) and Prise de Mousse (GSY10-12) wine strains show more consistency in their drug response profiles than do the individual isolates of Montrachet (GSY1-3) and French Red (GSY4-6). Interestingly, it is the individual isolates of both the Montrachet and the French Red wine strains that also showed the most variability in their genome structures (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>).</p><p>Halo assays for the control yeast strains are shown in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6B</xref>. As expected, the <italic>pdr5 </italic>strain, known to be hypersensitive to drugs, is extremely sensitive to CYH and to CTZ. It is very resistant to SMM, however, with no halo at all forming around the SMM disc. The <italic>ayt1</italic>&#x00394; strain's response to CTZ or CYH is similar to that of the WT diploid, but like the <italic>pdr5 </italic>strain it is very resistant to SMM. The <italic>YPL257W</italic>&#x00394; strain shows moderate resistance to SMM compared to the WT diploid, with no variant response to CTZ or CYH. Note that both of the haploid wild-type control strains, S288C ("WT-Hap" in figure) and RW2802, show greater resistance to SMM than does the WT diploid strain; S288C is moderately resistant and RW2802 is extremely resistant, with no halo detected in the presence of SMM. This may indicate that haploid strains are for some reason more resistant to SMM than diploid strains. It also appears that strain differences (i.e., compare RW2802 and S288C) may affect the degree of resistance to SMM.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>We have found that each of the three independent isolates of the four commercially-produced wine strains we examined (i.e., 12 strains total) are all <italic>S. cerevisiae </italic>strains, based on their array karyotypes showing that all have genomes highly similar to the standard laboratory <italic>S. cerevisiae </italic>strain (S288C). Two of the wine strains we examined &#x02013; Prise de Mousse (also known as EC1118 or Premier Cuv&#x000e9;e), and Pasteur Champagne &#x02013; were listed in company catalogs as <italic>S. cerevisiae var. bayanus </italic>or <italic>S. bayanus</italic>, and the other two as <italic>S. cerevisiae var. cerevisiae </italic>or <italic>S. cerevisiae </italic>(e.g., see [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B89">89</xref>]). Our hybridization data thus show that there is great similarity between <italic>S. cerevisiae var. bayanus </italic>and <italic>S. cerevisiae var. cerevisiae</italic>, supporting the view that variety or race designations within <italic>S. cerevisiae </italic>should be abolished if there is no overwhelming phenotypic or molecular evidence to support their existence; this conclusion was also reached by Fernandez-Espinar et al. in a study comparing different isolates of commercial wine yeasts by restriction fragment polymorphisms, pulsed-field gels, and PCR analysis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B90">90</xref>].</p><p>Contrary to previous results [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>], none of the strains we examined showed any whole chromosome aneuploidies for <italic>S. cerevisiae </italic>chromosomes, although two of the strains we examined (UCD522 and UCD595) were identical to those used in that study. We know from our work with hybrid yeast strains that array karyotyping can easily detect whole chromosome aneuploidies (B. Dunn, unpublished), so we believe that the wine strains we examined in this work indeed do not contain any whole chromosome aneuploidies; we do not know the basis for the discrepancy other than that the previous study used indirect (genetic) means to detect the aneuploidies and it is possible that some of the markers behaved aberrantly.</p><p>We also found that the wine strains we examined all shared in common a set of genome copy number changes relative to the standard S288C strain. Many of these changes are either in Ty1 transposons, where copy number changes can be explained by differences in transposition rates, or in tandemly-repeated genes, where gene copy number changes can be explained by unequal cross-overs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>]. In fact, copy number depletion relative to the <italic>S. cerevisiae </italic>S288C strain of Ty1 elements and the tandemly-repeated <italic>ASP3 </italic>and <italic>ENA </italic>regions have been noted previously in various non-S288C yeast strains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">57</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60">60</xref>], B. Dunn, unpublished); they therefore appear to be changes shared by many, if not all, non-S288C yeast strains; although they are thus not wine strain specific, they are shared by all the wine strains we examined.</p><p>We therefore propose a "commercial wine strain signature" that comprises those genes whose copy number is altered in all the wine yeast isolates we examined relative to the sequenced S288C strain, but which excludes any of the genes whose copy numbers are altered in ale or beer strains or in other non-S288C laboratory strains such as SK1 and Y55. The final list of genes in the "commercial wine strain signature" is given in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>; it is comprised of a subset of those genes for which a statistically significant change in copy number, either depletion or amplification, occurred in at least 3 of 4 strains, as determined by the CGH-Miner program. All Ty1 genes, the ENA1, 2 and 5 genes, and genes from the ASP3 region on Chromosome XII have been eliminated from this list since they appear to be copy number changes shared by all non-S288C yeast strains and are not wine-specific.</p><p>Also of interest are the genes that show inter- or intra-genic variation, shown in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>. These genes consist mainly of sets of transporter or sugar utilization genes residing at or near the telomeres. These genes can undergo a type of inter-chromosomal unequal cross-over or gene-conversion event through dispersed sub-telomeric sequences shared among the ends of the chromosomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B91">91</xref>], and thus can undergo changes in copy number relatively facilely. Although many other non-wine, non-S288C strains have been observed to have alterations (predominantly deletions) in sub-telomeric sugar utilization genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>], none of them show the exact pattern of the "commercial wine strain signature". This is not surprising, since it might be expected that the exact suite of transporter and sugar utilization genes would vary in defined patterns among yeasts, depending on the particular substrate (e.g., grape juice, malted barley, laboratory defined media, or wheat flour) on which they had been selected for good growth performance. In fact, the wine strains are unique in having several sets of sub-telomeric genes, most notably those at the right end of Chromosome I (<italic>YAR064W </italic>&#x02013; <italic>YAR075W</italic>), amplified relative to the S288C strain. On a blind assessment of a panel of karyoscopes generated from an ongoing study (B. Dunn, unpublished), which included a set of 6 additional commercial wine strains, as well as beer strains (one ale and one lager), laboratory non-S288C strains (Y55 and SK1), and S288C itself, we were easily able to identify the wine strains as a set distinct from the other strains. The assignment as a "wine" strain was based mainly on the presence of the amplified region at the right end of chromosome I, as well as small amplified telomeric regions on both ends of Chromosome III. In addition, a subset of the wine strains exhibited a characteristic depletion of either <italic>AYT1</italic>, <italic>ENB1 </italic>or <italic>YPL257W </italic>as discussed below. We thus believe that the list presented in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref> is a <italic>bona fide </italic>"commercial wine strain signature", at least for commercially-produced wine strains; the amplification of the right end of Chromosome I, which has never been reported before, is probably the most defining aspect of the "commercial wine strain signature". These particular genomic changes may be a result of long-term selection for strains that demonstrate good fermentative behavior and good organoleptic characteristics during wine-making. We expect that there may be slight changes made to the list, as more wine yeast array karyotype data are accumulated. We are planning to perform similar studies with "wild" wine yeast strains, as well as with more commercial wine yeasts in order to refine the list, if necessary.</p><p>We also observed internally-located single-copy genes (<italic>AYT1</italic>, <italic>ENB1</italic>, <italic>YPL257W</italic>) whose copy numbers vary either as part of the "commercial wine strain signature" or in inter- or intra-strain variation. It is possible that these genes have diverged in their sequences relative to the reference strain to a degree that hybridization no longer occurs, but it is more likely that rather than accumulation of multiple changes localized to just a few isolated genes (which would have to be the result of an extremely strong positive selection) among the whole genome, a more drastic change (either a deletion or amplification) has occurred to the gene. The mechanism by which this might happen is not known but could be explained by the presence of tandem repeats on either side of the gene, thus enabling loop-out or unequal cross-over events.</p><p>Many of the changes in genomic copy number in the "commercial wine strain signature", and in inter- and intra-strain differences, involve genes that encode transporter proteins or genes involved in drug resistance phenotypes in laboratory yeasts. Drug sensitivity results for the wine strains show that most are highly sensitive to SMM as compared to the laboratory strain, although it appears that Montrachet strains may not exhibit as high a level of SMM sensitivity as the other strains (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>). When the results of the drug sensitivity tests are compared with the copy number genotypes of the transporter, permease, drug response and other variable genes (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>), it is apparent that the situation is complex; among all of the genes that vary in copy number in these strains, only one gene's copy number status correlates well with an easily identifiable drug response &#x02013; <italic>CUP1</italic>, the copper-binding yeast metallothionein gene. It appears that the nine wine strains (i.e., all except GSY1, 2, and 5) which are highly depleted for the <italic>CUP1 </italic>gene (which is tandemly-repeated as 2 copies in the haploid S288C) show hypersensitivity to sulfomethuron methyl (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>). Interestingly, the <italic>CUP1 </italic>gene has been implicated as being highly-expressed in an azole-resistant yeast strain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B92">92</xref>], indicating that it may play a role in drug response as well as in copper detoxification. Additionally, <italic>pdr13 </italic>deletion mutants are hypersensitive to copper [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B93">93</xref>]; both studies support our present findings that there is a link between the <italic>CUP1 </italic>locus and drug sensitivity.</p><p>There is also a good correlation between the overall observed variability of the copy number genotypes of the wine isolates among each wine strain and the variability (or lack thereof) of the drug responses; the Montrachet and French Red strains showed the most variability in gene copy numbers among their individual isolates, and likewise these two strains show the most variability in the drug response profiles of the isolates (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>).</p><p>As mentioned above, we observed less inter-strain and intra-strain variation, especially aneuploidies, than would be expected based on previously published studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>]. However, the strains we studied were all commercial and/or academic strains that are maintained under fairly constant growth conditions, while many of the previous studies showing genome instability and genomic diversity in wine strains were performed with "wild" yeast strains, i.e., those strains that occur spontaneously in uninoculated wine fermentations. It should also be noted that in this study we have analyzed a set of strains that all originated from France. It is possible that as we expand our studies either to wine yeast strains whose origins are outside of this geographic region, or to "wild" yeast strains, there will be greater genomic differences. Nevertheless, specific inter-strain genomic differences among the four wine strains were found that uniquely identify each strain. The three Montrachet isolates are depleted for <italic>ENB1 </italic>and the <italic>HXT9</italic>, <italic>HXT11</italic>, and <italic>HXT12 </italic>genes, but not depleted for <italic>AYT1 </italic>or <italic>YPL257W</italic>. The Prise de Mousse isolates show exactly the opposite characteristics, being depleted for <italic>AYT1 </italic>and <italic>YPL257W</italic>, but not <italic>ENB1 </italic>or <italic>HXT9</italic>, <italic>HXT11</italic>, and <italic>HXT12</italic>. Two of the three Pasteur Red isolates are depleted for <italic>YPL257W</italic>, and all are partially depleted for <italic>HXT9</italic>, <italic>HXT11</italic>, and <italic>HXT12</italic>, but not depleted for <italic>AYT1 </italic>or <italic>ENB1</italic>. Finally, the Champagne isolates are depleted for all of these genes (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>). These results suggest the possibility of establishing a database that uniquely identifies every major wine yeast strain based on its array karyotype. This could allow rapid identification of wine strains in, for example, un-inoculated wine fermentations, or in suspected contaminated fermentations, etc., by the comparison of karyotypes from the unknown yeasts to those of the known yeasts.</p><p>Some amount of intra-strain variation was found among the French Red isolates and especially in the Montrachet isolates, in which a stretch of 37 genes on the left end of Chromosome VII was depleted in the Lalvin isolate relative to the other two isolates and to the S288C strain; the magnitude of this particular change was somewhat unexpected, and may indicate that wine yeast producers should be more vigilant in periodically checking the genomic integrity of their strains. Microarray karyotyping appears to be a method that can easily be used to check the genomic integrity of such strains.</p><p>Overall, however, the amount of both inter- and intra-strain genomic variation was low among the wine yeast strains, indicating firstly that these strains are closely related, and secondly, that they are quite genetically stable. This implies that these strains can generally be propagated under various conditions without fear of large-scale genomic rearrangements occurring. Our characterization of a "commercial wine strain signature", as well as the determination of unique signatures for various of wine yeast strains, may make it possible to use array karyotyping to help winemakers identify unknown yeasts in spontaneous fermentations, to detect contaminating yeasts during fermentation, and to identify the origins of novel yeast strains. Our results also allow the inference that the differences in the fermentation and organoleptic properties ascribed to these different strains may arise from a small number of genetic changes; it must be noted, though, that the microarray karyotyping technique only allows the detection of genetic changes (primarily copy number changes) at the whole-gene level, not single-nucleotide changes, of which there may be many. However, we can easily test, by adding back deleted genes into the genome, e.g., whether the observed copy number differences between the strains do indeed confer the different sensory properties in the finished wine that have been noted by winemakers.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Strains used</title><p>Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref> shows a list of the commercial wine yeast strains used in this study, including the manufacturer ("Source") of each strain. UCD-numbers in parentheses under "Product Name" refer to the Univ. of Calif. Davis Department of Viticulture and Enology strain collection number. All UCD strains were purchased directly from U. C. Davis (Davis, CA, USA), all Lalvin strains were acquired from Vinquiry (Windsor, CA, USA), and all Red Star strains were purchased from "The Wine Lab" (Napa, CA, USA, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B94">94</xref>]).</p><p>Six additional <italic>S. cerevisiae </italic>strains were used as controls for halo assays:</p><p><underline>JG436</underline>: <italic>MATa, pdr5::Tn5, leu2, ura3, met5 </italic>(obtained from N. Alexander; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B75">75</xref>]);</p><p><underline>ScAYT1&#x00394;</underline>: <italic>MATa, ayt1</italic>&#x00394;, <italic>ura3, met5 </italic>(obtained from N. Alexander; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B75">75</xref>]);</p><p><underline>RW2802</underline>: <italic>MATa, leu2, ura3, met5 </italic>(obtained from N. Alexander; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B75">75</xref>]);</p><p><underline>GSY28</underline>: <italic>MATa, YPL257W</italic>&#x00394;, <italic>his3</italic>&#x00394;<italic>1, leu2</italic>&#x00394;<italic>0, met15</italic>&#x00394;<italic>0, ura3</italic>&#x00394;<italic>0 </italic>(YeDelStrain #1035 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B95">95</xref>]);</p><p><underline>FY1679</underline>: <italic>MATa/MAT&#x003b1;, leu2</italic>&#x00394;<italic>1/+, +/his3</italic>&#x00394;<italic>200, trp1</italic>&#x00394;<italic>63/+, ura3-52/ura3-52 </italic>(S288C-based diploid strain obtained from laboratory of F. Winston; it is the result of a cross between FY23 and FY73; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B96">96</xref>]);</p><p><underline>S288C</underline>: <italic>MAT&#x003b1; </italic>(obtained from laboratory of G. Fink).</p><p>The S288C strain has been previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>] and carries no auxotrophic markers; it represents one of the most widely-used laboratory "wild-type" yeast strains and is also the strain background for the sequenced <italic>S. cerevisiae </italic>strain. The <italic>S. bayanus </italic>strain used in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref> was obtained from Cletus Kurtzman via Tom Pugh; it is the type strain of <italic>S. bayanus </italic>(NRRL Y-12624).</p></sec><sec><title>Microarray karyotyping protocol</title><p>In all karyotyping experiments described, we used microarrays onto which had been spotted PCR products corresponding to full-length ORFs from the S288C strain of <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>, analogous to previously described arrays [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B97">97</xref>]. The DNA used in the hybridizations was prepared as described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B98">98</xref>]. The reference DNA in all experiments was prepared from S288C (the S288C haploid strain; see above). We used S288C as the reference DNA since this is the strain that was sequenced and from which the PCR products used on the microarrays were generated; the Cy3-labeled DNA should thus give a green signal in every channel. After isolation the DNAs were then directly labeled with fluorescently-tagged nucleotides (Amersham, Piscataway, NJ, USA), either Cy3-dUTP for the reference strain or Cy-5 dUTP for the wine strains, using Klenow polymerase (NEB, Beverly, MA, USA) and random hexamers in a random-priming method as described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">61</xref>]. After labeling, the reactions were heat-inactivated, the experimental (Cy5-labeled) and reference (Cy3-labeled) DNAs were mixed, purified away from unincorporated label using Microcon-30 filters (Millipore, Billerica, MA, USA), and then hybridized to the microarrays at 65&#x000b0;C as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B99">99</xref>]. All experiments were performed using duplicate arrays, where we hybridized the same labeling reaction to each of the two arrays. Arrays were scanned with an Axon 4000A scanner and the data were extracted with GenePix (Molecular Devices Corp., Union City, CA, USA) software as described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B97">97</xref>]. The data were deposited in the Stanford Microarray Database [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B62">62</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">63</xref>] where they can be retrieved for further analysis; the raw data for all microarray hybridizations reported in this paper can also be downloaded from the site: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://microarray-pubs.stanford.edu/wine_yeast/"/>. For all data analysis described, the array data were filtered first to eliminate manually flagged bad spots, then filtered to include spots for which the ratio of green (Cy3) channel mean intensity to Median background intensity was &#x0003e; 1.5 and the ratio of red (Cy5) channel normalized mean intensity to Median background intensity was &#x0003e; 1.0. The filtering was fairly permissive in order to allow truly deleted genes in the wine yeasts (i.e., no red signal at all) to be detected. All data are presented as the average of the values from the duplicate arrays. Karyoscopes were generated by the Java TreeView program [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B67">67</xref>].</p><p>Note that prior to the data filtering described above, all array data were normalized by setting the average log fluorescence hybridization ratio of all array elements to a value of zero; differences in hybridization intensity due to ploidy differences are therefore eliminated. Thus, although most wine strains are of diploid or higher ploidy, the normalization process allows direct comparison to the haploid reference strain so that only changes in gene copy number relative to the haploid state are detected. For example, if a gene has a copy number of two in the WT haploid strain and a copy number of four in the WT diploid strain, the red:green (R/G) hybridization ratio will be 1.0 (and the log ratio will be zero) since the haploid-relative copy number is the same between both strains. If, however, a diploid strain (labeled in red) has experienced a depletion in the copy number so that it now has only two copies of the gene, the R/G hybridization ratio will be 0.5 because the copy number relative to the haploid state has been lowered.</p></sec><sec><title>CGH-Miner</title><p>The CGH-Miner program [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B68">68</xref>] was installed and employed as described in the CGH-Miner User guide and Manual [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B100">100</xref>]. The karyscope shown in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> was generated by the program using the parameters for BAC analysis because it gives the smallest size (three) of the moving-window for data smoothing. Eight separate S288C self-self hybridizations were used as "NN" controls in the CGH-Miner program, giving a robust baseline to determine the shared copy number changes in the wine strains. When the CGH-Miner program [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B68">68</xref>] generated the consensus plot shown in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>, it simultaneously created a file showing the genes that are significantly altered in copy number relative to "normal" (self-self) arrays; an abbreviated list of these genes with significantly-altered copy number are given in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>.</p></sec><sec><title>Halo assays</title><p>For each of the 18 yeast strains described above, 2 ml of liquid YPD medium [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B98">98</xref>] supplemented with adenine (50 mg/l final) and tryptophan (50 mg/l final) was inoculated with cells from frozen glycerol stocks. The cultures were grown at 25&#x000b0;C overnight until saturated. Cultures were measured for cell density using a Coulter Counter (Beckman-Coulter, Fullerton, CA, USA), then resuspended at 1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6 </sup>cells/ml in 4 ml of top agar (= 0.7% agar, 0.82X YPD plus adenine and tryptophan as above) which had been held at 42&#x000b0;C. After quickly vortexing, the mixture was poured smoothly onto YPD+Ade+Trp plates. The top agar was allowed to cool and harden, then 6.5 mm-diameter filter discs pre-loaded with the desired amount of drug were placed onto the surface of the top agar. The amounts of each drug loaded onto the filter discs were: 500 ng cycloheximide (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA; 2 &#x003bc;l of 250 &#x003bc;g/ml solution in water), 5 &#x003bc;g clotrimazole (Sigma; 4 &#x003bc;l of 1.25 mg/ml solution in acetone) and 20 &#x003bc;g sulfomethuron-methyl (DuPont, Wilmington, DE, USA; 8 &#x003bc;l of 2.5 mg/ml solution in acetone). Control filter discs containing 8 &#x003bc;l of either water or acetone were also placed on the plates; halos were never observed around these control discs. The plates were then incubated at 25&#x000b0;C for 2 &#x02013; 3 days after which photographs of the plates were taken. Final halo measurements used for the charts in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref> were calculated by first measuring the diameter of the total halo (including the central filter disc) and calculating its area, then subtracting the area of the filter disc to give the annular area (i.e., the area of the annulus defined by the outer edge of the disc to the outer boundary of the halo). The annular area for each experimental yeast strain was then divided by that of the strain FY1679 (S288C-based diploid) to yield an annular area ratio for each drug. Finally, the log<sub>2 </sub>of the annular area ratio was calculated and represent the y-axis values shown in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>, where positive values indicate greater sensitivity to the drug compared to the WT-diploid control, and negative values indicate greater resistance to the drug compared to WT.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Abbreviations</title><p>CGH: Comparative Genome Hybridization</p><p>CTZ: clotrimazole</p><p>CYH: cycloheximide</p><p>S-AM: S-adenosylmethionine</p><p>SGD: Saccharomyces Genome Database</p><p>SMM: sulfomethuron methyl</p><p>WT: Wild-type</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>BD planned and designed the experiments, performed the experiments and the data analysis, wrote the main draft of the paper, and generated the figures. RPL aided in the experimental design and in editing the manuscript. GS provided guidance over the entire project, and also aided in figure making, data analysis and editing of the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec><title>Additional material</title><p>The raw data files for all microarray hybridizations presented in this paper may be downloaded at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://microarray-pubs.stanford.edu/wine_yeast/"/></p></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Nancy Alexander for providing us with the <italic>ayt1</italic>, <italic>pdr5</italic>, and RW2802 yeast strains and Tom Pugh for providing the <italic>S. bayanus </italic>strain used in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>. We also thank Pei Wang for providing interactive support for the CGH-Miner program and Katja Schwartz for critical reading of the manuscript. Finally, we thank our three anonymous reviewers, all of whom helped improve the manuscript with their comments and insight. This work was supported by NSF ADVANCE grant DBI-0340856 to BD.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Romano</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Fiore</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Paraggio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Caruso</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Capece</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Function of yeast species and strains in wine flavour</article-title><source>Int J Food Microbiol</source><year>2003</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>169</fpage><lpage>180</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12892932</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0168-1605(03)00290-3</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Torrea</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ancin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Content of biogenic amines in a Chardonnay wine obtained through spontaneous and inoculated fermentations</article-title><source>J Agric Food Chem</source><year>2002</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>4895</fpage><lpage>4899</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12166978</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf011653h</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shibamoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of different strains of Saccharomyces cerevisiae on production of volatiles in Napa Gamay wine and Petite Sirah wine</article-title><source>J Agric Food Chem</source><year>2002</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>5649</fpage><lpage>5653</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12236692</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf020337f</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lilly</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lambrechts</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Pretorius</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of increased yeast alcohol acetyltransferase activity on flavor profiles of wine and distillates</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2000</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>744</fpage><lpage>753</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10653746</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.66.2.744-753.2000</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nadal</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Colomer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Pina</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular polymorphism distribution in phenotypically distinct populations of wine yeast strains</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>1996</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>1944</fpage><lpage>1950</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8787392</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martinez-Rodriguez</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Carrascosa</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin-Alvarez</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreno-Arribas</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Polo</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of the yeast strain on the changes of the amino acids, peptides and proteins during sparkling wine production by the traditional method</article-title><source>J Ind Microbiol Biotechnol</source><year>2002</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>314</fpage><lpage>322</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12483471</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.jim.7000323</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martinez-Rodriguez</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Carrascosa</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Polo</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Release of nitrogen compounds to the extracellular medium by three strains of Saccharomyces cerevisiae during induced autolysis in a model wine system</article-title><source>Int J Food Microbiol</source><year>2001</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>155</fpage><lpage>160</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11545216</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0168-1605(01)00486-X</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benitez</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Codon</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic constitution of industrial yeast</article-title><source>Microbiologia</source><year>1996</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>371</fpage><lpage>384</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8897417</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mortimer</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolution and variation of the yeast (Saccharomyces) genome</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><year>2000</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>403</fpage><lpage>409</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10779481</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.10.4.403</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fleet</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Yeast interactions and wine flavour</article-title><source>Int J Food Microbiol</source><year>2003</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12892919</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0168-1605(03)00245-9</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ganga</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinaga</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Valles</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramon</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Querol</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aroma improving in microvinification processes by the use of a recombinant wine yeast strain expressing the Aspergillus nidulans xlnA gene</article-title><source>Int J Food Microbiol</source><year>1999</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>178</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10359487</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0168-1605(98)00202-5</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodrigue</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Champagne</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Combined effects of sulfites, temperature, and agitation time on production of glycerol in grape juice by Saccharomyces cerevisiae</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>1993</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>2022</fpage><lpage>2028</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8357243</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Michnick</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Roustan</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Remize</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Barre</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Dequin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modulation of glycerol and ethanol yields during alcoholic fermentation in Saccharomyces cerevisiae strains overexpressed or disrupted for GPD1 encoding glycerol 3-phosphate dehydrogenase</article-title><source>Yeast</source><year>1997</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>783</fpage><lpage>793</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9234667</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1097-0061(199707)13:9&#x0003c;783::AID-YEA128&#x0003e;3.0.CO;2-W</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Remize</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Sablayrolles</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Dequin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Re-assessment of the influence of yeast strain and environmental factors on glycerol production in wine</article-title><source>J Appl Microbiol</source><year>2000</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>371</fpage><lpage>378</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10747217</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2672.2000.00964.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Romano</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzzi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Mortimer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Polsinelli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Production of high levels of acetoin in Saccharomyces cerevisiae wine yeasts is a recessive trait</article-title><source>J Appl Bacteriol</source><year>1995</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>169</fpage><lpage>174</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7698951</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Romano</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzzi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Turbanti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Polsinelli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acetaldehyde production in Saccharomyces cerevisiae wine yeasts</article-title><source>FEMS Microbiol Lett</source><year>1994</year><volume>118</volume><fpage>213</fpage><lpage>218</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8020744</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0378-1097(94)90506-1</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Codon</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Perez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Benitez</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Physiological and molecular characterization of flor yeasts: polymorphism of flor yeast populations</article-title><source>Yeast</source><year>1995</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1399</fpage><lpage>1411</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8585323</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramirez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vinagre</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ambrona</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Molina</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Maqueda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rebollo</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic instability of heterozygous, hybrid, natural wine yeasts</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>4686</fpage><lpage>4691</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15294803</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.70.8.4686-4691.2004</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Longo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Vezinhet</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chromosomal rearrangements during vegetative growth of a wild strain of Saccharomyces cerevisiae</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>1993</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>322</fpage><lpage>326</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8439158</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guijo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mauricio</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Salmon</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ortega</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Determination of the relative ploidy in different Saccharomyces cerevisiae strains used for fermentation and 'flor' film ageing of dry sherry-type wines</article-title><source>Yeast</source><year>1997</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>117</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9046092</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1097-0061(199702)13:2&#x0003c;101::AID-YEA66&#x0003e;3.0.CO;2-H</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miklos</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Varga</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sipiczki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome instability and chromosomal rearrangements in a heterothallic wine yeast</article-title><source>J Basic Microbiol</source><year>1997</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>345</fpage><lpage>354</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9373949</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nadal</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Carro</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernandez-Larrea</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pina</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis and dynamics of the chromosomal complements of wild sparkling-wine yeast strains</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>1999</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>1688</fpage><lpage>1695</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10103269</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bakalinsky</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Snow</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The chromosomal constitution of wine strains of Saccharomyces cerevisiae</article-title><source>Yeast</source><year>1990</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>367</fpage><lpage>382</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2220073</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Naumov</surname><given-names>GI</given-names></name><name><surname>Naumova</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Antunovics</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Sipiczki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Saccharomyces bayanus var. uvarum in Tokaj wine-making of Slovakia and Hungary</article-title><source>Appl Microbiol Biotechnol</source><year>2002</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>727</fpage><lpage>730</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12226732</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00253-002-1077-6</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rachidi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Barre</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Blondin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multiple Ty-mediated chromosomal translocations lead to karyotype changes in a wine strain of Saccharomyces cerevisiae</article-title><source>Mol Gen Genet</source><year>1999</year><volume>261</volume><fpage>841</fpage><lpage>850</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10394922</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s004380050028</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bidenne</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Blondin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Dequin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Vezinhet</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of the chromosomal DNA polymorphism of wine strains of Saccharomyces cerevisiae</article-title><source>Curr Genet</source><year>1992</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1611665</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00351734</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Naumov</surname><given-names>GI</given-names></name><name><surname>Naumova</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Masneuf</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Aigle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kondratieva</surname><given-names>VI</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubourdieu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Natural polyploidization of some cultured yeast Saccharomyces sensu stricto: auto- and allotetraploidy</article-title><source>Syst Appl Microbiol</source><year>2000</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>442</fpage><lpage>449</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11108025</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tamai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Momma</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshimoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaneko</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Co-existence of two types of chromosome in the bottom fermenting yeast, Saccharomyces pastorianus</article-title><source>Yeast</source><year>1998</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>923</fpage><lpage>933</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9717238</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1097-0061(199807)14:10&#x0003c;923::AID-YEA298&#x0003e;3.3.CO;2-9</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Oeller</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure of evolving populations of Saccharomyces cerevisiae: adaptive changes are frequently associated with sequence alterations involving mobile elements belonging to the Ty family</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>1986</year><volume>83</volume><fpage>7124</fpage><lpage>7127</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3018758</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Puskas-Rozsa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Simlar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilke</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adaptation and major chromosomal changes in populations of Saccharomyces cerevisiae</article-title><source>Curr Genet</source><year>1992</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1611666</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00351736</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dunham</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Badrane</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferea</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenzweig</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Botstein</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characteristic genome rearrangements in experimental evolution of Saccharomyces cerevisiae</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2002</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>16144</fpage><lpage>16149</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12446845</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.242624799</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McClintock</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The significance of responses of the genome to challenge</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1984</year><volume>226</volume><fpage>792</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15739260</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Origin of concatemeric T7 DNA</article-title><source>Nat New Biol</source><year>1972</year><volume>239</volume><fpage>197</fpage><lpage>201</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4507727</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Slade</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Burchard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dow</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kidd</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Friend</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Marton</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Widespread aneuploidy revealed by DNA microarray expression profiling</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2000</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>333</fpage><lpage>337</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10888885</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/77116</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Perez-Ortin</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Querol</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Puig</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Barrio</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular characterization of a chromosomal rearrangement involved in the adaptive evolution of yeast strains</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><year>2002</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1533</fpage><lpage>1539</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12368245</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.436602</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Puig</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Querol</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Barrio</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Perez-Ortin</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mitotic recombination and genetic changes in Saccharomyces cerevisiae during wine fermentation</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2000</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>2057</fpage><lpage>2061</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10788381</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.66.5.2057-2061.2000</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aguilera</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chavez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Malagon</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mitotic recombination in yeast: elements controlling its incidence</article-title><source>Yeast</source><year>2000</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>731</fpage><lpage>754</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10861900</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/1097-0061(20000615)16:8&#x0003c;731::AID-YEA586&#x0003e;3.0.CO;2-L</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B38"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frankel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Wine and Oil Production in Antiquity in Israel and Other Mediterranean Countries.</article-title><source>Jsot/ASOR Series</source><year>1998</year><volume>10</volume><publisher-name>Sheffield, UK , Sheffield Academic Press</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B39"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McGovern</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name></person-group><source>Ancient Wine: The Search for the Origins of Viniculture.</source><year>2003</year><publisher-name>Princeton , Princeton University Press</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B40"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cavalieri</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>McGovern</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartl</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Mortimer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Polsinelli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence for S. cerevisiae fermentation in ancient wine</article-title><source>J Mol Evol</source><year>2003</year><volume>57 Suppl 1</volume><fpage>S226</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15008419</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00239-003-0031-2</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B41"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mortimer</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genealogy of principal strains of the yeast genetic stock center</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>1986</year><volume>113</volume><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3519363</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B42"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eisen</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DNA arrays for analysis of gene expression</article-title><source>Methods Enzymol</source><year>1999</year><volume>303</volume><fpage>179</fpage><lpage>205</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10349646</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B43"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holloway</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>van Laar</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Tothill</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowtell</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Options available--from start to finish--for obtaining data from DNA microarrays II</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2002</year><volume>32 Suppl</volume><fpage>481</fpage><lpage>489</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12454642</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng1030</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B44"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pinkel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Landegent</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuscoe</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Segraves</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fluorescence in situ hybridization with human chromosome-specific libraries: detection of trisomy 21 and translocations of chromosome 4</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>1988</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>9138</fpage><lpage>9142</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2973607</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B45"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pollack</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Perou</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Alizadeh</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Eisen</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Pergamenschikov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeffrey</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Botstein</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide analysis of DNA copy-number changes using cDNA microarrays</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>1999</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>46</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10471496</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/12640</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B46"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Albertson</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Profiling breast cancer by array CGH</article-title><source>Breast Cancer Res Treat</source><year>2003</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>289</fpage><lpage>298</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12755488</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1023025506386</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B47"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kashiwagi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Uchida</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide profiling of gene amplification and deletion in cancer</article-title><source>Hum Cell</source><year>2000</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>135</fpage><lpage>141</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11197775</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B48"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pollack</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Sorlie</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Perou</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rees</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeffrey</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lonning</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Tibshirani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Botstein</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Borresen-Dale</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microarray analysis reveals a major direct role of DNA copy number alteration in the transcriptional program of human breast tumors</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2002</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>12963</fpage><lpage>12968</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12297621</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.162471999</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B49"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lashkari</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>McCusker</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Whole genome analysis: experimental access to all genome sequenced segments through larger-scale efficient oligonucleotide synthesis and PCR</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>1997</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>8945</fpage><lpage>8947</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9256414</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.94.17.8945</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B50"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Perez-Ortin</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia-Martinez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Alberola</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DNA chips for yeast biotechnology. The case of wine yeasts</article-title><source>J Biotechnol</source><year>2002</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>227</fpage><lpage>241</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12141989</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0168-1656(02)00134-7</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B51"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bond</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Neal</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Donnelly</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>James</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aneuploidy and copy number breakpoints in the genome of lager yeasts mapped by microarray hybridisation</article-title><source>Curr Genet</source><year>2004</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>360</fpage><lpage>370</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15103502</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00294-004-0504-x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B52"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Winzeler</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Castillo-Davis</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name><name><surname>Oshiro</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartl</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic diversity in yeast assessed with whole-genome oligonucleotide arrays</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2003</year><volume>163</volume><fpage>79</fpage><lpage>89</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12586698</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B53"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Backhus</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>DeRisi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name><name><surname>Bisson</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional genomic analysis of a commercial wine strain of Saccharomyces cerevisiae under differing nitrogen conditions</article-title><source>FEMS Yeast Res</source><year>2001</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>125</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12702356</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1567-1356(01)00019-8</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B54"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Erasmus</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Merwe</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name><name><surname>van Vuuren</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide expression analyses: Metabolic adaptation of Saccharomyces cerevisiae to high sugar stress</article-title><source>FEMS Yeast Res</source><year>2003</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>375</fpage><lpage>399</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12748050</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1567-1356(02)00203-9</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B55"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rossignol</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Dulau</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Julien</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Blondin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide monitoring of wine yeast gene expression during alcoholic fermentation</article-title><source>Yeast</source><year>2003</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>1369</fpage><lpage>1385</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14663829</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/yea.1046</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B56"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Infante</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dombek</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rebordinos</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Cantoral</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide amplifications caused by chromosomal rearrangements play a major role in the adaptive evolution of natural yeast</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2003</year><volume>165</volume><fpage>1745</fpage><lpage>1759</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14704163</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B57"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lashkari</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>DeRisi</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>McCusker</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Namath</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Gentile</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Yeast microarrays for genome wide parallel genetic and gene expression analysis</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>1997</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>13057</fpage><lpage>13062</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9371799</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.94.24.13057</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B58"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Primig</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Winzeler</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Tevzadze</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name><name><surname>Conway</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Esposito</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The core meiotic transcriptome in budding yeasts</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2000</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>415</fpage><lpage>423</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11101837</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/82539</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B59"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Edwards-Ingram</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Gent</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoyle</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Stateva</surname><given-names>LI</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative genomic hybridization provides new insights into the molecular taxonomy of the Saccharomyces sensu stricto complex</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>1043</fpage><lpage>1051</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15173111</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.2114704</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B60"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hauser</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Fellenberg</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gil</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bastuk</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoheisel</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Perez-Ortin</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Whole genome analysis of a wine yeast strain</article-title><source>Comparative and Functional Genomics</source><year>2001</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>79</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cfg.73</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B61"><citation citation-type="other"><article-title>Genomic DNA Labeling Protocol
</article-title><fpage> [http://cmgm.stanford.edu/pbrown/protocols/4_genomic.html]</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="B62"><citation citation-type="other"><article-title>Stanford Microarray Database</article-title><fpage> [http://smd.stanford.edu/]</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="B63"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sherlock</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Hernandez-Boussard</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kasarskis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Binkley</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Matese</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Dwight</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaloper</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Weng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ball</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Eisen</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Spellman</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name><name><surname>Botstein</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Cherry</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Stanford Microarray Database</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2001</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>152</fpage><lpage>155</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11125075</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/29.1.152</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B64"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Masneuf</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Groth</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Piskur</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubourdieu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New hybrids between Saccharomyces sensu stricto yeast species found among wine and cider production strains</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>1998</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>3887</fpage><lpage>3892</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9758815</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B65"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Egli</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Edinger</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitrakul</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Henick-Kling</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dynamics of indigenous and inoculated yeast populations and their effect on the sensory character of Riesling and Chardonnay wines</article-title><source>J Appl Microbiol</source><year>1998</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>779</fpage><lpage>789</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9830113</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2672.1998.00521.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B66"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kunkee</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Vilas</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Toward an understanding of the relationship between yeast strain and flavor production during vinifications: Flavor effects in vinifications of a nondistinct variety of grapes by several strains of wine yeast</article-title><source>Vitic Enol Sci</source><year>1994</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>46</fpage><lpage>50</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B67"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saldanha</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Java treeview--extensible visualization of microarray data</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2004</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>3246</fpage><lpage>3248</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15180930</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bth349</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B68"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Pollack</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Narasimhan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Tibshirani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A method for calling gains and losses in array CGH data</article-title><source>Biostatistics</source><year>2005</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>58</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15618527</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/biostatistics/kxh017</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B69"><citation citation-type="other"><article-title>Saccharomyces Genome Database</article-title><fpage>[http://www.yeastgenome.org/]</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="B70"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cherry</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ball</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Chervitz</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dwight</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hester</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Juvik</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Roe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Schroeder</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Weng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Botstein</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SGD: Saccharomyces Genome Database</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1998</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>79</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9399804</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/26.1.73</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B71"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Delaveau</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Delahodde</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Carvajal</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Subik</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacq</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PDR3, a new yeast regulatory gene, is homologous to PDR1 and controls the multidrug resistance phenomenon</article-title><source>Mol Gen Genet</source><year>1994</year><volume>244</volume><fpage>501</fpage><lpage>511</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8078477</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00583901</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B72"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Launhardt</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hinnen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Munder</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Drug-induced phenotypes provide a tool for the functional analysis of yeast genes</article-title><source>Yeast</source><year>1998</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>935</fpage><lpage>942</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9717239</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1097-0061(199807)14:10&#x0003c;935::AID-YEA289&#x0003e;3.3.CO;2-0</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B73"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kellis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Endrizzi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Birren</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lander</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sequencing and comparison of yeast species to identify genes and regulatory elements</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2003</year><volume>423</volume><fpage>241</fpage><lpage>254</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12748633</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature01644</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B74"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hurst</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Ka/Ks ratio: diagnosing the form of sequence evolution</article-title><source>Trends Genet</source><year>2002</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>486</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12175810</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0168-9525(02)02722-1</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B75"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>McCormick</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Hohn</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The identification of the Saccharomyces cerevisiae gene AYT1(ORF-YLL063c) encoding an acetyltransferase</article-title><source>Yeast</source><year>2002</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>1425</fpage><lpage>1430</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12478589</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/yea.924</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B76"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nourani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wesolowski-Louvel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Delaveau</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacq</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Delahodde</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multiple-drug-resistance phenomenon in the yeast Saccharomyces cerevisiae: involvement of two hexose transporters</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>1997</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>5453</fpage><lpage>5460</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9271421</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B77"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akache</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Turcotte</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New regulators of drug sensitivity in the family of yeast zinc cluster proteins</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2002</year><volume>277</volume><fpage>21254</fpage><lpage>21260</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11943786</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M202566200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B78"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>do Valle Matta</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jonniaux</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Balzi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Goffeau</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>van den Hazel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Novel target genes of the yeast regulator Pdr1p: a contribution of the TPO1 gene in resistance to quinidine and other drugs</article-title><source>Gene</source><year>2001</year><volume>272</volume><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>119</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11470516</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0378-1119(01)00558-3</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B79"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mizoguchi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamauchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamanaka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishimura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanmoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Different missense mutations in PDR1 and PDR3 genes from clotrimazole-resistant sake yeast are responsible for pleiotropic drug resistance and improved fermentative activity</article-title><source>J Biosci Bioeng</source><year>2002</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>221</fpage><lpage>227</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16233191</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1263/jbb.93.221</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B80"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mizoguchi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishimura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Disruption of the ABC transporter genes PDR5, YOR1, and SNQ2, and their participation in improved fermentative activity of a sake yeast mutant showing pleiotropic drug resistance</article-title><source>J Biosci Bioeng</source><year>2000</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>569</fpage><lpage>576</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16232800</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1389-1723(00)80059-6</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B81"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heymann</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ernst</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Winkelmann</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A gene of the major facilitator superfamily encodes a transporter for enterobactin (Enb1p) in Saccharomyces cerevisiae</article-title><source>Biometals</source><year>2000</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10831226</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1009250017785</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B82"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Codon</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Benitez</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Korhola</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chromosomal polymorphism and adaptation to specific industrial environments of Saccharomyces strains</article-title><source>Appl Microbiol Biotechnol</source><year>1998</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>154</fpage><lpage>163</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9534255</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s002530051152</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B83"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Umezu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiraoka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Maki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structural analysis of aberrant chromosomes that occur spontaneously in diploid Saccharomyces cerevisiae: retrotransposon Ty1 plays a crucial role in chromosomal rearrangements</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2002</year><volume>160</volume><fpage>97</fpage><lpage>110</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11805048</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B84"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Gabriel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reciprocal translocations in Saccharomyces cerevisiae formed by nonhomologous end joining</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2004</year><volume>166</volume><fpage>741</fpage><lpage>751</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15020464</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/genetics.166.2.741</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B85"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sakurai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tohda</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumagai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Giga-Hama</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A distinct type of alcohol dehydrogenase, adh4+, complements ethanol fermentation in an adh1-deficient strain of Schizosaccharomyces pombe</article-title><source>FEMS Yeast Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>649</fpage><lpage>654</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15040954</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.femsyr.2003.12.009</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B86"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dawes</surname><given-names>IW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Application of genome-wide expression analysis to identify molecular markers useful in monitoring industrial fermentations</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2003</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>7535</fpage><lpage>7540</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14660410</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.69.12.7535-7540.2003</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B87"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lyons</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gasch</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaither</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Botstein</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name><name><surname>Eide</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide characterization of the Zap1p zinc-responsive regulon in yeast</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2000</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>7957</fpage><lpage>7962</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10884426</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.97.14.7957</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B88"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giaever</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Connelly</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Riles</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Veronneau</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dow</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucau-Danila</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Andre</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Arkin</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Astromoff</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>El-Bakkoury</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bangham</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Benito</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Brachat</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Campanaro</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Curtiss</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Deutschbauer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Entian</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Flaherty</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Foury</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Garfinkel</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerstein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gotte</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Guldener</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Hegemann</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hempel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Herman</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaramillo</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Kotter</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>LaBonte</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamb</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lussier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Menard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ooi</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Revuelta</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ross-Macdonald</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Scherens</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Schimmack</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Shafer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Shoemaker</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Sookhai-Mahadeo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Storms</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Strathern</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Valle</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Voet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Volckaert</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilhelmy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Winzeler</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Youngman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Bussey</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Boeke</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Philippsen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional profiling of the Saccharomyces cerevisiae genome</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2002</year><volume>418</volume><fpage>387</fpage><lpage>391</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12140549</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature00935</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B89"><citation citation-type="other"><article-title>Welcome to Lesaffre Yeast Corporation | Wine Yeast Division | Products</article-title><fpage>http://www.lesaffreyeastcorp.com/wineyeast/products.html</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="B90"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fernandez-Espinar</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramon</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartra</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Querol</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Study of the authenticity of commercial wine yeast strains by molecular techniques</article-title><source>Int J Food Microbiol</source><year>2001</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11759747</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0168-1605(01)00502-5</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B91"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Szauter</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Pardue</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Szostak</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transfer of yeast telomeres to linear plasmids by recombination</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1984</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>191</fpage><lpage>201</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6091911</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0092-8674(84)90205-8</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B92"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of genes differentially expressed in association with reduced azole susceptibility in Saccharomyces cerevisiae</article-title><source>J Antimicrob Chemother</source><year>2003</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>1131</fpage><lpage>1140</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12697649</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jac/dkg217</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B93"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>DY</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of PDR13 in tolerance to high copper stress in budding yeast</article-title><source>FEBS Lett</source><year>2001</year><volume>508</volume><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11707276</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0014-5793(01)03038-1</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B94"><citation citation-type="other"><article-title>The Wine Lab</article-title><fpage>http://www.thewinelab.com/</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="B95"><citation citation-type="other"><article-title>Saccharomyces Genome Deletion Project</article-title><fpage> [http://www</fpage><lpage>sequence.stanford.edu/group/yeast_deletion_project/deletions3.html]</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B96"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Winston</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Dollard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ricupero-Hovasse</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Construction of a set of convenient Saccharomyces cerevisiae strains that are isogenic to S288C</article-title><source>Yeast</source><year>1995</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7762301</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B97"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>DeRisi</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Iyer</surname><given-names>VR</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exploring the metabolic and genetic control of gene expression on a genomic scale</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1997</year><volume>278</volume><fpage>680</fpage><lpage>686</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9381177</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.278.5338.680</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B98"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Treco</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Ausubel FM, Brent R, Kingston RE, Moore DD, Seidman JG, Smith JA, Struhl R</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Preparation of Yeast DNA</article-title><source>Current Protocols in Molecular Biology</source><series>Current Protocols in Molecular Biology</series><year>2003</year><publisher-name> John Wiley &#x00026; Sons</publisher-name><fpage>13.11</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14686320</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B99"><citation citation-type="other"><article-title>Hybridization of Arrays</article-title><fpage> [http://cmgm.stanford.edu/pbrown/protocols/5_hyb_yeast.html]</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="B100"><citation citation-type="other"><article-title>CGH Miner Users Guide and Manual</article-title><fpage> [http://www</fpage><lpage>stat.stanford.edu/~wp57/CGH-Miner/CGH-Miner-Manual.pdf]</lpage></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>



