<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cancer Cell Int</journal-id><journal-title>Cancer Cell International</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1475-2867</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15910691</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1166566</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1475-2867-5-15</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1475-2867-5-15</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Primary Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Influence of <italic>RAR</italic>&#x003b1; gene on <italic>MDR1 </italic>expression and P-glycoprotein function in human leukemic cells</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Stromskaya</surname><given-names>Tatjana P</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>stromskaya@mail.ru</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rybalkina</surname><given-names>Ekaterina Y</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>Kate_rybalkina@mail.ru</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zabotina</surname><given-names>Tatjana N</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>tat-zabotina@yandex.ru</email></contrib><contrib id="A4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shishkin</surname><given-names>Alexander A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>klounv@mail.ru</email></contrib><contrib id="A5" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Stavrovskaya</surname><given-names>Alla A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>astavrovskaya@yahoo.com</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Institute of Carcinogenesis, N.N. Blokhin Russian Cancer Research Centre of the Russian Academy of Medical Sciences, Kashirskoye sh 24, Moscow 115478, Russia</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2005</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>24</day><month>5</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cancerci.com/content/5/1/15"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>10</month><year>2004</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>24</day><month>5</month><year>2005</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2005 Stromskaya et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2005</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Stromskaya et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>
               Stromskaya
               P
               Tatjana
               
               stromskaya@mail.ru
            </dc:author><dc:title>
            Influence of RAR&#x003b1; gene on MDR1 expression and P-glycoprotein function in human leukemic cells
         </dc:title><dc:date>2005</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>Cancer Cell International 5(1): 15-. (2005)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1475-2867(2005)5:1&#x0003c;15&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1475-2867</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Multidrug resistance (MDR) phenotype of malignant cells is the major problem in the chemotherapy of neoplasia. The treatment of leukemia with retinoids is aimed on the induction of leukemic cells differentiation. However the interconnections between retinoid regulated differentiation of leukemic cells and regulation of MDR remains unclear.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><p>Four lines of cultured leukemic cells of diverse types of differentiation were infected with <italic>RAR</italic>&#x003b1; gene and stable transfectants were isolated. We investigated the differentiation of these cells as well as the expression of <italic>RAR</italic>&#x003b1; and <italic>MDR1 </italic>genes and P-glycoprotein (Pgp, MDR protein) functional activity in these cells.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>All <italic>RAR</italic>&#x003b1; transfected sublines demonstrated the increase in the quantity of <italic>RAR</italic>&#x003b1; mRNA. All these sublines became more differentiated. Intrinsic activity of <italic>MDR1 </italic>gene (but not Pgp functional activity) was increased in one of the transfectants. <italic>All-trans</italic>-retinoic acid (ATRA) induced Pgp activity in two of three infectants to a larger extent than in parental cells.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>The data show that RAR&#x003b1; regulates <italic>MDR1/ </italic>Pgp activity in human leukemic cells, in the first place, Pgp activity induced by ATRA. These results show that RAR&#x003b1; overexpression in leukemic cells could result in MDR.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Multidrug resistance (MDR) phenotype of malignant cells is the major problem in the chemotherapy of neoplasia. P-glycoprotein (Pgp) activity is recognised to be one of the major mechanisms responsible for MDR. Pgp transports many structurally diverse compounds across the cell membrane and confers the MDR phenotype in tumor cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. A number of signaling pathways participate in the regulation of <italic>MDR1 </italic>gene expression and the activity of its product, Pgp [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. Some of these signaling pathways could participate in coordinated regulation of <italic>MDR1/</italic>Pgp activity, cell proliferation and cell differentiation. It was shown that retinoic acid (RA) can modulate <italic>MDR1 </italic>gene expression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. Retinoids are known to be involved into the regulation of the cell growth, differentiation and apoptosis. In the last decade retinoids became implicated into the treatment of leukemia and some solid tumors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. This approach changed the focus of the haematological diseases treatment from the cytotoxicity of the anti-cancer drugs to the reversal of arrested maturation of leukemic cells. Retinoids act via two families of receptors (RARs &#x02013; RAR&#x003b1;, RAR&#x003b2;, RAR&#x003b3;) and RXRs (RXR&#x003b1;, RXR&#x003b2;, RXR&#x003b3;). There is the evidence that RAR&#x003b1; is the crucial receptor mediating the biological effects during retinoid signaling in some cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. Cell differentiation caused by the stable overexpression of receptor RAR&#x003b1; was shown to result in constitutive over expression of <italic>MDR1 </italic>gene in some cultured cells of solid tumors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. However the interconnections between RA/RAR&#x003b1; regulated differentiation of leukemic cells and regulation of <italic>MDR1</italic>/Pgp activity remains unclear. In some leukemic cells RA did not influence <italic>MDR1 </italic>and/or Pgp activity, while in the others it either augmented or reduced <italic>MDR1</italic>/Pgp expression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. The aim of this study is to investigate if effects of <italic>all-trans</italic>-retinoic acid (ATRA) on <italic>MDR1</italic>/Pgp activity in leukemic cells are connected with <italic>RAR</italic>&#x003b1; expression and with the leukemic cell differentiation. We isolated sublines of cultured leukemic cells characterized by the stable <italic>RAR</italic>&#x003b1; overexpression and investigated the constitutive and ATRA induced <italic>MDR1</italic>/Pgp activity in these cells. Our data show that various <italic>RAR</italic>&#x003b1; transformed leukemic cell lines acquired more differentiated phenotype. Constitutive level of <italic>MDR1 </italic>gene expression increased in one of <italic>RAR</italic>&#x003b1; overexpressing cell sublines. <italic>RAR</italic>&#x003b1; overexpression did not influence Pgp functional activity while Pgp activity induced by ATRA was elevated in all infectants studied. This shows that the main effect of <italic>RAR</italic>&#x003b1; in the cells studied is its influence on the induced functional activity of Pgp.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Cell lines and culture</title><p>Lines of cultured leukemic cells used in the study: H9 cells (acute human T-cell leukemia) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>], KG-1 cell line (cells of acute myelogenous leukemia) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>], K562 cell line (cells obtained from the patient in blast crisis of chronic myeloid leukemia) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>], NB4 (acute promyelocytic leukemia) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>].</p><p>Cells were grown in RPMI-1640 medium supplemented with 10% fetal calf serum (Gibco, USA), 2 mM L-glutamine, 50 &#x003bc;g/ml gentamycin at 37&#x000b0;C in a fully humidified atmosphere of 95% air and 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. All the derived cell lines described in this paper were obtained by retroviral infection and selection with the appropriate antibiotic. ATRA (<italic>all-trans</italic>-retinoic acid, Sigma, USA) was added to the culture medium at seeding or 24 hours after seeding (see Legends to Figures).</p></sec><sec><title>Expression vector and retrovilal infection</title><p>The PA317/LRARSN retroviral vector-producing cell line was used. All the procedure was described earlier [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. In brief, the vector used contains a cDNA fragment harbouring the complete coding sequence of the <italic>RAR</italic>&#x003b1; gene driven by the Moloney murine leukemia virus long-terminal repeat as well as the SV40 early promoter-driving neomycin phosphotransferase gene (<italic>neo</italic>) as a selectable marker [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. The cells (4 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5 </sup>per 25-cm<sup>2 </sup>flask) were seeded 24 h before infection. Conditioned medium from a retrovirus-producing cell line was filtered through a 0.45-&#x003bc;m membrane (Millipore, USA), diluted 1:1 with medium, containing 1% serum and 8 &#x003bc;g /ml Polybrene and added to the cells for 24 h at 37&#x000b0;C, 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. Further selection were carried out by culturing cells in medium supplemented with 400 &#x003bc;g/ml G418 (Gibco, USA) for at least 21 days. The medium was changed twice a week. The pool of G418-resistant cells was resuspended in culture medium and progressively expanded.</p></sec><sec><title>Assay of cell growth, apoptosis and differentiation</title><p>Cells were seeded into 24-well plates (1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>4 </sup>cell per well) and the cell number was counted at days 1, 3, 5 and 8 after seeding. The apoptosis in the populations of the parental and <italic>RAR&#x003b1; </italic>infected cell lines was performed using the standard procedure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. Cells were collected 24 h after seeding, washed with PBS, and fixed in 70% ethanol overnight at 4&#x000b0;C. Fixed cells were suspended in citric buffer and stained with propidium iodide (5 mcg/ml) in PBS for 1 hour at 4&#x000b0;C. DNA content was subsequently measured by FACScan (Becton Dickinson, USA).</p><p>The immunophenotype of the cells was evaluated as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. Surface expression of the following antigens was determined: CD3, CD5, CD7, CD8, CD11b, CD13, CD15, CD33, CD34, HAE3 and HAE9. In brief, cells were incubated with phycoerythrin-labelled monoclonal mouse antibodies for 20 min at 4&#x000b0;C (Becton, Dickinson), washed with RPMI 1640 medium and analyzed with a flow cytometer (Becton Dickinson).</p></sec><sec><title>Analysis of rhodamine 123 (Rh123) efflux by the cells</title><p>The technique used in the study was described in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. Cells were loaded with 5 &#x003bc;g/ml Rh123 (Sigma) for 10 min at 37&#x000b0;C, washed twice with cold PBS, pH 7.2, and incubated for 30 min in dye-free medium at 37&#x000b0;C. After the completion of incubation, cell were washed twice with cold PBS. Cell fluorescence was measured on a flow cytometer FACScan (Becton Dickinson, USA). Each measurement counted 5000 events. Non-viable cells were gated out of the analysis on the basis of side scatter.</p></sec><sec><title>RNA isolation and reverse transcriptase polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) analysis of RAR&#x003b1; and MDR1 genes expression</title><p>The cells were dissolved in TRI reagent (Sigma, USA). Total RNA was isolated as described in the manufacturer's manual. For analysis, aliquots of isolated RNA were denatured with formamide and subjected to electrophoresis in 1.8% agarose gels. The samples with clearly visualized 18S and 28S RNA bands were used for further procedures. First-strand cDNA was synthesized using reverse transcriptase M-MuLV (MBI Fermentas, Russia) with 4 &#x003bc;g RNA as a template, 2.5 ng random hexamers, 0.25 mM of each deoxynucleotide triphosphate (SibEnzyme, Russia), dithiothreitol, 4 Units of RNAase inhibitor (MBI Fermentas, Russia) and 100 Units of M-MuLV RT. The reaction was performed at 42&#x000b0;C for 50 min, and 1/60 volume of reaction mixture was used for amplification. PCR was done in a total volume of 25 &#x003bc;l using the thermocycler "Tercyc" (DNA-technology, Russia). The PCR mixture consisted of (NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>-containing PCR buffer ("MBI Fermentas"), 0.160 mM dNTPs mix ("MBI Fermentas"), 2 mM MgCl2, 20 pmoles of each specific primer and 0.8 Unit of Taq-polymerase ("MBI Fermentas"). PCR was done as follows: 94&#x000b0;C for 2 seconds, Tm (different for each gene) for 10 seconds, 72&#x000b0;C for 5 seconds. Semi-quantitative PCR analysis of <italic>RARa </italic>and <italic>MDR1 </italic>genes expression were performed using oligomers amplifying a 333 bp and 167 bp products, respectively. Specific gene primers used for RT-PCR are given in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>. The amounts of template cDNAs were normalized by PCR amplification of &#x003b2;2-microglobulin cDNA (internal control). The optimal numbers of PCR cycles were 24 for the b2-microglobulin, 26 for RAR&#x003b1;-specific product, 33 for <italic>MDR1 </italic>(for all cells lines except KG1 and KG1/RAR, for these cells the numbers of PCR cycles <italic>MDR1</italic>-specific product were 26). These numbers of cycles yielded clearly detectable PCR products within an exponential range. PCR products were amplified in separate tubes, resolved by electrophoresis in 2% agarose gel, stained with ethidium bromide and visualized in UV light.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Specific gene primers used for RT-PCR</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="center">Gene</td><td align="center">Product size</td><td align="center">Primer</td><td align="center">Sequence</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center"><italic>RAR&#x003b1;</italic></td><td align="center">333 bp</td><td align="center">F</td><td align="center">5'-GTCTTTGCCTTCGCCAACCAG-3'</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="center">R</td><td align="center">5'-GCCCTCTGAGTTCTCCAACA-3'</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><italic>MDR1</italic></td><td align="center">127 bp</td><td align="center">F</td><td align="center">5'-CCCATCATTGCAATAGCAGG-3'</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="center">R</td><td align="center">5'-GTTCAAACTTCTGCTCCTGA-3'</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><italic>&#x003b2;2m</italic></td><td align="center">114 bp</td><td align="center">F</td><td align="center">5'-ACCCCCACTGAAAAAGATGA-3'</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="center">R</td><td align="center">5'-ATCTTCAAACCTCCATGATG-3'</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>Influence of RAR&#x003b1; gene overexpression on cell differentiation, proliferation and spontaneous apoptosis</title><p><italic>RAR&#x003b1; </italic>gene was introduced into the cultured leukemic cells of diverse types of differentiation as described in Methods. The sublines of H9, KG-1, K562 and NB4 cells characterized by the capability to grow in the medium supplemented with G418 were isolated (H9/RAR, KG-1/RAR, K562/RAR and NB4/RAR). Semi-quantitative RT-PCR revealed more pronounced expression of <italic>RAR&#x003b1; </italic>mRNA in all transfected cell lines in comparison with the wild type cells (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). ATRA (5 &#x003bc;M applied for 48 h) increased <italic>RAR&#x003b1; </italic>mRNA in some <italic>RAR&#x003b1; </italic>transformed cells (H9/RAR, KG-1/RAR, K562/RAR) to a greater extent than in parental cells (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Expression of <italic>RAR&#x003b1; </italic>mRNA in parental and <italic>RAR&#x003b1; </italic>transfected cell lines. RT PCRM</bold>. k- &#x02013; water. ATRA (5 &#x003bc;M) was added to cell cultures 24 h after seeding for 48 h. Then the cells were collected and processed as specified in "Methods" (RNA isolation and reverse transcriptase polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) analysis of <italic>RAR&#x003b1; </italic>gene expression). This figure is representative of 2 separate experiments.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1475-2867-5-15-1"/></fig><p>The investigation of the differentiation status of these cells shows that all <italic>RAR&#x003b1; </italic>transfected sublines differ from the parental cell populations (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). <italic>RAR&#x003b1; </italic>transfected H9 culture contains more cell variants expressing CD5 and CD8 antigens than parental cell line (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A</xref>). Thus the number of cells with antigens of later lymphoid differentiation markers increased in <italic>RAR&#x003b1; </italic>overexpressing H9 cells. There is phenotypic evidence of granulocytic differentiation in KG-1/RAR cell subline as indicated by a reduction in CD13 expression and the increase in the expression of CD11b antigen in comparison with parental cells (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2B</xref>). In KG-1/RAR cell population the portion of CD34 cells decreased and the portion of CD33 cells increased (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2B</xref>). This also testifies to increased differentiation of these <italic>RAR&#x003b1; </italic>overexpressing cells. In K562/RAR population the number of the cells of erythroid differentiation (expressing HAE9 and HAE3 antigens) is larger than in K562 population (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2C</xref>). Hemoglobin synthesis is increased in K562/RAR culture more than 5-fold in comparison with parental cells (not shown). In NB4/RAR population the number of the cells of myelogenous differentiation (expressing CD11b and CD15 antigens) is larger than in NB4 population (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2D</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>Comparison of antigen expression by the parental and <italic>RAR&#x003b1; </italic>infected cell lines</bold>. Cells were incubated for 30 min at 4&#x000b0;C in the presence of an appropriate monoclonal antibody. After three washes with PBS, cells were incubated for 30 min at 4&#x000b0;C with goat antimouse IgG labeled with phycoerythrin and then analyzed in flow cytometer (Becton Dickinson).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1475-2867-5-15-2"/></fig><p>The percentage of cells undergoing spontaneous apoptosis increased 2-3-fold in all <italic>RAR&#x003b1; </italic>transfected cell populations (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). This could be connected with more differentiated phenotype of <italic>RAR&#x003b1; </italic>transformed cells. It seems that in the population of H9/RAR cells the increased number of apoptotic cells could be at least in part connected with increased expression of CD95 (Fas/APO1): in this <italic>RAR&#x003b1; </italic>transformed subline CD95 increased almost 10-fold in comparison with parental cell population (from 2,6% in H9 to 21,4% in H9/RAR culture). However in KG-1 and K562 cell populations the number of CD95 expressing cell did not increase after <italic>RAR&#x003b1; </italic>transformation.</p><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>Spontaneous apoptosis in the populations of the parental and <italic>RAR&#x003b1; </italic>infected cell lines</bold>. Propidium iodide flow cytometry detection of dead cells was performed using the standard procedure. Cells were collected 24 h after seeding, washed with PBS, and fixed in 70% ethanol overnight at 4&#x000b0;C. Fixed cells were suspended in citric buffer and stained with 5 mcg/ml propidium iodide in PBS for 1 hour at 4&#x000b0;C. DNA content was subsequently measured by FACScan (Becton Dickinson, USA). All cells with sub-G<sub>0 </sub>DNA content were regarded as dead cells. This figure is representative of 3 separate experiments.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1475-2867-5-15-3"/></fig><p>As Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref> shows, <italic>RAR&#x003b1; </italic>transfected KG-1, K562 and NB4 cells proliferated more slowly than parental cells. However H9/RAR cells did not demonstrate slower proliferation rate. Thus, more differentiated status of the <italic>RAR&#x003b1; </italic>transformed cell populations was not necessary connected with the decrease in the proliferation rates. All <italic>RAR&#x003b1; </italic>transformed cells seem to be more sensitive than wild type cells to inhibitory action of ATRA on cell proliferation (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><bold>Proliferation rates of parental and <italic>RAR&#x003b1; </italic>infected cells</bold>. Cells were seeded into 24-well plates (1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>4 </sup>cell per well) and the cell number was counted at days 1,3,5,8 after seeding. This figure is representative of 3 separate experiments.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1475-2867-5-15-4"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><bold>Influence of retinoic acid (ATRA, 5 &#x003bc;M) on the proliferation of parental and <italic>RAR&#x003b1; </italic>transfected cells</bold>. Cells were seeded into 24-well plates (1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>4 </sup>cell per well), ATRA was added at seeding and the cell number was counted at days 1, 3, 5 and 8 after seeding. This figure is representative of 3 separate experiments.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1475-2867-5-15-5"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Influence of RAR&#x003b1; overexpression on MDR1 gene activity</title><p>We studied intrinsic and ATRA induced expression of <italic>MDR1 </italic>gene in all cell lines by semi-quantitative RT-PCR technique. The basal levels of <italic>MDR1 </italic>mRNA varied in different wild type cells: in H9 and NB4 cells constitutive <italic>MDR1 </italic>gene expression was not revealed, in K562 wild type cells some <italic>MDR1 </italic>mRNA was found, in KG-1 cells the quantity of <italic>MDR1 </italic>mRNA was large (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>). It is noteworthy that the optimal number of PCR cycles were 33 for <italic>MDR1</italic>-specific product in all cells while for studies of KG1 and KG1/RAR cells we used 26 PCR cycles. In <italic>RAR&#x003b1; </italic>transfected H9 cells the constitutive expression of <italic>MDR1 </italic>gene slightly increased, while in KG-1/RAR and NB4/RAR cells the constitutive <italic>MDR1 </italic>mRNA quantity was not elevated in comparison with the wild type cells, it seems to be even slightly decreased in K562/RAR (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>). Thus the alterations of the basal level of <italic>MDR1 </italic>expression in <italic>RAR&#x003b1; </italic>transformed cells seem to vary in different cell lines.</p><fig position="float" id="F6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><bold>Intrinsic and retinoic acid induced expression of <italic>MDR1 </italic>gene in parental and <italic>RAR&#x003b1; </italic>transfected cells</bold>. k- &#x02013; water. ATRA (5 &#x003bc;M) was added to cell cultures 24 h after seeding for 48 h. Then the cells were collected and processed as specified in "Methods" (RNA isolation and reverse transcriptase polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) analysis of <italic>MDR1 </italic>gene expression). The optimal numbers of PCR cycles were 33 for <italic>MDR1</italic>-specific product for all cells lines except KG1 and KG1/RAR, for these cells the numbers of PCR cycles for <italic>MDR1</italic>-specific product were 26. This figure is representative of 2 separate experiments.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1475-2867-5-15-6"/></fig><p>ATRA (5 &#x003bc;M applied for 48 h) increased <italic>MDR1 </italic>gene expression in all examined cell lines either in parental or <italic>RAR&#x003b1; </italic>transfected cells (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>). In H9/RAR cells effect of ATRA on <italic>MDR1 </italic>expression was significantly greater in comparison with parental cells. In other ATRA treated <italic>RAR&#x003b1; </italic>transformed cell sublines <italic>MDR1 </italic>expression was undistinguishable from ATRA treated parental cells (Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Influence of RAR&#x003b1; gene transformation on Rh123efflux by the cells</title><p>The retention of Rh123 by the cells is considered as a test for Pgp functional activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. Rh123 efflux from the cells was increased in K562/RAR cells in comparison with the parental cell population (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7B</xref>, Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). In H9 and KG-1 <italic>RAR&#x003b1; </italic>transformed cells there were alterations in the Rh123 retention (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7C</xref>): in the populations of H9/RAR and KG-1/RAR cultures the fraction of more dull cells decreased in comparison with parental cultures (mean fluorescence intensity of the cell sublines studied are given in the table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). This shows that Pgp activity was not elevated in these <italic>RAR&#x003b1; </italic>transformed cell populations and suggests that there is some decrease in Pgp functional activity.</p><fig position="float" id="F7"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p><bold>Evaluation of Rh123 efflux from the parental and cells <italic>RAR&#x003b1; </italic>transfected cells</bold>. Cells were loaded with 5 &#x003bc;g/ml Rh123 for 10 min at 37&#x000b0;C, than washed twice with cold PBS, and incubated for 30 min in dye-free medium at 37&#x000b0;C. After the completion of incubation, cell were washed twice with cold PBS. Cell fluorescence was measured on a flow cytometer FACScan (Becton Dikinson, USA). Each measurement counted 5000 events. Non-viable cells were gated out of the analysis on the basis of side scatter. This figure is representative of 2 separate experiments.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1475-2867-5-15-7"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Influence of <italic>RAR&#x003b1; </italic>transformation on the intrinsic and induced expression of <italic>MDR1 </italic>gene</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td></td><td align="center" colspan="2"><italic>MDR1 </italic>expression</td><td align="center" colspan="2">Rh123 efflux (mean fluorescence intensity)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td colspan="4"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="center">Cells</td><td align="center">intrinsic</td><td align="center">ATRA induced</td><td align="center">intrinsic</td><td align="center">ATRA induced</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center"><bold>H9</bold></td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center"><bold>450</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>457</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="center"><bold>H9/RAR</bold></td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">++</td><td align="center"><bold>506</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>416</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="center">K562</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">++</td><td align="center"><bold>446</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>370</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="center">K562/RAR</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">++</td><td align="center"><bold>403</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>333</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="center">KG-1</td><td align="center">++</td><td align="center">+++</td><td align="center"><bold>65,7</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>38,3</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="center">KG-1/RAR</td><td align="center">++</td><td align="center">+++</td><td align="center"><bold>90,7</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>20,2</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="center">NB4</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">++</td><td align="center"><bold>n.d.</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>n.d.</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="center">NB4/RAR</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">++</td><td align="center"><bold>n.d.</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>n.d.</bold></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>There was increase in the portion of Rh123 dull cells after ATRA treatment both in K562 and K562/RAR cell populations (mean fluorescence intensity of both populations decreased approximately on 17%) (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8C, D</xref>, Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). ATRA induced Rh123 efflux from H9/RAR cells, while in H9 parental population this drug had no effect (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8A, B</xref>, Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). In KG-1/RAR cells ATRA induced very prominent increase in the number of Rh123 dull cells (more than 70% decrease of mean fluorescence intensity), while in the parental cell population ATRA decreased mean fluorescence intensity to a lesser extent (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8E, F</xref>, Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F8"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p><bold>Influence of retinoic acid (ATRA) on Rh123 efflux from the parental and cells <italic>RAR&#x003b1; </italic>transfected cells</bold>. ATRA (5 &#x003bc;M) was added to cell cultures 24 h after seeding for 48 h. Than cells were loaded with 5 &#x003bc;g/ml Rh123 for 10 min at 37&#x000b0;C, than washed twice with cold PBS, and incubated for 30 min in dye-free medium at 37&#x000b0;C. After the completion of incubation, cell were washed twice with cold PBS. Cell fluorescence was measured on a flow cytometer FACScan (Becton Dikinson, USA). Each measurement counted 5000 events. Non-viable cells were gated out of the analysis on the basis of side scatter. This figure is representative of 2 separate experiments.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1475-2867-5-15-8"/></fig></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>The treatment of leukemia with retinoids is aimed on the induction of leukemic cells differentiation. The question is: are there interconnections between RA/RAR&#x003b1; regulated differentiation of leukemic cells and <italic>MDR1</italic>/Pgp activity? In this study we have isolated more differentiated variants of the cultured leukemic cells by the introduction into the cells of <italic>RAR&#x003b1; </italic>gene encoding one of RA receptors. All <italic>RAR&#x003b1; </italic>transformed leukemic cell populations were characterized by the higher <italic>RAR&#x003b1; </italic>gene expression in comparison with the parental cells. All <italic>RAR&#x003b1; </italic>transformed leukemic cell populations became more differentiated. This was demonstrated by the studies of the differentiation markers, by the increase in the number of cells dying by spontaneous apoptosis and by the decrease of the proliferation rates of most <italic>RAR&#x003b1; </italic>transfected cell sublines. Thus, <italic>RAR&#x003b1; </italic>overexpression could result in the increase of the differentiation of various leukemic cell populations.</p><p>We compared <italic>MDR1 </italic>gene expression and Pgp functional activity tested by Rh123 retention in parental and <italic>RAR&#x003b1; </italic>transformed cells. The results are summarized in the Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>. Increased constitutive (uninduced) expression of <italic>MDR1 </italic>gene was found in one of four cell lines after <italic>RAR&#x003b1; </italic>transformation (H9/RAR, Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>, Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>). In the previous experiments with melanoma and hepatoblastoma human cells we have shown that constitutive expression of <italic>MDR1 </italic>gene was increased after <italic>RAR&#x003b1; </italic>transfection in both <italic>RAR&#x003b1; </italic>transformed cell sublines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. Thus interconnections between regulation of the basal <italic>MDR1 </italic>and <italic>RAR&#x003b1; </italic>activities could exist both in the cells of solid tumors and in the leukemic cells. Our data suggest, that in the cell populations of solid tumors <italic>RAR&#x003b1; </italic>overexpression could be accompanied by constitutive <italic>MDR1 </italic>over-expression more often than in the cells of hematopoietic malignancies.</p><p>Our study did not reveal the occurrence of the functional Pgp in leukemic cells studied after <italic>RAR&#x003b1; </italic>transformation. In H9/RAR cells elevation of the constitutive <italic>MDR1 </italic>expression did not lead to the increase in Rh123 efflux (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7A</xref>, Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). Some studies also have described discrepancies between Pgp (protein) or <italic>MDR1 </italic>mRNA expression and Pgp function in leukemic cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. These discrepancies could occur for a variety of reasons. Anyway, our data show that increase in the differentiation of leukemic cell populations induced by <italic>RAR&#x003b1; </italic>overexpression did not result in the elevation of constitutive Pgp functional activity. In our previous study we found that <italic>RAR&#x003b1; </italic>overexpression did not change Pgp functional activity in two <italic>RAR&#x003b1; </italic>transformed sublines of human cells (melanoma and hepatoblastoma) but did change it in the rat cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. It seems that exogeneous <italic>RAR&#x003b1; </italic>in the cells of human malignancies does not influence basal Pgp functional activity.</p><p>In KG-1/RAR characterized by the increased differentiaion (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>) we had not found increase in the constitutive <italic>MDR1 </italic>expression and Pgp functional activity decreased (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7C</xref>, Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). It is known that blood stem cells and early progenitors expressing CD34 antigen also express high levels of functionally active Pgp [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>]. Maturation of these cells is accompanied by the decrease in Pgp expression and even more rapid decrease in Pgp functional activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>]. It may be suggested that alterations of Pgp function in KG-1/RAR are connected with the differentiation of these cells.</p><p>The situation with Pgp functional activity induced by ATRA in the cells studied differs from the situation with constitutive activity of this protein. In all three <italic>RAR&#x003b1; </italic>transfected cells ATRA had induced Pgp fuctional activity (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>. Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). Moreover, in two <italic>RAR&#x003b1; </italic>transformed sublines (H9/RAR and KG-1/RAR) ATRA activated Pgp, while in the parental cells it had either no effect (H9) or activated Pgp to a lesser extent (KG-1) (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). These data suggest that <italic>RAR&#x003b1; </italic>participate in the control of induced, but not in constitutive Pgp functional activity in leukemic cells.</p><p>The regulation of <italic>MDR1 </italic>gene transcription and Pgp functional activities are the complex processes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. The studies of these processes are underway. Our data show that <italic>RAR&#x003b1; </italic>gene overexpression could influence the induced Pgp functional activity in leukemic cells, i.e. could participate in the occurrence of multidrug resistance in the populations of these malignant cells. It seems that this influence could depend on the cell context.</p></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This work was supported by grants 04-04-48613a and 02-04-48200 from the Russian Foundation for Basic Research.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ambudkar</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name><surname>Dey</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hrycyna</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramachandra</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pastan</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Gottesman</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biochemical, cellular, and pharmacological aspects of the multidrug transporter</article-title><source>Annu Rev Pharmacol Toxicol</source><year>1999</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>361</fpage><lpage>398</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10331089</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.pharmtox.39.1.361</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scotto</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transcriptional regulation of ABC drug transporters</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>2003</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>7496</fpage><lpage>511</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14576854</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.onc.1206950</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Mickley</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>YN</given-names></name><name><surname>Richert</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Rudick</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Biedler</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Fojo</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expression of a drug resistance gene in human neuroblastoma cell lines: modulation by retinoic acid-induced differentiation</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>1989</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>4337</fpage><lpage>4344</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2573830</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stromskaya</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name><surname>Rybalkina</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name><name><surname>Shtil</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Zabotina</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name><name><surname>Filippova</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Stavrovskaya</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of exogenous RAR&#x003b1; gene on MDR1 expression and P-glycoprotein function in human and rodent cell lines</article-title><source>Br J Cancer</source><year>1998</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>1718</fpage><lpage>1725</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9667638</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tokura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shikami</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Miwa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Watarai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wakabayashi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Satoh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Imamura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mihara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Katoh</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kita</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nitta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Augmented expression of P-gp/multi-drug resistance gene by all-trans retinoic acid in monocytic leukemic cells</article-title><source>Leuk Res</source><year>2002</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>29</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11734301</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0145-2126(01)00094-7</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Altucci</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Gronemeyer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The promise of retinoids to fight against cancer</article-title><source>Nature Rev Cancer</source><year>2001</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>181</fpage><lpage>193</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11902573</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35106036</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Offterdinger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Grunt</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Activation of retinoic acid receptor &#x003b1; is sufficient for full induction of retinoic responses in SK-BR-3 and T47D human breast cancer cells</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2000</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>5479</fpage><lpage>5487</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11034091</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Marie</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Maisonneuve</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Faussat-Suberville</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zittoun</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of differentiating agents on modulation of MDR1 gene expression in multidrug-resistant hematopoietic HL60/DNR cell line</article-title><source>Exp Hematol</source><year>1993</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>779</fpage><lpage>784</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8099018</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Popovic</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarngadharan</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Read</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallo</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detection, isolation and continuous production of cytopathic retroviruses (HTLV III) from patients with AIDS and at risk for AIDS</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1984</year><volume>224</volume><fpage>497</fpage><lpage>500</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6200935</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koeffler</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name><name><surname>Golde</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acute myelogenous leukemia: a human cell line responsive to colony-stimulating activity</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1978</year><volume>200</volume><fpage>1153</fpage><lpage>1154</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">306682</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lozzio</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name><name><surname>Lozzio</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Properties and usefulness of the original K-562 human myelogenous leukemia cell line</article-title><source>Leuk Res</source><year>1979</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>363</fpage><lpage>370</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">95026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0145-2126(79)90033-X</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lanotte</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin-Thouvenin</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Najman</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Balerini</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Valensi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>NB4, a maturation inducible cell line with t(15;17) marker isolated from human acute promyelocytic leukemia (M3)</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>1991</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>1080</fpage><lpage>1086</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1995093</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>LeM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Retinoic acid-induced granulocytic differentiation of HL-60 is mediated directly through the retinoic acid receptor (RAR&#x003b1;)</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>1990</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>2154</fpage><lpage>2163</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1970118</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ohta</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yatomi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sweeney</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hakomory</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Igarashi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A possible role of sphingosine in induction of apoptosis by tumor necrosis factor-alpha in human neutrophils</article-title><source>FEBS Lett</source><year>1994</year><volume>355</volume><fpage>267</fpage><lpage>270</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7988686</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0014-5793(94)01218-0</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Turkina</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Baryshnikov</surname><given-names>JuA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sedjakhina</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><name><surname>Folomeshkina</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name><surname>Sokolova</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Khoroshko</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Stavrovskaya</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Studies of P-glycoprotein in chronic myeloid leukemia patients: expression, activity and correlations with CD34 antigen</article-title><source>Bri J Haematol</source><year>1996</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>88</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2141.1996.273807.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Egudina</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name><surname>Stromskaya</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name><surname>Frolova</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Stavrovskaya</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Early steps of P-glycoprotein expression in cell cultures studied with vital fluorochrome</article-title><source>FEBS Letters</source><year>1993</year><volume>329</volume><fpage>63</fpage><lpage>66</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8102609</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0014-5793(93)80194-Y</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feller</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuiper</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lankelma</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruhdal</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheper</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinedo</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Broxterman</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional detection of MDR/P170 and MRP/P190 mediated multidrug resistance in tumour cells by flow cytometry</article-title><source>Br J Cancer</source><year>1995</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>543</fpage><lpage>549</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7669559</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marie</surname><given-names>J-P</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Gurbuxani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Legrand</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Zittoun</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MDR1/P-glycoprotein in haematological neoplasms</article-title><source>Eur J Cancer</source><year>1996</year><fpage>1034</fpage><lpage>1038</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8763345</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0959-8049(96)00055-X</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bailly</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaffre'zou</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Demur</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gassar</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bordier</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Laurent</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lack of correlation between expression and function of Pgp in acute myeloid leukemia</article-title><source>Leukemia</source><year>1995</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>799</fpage><lpage>807</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7769842</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chaudhary</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mechetner</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name><surname>Roninson</surname><given-names>IB.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expression and activity of the multidrug resistance P-glycoprotein in human peripheral blood lymphocytes</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>1992</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>2735</fpage><lpage>2739</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1360267</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>List</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of multidrug resistance and its pharmacological modulation in acute myeloid leukemia</article-title><source>Leukemia</source><year>1996</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>937</fpage><lpage>942</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8667648</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>



