<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Gastroenterol</journal-id><journal-title>BMC Gastroenterology</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1471-230X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15969757</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1184069</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1471-230X-5-20</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-230X-5-20</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The presence of the proteolysis-inducing factor in urine does not predict the malignancy of a pancreatic tumour</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Teich</surname><given-names>Niels</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>niels.teich@medizin.uni-leipzig.de</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kleeff</surname><given-names>J&#x000f6;rg</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>joerg_kleeff@med.uni-heidelberg.de</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lochs</surname><given-names>Herbert</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>herbert.lochs@charite.de</email></contrib><contrib id="A4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>M&#x000f6;ssner</surname><given-names>Joachim</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>moej@medizin.uni-leipzig.de</email></contrib><contrib id="A5" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Keim</surname><given-names>Volker</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>keimv@medizin.uni-leipzig.de</email></contrib><contrib id="A6" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Friess</surname><given-names>Helmut</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>helmut_friess@med.uni-heidelberg.de</email></contrib><contrib id="A7" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ockenga</surname><given-names>Johann</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>johann.ockenga@charite.de</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Universit&#x000e4;t Leipzig, Medizinische Klinik und Poliklinik II, Leipzig, Germany</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Universit&#x000e4;t Heidelberg, Chirurgische Universit&#x000e4;tsklinik, Heidelberg, Germany</aff><aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Charit&#x000e9; Berlin, Medizinische Klinik und Poliklinik, Gastroenterologie, Hepatologie und Endokrinologie, Berlin, Germany</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2005</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>21</day><month>6</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><fpage>20</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-230X/5/20"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>2</month><year>2005</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>6</month><year>2005</year></date></history><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2005 Teichs et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p></license><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>The proteolysis-inducing factor (PIF) was identified as a tumour product in various gastrointestinal cancers. A previous study in pancreatic cancer patients suggested PIF expression as a tumour marker, which is not related to tumour size. We hypothesized that PIF could be a useful marker to exclude benign pancreatic tumors, as chronic pancreatitis with a pancreatic mass.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><p>Urine of patients with a pancreatic mass of uncertain malignancy was investigated for PIF expression by Western blot. Sufficient urine protein for analysis was available in 59 patients. The diagnosis was established by histology in 54 patients and by follow up in five patients with chronic pancreatitis. In addition, serum CA19-9 was measured.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>The sensitivity (specifity) for the detection of a malignant pancreatic tumour was 90% (75%) and 54% (71%) for CA19-9 and PIF, respectively. The sensitivity (specifity) for the distinction of pancreatic cancer from chronic pancreatitis was 89% (80%) and 57% (63%) for CA19-9 and PIF, respectively.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Evaluation of PIF in urine is of no diagnostic value in patients with a pancreatic mass of unknown malignancy.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Distinction between benign and malignant pancreatic tumours is still difficult, despite significant progress in imaging techniques. Patients with chronic pancreatitis are at increased risk to develop pancreatic cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Pancreatic inflammation, as observed in chronic pancreatitis, can be mistaken on imaging as cancer and inversely. Serum carbohydrate antigen 19-9 (CA19-9) levels are elevated in 80% of pancreatic cancer patients, but can also be increased in 20% of patients with chronic pancreatitis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. An accurate and non-invasive test to differentiate pancreatic cancer from chronic pancreatitis is not available.</p><p>Cancer frequently induces cachexia, but not all cancer patients will develop cachexia. This is not necessarily a late phenomenon in tumour progression. It may be present at diagnosis and may be the leading symptom that induces search for a tumour. A study of pancreatic cancer patients revealed that patients had lost a median of about 14% of their usual body weight at the time of diagnosis, and that this weight loss was progressive, increasing to a median of 25% at the time of the last assessment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. The central role in this process of &#x02013; predominant &#x02013; skeletal muscle waste seems to play the proteolysis-inducing factor (PIF) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>].</p><p>PIF is a 24-kDa sulphated glycoprotein synthesized by cachexia-inducing murine and human tumours, which induces catabolism of myofibrillar proteins in skeletal muscle via a direct stimulation of the proteasome pathway in muscle cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. Administration of PIF to normal mice leads to a rapid decrease in body weight, which is based primarily on a loss of skeletal muscle mass [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>].</p><p>PIF is expressed in a variety of gastrointestinal cancers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. It was detected in the urine of 44 from 55 pancreatic cancer patients, who had a significantly greater total weight loss and rate of weight loss than patients whose urine did not contain PIF. Interestingly, PIF expression was not dependent on cancer stage, but seemed to be a qualitative marker of pancreatic cancer: even stage 2 tumours expressed PIF in 83 per cent [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>].</p><p>PIF has not been investigated in benign pancreatic diseases. We therefore hypothesized that PIF production in patients with a pancreatic tumour would clearly indicate the malignant nature of the disease. Special attention was paid to a clear distinction to a pancreatic mass caused by chronic pancreatitis.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><p>100 patients with a pancreatic mass of uncertain malignancy (detected by computed tomography, magnet resonance tomography, ultrasound and/or endoscopic retrograde cholangiopancreaticography) were investigated. Patients with UICC stage 4 (locally extended and metastasised disease) were not enrolled. After collection of urine from all study participants, we investigated 30 ml urine for the presence of PIF with a specific mouse monoclonal antibody in a Western blot setting as described recently [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. In brief, urine protein was precipitated with ammonium sulphate and dialysed against water between 12 and 15 hours (overnight) with a molecular weight cut-off of 10 kD (Slide-A-Lyzer Dialysis Cassette). 5 &#x003bc;g of concentrated samples were separated with sodium dodecylsulphate polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis and subsequently blotted on nitrocellulose membranes. After incubation with 10 &#x003bc;g/ml of the mouse monoclonal PIF antibody (provided with courtesy by MJ Tisdale) and streptavidine horseradish peroxidase conjugate, the bands were detected using the Fluorescent ECL Plus system (Amersham). In addition, CA19-9 in serum was measured with an electrochemiluminescence immunoassay (CA19-9<sup>&#x000ae;</sup>Roche Diagnostics or ADVIA Centaur<sup>&#x000ae;</sup>, Bayer Healthcare), the upper limit of normal was 22 U/ml. The ethics committees of the three participating centres approved this protocol.</p></sec><sec><title>Results and discussion</title><p>The analysis failed in 41 patients due to insufficient amount of urinary protein after dialysis. In 59 patients, PIF Western blot was successfully performed (figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). This cohort was subsequently assessed: it included 31 male and 28 female patients (median age 59 years, range 33&#x02013;89 years). The diagnoses of the patients were shown in figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>. Final diagnosis was done by histology in 54 patients or follow up for at least one year in five patients with chronic pancreatitis, who did not undergo surgery.</p><p>The diagnostic values of PIF for the detection of a malignant pancreatic tumour and with special attention to pancreatic cancer are shown in table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>. Summarizing all 59 patients, the median CA19-9 values in patients with benign or malignant pancreatic tumours were 16.5 (standard deviation (SD): 141) and 477 (SD: 22173 U/l), respectively (p &#x0003c; 0.05). The median CA19-9 values in patients with chronic pancreatitis and pancreatic cancer were 15.0 (SD: 18) and 478.5 U/l (SD: 22022), respectively (p &#x0003c; 0.05). The analysis of CA19-9 in dependence on the presence of PIF in urine in PIF negative patients revealed 22.5 U/l (SD: 742) and 580.5 U/l in PIF positive patients (SD: 25203) (p &#x0003c; 0.05). PIF was detected in two patients with CA19-9 negative pancreatic cancer, but was not detectable in 16 pancreatic cancer patients (15 of them with elevated CA19-9).</p><p>This is the first attempt to evaluate the proteolysis-inducing factor as a diagnostic marker of pancreatic cancer in patients with a potentially resectable pancreatic tumour. We found a weak association with malignancy, but the diagnostic value to distinguish benign from malignant pancreatic tumours is lower than CA19-9. PIF seems to be of a rather limited importance to answer this question in every-day care.</p><p>A major drawback of our data is the high amount of patients with insufficient urinary protein after extraction and dialysis. For practical reasons in this multi-centre collaboration, we tried to investigate PIF in a small urine sample, as initially suggested by Todorov et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. Our problem could be potentially solved by the collection of higher urine volumes in further studies.</p><p>PIF was detected in 6 patients with chronic pancreatitis without evidence for a malignancy by 12 months follow up or histology. This raises the question about the origin of PIF in these patients. Although the majority of investigations found PIF expression only in tumour tissue, the expression of PIF in non-malignant tissue has been also reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. The primary role of PIF seems to be in regulation of development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. After cloning of the cDNA for PIF, a human homologue &#x02013; the human cachexia associated protein (HCAP) &#x02013; has been identified, which is minimally expressed in normal tissues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. It can be speculated, that the ongoing inflammation in patients with chronic pancreatitis is capable to generate PIF. This could explain the low specifity of PIF to detect pancreatic malignancies in our study. Three patients with pancreatic cancer had normal CA19-9 values, two of them were PIF-positive. A sequential testing of PIF in the case of a CA19-9-negative pancreatic tumour may be beneficial but has to be considered cautiously based on these small patient numbers. However, even this approach would fail to detect all pancreatic cancer patients in our study.</p><p>Although our data indicate that PIF is not helpful as a diagnostic marker of pancreatic cancer, a benefit may be the early identification of patients who need nutritional intervention [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. In previous studies the detection of PIF was associated with prior weight loss. PIF induces an increase of the ubiquitin &#x02013; proteasome activity resulting in protein catabolism. Administration of the polyunsaturated fatty acid eicosapentaenoic acid (EPA) attenuates protein degradation by antagonizing the PIF induced up regulation of the ubiquitin &#x02013; proteasome proteolytic pathway in cachectic tumour bearing mice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. A first randomised placebo &#x02013; controlled trial in patients with pancreatic cancer suggest that a EPA enriched oral supplement has the potential to induce a net gain of weight, lean body mass and improvement of quality of life [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>PIF is not superior to the established tumour marker CA19-9 to distinguish benign from malignant pancreatic tumours. Further investigations should clarify whether the onset of PIF expression in the long-term follow-up of chronic pancreatitis patients is associated with early malignancy and whether it precedes morphologic and clinical signs of pancreatic cancer. In future, the evaluation of PIF as an indicator for early nutritional intervention seems to be warranted.</p></sec><sec><title>Abbreviations</title><p>proteolysis-inducing factor PIF</p><p>pancreatic cancer PaCa</p><p>chronic pancreatitis CP</p><p>carbohydrate antigen 19-9 CA19-9</p><p>eicosapentaenoic acid EPA</p><p>standard deviation SD</p></sec><sec><title>Competing interests</title><p>The author(s) declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>N.T and J.O. had the initial idea and initiated the study. N.T. co-ordinated the laboratory analysis. All authors ascertained patients in this multicenter investigation, wrote and discussed the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec><title>Pre-publication history</title><p>The pre-publication history for this paper can be accessed here:</p><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-230X/5/20/prepub"/></p></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Professor M.J. Tisdale for kindly providing the anti-PIF-antibody. We furthermore thank S. Kistner and T. Herrmann for expert technical assistance.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Malka</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hammel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Maire</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Rufat</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Madeira</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Pessione</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruszniewski</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Risk of pancreatic adenocarcinoma in chronic pancreatitis</article-title><source>Gut</source><year>2002</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>849</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12427788</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/gut.51.6.849</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Satake</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeuchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of CA19-9 with other tumor markers in the diagnosis of cancer of the pancreas</article-title><source>Pancreas</source><year>1994</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>720</fpage><lpage>724</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7846015</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wigmore</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Plester</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Fearon</surname><given-names>KCH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Changes in nutritional status associated with unresectable pancreatic cancer</article-title><source>Br J Cancer</source><year>1997</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>106</fpage><lpage>109</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9000606</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Todorov</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Cariuk</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>McDevitt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Coles</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Fearon</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tisdale</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of a cancer cachectic factor</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1996</year><volume>379</volume><fpage>739</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8602222</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/379739a0</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lorite</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Tisdale</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Activation of ATP-ubiquitin-dependent proteolysis in skeletal muscle in vivo and murine myoblasts in vitro by a proteolysis-inducing factor (PIF)</article-title><source>Br J Cancer</source><year>2001</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>297</fpage><lpage>302</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11461093</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1054/bjoc.2001.1879</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tisdale</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The 'cancer cachectic factor'</article-title><source>Support Care Cancer</source><year>2003</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>78</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12560934</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cabal-Manzano</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhargava</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Torres-Duarte</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhargava</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Wainer</surname><given-names>IW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Proteolysis-inducing factor is expressed in tumours of patients with gastrointestinal cancers and correlates with weight loss</article-title><source>Br J Cancer</source><year>2001</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>1599</fpage><lpage>1601</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11401311</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1054/bjoc.2001.1830</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wigmore</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Todorov</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name><surname>Barber</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Tisdale</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Fearon</surname><given-names>KCH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characteristics of patients with pancreatic cancer expressing a novel cancer cachectic factor</article-title><source>Br J Surg</source><year>2000</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>58</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10606911</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2168.2000.01317.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caruik</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lorite</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Todorov</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>WN</given-names></name><name><surname>Wigmore</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Tisdale</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Induction of cachexia in mice by a product isolated from the urine of cachectic cancer patients</article-title><source>Br J Cancer</source><year>1997</year><volume>76</volume><fpage>606</fpage><lpage>613</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9303359</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schittek</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hipfel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sauer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalbacher</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevanovic</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Schirle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schroeder</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Blin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Meier</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Rassner</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Garbe</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dermcidin: a novel antibiotic peptide secreted by sweat glands</article-title><source>Nat Immunol</source><year>2001</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>1133</fpage><lpage>1137</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11694882</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ni732</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Weremowicz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Seth</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Keshaviah</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lahti-Domenici</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name><name><surname>Monitto</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Merlos-Suarez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hulette</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Morton</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Marks</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Duyao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hruban</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gabrielson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Gelman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Polyak</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A neural survival factor is a candidate oncogene in breast cancer</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2003</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>10931</fpage><lpage>10936</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12953101</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1932980100</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ockenga</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pirlich</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gastell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lochs</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tumoranorexie &#x02013; Tumorkachexie in der Gastroenterologie: Standards und Visionen</article-title><source>Z Gastroenterol</source><year>2002</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>929</fpage><lpage>936</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12436371</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-2002-35411</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whitehouse</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Drake</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Tisdale</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanism of attenuation of skeletal muscle protein catabolism in cancer cachexia by eicosapentaenoic acid</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2001</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>3604</fpage><lpage>3609</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11325828</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fearon</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>von Meyenfeldt</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Moses</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>van Geenen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gouma</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Giacosa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>van Gossum</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Barber</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Aaronson</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name><name><surname>Voss</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Tisdale</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of a protein and energy dense N-3 fatty acid enriched oral supplement on loss of weight and lean tissue in cancer cachexia: a randomised double blind trial</article-title><source>Gut</source><year>2003</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>1479</fpage><lpage>1486</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12970142</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/gut.52.10.1479</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list><sec sec-type="display-objects"><title>Figures and Tables</title><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Western blot analysis for PIF after urinary protein extraction. Lane 1: Rainbow<sup>&#x000ae; </sup>recombinant protein molecular weight marker (#RPN 800, Amersham Life Science); lane 2: healthy control person, lanes 3 and 5: chronic pancreatitis, PIF not detected, lanes 4 and 7: pancreatic cancer, UICC stage 1 and 2, respectively, PIF detected (24 kD, broken line); lanes 6: chronic pancreatitis, PIF detected; lane 8: positive control (pancreatic cancer, UICC stage 4)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-230X-5-20-1"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Diagnoses in PIF positive and PIF negative patients</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-230X-5-20-2"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Diagnostic values of PIF in comparison to CA19-9 to discriminate malignant vs. benign and pancreatic cancer (PaCa) vs. chronic pancreatitis (CP).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td></td><td align="center" colspan="2"><bold>all malignant vs. all benign</bold></td><td align="center" colspan="2"><bold>PaCa vs. CP</bold></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td></td><td align="center"><bold>PIF</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>CA19-9</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>PIF</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>CA19-9</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="5"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Sensitivity</bold></td><td align="center">54%</td><td align="center">90%</td><td align="center">57%</td><td align="center">89%</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Specifity</bold></td><td align="center">71%</td><td align="center">75%</td><td align="center">63%</td><td align="center">80%</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>positive predictive value</bold></td><td align="center">73%</td><td align="center">88%</td><td align="center">74%</td><td align="center">93%</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>negative predictive value</bold></td><td align="center">52%</td><td align="center">80%</td><td align="center">44%</td><td align="center">73%</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec></back></article>



