<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="letter"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Environ Health Perspect</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Environ. Health Perspect</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Environmental Health Perspectives</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0091-6765</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1552-9924</issn><publisher><publisher-name>National Institue of Environmental Health Sciences</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15866749</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1257578</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ehp0113-a0296b</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Perspectives</subject><subj-group><subject>Correspondence</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Maternal and Paternal Risk Factors for Hypospadias</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bianca</surname><given-names>Sebastiano</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ehp0113-a0296a"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ingegnosi</surname><given-names>Carmela</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ehp0113-a0296a"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af1-ehp0113-a0296a">Dipartimento Materno Infantile, Centro di Consulenza Genetica e di, Teratologia della Riproduzione, ARNAS, P.O. Garibaldi Nesima, Catania, Italy, E-mail:
<email>sebastiano.bianca@tiscali.it</email></aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ettore</surname><given-names>Giuseppe</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-ehp0113-a0296a"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af2-ehp0113-a0296a">Dipartimento Materno Infantile, U.O. Ginecologia e Ostetricia, ARNAS, P.O. Garibaldi Nesima, Catania, Italy</aff><author-notes><fn><p>The authors declare they have no competing financial interests.</p></fn><fn><p>Editor&#x02019;s note: In accordance with journal policy, Pierik et al. were asked whether they wanted to respond to this letter, but they chose not to do so.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>5</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><volume>113</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage seq="b">A296</fpage><lpage>A296</lpage><permissions><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/" license-type="public-domain"><license-p>Publication of EHP lies in the public domain and is therefore without copyright. All text from EHP may be reprinted freely. Use of materials published in EHP should be acknowledged (for example, ?Reproduced with permission from Environmental Health Perspectives?); pertinent reference information should be provided for the article from which the material was reproduced. Articles from EHP, especially the News section, may contain photographs or illustrations copyrighted by other commercial organizations or individuals that may not be used without obtaining prior approval from the holder of the copyright. </license-p></license></permissions><related-article id="d35e81" related-article-type="commentary-article" xlink:href="15531444" ext-link-type="pubmed" vol="112" page="1570"/></article-meta></front><body><p>Hypospadias is a common congenital anomaly, characterized by incomplete fusion of the urethral folds during fetal development, which results in the urethra opening on the ventral surface of the penis or on the scrotum. In their article, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4-ehp0113-a0296b">Pierik et al. (2004)</xref> proposed multiple possible maternal and paternal risk factors related to the development of isolated hypospadias, including genetic, endocrine, and environmental factors.</p><p>Concerns and alarms have been raised about the potential effects of endocrine disruptors, which include derivatives of poly-aromatic hydrocarbons and pesticides, on the developing male reproductive tract. We have recently published two case&#x02013;control studies on risk factors and hypospadias, one on a possible association with maternal age (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2-ehp0113-a0296b">Bianca et al. 2005</xref>) and the other on the role of endocrine disruptors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3-ehp0113-a0296b">Bianca et al. 2003</xref>).</p><p>In the first study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2-ehp0113-a0296b">Bianca et al. 2005</xref>), we evaluated 415 newborns with isolated hypospadias and 812 controls. Our results suggest that an increased risk for hypospadias exists in women at the extremes of the age distribution (&#x0003c; 20 years and &#x0003e; 40 years; <italic>p</italic> = 0.000 and 0.026, respectively) relative to women in the middle of the distribution, with a mechanism probably related to hormonal disruption. It has been postulated that changes in concentrations of sex hormones during the fetal critical period of genital development (weeks 8&#x02013;14), caused by endogenous or exogenous factors, may play a role in the development of hypospadias and that hypospadias could be associated with early malfunction of the placenta, resulting in decreased secretion of placental and fetal hormones that could in turn disturb fetal development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1-ehp0113-a0296b">Akre et al. 1999</xref>). Mothers at the extremes of the age distribution may be more susceptible to this hormonal disruption. The association between hypospadias and maternal age, both for younger and older women, might be explained as a &#x0201c;defect in nature&#x02019;s quality control&#x0201d; caused by a reduction of defensive maternal mechanisms that would be less efficient in the elimination of malformed fetuses in the mothers of hypospadias cases. This hypothesis may also apply to other birth defects where a relationship with maternal age has been demonstrated.</p><p>In the second study of 68 cases and 211 controls (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3-ehp0113-a0296b">Bianca et al. 2003</xref>), we identified a high incidence of hypospadias in two towns in southeastern Sicily, which have intense industrial (Augusta) and agricultural (Vittoria) activities. Our results showed an incidence that was 3.8 [95% confidence interval (CI), 2.16&#x02013;6.14] and 2.3 times (95% CI, 1.48&#x02013;3.43) higher, respectively, than expected (3.2 per 1,000 male live births in southeastern Sicily). The odds ratios for fathers&#x02019; job exposure alone were 5.5 (95% CI, 1.22&#x02013;24.7) for working in an oil refinery in Augusta and 2.9 (95% CI, 1.01&#x02013;8.55) for working in hothouses in Vittoria.</p><p>Pollutants in both areas include compounds with proven estrogenic activity and other chemicals: pesticides and herbicides and their metabolites; dieldrin, chlordane, and endosulfan; polychlorinated biphenyls and dioxins; bisphenols used in epoxy resins; and some phthalates used as plasticizers in a wide variety of applications, including polyvinyl compounds and alkyphenol ethoxylates. The direct cause&#x02013;effect relationship between environmental pollutants, which act as endocrine disruptors, and the increased incidence of hypospadias in these areas is difficult to establish and demonstrate.</p><p>Our study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3-ehp0113-a0296b">Bianca et al. 2003</xref>), suggested that exposure to large amounts of industrial and agricultural pollutants is sufficient to increase the risk of hypospadias. Other risk factors, such as reproductive history, may be involved in the etiology of hypospadias. Disturbances in sexual differentiation occur when endogenous and/or exogenous factors act to disrupt the metabolism of gonadal hormones during development.</p><p>Further epidemiologic and biologic studies are needed to explain, in a multi-factorial model, which factors (genetic and/or environmental) interact and influence the etiology of this congenital abnormality.</p></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="b1-ehp0113-a0296b"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Akre</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipworth</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Cnattingius</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sparen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ekbom</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>Risk factor patterns for cryptorchidism and hypospadias</article-title><source>Epidemiology</source><volume>10</volume><fpage>364</fpage><lpage>369</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10401869</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b2-ehp0113-a0296b"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Bianca</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ingegnosi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ettore</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Maternal age and hypospadias</article-title><source>Acta Obstet Gynecol Scand</source><volume>84</volume><fpage>410</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15762979</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b3-ehp0113-a0296b"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Bianca</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Li Volti</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Caruso-Nicoletti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ettore</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Barone</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lupo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Elevated incidence of hypospadias in two Sicilian towns where exposure to industrial and agricultural pollutants is high</article-title><source>Reprod Toxicol</source><volume>17</volume><fpage>539</fpage><lpage>545</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14555191</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b4-ehp0113-a0296b"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Pierik</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name><name><surname>Burdorf</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Deddens</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Juttmann</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>RFA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Maternal and paternal risk factors for cryptorchidism and hypospadias: a case&#x02013;control study in newborn boys</article-title><source>Environ Health Perspect</source><volume>112</volume><fpage>1570</fpage><lpage>1576</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15531444</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
