<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Transl Med</journal-id><journal-title>Journal of Translational Medicine</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1479-5876</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">16131400</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1236966</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1479-5876-3-33</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1479-5876-3-33</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Commentary</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Implementations of translational medicine</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sonntag</surname><given-names>Kai-Christian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>kai.sonntag@mclean.harvard.edu</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Harvard Medical School, Center for Neuroregeneration Research, MRC 102, McLean Hospital, 115 Mill Street, Belmont, MA 02478, USA</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2005</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>8</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><volume>3</volume><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.translational-medicine.com/content/3/1/33"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>5</day><month>8</month><year>2005</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>30</day><month>8</month><year>2005</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2005 Sonntag; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2005</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Sonntag; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>
               Sonntag
               Kai-Christian
               
               kai.sonntag@mclean.harvard.edu
            </dc:author><dc:title>
            Implementations of translational medicine
         </dc:title><dc:date>2005</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>Journal of Translational Medicine 3(1): 33-. (2005)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1479-5876(2005)3:1&#x0003c;33&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1479-5876</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><p>New developments in science are rapidly influencing and shaping basic and clinical research and medicine. This has led to the emergence of multiple opportunities and challenges on many levels in the bio-medical and other associated fields. To face these opportunities and challenges, new concepts and strategies are needed. These can be provided by translational research/medicine as an integrative concept based on a multidirectional understanding of research and medicine embedded in a socio-economical environment. Although the implementation of translational research/medicine faces many obstacles, some of its goals have already been part of new programs in local institutions and in medical or scientific societies. These implementations are important in creating a unified national and international system of translational research/medicine.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><p>The rapid evolutions in science have generated a tremendous spectrum of new technologies and tools in both basic and clinical research/medicine. This includes the constant improvement of old and the discovery of new diagnostics and therapies, which increasingly contain and integrate elements from different fields, such as biomedical and other sciences, modern and traditional medicine and various technology branches. In addition, the application of these developments in clinical settings have created a "feed-back-loop" providing crucial information about their feasibility and success in improving human health. This network of scientific and clinical research/medicine has become one of the factors in shaping modern societies not only by being a major economical factor (see [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>] for details), but also by challenging basic values and traditional thinking. To face the emerging challenges of creating a balanced and effective healthcare system, new concepts are needed for providing a framework of integrative strategies and solutions that efficiently combine basic and clinical research/medicine.</p><p>So far, translational research/medicine has rather been a linear concept rooted in traditional (academic) approaches to provide therapies for diseases (from bench to bedside), while paying little attention to patient-oriented research that involves understanding the underlying cause of disease and its treatments (from bedside to bench). Moreover, not much attention has been paid to many socio-economical aspects that are associated with research or medicine. Therefore, new definitions based on a bi- or multi-directional understanding of translational research/medicine have been proposed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>] and, recently, a strategic outline to successfully implement the goals of this new concept has been outlined in an article by H&#x000f6;rig et al. in Nature Medicine [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>].</p><p>This commentary aims to add a few additional aspects by emphasizing two major factors that strongly influence and, in turn, are influenced by translational research/medicine: (1) The rapid evolution of new technologies and therapeutic approaches, and (2) examples of attempts to create programs, which are based on a translational understanding of basic and clinical research and/or medicine.</p><p>In the past two decades, biomedical and other research fields like gene therapy, the human genome project (HUGO), stem cell research, cloning, nanotechnology and others have revolutionized medicine and generated entirely new fields and approaches in treatment of diseases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. Thus, it is becoming more and more obvious that new forms of therapies, such as gene- or cell-replacement-therapy, will have a place in future therapeutic approaches. In addition, the rapid expansion of bio- and other technology development are expected to lead to an advanced understanding of diseases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. These new fields not only offer multiple new opportunities in the research and biomedical sector, but also require attention on multiple other levels involving religious and ethical issues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>] including new definitions of life, disease, and treatment, the power and limitations of technology, the availability of resources, and the adjustment of social and political actions.</p><p>How can these fields be combined and integrated in the concept of translational research/medicine? Are there any attempts to develop programs based on a "translational" thinking in research and medicine? So far, the concepts of translational research/medicine have been described and discussed in the context of different medical fields, e.g. in obstetrics and gynecology [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>], radiation therapy and radiobiology [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>], cancer therapy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>], psychiatry [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>], pain research [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>], gastroenterology [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>] or in the broader context of research and medicine [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. And, so far, it seems that there is an overall agreement in defining the goals of translational research/medicine and delineating the obstacles in their implementations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. In addition, many of these articles have provided suggestions and strategies how to translate these concepts into practice (e.g. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>]). However, it should be emphasized that translational research/medicine does not affect specialized fields alone. Rather it should be an integrative concept that, with implications to everybody in the field, should be part of a broader understanding of how research and medicine should be organized. A major part of these processes refers to education and training opportunities and there have been examples published how this can be implemented by personal experience (e.g. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>]), by the quest for specialized institutions (e.g. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>]), or by using existing educational systems (e.g. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>]). It should also be noted that scientific/medical societies have started to adopt and integrate many aspects of the concept of translational research/medicine in their agendas and are in the process to find new creative and innovative strategies on multiple levels, including education, public discussions, funding opportunities, career development, etc. This especially applies to societies, which integrate a vast spectrum of bioresearch, biotechnology and biomedical fields such as the American Society for Gene Therapy (ASGT; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.asgt.org"/>) or the International Society for Stem Cell Research (ISSCR; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.isscr.org"/>). On the local level, there are existing clinical programs that aim to improve the clinical education by emphasizing translational thinking (e.g. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>]) or other programs with a broader approach of being integrative between researchers, clinicians and health care providers. The latter programs &#x02013; like the medical societies &#x02013; offer new opportunities to facilitate collaborations between researchers and clinicians and represent a platform to process the multilevel challenges emerging from the rapid advances in the biomedical fields. For example, the Harvard Medical School has launched two new centers, the Harvard Center for Neuroregeneration (HCNR; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.hcnr.harvard.med.edu"/>) and the Harvard Stem Cell Institute (HSCI; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://stemcell.harvard.edu"/>), whose goals are to create an environment that combines investigators on multiple levels and address many features of translational research/medicine like identification of new and alternative funding opportunities including academia-industry synergies, healthcare delivery, the improvement of infrastructural hurdles by creating core facilities, training opportunities, etc. These "enterprises" require significant logistical efforts and often rely on established systems, which can provide, space, informatics, administration, and skilled personnel. Although these are local efforts and might not reflect the overall situation, it shows that efforts are made and many aspects of translational research/medicine can be realized. The experiences gained from these local "enterprises" might be then translatable and integrated into a bigger national and international network creating a more unified system of translational research/medicine.</p><p>In summary, translational research/medicine is not a single standing idea that can be applied whenever it is needed. Rather, it is a concept that needs the attention from everyone and should be the foundation of a modern understanding of health provision. It is essential to face the challenges emerging from the rapid advances in the biomedical and other associated fields. Its implementation needs a multilevel effort in many different areas, which together create a health system as a whole. Some of the goals in translational research/medicine are already part of new programs in local institutions and in medical or scientific societies. These implementations are important in creating an overall and unifying network of translational research/medicine.</p></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The author wishes to thank Dr. Christian Brander for review and helpful comments of the manuscript.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Horig</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Marincola</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Marincola</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Obstacles and opportunities in translational research</article-title><source>Nat Med</source><year>2005</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>705</fpage><lpage>708</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16015353</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nm0705-705</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marincola</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Translational Medicine: A two-way road</article-title><source>J Transl Med</source><year>2003</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14527344</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1479-5876-1-1</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rustgi</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Translational research: what is it?</article-title><source>Gastroenterology</source><year>1999</year><volume>116</volume><fpage>1285</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10348809</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Phillipson</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>If it's not integrative, it may not be translational</article-title><source>Clin Invest Med</source><year>2002</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>94</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12137259</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dauphinee</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Breaking down the walls: thoughts on the scholarship of integration</article-title><source>Acad Med</source><year>2000</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>881</fpage><lpage>886</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10995608</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Stahl</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Stephenson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Whelan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biomedical education in the 21st century</article-title><source>Mo Med</source><year>2004</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>484</fpage><lpage>486</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15535023</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Molidor</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sturn</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Maurer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Trajanoski</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New trends in bioinformatics: from genome sequence to personalized medicine</article-title><source>Exp Gerontol</source><year>2003</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>1031</fpage><lpage>1036</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14580855</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0531-5565(03)00168-2</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bast</surname><given-names>RCJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Translational research--traffic on the bridge</article-title><source>Biomed Pharmacother</source><year>2001</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>565</fpage><lpage>571</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11769968</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0753-3322(01)00144-5</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kagarise</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheldon</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Translational ethics: a perspective for the new millennium</article-title><source>Arch Surg</source><year>2000</year><volume>135</volume><fpage>39</fpage><lpage>45</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10636345</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archsurg.135.1.39</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Where is translational research?</article-title><source>Bjog</source><year>2004</year><volume>111</volume><fpage>395</fpage><lpage>396</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15104600</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dische</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Saunders</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Translational Research--a new entity?</article-title><source>Acta Oncol</source><year>2001</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>995</fpage><lpage>999</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11845966</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/02841860152708297</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>International Conference on Translational Research ICTR 2003 Conference Summary: marshalling resources in a complex time</article-title><source>Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys</source><year>2004</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>307</fpage><lpage>319</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14751498</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijrobp.2003.09.056</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Licinio</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Translational research in psychiatry: pitfalls and opportunities for career development</article-title><source>Mol Psychiatry</source><year>2004</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>117</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14966470</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.mp.4001479</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Translational pain research: bridging the gap between basic and clinical research</article-title><source>Pain</source><year>2002</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>183</fpage><lpage>187</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12044614</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0304-3959(02)00109-4</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sartor</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Translational research: Bridging the widening gap between basic and clinical research</article-title><source>Gastroenterology</source><year>2003</year><volume>124</volume><fpage>1178</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12730855</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0016-5085(03)00341-X</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nathan</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The several Cs of translational clinical research</article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><year>2005</year><volume>115</volume><fpage>795</fpage><lpage>797</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15841166</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI200524753</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mankoff</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Brander</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferrone</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Marincola</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lost in Translation: Obstacles to Translational Medicine</article-title><source>J Transl Med</source><year>2004</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>14</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15149545</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1479-5876-2-14</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ioannidis</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Materializing research promises: opportunities, priorities and conflicts in translational medicine</article-title><source>J Transl Med</source><year>2004</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>5</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14754464</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1479-5876-2-5</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pober</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Neuhauser</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Pober</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Obstacles facing translational research in academic medical centers</article-title><source>Faseb J</source><year>2001</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>2303</fpage><lpage>2313</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11689456</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1096/fj.01-0540lsf</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hotez</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Should we establish a North American school of global health sciences?</article-title><source>Am J Med Sci</source><year>2004</year><volume>328</volume><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>77</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15311164</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00000441-200408000-00001</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><name><surname>Crowley</surname><given-names>WFJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Genel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Salber</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sandy</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sherwood</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Catanese</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Tilson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Getz</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Larson</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheinberg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Reece</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Slavkin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Dobs</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Grebb</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Korn</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rimoin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Central challenges facing the national clinical research enterprise</article-title><source>Jama</source><year>2003</year><volume>289</volume><fpage>1278</fpage><lpage>1287</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12633190</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.289.10.1278</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mark</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelch</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinician scientist training program: a proposal for training medical students in clinical research</article-title><source>J Investig Med</source><year>2001</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>486</fpage><lpage>490</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11730083</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fenton</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>James</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Insel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Psychiatry residency training, the physician-scientist, and the future of psychiatry</article-title><source>Acad Psychiatry</source><year>2004</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>263</fpage><lpage>266</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15673819</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/appi.ap.28.4.263</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Translational research: getting the word and the meaning right</article-title><source>Arthritis Rheum</source><year>2003</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>720</fpage><lpage>721</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14558060</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/art.11370</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Heft</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Dionne</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeffcoat</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Alfano</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Valachovic</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipton</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Capacity for training in clinical research: status and opportunities</article-title><source>J Dent Educ</source><year>2003</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>622</fpage><lpage>629</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12856962</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwartz-Bloom</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Science education: a neuroscientist's view of translational medicine</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2005</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>5667</fpage><lpage>5669</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15958732</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1693-05.2005</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Herold</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>McArdle</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Stagnaro-Green</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Translational medicine in the first year: integrative cores</article-title><source>Acad Med</source><year>2002</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>1171</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12431953</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00001888-200211000-00040</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>DePaolo</surname><given-names>LV</given-names></name><name><surname>Leppert</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Providing research and research training infrastructures for clinical research in the reproductive sciences</article-title><source>Am J Obstet Gynecol</source><year>2002</year><volume>187</volume><fpage>1087</fpage><lpage>1090</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12389010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1067/mob.2002.125896</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crowley</surname><given-names>WFJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Thier</surname><given-names>SO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A program to facilitate clinical research in an AHC: the first five years</article-title><source>Acad Med</source><year>2001</year><volume>76</volume><fpage>403</fpage><lpage>409</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11346512</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Halpain</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeste</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name><name><surname>Trinidad</surname><given-names>GI</given-names></name><name><surname>Wetherell</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lebowitz</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intensive short-term research training for undergraduate, graduate, and medical students: early experience with a new national-level approach in geriatric mental health</article-title><source>Acad Psychiatry</source><year>2005</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>58</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15772406</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/appi.ap.29.1.58</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>



