<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Dyn Med</journal-id><journal-title>Dynamic medicine : DM</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1476-5918</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15877822</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1142518</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1476-5918-4-5</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1476-5918-4-5</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Commentary</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Paramagnetic artifact and safety criteria for human brain mapping</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Seiyama</surname><given-names>Akitoshi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>aseiyama@phys1.med.osaka-u.ac.jp</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Seki</surname><given-names>Junji</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>sekij@ri.ncvc.go.jp</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Iwamoto</surname><given-names>Mari</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I4">4</xref><email>iwamoto@uwajima-mh.go.jp</email></contrib><contrib id="A4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yanagida</surname><given-names>Toshio</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I5">5</xref><email>yanagida@phys1.med.osaka-u.ac.jp</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Brain Information Group, Kansai Advanced Research Center, Communications Research Laboratory, 588-2 Iwaoka, Nishi-ku, Kobe, Hyogo 651-2492, Japan</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Division of Physiology and Biosignaling, Osaka University Graduate School of Medicine, 2-2 Yamadaoka, Suita, Osaka 565-0871, Japan</aff><aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Department of Biomedical Engineering, National Cardiovascular Center Research Institute, 5-7-1 Fujishiro-dai, Suita, Osaka 565-8565, Japan</aff><aff id="I4"><label>4</label>Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Ehime University, School of Medicine, Shizukawa, Shigenobu-cho, Onsen-gun, Ehime 791-0295, Japan</aff><aff id="I5"><label>5</label>Soft Biosystem Group, Graduate School of Frontier Biosciences, Osaka University, 2-2 Yamadaoka, Suita, Osaka 565-0871, Japan</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2005</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>7</day><month>5</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><volume>4</volume><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.dynamic-med.com/content/4/1/5"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>9</day><month>3</month><year>2005</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>7</day><month>5</month><year>2005</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2005 Seiyama et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2005</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Seiyama et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>
               Seiyama
               Akitoshi
               
               
               aseiyama@phys1.med.osaka-u.ac.jp
            </dc:author><dc:title>
            Paramagnetic artifact and safety criteria for human brain mapping
         </dc:title><dc:date>2005</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>Dynamic Medicine 4(1): 5-. (2005)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1476-5918(2005)4:1&#x0003c;5&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1476-5918</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><p>Biological effects of magnetic field and their safety criteria, especially effects of gradient magnetic field on the cerebral and pulmonary circulation during functional brain mapping are still unclear. Here we estimated that magnetically induced artifacts for the blood oxygenation level- and flow- based functional magnetic resonance imaging are less than 0.1%, and disturbance in the pulmonary circulation is less than 1.3% even if the field strength of magnetic resonance system is risen up to 10 tesla. These paramagnetic effects are considered to be small and harmless during human brain mapping.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) has become a vital tool for human brain function studies and medical diagnosis. Magnetic field strengths are expected to rise from the current 1.5 to 7 tesla (T) or further to achieve higher spatial resolution and signal-to-noise ratio, although biological effects of magnetic fields and their safety criteria for human subjects are still unclear. Biological effects of magnetic fields depend mainly on 1) the field strength and its gradient, 2) area and duration time of exposure to the field, and 3) the static or dynamic properties of magnetic field [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. The threshold of time-varying magnetic fields to human exposure is a frequent theme and examined experimentally and theoretically [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>], because they might produce cardiac and peripheral nerve stimulation, heating, and magneto-phosphene during exposure. Furthermore, movement of subjects or patients within a static magnetic field produces sensory effects such as vertigo, nausea, and a peculiar metallic taste [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>].</p><p>On the other hand, the static magnetic field has a potential to affect the blood flow through the following three mechanisms: 1) magnetohydrodynamic action, which is theoretically predicted to decrease the aortic blood flow velocity by 10% under homogeneous magnetic fields at about 5 T [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>], 2) diamagnetic anisotropic interaction, which modifies the orientation of sickled and normal erythrocytes at homogeneous magnetic field of 0.35 T[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>] and 4 T [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>], respectively, and 3) paramagnetic interaction under a strong spatial gradient of magnetic field, which was applied to separate paramagnetic erythrocyte from whole blood [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><sec><title>Paramagnetic interaction between gradient magnetic fields and flowing erythrocytes</title><p>To estimate maximal effects of the gradient magnetic field, which is applied to the human in MR measurements, on the cerebral and pulmonary microcirculation, we examined the effects of gradient magnetic fields on erythrocyte flow in a model of branched blood vessels with Reynold's number as small as that for blood flow in capillaries and venules (see <bold>'Supplementary Method 1' in Additional file </bold><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>), which are major contributors to signal changes in fMRI. An inhomogeneous magnetic field (field strength and spatial gradient product: up to 60 T<sup>2</sup>/m) was transversally applied to the blood flow using an electromagnet whose direction of magnetic field is perpendicular to the vessel axis (see Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref> of Ref. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]), which covered the gradient field of 10-T MRI system (see Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>). We observed that the spatial distribution of 70% oxygenated erythrocytes flowing in the branched vessel deviated in proportion to the product of magnetic field strength and its gradient up to 20 T<sup>2</sup>/m, above which the deviation saturated. On the other hand, fully oxygenated erythrocytes flow showed no deviation. The deviation of spatial distribution of 70% oxygenated erythrocytes can be attributed to paramagnetic attraction by an inhomogeneous magnetic field [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>].</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Paramagnetic effects of gradient magnetic fields on the pulmonary circulation during human brain mapping. (A) Magnetic field strength (Bz), and calculated field gradient (-dBz/dz) and force product (-Bz&#x000b7;dBz/dz) along the centerline of the magnet (see '<bold>Supplementary Method 2' in Additional file 1</bold>). Maximal values of -dBz/dz at Bz = 1.5, 3.0, 4.0, 7.0 and 10 T were 1.03, 2.06, 2.75, 4.81 and 6.87 T/m, respectively (at z = 1.47 m). Maximal values of -Bz&#x000b7;dBz/dz at Bz = 1.5, 3.0, 4.0, 7.0 and 10 T were 1.21, 4.84, 8.60, 26.40 and 53.75 T<sup>2</sup>/m, respectively (at z = 1.14 m), which are well covered by the range of our experiment shown in Fig. 1B. The head and lung of a healthy volunteer, whose height is 1.75 m, head length is 0.25 m, length of epigastric fossa from top of head is 0.5 m, were positioned at the magnet's center (A: z = 0 m) and at maximal of -Bz&#x000b7;dBz/dz (B: z = 1.14 m), respectively. (B) Maximally estimated redistribution of erythrocytes estimated in the pulmonary circulation at position B (see 'Supplementary Method 3' in Additional file).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1476-5918-4-5-1"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Effect of gradient magnetic fields on the pulmonary circulation</title><p>First, we estimated the maximal effects of the deviation of erythrocyte distribution on the pulmonary blood flow, which could cause a ventilation perfusion mismatch (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref>). When a volunteer was positioned under the maximal inhomogeneous magnetic field (position B in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>), the deviation of erythrocyte distribution in the pulmonary blood flow increased with increases in the product of field strength and its gradient but it saturated above |Bz&#x000b7;dBz/dz| &#x0003e; 40 T<sup>2</sup>/m (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref>). However, the estimated value of deviation (maximally ca. 1.3%) was small and its effect on the ventilation perfusion mismatch is negligible even under the maximal inhomogeneous magnetic field generated by the 10-T system.</p></sec><sec><title>Effect of gradient magnetic fields on the cerebral microcirculation</title><p>Next, we estimated maximal effects of such deviation of erythrocyte distribution on signal changes in functional neuroimaging based on the commonly used blood oxygenation-level dependent (BOLD) (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A</xref>) and flow sensitive alternating inversion recovery (FAIR) (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2B</xref>) techniques. The gradient magnetic fields produced underestimation of BOLD and overestimation of FAIR signals almost linearly with the increases in the magnetic field strength. However, the values (0.024% for BOLD and 0.07% for FAIR) were quite small and these artifacts are negligible even for the 10-T system.</p><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Effects of magnetic field under gradient echo echo planar imaging (GE-EPI) on the cerebral microcirculation. (A) Maximal effects of magnetic field under GE-EPI on BOLD signal at position A during functional brain mapping at slice gradient = 40 mT/m for all MR systems (see <bold>'Supplementary Method 4' in Additional file 1</bold>). (B) Maximal effects of magnetic field under GE-EPI on FAIR signal at position A during functional brain mapping at slice gradient = 40 mT/m for all MR systems (see <bold>'Supplementary Method 5' in Additional file</bold>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1476-5918-4-5-2"/></fig></sec></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Our results suggest that paramagnetic artifacts in the functional neuroimaging and disturbance in the pulmonary microcirculation during magnetic resonance imaging are quite small using the MR system with field strength up to 10 T.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>AS conceived, designed and coordinated the study, carried out the experiments, and drafted the manuscript. JS participated in the design and coordination of the study. MI participated in the experiments. TY participated in the design and coordination of the study, and directed it. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S1"><caption><title>Additional File 1</title><p>Supplementary Method 1: Experimental Setup. Supplementary Method 2: Estimation of magnetic fields. Supplementary Method 3: Estimation of redistribution of erythrocytes in the pulmonary circulation. Supplementary Method 4: Estimation of paramagnetic artifacts in BOLD signal. Supplementary Method 5: Estimation of paramagnetic artifacts in FAIR signal</p></caption><media xlink:href="1476-5918-4-5-S1.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>International Electrotechnical Commission</collab></person-group><article-title>Internationalstandard: Part 2. Particular requirements for the safety of magnetic resonance equipment for medical diagnosis</article-title><source>CEI/IEC 60601-2-33</source><year>2002</year></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schaefer</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bourland</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Nyenhuis</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Review of patient safety in time-varying gradient fields</article-title><source>J Magn Reson Imag</source><year>2000</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>20</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/1522-2586(200007)12:1&#x0003c;20::AID-JMRI3&#x0003e;3.0.CO;2-Y</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schenck</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Safety of strong, static magnetic fields</article-title><source>J Magn Reson Imag</source><year>2000</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>2</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/1522-2586(200007)12:1&#x0003c;2::AID-JMRI2&#x0003e;3.0.CO;2-V</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>IIH</given-names></name><name><surname>Saha</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of an intensive magnetic fields on blood flow</article-title><source>J Bioelectricity</source><year>1984</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>293</fpage><lpage>298</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murayama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Orientation of sickled erythrocytes in a magnetic field</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1965</year><volume>206</volume><fpage>420</fpage><lpage>422</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5835725</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamagishi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeuchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Higashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Date</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diamagnetic orientation of blood cells in high magnetic field</article-title><source>Physica B</source><year>1992</year><volume>177</volume><fpage>523</fpage><lpage>526</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Melville</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Roath</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Direct magnetic separation of red cells from whole blood</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1975</year><volume>255</volume><fpage>706</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1134566</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seiyama</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Maeda</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Shiga</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of distribution of flowing erythrocytes in a model vessel under an inhomogeneous magnetic field</article-title><source>Eur Biophys J</source><year>1996</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s002490050009</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Okazaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Maeda</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Shiga</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of an inhomogeneous magnetic field on flowing erythrocytes</article-title><source>Eur Biophys J</source><year>1987</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>145</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3830092</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00253838</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>



