<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="letter"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Environ Health Perspect</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Environ. Health Perspect</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Environmental Health Perspectives</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0091-6765</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1552-9924</issn><publisher><publisher-name>National Institute of Environmental Health Sciences</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">16203224</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1281320</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ehp0113-a0657c</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Perspectives</subject><subj-group><subject>Correspondence</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Toxicity Tests: &#x0201c;Inert&#x0201d; and Active Ingredients</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Surgan</surname><given-names>Michael H.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ehp0113-a0657c"/></contrib><aff id="af1-ehp0113-a0657c">Environmental Protection Bureau New York State Attorney General&#x02019;s Office, New York, New York, E-mail:
<email>michael.surgan@oag.state.ny.us</email></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn><p>The author is the chief scientist in the New York State Attorney General&#x02019;s Environmental Protection Bureau and was actively involved in the 1996 action against Monsanto.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>10</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><volume>113</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage seq="c">A657</fpage><lpage>A658</lpage><permissions><copyright-year>2005</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/" license-type="public-domain"><license-p>Publication of EHP lies in the public domain and is therefore without copyright. All text from EHP may be reprinted freely. Use of materials published in EHP should be acknowledged (for example, ?Reproduced with permission from Environmental Health Perspectives?); pertinent reference information should be provided for the article from which the material was reproduced. Articles from EHP, especially the News section, may contain photographs or illustrations copyrighted by other commercial organizations or individuals that may not be used without obtaining prior approval from the holder of the copyright. </license-p></license></permissions><related-article id="d35e63" related-article-type="commentary-article" xlink:href="15929894" ext-link-type="pubmed" vol="113" page="716"/></article-meta></front><body><p>The findings of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2-ehp0113-a0657c">Richard et al. (2005)</xref> are an important addition to our understanding that the health and environmental effects of formulated pesticide products are not fully reflected in tests conducted on the active ingredient(s) alone. It has been long known that the adjuvants (commonly and misleadingly called &#x0201c;inert&#x0201d; ingredients) may be toxic and may enhance or supplement the toxic effects of the active pesticidal ingredient.</p><p>In the case of glyphosate-containing products, this phenomenon was well demonstrated in the data submitted to the (EPA) by the registrant (Monsanto), and summarized by the U.S. EPA in the Reregistration Eligibility Document (RED) for glyphosate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3-ehp0113-a0657c">U.S. EPA 1993</xref>). For example, based on the registrant&#x02019;s own tests of acute toxicity to freshwater fish, the U.S. EPA classified technical grade glyphosate as &#x0201c;slightly toxic&#x0201d; to &#x0201c;practically non-toxic&#x0201d; and formulated products ranged from &#x0201c;moderately toxic&#x0201d; to &#x0201c;practically non-toxic.&#x0201d; Tested alone, the surfactant adjuvant (identified as &#x0201c;inert&#x0201d;) was &#x0201c;highly toxic&#x0201d; to &#x0201c;slightly toxic.&#x0201d; Similar differences were reported in tests of acute toxicity to freshwater invertebrates.</p><p>Based in part on the data in the glyphosate RED (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3-ehp0113-a0657c">U.S. EPA 1993</xref>), the New York State Attorney General&#x02019;s office successfully pursued an action against Monsanto in 1996 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1-ehp0113-a0657c">Attorney General of the State of New York 1996</xref>). At that time, Monsanto was making advertising claims about the toxicity of the Roundup products based on data from tests on the active ingredient alone. Such claims are scientifically unfounded and inherently deceptive. The Attorney General&#x02019;s action was facilitated by the availability of at least some limited information about the inert ingredients and their toxicity. That same sort of information enabled <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2-ehp0113-a0657c">Richard et al. (2005)</xref> to conduct their study.</p><p>Unfortunately, that is not always the case, and for many pesticide products, little or no information about the identity of inert ingredients is publicly available. Registrants are generally required to conduct acute toxicity tests on formulated products, but they traditionally conduct chronic toxicity tests on the active ingredient alone. Even when formulated products are tested, the identity of inert ingredients is rarely revealed in the open literature, publicly available regulatory documents, or product labels. Therefore, independent research is stymied, and the public is ill-informed in the marketplace.</p></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="b1-ehp0113-a0657c"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Attorney General of the State of New York</collab> 1996. In the Matter of Monsanto Company, Respondent. Assurance of Discontinuance Pursuant to Executive Law &#x000a7; 63(15). New York:Attorney General of the State of New York, Consumer Frauds and Protection Bureau, Environmental Protection Bureau.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b2-ehp0113-a0657c"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Richard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Moslemi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sipahutar</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Benachour</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Seralini</surname><given-names>G-E</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Differential effects of glyphosate and Roundup on human placental cells</article-title><source>Environ Health Perspect</source><volume>113</volume><fpage>716</fpage><lpage>720</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15929894</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b3-ehp0113-a0657c"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>U.S. EPA</collab> 1993. Reregistration Eligibility Decision (RED). Glyphosate. EPA-738-R-93-014. Washington, DC:U.S. Environmental Protection Agency. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cfpub.epa.gov/oppref/rereg/status.cfm?show=rereg">http://cfpub.epa.gov/oppref/rereg/status.cfm?show=rereg</ext-link> [accessed 1 September 2005].</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
