<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="news"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Environ Health Perspect</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Environ. Health Perspect</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Environmental Health Perspectives</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0091-6765</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1552-9924</issn><publisher><publisher-name>National Institue of Environmental Health Sciences</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15945148</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1257619</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ehp0113-a00376</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Environews</subject><subj-group><subject>NIEHS News</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Beyond the Bench: Oasis of Fun at Mount Desert Island</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tillett</surname><given-names>Tanya</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>6</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><volume>113</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>A376</fpage><lpage>A377</lpage><permissions><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/" license-type="public-domain"><license-p>Publication of EHP lies in the public domain and is therefore without copyright. All text from EHP may be reprinted freely. Use of materials published in EHP should be acknowledged (for example, ?Reproduced with permission from Environmental Health Perspectives?); pertinent reference information should be provided for the article from which the material was reproduced. Articles from EHP, especially the News section, may contain photographs or illustrations copyrighted by other commercial organizations or individuals that may not be used without obtaining prior approval from the holder of the copyright. </license-p></license></permissions></article-meta></front><body><p>Kids, summer, and water are three things that just naturally go together. The Community Outreach and Education Program (COEP) of the Center for Membrane Toxicity Studies, housed at Mount Desert Island Biological Laboratory in Bar Harbor, Maine, is using its open-air Myers Marine Aquarium Visitors Center to maximize this combination and get kids excited about learning during the summer months. The Center for Membrane Toxicity Studies, one of the NIEHS Marine and Freshwater Biomedical Sciences Centers, educates children about the environment and their own role in keeping it healthy.</p><p>For about five years, the COEP has provided environmental health enrichment to the surrounding community through the Myers Marine Aquarium Visitors Center. Aquarium staff provide weekly programs in the summer for local and tourist visitors to learn about the center&#x02019;s research. In a typical tour, visitors learn about water pollutants and how they affect our health and environment, and are also given information on water quality management.</p><p>Because school-aged children are the target audience, the message delivery is kept simple and fun. The aquarium has several tanks that allow for viewing and touching of the lab&#x02019;s research species and other sea life from the Gulf of Maine. Cartoon-emblazoned posters illustrate center findings on how pollutants are processed in the body and describe in nonspecialist language our own responsibility in safeguarding the environment we live in. As part of the tour, center staff describe their research projects and allow visitors to view specimens through microscopes.</p><p>&#x0201c;When we talk about environmental stewardship, I am always amazed by the reaction of the children,&#x0201d; says Jeri Bowers, the COEP associate director. &#x0201c;They love to get involved and to feel like they are playing an important role in maintaining a healthy environment; they take it very seriously. Our hope is that we can capture that enthusiasm and interest while they&#x02019;re young&#x02014;and influence their behavior well into adulthood.&#x0201d;</p><p>The aquarium attracts large numbers of student groups. One particularly memorable visit was a May 2004 tour by a group of 40 children with Almstr&#x000f6;m syndrome, a rare hereditary disorder that can affect multiple organ systems and cause blindness, hearing impairment, type 2 diabetes mellitus, heart failure, and liver disease. The visit was arranged by researchers at the nearby Jackson Laboratory, who discovered the gene for Almstr&#x000f6;m syndrome and provide their own outreach to children affected by the illness. Bowers says the tactile component of the aquarium experience was especially important and beneficial for these children, most of whom can&#x02019;t see or hear.</p><p>Along with the strong community outreach it offers through the aquarium and labs, Mount Desert Island also has exciting environmental health research in progress that staff hope will someday become part of the children&#x02019;s experience. Earlier this year, the lab set up a website (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ctd.mdibl.org/">http://ctd.mdibl.org/</ext-link>) for the Comparative Toxicogenomics Database, a data system being created to provide centralized data on diverse organisms to scientists worldwide. The lab has also received NIH approval to sequence the genome of the skate, data that will eventually be entered into the Comparative Toxico-genomics Database. One of the future goals of the researchers is to incorporate the electronic data into the visitors program so that children can access the database on computers set up as part of the aquarium tour.</p></body><floats-group><fig id="f1-ehp0113-a00376" position="float"><caption><title><bold>Diving in.</bold> Children learn about the marine environment and their role in keeping it healthy at the Myers Marine Aquarium Visitors Center.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="ehp0113-a00376f1"/></fig></floats-group></article>
