<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="letter"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Environ Health Perspect</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Environ. Health Perspect</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Environmental Health Perspectives</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0091-6765</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1552-9924</issn><publisher><publisher-name>National Institute of Environmental Health Sciences</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">16140604</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1280431</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ehp0113-a0581c</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Perspectives</subject><subj-group><subject>Correspondence</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Blood Lead and IQ in Older Children</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Carpenter</surname><given-names>David O.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ehp0113-a0581c"/></contrib><aff id="af1-ehp0113-a0581c">Institute for Health and the Environment University at Albany, Rensselaer, New York, E-mail:
<email>carpent@uamail.albany.edu</email></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn><p>The author declares he has no competing financial interests.</p></fn><fn><p>Editor&#x02019;s note: In accordance with journal policy, Chen et al. were asked whether they wanted to respond to this letter, but they chose not to do so.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>9</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><volume>113</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage seq="c">A581</fpage><lpage>A582</lpage><permissions><copyright-year>2005</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/" license-type="public-domain"><license-p>Publication of EHP lies in the public domain and is therefore without copyright. All text from EHP may be reprinted freely. Use of materials published in EHP should be acknowledged (for example, ?Reproduced with permission from Environmental Health Perspectives?); pertinent reference information should be provided for the article from which the material was reproduced. Articles from EHP, especially the News section, may contain photographs or illustrations copyrighted by other commercial organizations or individuals that may not be used without obtaining prior approval from the holder of the copyright. </license-p></license></permissions><related-article id="d35e66" related-article-type="commentary-article" xlink:href="15866769" ext-link-type="pubmed" vol="113" page="597"/></article-meta></front><body><p>In their article about blood lead and IQ in older children, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2-ehp0113-a0581c">Chen et al. (2005)</xref> made the very important observation that IQ (intelligence quotient) in older children correlates better with their current blood lead level than with levels determined at 2 years of age. This observation has enormous public health implications in terms of defining who is at risk of cognitive decrement upon exposure to lead, and challenges the widely held assumption that the effects of lead on neurobehavioral function are exclusively developmental. My colleagues and I (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1-ehp0113-a0581c">Carpenter et al. 2002</xref>) previously studied the effects of gestational and lactational exposure of rats to lead with measurement of long-term potentiation in hippocampal brain slices. Long-term potentiation is an electrophysiological measure of synaptic plasticity that is widely viewed as being at least one component of learning and memory, and it is reduced upon <italic>in vivo</italic> lead exposure. To our surprise we also found that acute perfusion of low concentrations of lead onto brain slices from control animals resulted in reduction of long-term potentiation, suggesting that the effect is more pharmacologic than developmental. The results of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2-ehp0113-a0581c">Chen et al. (2005)</xref> in humans and our studies in rats suggest that lead causes both developmental and pharmacologic impairment of cognitive function. If this is true, then steps should be taken to prevent exposure to lead and to reduce lead levels in individuals of any age, not just young children.</p></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="b1-ehp0113-a0581c"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Carpenter</surname><given-names>DO</given-names></name><name><surname>Hussain</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Lombardo</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Electrophysiologic and behavioral effects of perinatal and acute exposure of rats to lead and polychlorinated biphenyls</article-title><source>Environ Health Perspect</source><volume>110</volume><issue>suppl 3</issue><fpage>377</fpage><lpage>386</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12060832</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b2-ehp0113-a0581c"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dietrich</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name><name><surname>Ware</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Radcliffe</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogan</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>IQ and blood lead from 2 to 7 years of age: are the effects in older children the residual of high blood lead concentrations in 2-year-olds?</article-title><source>Environ Health Perspect</source><volume>113</volume><fpage>597</fpage><lpage>601</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15866769</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
