<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Environ Health Perspect</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Environ. Health Perspect</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Environmental Health Perspectives</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0091-6765</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1552-9924</issn><publisher><publisher-name>National Institute of Environmental Health Science</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15579411</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1253657</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1289/ehp.7249</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ehp0112-001671</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject><subj-group><subject>Articles</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Effects of Loud Noise Exposure on DNA Integrity in Rat Adrenal Gland</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Frenzilli</surname><given-names>Giada</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lenzi</surname><given-names>Paola</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Scarcelli</surname><given-names>Vittoria</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fornai</surname><given-names>Francesco</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pellegrini</surname><given-names>Antonio</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Soldani</surname><given-names>Paola</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Paparelli</surname><given-names>Antonio</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nigro</surname><given-names>Marco</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Dipartimento di Morfologia Umana e Biologia Applicata, University of Pisa, Pisa, Italy</aff><author-notes><corresp id="fn1-ehp0112-001671">Address correspondence to G. Frenzilli, Dipartimento di Morfologia Umana e Biologia Applicata, Sez. Biologia e Genetica University of Pisa, Via Volta, 4-56126 Pisa, Italy. Telephone: 39-050-2219111. Fax: 39-050-2219101. E-mail:
<email xlink:type="simple">giada@biomed.unipi.it</email></corresp><fn><p>We gratefully acknowledge C. Ghezzani for his excellent technical assistance in the image analysis.</p></fn><fn><p>This work was supported by the Italian Ministry of Research and by the University of Pisa.</p></fn><fn><p>The authors declare they have no competing financial interests.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>12</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>9</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><volume>112</volume><issue>17</issue><fpage>1671</fpage><lpage>1672</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>12</day><month>5</month><year>2004</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>9</month><year>2004</year></date></history><permissions><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/" license-type="public-domain"><license-p>Publication of EHP lies in the public domain and is therefore without copyright. All text from EHP may be reprinted freely. Use of materials published in EHP should be acknowledged (for example, ?Reproduced with permission from Environmental Health Perspectives?); pertinent reference information should be provided for the article from which the material was reproduced. Articles from EHP, especially the News section, may contain photographs or illustrations copyrighted by other commercial organizations or individuals that may not be used without obtaining prior approval from the holder of the copyright. </license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Loud noise is generally considered an environmental stressor causing negative effects on acoustic, cardiovascular, nervous, and endocrine systems. In this study, we investigated the effects of noise exposure on DNA integrity in rat adrenal gland evaluated by the comet assay. The exposure to loud noise (100 dBA) for 12 hr caused a significant increase of DNA damage in the adrenal gland. Genetic alterations did not decrease 24 hr after the cessation of the stimulus. We hypothesize that an imbalance of redox cell status is responsible for the induction and persistence of noise-induced cellular damage.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>adrenal gland</kwd><kwd>comet assay</kwd><kwd>DNA damage</kwd><kwd>loud noise</kwd><kwd>rat</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><p>During daily life, people are exposed to potentially hazardous noise levels related to work environment, urban traffic, household appliances, discos, and the like (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11-ehp0112-001671">Kawecka-Jaszcz 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13-ehp0112-001671">Lang et al. 1992</xref>). The World Health Organization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5-ehp0112-001671">Berglund et al. 1999</xref>) estimated that approximately 20% of the European population is exposed to noise generated by urban traffic &#x0003e; 65 dBA, a level regarded as a maximum safety threshold, whereas 40% of Europeans are exposed to noise levels between 55 and 65 dBA, which might be responsible for several disorders of both auditory and extra-auditory organs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5-ehp0112-001671">Berglund et al. 1999</xref>).</p><p>Extraauditory effects of noise have been related to psychophysiologic stress and the involvement of the pituitary&#x02013;adrenocortical axis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3-ehp0112-001671">Axelrod and Reisine 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12-ehp0112-001671">Ising and Braun 2000</xref>). Most studies on the effects of noise exposure on the hypothalamus&#x02013;pituitary&#x02013;adrenocortical axis have been performed by measuring behavioral, endocrine, and biochemical variables (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1-ehp0112-001671">Alario et al. 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2-ehp0112-001671">Armario et al. 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6-ehp0112-001671">Borrell et al. 1980</xref>), whereas few studies have investigated the cellular effects induced by exposure to noise stress. Among these, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19-ehp0112-001671">Pellegrini et al. (1997)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24-ehp0112-001671">Soldani et al. (1999)</xref> demonstrated the occurrence of ultrastructural modifications in the adrenal gland of noise exposed rats. Moreover, recent findings showed that ultra-structural alterations in the rat myocardium detected after loud noise exposure were also accompanied by DNA damage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15-ehp0112-001671">Lenzi et al. 2003</xref>).</p><p>The purpose of the present study was to investigate whether levels of loud noise comparable with those present in modern daily life (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4-ehp0112-001671">Baker 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5-ehp0112-001671">Berglund et al. 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7-ehp0112-001671">Br&#x000fc;el 1970</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1-ehp0112-001671">Figure 1</xref>) were able to produce DNA damage in rat adrenal gland for the same doses and time intervals previously detected as effective for inducing cellular alterations in the heart (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15-ehp0112-001671">Lenzi et al. 2003</xref>).</p><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Animals.</title><p>Male Wistar rats weighing 200&#x02013;250 g (Harlan Labs, San Pietro al Natisone, Italy) were used for the experiments. Animals were housed in the animal facility, fed <italic>ad libitum</italic>, and kept under closely controlled environmental conditions (12 hr light:dark cycle, lights on between 0700 and 1900 hr; room temperature, 21&#x000b0;C). Animals were treated in accordance with the <italic>Guidelines for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16-ehp0112-001671">National Institutes of Health 1996</xref>). All possible efforts were made to reduce animal suffering and minimize the number of animals used.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Experimental procedures.</title><p>Noise level was set at 100 dBA by the use of two loud speakers (15 W) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15-ehp0112-001671">Lenzi et al. 2003</xref>) and lasted for 12 hr. Control rats were placed in the same kind of cage without being exposed to noise. Animals were randomly assigned to experimental and control groups, each consisting of four specimens. Experimental rats were sacrificed either soon after cessation of the noise stimulus or 24 hr later by decapitation, to avoid the interference of deep anesthesia with DNA integrity, and the adrenal gland was immediately dissected.</p></sec><sec><title>Light microscopy.</title><p>To check for potential occurrence of cell death, we processed tissue samples using routine histologic procedures. Briefly, 8-&#x003bc;m-thick sections were cut with a microtome and stained with hematoxylin-eosin and toluidine blue. No cell death was observed.</p></sec><sec><title>Evaluation of DNA damage.</title><p>We evaluated DNA integrity in rat adrenal gland by the use of alkaline single-cell gel electrophoresis or comet assay, according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23-ehp0112-001671">Singh et al. (1988)</xref>, with minor modifications (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15-ehp0112-001671">Lenzi et al. 2003</xref>). Electrophoretic DNA migration is proportional to the level of DNA damage producing cometlike images under a fluorescence microscope (magnification 200&#x000d7;) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2-ehp0112-001671">Figure 2</xref>). We used an image analyzer (Komet, version 4; Kinetic Imaging Ltd., Bromborough, UK) to quantify the percentage of DNA migrated in the tail of at least 100 cells per animal. We used multifactor analysis of variance to assess the significance of factor effects such as animals, slides, and doses. For statistical analysis we used the software Statgraphics Plus for Windows (version 2.1; Microsoft Corp., Redmond, WA, USA).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p>We evaluated the effect of loud noise on the presence of DNA damage in single cells dissociated from adrenal gland as the percentage of migrated DNA after electrophoresis in exposed and control rats. We observed a significant increase of DNA migration (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001), compared with controls, in the adrenal gland soon after the cessation of acoustic stress, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3-ehp0112-001671">Figure 3</xref>. This pattern of DNA migration persisted 24 hr after noise exposure, suggesting the absence of recovery (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3-ehp0112-001671">Figure 3</xref>). Light microscopy did not reveal the occurrence of cell death. This finding excludes the possibility that the number of strand breaks observed in the present study is due to nonspecific loss of DNA integrity related to cell death processes, providing supporting evidence of a genotoxic effect induced by loud noise.</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>This study demonstrates that loud noise exposure produces a significant loss of DNA integrity in the rat adrenal gland. This effect persisted almost unchanged 24 hr after the cessation of the stimulus. We can exclude the possibility that the elevation of DNA strand breaks was due to cell-death&#x02013;associated fragmentation; indeed, light microscopy revealed a negligible occurrence of necrotic events. The same level and duration of the acoustic stress (100 dBA for 12 hr) were previously demonstrated to be effective in inducing ultrastructural alterations in rat adrenal cells, mainly involving the mitochondria and endoplasmic reticulum (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19-ehp0112-001671">Pellegrini et al. 1997</xref>). The adrenal gland is known to react to stressful stimuli, including noise. According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12-ehp0112-001671">Ising and Braun (2000)</xref>, habitual noise produces sympathetic activation and chronic increases in noradrenaline; nonhabitual noise produces an acute increase of noradrenaline and adrenaline; and extremely intense noise produces a defeat reaction with an increase of cortisol and adrenal stress hormone. The intense functional stimulation has been reported as potential cause for morphologic changes in subcellular structure, involving those organelles where steroids are synthesized, such as smooth endoplasmic reticulum and mitochondria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22-ehp0112-001671">Simpson and Waterman 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24-ehp0112-001671">Soldani et al. 1999</xref>).</p><p>Concerning the persistence of genetic damage, it is noteworthy that DNA single-strand breaks are usually repaired within 15 min and that DNA double-strand breaks are repaired within 2 hr (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20-ehp0112-001671">Plappert et al. 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26-ehp0112-001671">Vijayalaxmi et al. 1993</xref>). Thus, such a maintenance of genotoxic effects 24 hr after noise exposure might be the consequence of a long-lasting clastogenic agent.</p><p>Our results on DNA damage might be interpreted as the output of two main events, namely, the clastogenic effect of oxyradicals and/or the DNA repair of oxidized bases, which implies the expression of alkali-labile sites, detected by the alkaline comet assay.</p><p>The negative effects of noise on cell structure and function were supposed to be, at least in part, mediated by the increase of reactive oxygen species (ROS) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15-ehp0112-001671">Lenzi et al. 2003</xref>). ROS levels in the cochlea were found the be significantly higher 1 hr after exposure to 110 dB noise (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17-ehp0112-001671">Ohlemiller et al. 1999a</xref>), persisting after the cessation of the exposure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18-ehp0112-001671">Ohlemiller et al. 1999b</xref>). In this respect, it is worthy to note that DNA is a main target of ROS toxicity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9-ehp0112-001671">Cross et al. 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14-ehp0112-001671">Lemasters et al. 1992</xref>). Oxidative damage of DNA is known to induce single-strand breaks and inter-/intrastrand cross-links (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8-ehp0112-001671">Caraceni et al. 1997</xref>). The involvement of ROS might play a causal role in the induction and persistence of genetic damage related to loud noise exposure also in extra-auditory organs. Indeed, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25-ehp0112-001671">Van Campen et al. (2002)</xref> reported an elevation of 8-hydroxy-2&#x02032;-deoxyguanosine in brain and liver (besides the higher cochlear involvement) of rats exposed to loud noise (120 dB). According to these findings, the association between noise exposure, oxidative processes, and persisting DNA damage deserves further attention due to the long-lasting consequences in term of mutagenic and carcinogenic risk (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10-ehp0112-001671">Emerit 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21-ehp0112-001671">Preston-Martin et al. 1989</xref>).</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="b1-ehp0112-001671"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Alario</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Beato</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Trancho</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year>1987</year><article-title>Body weight gain, food intake and adrenal development in chronic noise stressed rats</article-title><source>Physiol Behav</source><volume>40</volume><fpage>29</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3039551</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b2-ehp0112-001671"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Armario</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Castellanos</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Balash</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>1984</year><article-title>Adaptation of anterior pituitary hormones to chronic noise stress in rats</article-title><source>Behav Neural Biol</source><volume>41</volume><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>76</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6431962</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b3-ehp0112-001671"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Axelrod</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Reisine</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name></person-group><year>1984</year><article-title>Stress hormones: their interaction and regulation</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>224</volume><fpage>452</fpage><lpage>459</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6143403</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b4-ehp0112-001671"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group> 1993. Noise: The Invisible Hazard. Columbia, MO:University of Missouri Extension.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b5-ehp0112-001671"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group><name><surname>Berglund</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindvall</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwela</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group> eds. 1999. Guidelines for Community Noise. London:World Health Organization.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b6-ehp0112-001671"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Borrell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Torrellas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Guaza</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Borrell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>1980</year><article-title>Sound stimulation and its effects on pituitary-adrenocortical function and brain catecholamines in rats</article-title><source>Neuroendocrinology</source><volume>31</volume><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>59</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7393405</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b7-ehp0112-001671"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Br&#x000fc;el</surname><given-names>PV</given-names></name></person-group><year>1970</year><article-title>Do we measure damaging noise correctly?</article-title><source>B &#x00026; K Technical Review</source><volume>1</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>32</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b8-ehp0112-001671"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Caraceni</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>De Maria</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryu</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Colantoni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Maidt</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>Proteins but not nucleic acids are molecular targets for the free radical attack during reoxygenation of rat hepatocytes</article-title><source>Free Radic Biol Med</source><volume>23</volume><fpage>339</fpage><lpage>344</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9199897</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b9-ehp0112-001671"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Cross</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Halliwell</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Borish</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name><name><surname>Pryor</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ames</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Saul</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1987</year><article-title>Oxygen radicals and human disease</article-title><source>Ann Intern Med</source><volume>107</volume><fpage>526</fpage><lpage>545</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3307585</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b10-ehp0112-001671"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Emerit</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><year>1994</year><article-title>Reactive oxygen species, chromosome mutation, and cancer</article-title><source>Free Radical Biol Med</source><volume>16</volume><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>109</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8300000</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b11-ehp0112-001671"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Kawecka-Jaszcz</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year>1991</year><article-title>Effect of professional work and environmental factors on arterial blood pressure</article-title><source>Med Pract</source><volume>42</volume><fpage>291</fpage><lpage>296</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b12-ehp0112-001671"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Ising</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Braun</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Acute and chronic endocrine effects of noise: review of the research conducted at the Institute for Water, Soil and Air Hygiene</article-title><source>Noise Health</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>7</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12689468</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b13-ehp0112-001671"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fouriaud</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacquinet-Salord</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group><year>1992</year><article-title>Length of occupational noise exposure and blood pressure</article-title><source>Int Arch Occup Environ Health</source><volume>63</volume><fpage>369</fpage><lpage>372</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1544682</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b14-ehp0112-001671"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group><name><surname>Lemasters</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Caldwell-Kenkel</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Nieminen</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Herman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Thurman</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group> 1992. Hypoxic, ischemic and reperfusion injury in the liver. In: Pathophysiology of Reperfusion Injury (Das DK, ed). Boca Raton, FL:CRC, 101&#x02013;135.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b15-ehp0112-001671"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Lenzi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Frenzilli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Gesi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferrucci</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lazzeri</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Fornai</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>DNA damage associated with ultrastructural alterations in rat myocardium after loud noise exposure</article-title><source>Environ Health Perspect</source><volume>111</volume><fpage>467</fpage><lpage>471</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12676600</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b16-ehp0112-001671"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>National Institutes of Health</collab> 1996. Guidelines for Care and Use of Laboratory Animals. Washington, DC:National Academies Press.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b17-ehp0112-001671"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Ohlemiller</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>McFadden</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Flood</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Reaume</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1999a</year><article-title>Targeted deletion of the cytosolic Cu/Zn-superoxide dismutase gene (Sod1) increases susceptibility to noise-induced hearing loss</article-title><source>Audiol Neurootol</source><volume>5</volume><fpage>237</fpage><lpage>246</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10436316</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b18-ehp0112-001671"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Ohlemiller</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Dugan</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name></person-group><year>1999b</year><article-title>Early elevation of cochlear reactive oxygen species following noise exposure</article-title><source>Audiol Neurootol</source><volume>4</volume><fpage>229</fpage><lpage>236</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10436315</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b19-ehp0112-001671"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Pellegrini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Soldani</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gesi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenzi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Natale</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Paparelli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>Effect of varying noise stress duration on rat adrenal gland: an ultrastructural study</article-title><source>Tissue Cell</source><volume>29</volume><fpage>597</fpage><lpage>602</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9364808</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b20-ehp0112-001671"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Plappert</surname><given-names>UG</given-names></name><name><surname>Stocker</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Fender</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Fliedner</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name></person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>Changes in the repair of blood cells as a biomarker for chronic low-dose exposure to ionizing radiation</article-title><source>Environ Mol Mutagen</source><volume>30</volume><fpage>153</fpage><lpage>160</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9329640</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b21-ehp0112-001671"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Preston-Martin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name><name><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name></person-group><year>1989</year><article-title>Noise trauma in the aetiology of acoustic neuromas in men in Los Angeles County. 1978&#x02013;1985</article-title><source>Br J Cancer</source><volume>59</volume><fpage>783</fpage><lpage>786</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2736213</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b22-ehp0112-001671"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Waterman</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><year>1988</year><article-title>Regulation of the synthesis of steroidogenic enzymes in adrenal cortical cells by ACTH</article-title><source>Annu Rev Physiol</source><volume>50</volume><fpage>427</fpage><lpage>440</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2837136</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b23-ehp0112-001671"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><name><surname>McCoy</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Tice</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name></person-group><year>1988</year><article-title>A simple technique for quantitation of low levels of DNA damage in individual cells</article-title><source>Exp Cell Res</source><volume>175</volume><fpage>184</fpage><lpage>191</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3345800</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b24-ehp0112-001671"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Soldani</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gesi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenzi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Natale</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Fornai</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Pellegrini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>Long-term exposure to noise modifies rat adrenal cortex ultrastructure and corticosterone plasma levels</article-title><source>J Submicrosc Cytol Pathos</source><volume>31</volume><fpage>441</fpage><lpage>448</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b25-ehp0112-001671"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Van Campen</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Franks</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathias</surname><given-names>PI</given-names></name><name><surname>Toraason</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Oxidative DNA damage is associated with intense noise exposure in the rat</article-title><source>Hear Res</source><volume>164</volume><fpage>29</fpage><lpage>38</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11950522</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b26-ehp0112-001671"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Vijayalaxmi</surname></name><name><surname>Strauss</surname><given-names>GHS</given-names></name><name><surname>Tice</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name></person-group><year>1993</year><article-title>An analysis of &#x003b3; -ray-induced DNA damage in human blood leukocytes, lymphocytes and granulocytes</article-title><source>Mutat Res</source><volume>292</volume><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>128</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7692248</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="f1-ehp0112-001671" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Sources and levels of noise exposure. Data represent a synthesis of data from different sources (see &#x0201c;Materials and Methods&#x0201d;).
<break/>*WHO safeness threshold limit (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5-ehp0112-001671">Berglund et al. 1999</xref>).</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="ehp0112-001671f1"/></fig><fig id="f2-ehp0112-001671" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Images of ethidium-bromide&#x02013;stained nuclei exhibiting different degrees of DNA damage after electrophoresis. The amount of DNA damage increases from <italic>A</italic> to <italic>E</italic>, as shown by the percentage of &#x0201c;tail&#x0201d; DNA: (<italic>A</italic>) 0.5%, (<italic>B</italic>) 10%, (<italic>C</italic>) 45%, (<italic>D</italic>) 93%, and (<italic>E</italic>) 99%. Bar = 20 &#x003bc;m.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="ehp0112-001671f2"/></fig><fig id="f3-ehp0112-001671" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>DNA damage induced by loud noise exposure in rat adrenal gland cells soon after 12 hr of noise exposure (<italic>t</italic> = 0) and 24 hr after the cessation of the stimulus (<italic>t</italic> = 24). Data are expressed as mean &#x000b1; SD of DNA migrations.
<break/>*<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01. **<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="ehp0112-001671f3"/></fig></floats-group></article>
