<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="letter"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Environ Health Perspect</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Environ. Health Perspect</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Environmental Health Perspectives</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0091-6765</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1552-9924</issn><publisher><publisher-name>National Institue of Environmental Health Sciences</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15345352</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1247542</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ehp0112-a0724b</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Perspectives</subject><subj-group><subject>Correspondence</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Activities and Organophosphate Exposures: Need for the Numbers</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Krieger</surname><given-names>Robert I.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Xiaofei</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Personal Chemical Exposure Program, Department of Entomology, University of California, Riverside, Riverside, California, E-mail:
<email>bob.krieger@ucr.edu</email></aff><author-notes><fn><p>The authors declare they have no competing financial interests.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>9</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><volume>112</volume><issue>13</issue><fpage seq="b">A724</fpage><lpage>A725</lpage><permissions><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/" license-type="public-domain"><license-p>Publication of EHP lies in the public domain and is therefore without copyright. All text from EHP may be reprinted freely. Use of materials published in EHP should be acknowledged (for example, ?Reproduced with permission from Environmental Health Perspectives?); pertinent reference information should be provided for the article from which the material was reproduced. Articles from EHP, especially the News section, may contain photographs or illustrations copyrighted by other commercial organizations or individuals that may not be used without obtaining prior approval from the holder of the copyright. </license-p></license></permissions><related-article id="d35e66" related-article-type="commentary-article" xlink:href="14754567" ext-link-type="pubmed" vol="112" page="142"/></article-meta></front><body><p>The article &#x0201c;Agricultural Task and Exposure to Organophosphate Pesticides among Farmworkers&#x0201d; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1-ehp0112-a0724b">Coronado et al. 2004</xref>) seems to be founded on an erroneous premise and presents virtually no data to estimate levels of worker or child exposure. Useful data generated in conjunction with this research probably exists, but they were not published.</p><p>In the abstract, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1-ehp0112-a0724b">Coronado et al. (2004)</xref> state that</p><disp-quote><p>Little is known about pesticide exposure among farmworkers, and even less is known about the exposure associated with performing specific tasks.</p></disp-quote><p>The investigators open weakly by ignoring the substantial exposure (amount per person) data available related to work tasks of handlers [Pesticide Handlers Exposure Database; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4-ehp0112-a0724b">U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) 1995</xref>] and harvesters (U.S. EPA Transfer Coefficients) in the open literature and regulatory files of registrants and the U.S. EPA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5-ehp0112-a0724b">U.S. EPA 1998</xref>).</p><p>We commend <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1-ehp0112-a0724b">Coronado et al. (2004)</xref> for their use of a very large random sample of 213 farmworkers from 24 communities. The sensitive metabolite analyses of urine were reported as &#x0201c;percent detectable dimethyl metabolites&#x0201d; without reference to the total amounts measured in the various urine specimens. This is unacceptable for exposure assessment if their intent was, as they stated, to &#x0201c;examine the association between specific agricultural tasks and levels of exposure among adult workers and children living in the same household.&#x0201d; Failure to report urine metabolite levels deprives readers of the opportunity to transform percentages to dose, a measure of exposure. Dose (micrograms per person) defines the relationship of agricultural task to organophosphate (OP) exposure. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1-ehp0112-a0724b">Coronado et al. (2004)</xref> must have calculated the metabolite levels, but their failure to present those data seriously devalues the contribution and the cooperation of their subjects.</p><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1-ehp0112-a0724b">Coronado et al. (2004)</xref> reported the percentage of detectable dimethyl urinary metabolites in children (<italic>n</italic> = 211; 2&#x02013;6 years of age). These data do not permit estimation of dose, and they prohibit full evaluation of the relationship of exposure from parents&#x02019; work tasks or other sources to the dimethyl metabolites from residential exposures, particularly diet (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2-ehp0112-a0724b">Krieger et al. 2003</xref>). It seems that the urine OP metabolite levels of children are more likely linked to dietary exposure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6-ehp0112-a0724b">Zhang and Krieger 2004</xref>) than to environmental sources (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3-ehp0112-a0724b">Lowenhurz et al. 1997</xref>) proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1-ehp0112-a0724b">Coronado et al. (2004)</xref>. Meaningful discussion is again prohibited by the lack of metabolite urine levels presented.</p><p>The data presented by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1-ehp0112-a0724b">Coronado et al. (2004)</xref> are not adequate. We believe that the metabolite levels in urine should be published in <italic>EHP</italic> or otherwise made available to investigators.</p></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="b1-ehp0112-a0724b"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Coronado</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Strong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffith</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name><surname>Islas</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Agricultural task and exposure to organophosphate pesticides among farmworkers</article-title><source>Environ Health Perspect</source><volume>112</volume><fpage>142</fpage><lpage>147</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14754567</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b2-ehp0112-a0724b"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Krieger</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></name><name><surname>Dinoff</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Preformed biomarkers in produce inflate human organophosphate exposure assessements [Letter]</article-title><source>Environ Health Perspect</source><volume>111</volume><fpage>A688</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14527854</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b3-ehp0112-a0724b"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Lowenhurz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fenske</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Simcox</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bellamy</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>Biological monitoring of organophosphorus pesticide exposure among children of agricultural workers</article-title><source>Environ Health Perspect</source><volume>105</volume><fpage>1344</fpage><lpage>1353</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9405329</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b4-ehp0112-a0724b"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>U.S. EPA</collab> 1995. Pesticide Handlers Exposure Database. Washington, DC:U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, Office of Pesticide Programs, Occupational and Residential Exposure Branch.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b5-ehp0112-a0724b"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>U.S. EPA</collab> 1998. EPA Series 875&#x02014;Occupational and Residential Exposure Test Guidelines. Group B&#x02014;Postapplication Exposure Monitoring Test Guidelines. Washington, DC:U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, Office of Pesticide Programs.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b6-ehp0112-a0724b"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Krieger</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Dialkyl phosphates (DAPs) in produce confound biomonitoring in organophosphate risk assessment [Abstract]</article-title><source>Toxicologist</source><volume>78</volume><fpage>528</fpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
