<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cell Commun Signal</journal-id><journal-title>Cell communication and signaling : CCS</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1478-811X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15836785</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1097746</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1478-811X-3-7</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1478-811X-3-7</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Commentary</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Recognizing scientific excellence in the biology of cell adhesion</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wary</surname><given-names>Kishore K</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>kwary@ibt.tamhsc.edu</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Center for Extracellular Matrix Biology, Institute of Biosciences and Technology, Texas A &#x00026; M University System-Health Science Center, Texas Medical Center, 2121 W. Holcombe Blvd. Houston, TX-77030, USA</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2005</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>18</day><month>4</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><volume>3</volume><fpage>7</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biosignaling.com/content/3/1/7"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>8</day><month>3</month><year>2005</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>4</month><year>2005</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2005 Wary; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2005</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Wary; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>
               Wary
               K
               Kishore
               
               kwary@ibt.tamhsc.edu
            </dc:author><dc:title>
            Recognizing scientific excellence in the biology of cell adhesion
         </dc:title><dc:date>2005</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>Cell Communication and Signaling 3(1): 7-. (2005)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1478-811X(2005)3:1&#x0003c;7&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1478-811X</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><p>The prestigious 2005 Japan Prize for Cell Biology has been awarded to Dr. Masatoshi Takeichi, Director of RIKEN Developmental Biology, Kobe, Japan, and Dr. Erkki Ruoslahti, Distinguished Professor, The Burnham Institute, La Jolla, USA for their "Fundamental contribution in elucidating the molecular mechanisms of cell adhesion". The award is scheduled to be presented to the scientists in ceremonies in Tokyo on April 20, 2005 as part of a week-long celebration of "Japan Prize Week".</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>What is cell adhesion?</title><p>Well, why does our skin look so smooth on the surface? How do skin cells adhere to each other and the underlying connective tissue to resist wound and bruise? How do two 'unlike' or 'like' cells live side-by-side? How are muscles and tendons glued to the bones? How do endothelial and epithelial cells are separated from each other? What mechanisms divide astrocytes, neurons, and the endothelial cells that make up the neurovascular unit? The answer is "cell adhesion", which is because of the characteristic properties of proteins and molecules that act like 'glue' or 'sticky molecules'. If cells or tissues do not hold each other, like in blistering skin in which something as gentle as a human touch can cause the skin to blister and peel away, inviting fatal infection and wound that may never heal. Suffice to say, the chances of survival will be somewhat diminished.</p></sec><sec><title>What are cell adhesion molecules?</title><p>In the late 1970's two ideas were put forward. First, the chemoaffinity hypothesis proposed that cell-cell contacts are mediated by unique set of cell adhesion molecules presented by adjacent cells. Second, adhesion molecules are limited, but their affinity could switch from low to high and <italic>vice versa</italic>. Soon afterwards, several important cell adhesion molecules were discovered and described including the cadherins, neuronal cell adhesion molecules (NCAM), extracellular matrix (ECM) molecules, proteoglycans, the immunoglobulin cell adhesion molecules, junctional adhesion molecules (JAMs), connexins, and selectins. Those ideas are very much alive and many cell adhesion molecules discovered recently are being tested with stringent criteria with better technologies today.</p></sec><sec><title>How do these molecules promote cell adhesion?</title><p>There may not be a unifying answer to that question. In one of the landmark articles, Dr. Masatoshi Takeichi [Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>] described calcium-dependent and -independent mechanisms of cell adhesion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Cell-aggregation assays of disaggregated tissue and cells provided indication that the cadherins promote 'homophilic' interactions, a process that requires presence of Calcium metal ions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. Cadherins are transmembrane proteins containing an extracellular, a transmembrane, and a cytoplasmic segment. The extracellular domains of cadherins mediate Calcium-dependent intercellular adhesion by homophilic interactions. The binding properties and specificities of the adhesive interactions are located in the N-terminal segment of the molecules. A total of 17 classical cadherins have been described in the literature. Cadherin superfamily is made of 85 members. The classical cadherins are mainly involved in the cell adhesion. The roles of the other members of cadherin superfamily remain to be elucidated. Cell adhesions mediated by cadherins are cell type specific. In epithelial and endothelial cells, cadherins mediate formation of adherens junctions. It is now clear that the intracellular signaling components of cadherin determine the epithelial morphogenesis and tissue architectures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. The loss of cadherin expression by neoplastic cells is a hallmark of tumor progression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. Dr. Erkki Ruoslahti [Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref>] provided evidence that most ECM molecules such as fibronectin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>] promote both cell-cell and cell-matrix interaction by interacting with a family of cell adhesion receptor called the integrins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. In contrast to static ECM, some of the soluble ECM molecules can serve as a 'bridge' between two like or unlike cells [Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>]. Such interactions are both transient as well as static, for example, at the sites of injury and inflammation, and these interactions could be low or high affinity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. The development of specific monoclonal antibodies such as (Ligand-induced binding site, LIBS, and cation- and ligand-induced binding site, CLIBS) as well as fluorescence energy transfer experiments provided further clues to the nature of the molecular interactions of integrin with the ECM molecules [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. Moreover, molecular genetic analyses have provided evidence that multicellular organisms are dependent on adhesion of cells to each other and the ECM molecules, without which many cells will fail to stick [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. Accordingly, gene deletion studies in mouse embryos have provided evidence that both cadherin and fibronectin molecules are required for embryonic development. The studies of cultured cells have provided early evidence that both fibronectin and cadherins help organize the cytoskeleton. In short, the prize is all about elucidating the molecular mechanisms as to how cell adhesion works [Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>].</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>A </bold>Dr. Masatoshi Takeichi (left), and <bold>(B) </bold>Dr. Erkki Ruoslahti (right). Image (A) is provided by Dr. Takeichi, and (B) obtained from public domain.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1478-811X-3-7-1"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>Schematics of cell adhesion mediated by cadherin and by extracellular matrix (ECM) proteins. </bold>Cadherin molecule connects adjacent cells by homophilic interactions in a metal ion dependent manner. Integrin cell adhesion receptors can interact with both static as well as soluble ECM ligands. In addition, integrins can also bind cell-associated ligands (not shown).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1478-811X-3-7-2"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>(A) Cell-cell adhesion- </bold>Epithelial cells were stained with anti-E-cadherin monoclonal antibody and detected by fluorescent dye microcopy. Green fluorescent represents E-cadherin molecules connecting cells. Red color represents nucleus. <bold>(B) Cell-matrix adhesion</bold>- Adherent endothelial cell was stained with anti-fibronectin monoclonal antibody and detected by fluorescent microscopy. Images are not in scale, magnification, 200&#x000d7;</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1478-811X-3-7-3"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Cell-aggregation and cell adhesion assays</title><p>Cell biologists use proteolytic enzymes such trypsin and Ethylenediaminetetra-acetic acid (EDTA) to detach/disaggregate cells from the culture dishes and to prepare of primary cells from intact tissues. Trypsin is a proteolytic enzyme, while EDTA, a metal ion chelator. When used in right combination, they can disrupt both cell-cell and cell-matrix interactions, that is to say these two substances can disaggregate cells and tissues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Cell-cell and cell-matrix interactions appear to go hand-in-hand [Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>]. Upon attachment adherent cells sense presence of Calcium in the environment, calcium is required for both cell-cell and cell-matrix interactions. Dr. Takeichi described as to how cell-cell interactions between "like" cells and "unlike" cells can be induced by E-cadherin molecules [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. In normal adherent cells such as endothelial (vascular endothelial cadherin, called VE-Cadherin) and epithelial cells (epithelial cadherin, called E-cadherin) cadherins connect two or more cells in a "zipper" like fashion in presence of calcium [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. Importantly, calcium prevents the degradation of cadherin and promotes cell adhesion activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Cadherin may also be important for mediating "contact-inhibition", a property of normal adherent cells. In a nutshell, Dr. Takeichi observed and described calcium-dependent and -independent mechanisms of cell adhesion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>].</p><p>Short-term incubation of adherent cells with trypsin can digest most ECM molecules and addition of EDTA helps disrupt interactions of cell adhesion mediated by integrins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. Dr. Ruoslahti described purification and characterization of fibronectin from blood plasma, and went onto identify the Arg-Gly-Asp (RGD) tri-peptide cell adhesion motif, that remains as a conceptual breakthrough [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. Structurally, the fibronectin represents a prototypic ECM molecule that displays highly modular structure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. Fibronectin possesses repeating structural motifs, classified as fibronectin repeats FN-I, FN-II, and FN-III that are grouped together into functional domains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. Many cell types secrete fibronectin polypeptide ranging between 220&#x02013;250 kDa sizes. Functionally, fibronectin plays critical roles in cell adhesion-dependent cellular activities both in development and adult tissue homeostasis, proliferation, and migration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. Cell adhesion assays provided evidence that cell attachment mediated by specific subset of integrins onto fibronectin can be blocked by RGD tri-peptides. Subsequently, many laboratories around the world have also cloned, characterized and described ECM proteins that also may contain RGD or variant cell binding sites. Detergent solubilized plasma-membrane proteins passed through a column chromatography conjugated to RGD-peptides allowed purification of RGD-binding cell adhesion receptors, which is now known as integrins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. For detail, please see the RGD story by E. Ruoslahti [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. Secreted fibronectin can organize and assemble large protein complex by interacting with many other ECM molecules in the extracellular space such as the fibrinogen and collagens, glycosaminoglycans, proteoglycans, tenascin, fibulin and thrombospondin. Many normal cells have been described as "anchorage-dependent" cells that require attachment factor such as fibronectin, without which cells die of apoptosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. Apart from just being a structural support, Fibronectin can trap or sequester growth factors and cytokines, and induce signaling activities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. In contrast, neoplastic cells that accumulate mutant copies of genetic materials no longer require fibronectin to grow, divide or metastasize, and this phenomena is called "anchorage-independence". Fibronectin also interacts with bacterial adhesion molecules, a pathological process that helps bacteria to colonize and infect host tissues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>In addition to providing structural support, both cadherins and fibronectin molecules are also required for cell polarity, and informing the cells and tissues about their position in time and space, called positional cues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. A biological process that allow cells to sense their immediate physical and chemical environment correctly, for example, to help cells sense presence of glucose and insulin, cytokines and growth hormones, signaling molecules and metal ions. However, such regulatory mechanisms could be altered in many pathological states including tumor growth, angiogenesis and metastasis. Complete understanding of the mechanisms of regulation of cell-adhesion molecules and their signaling activities remains an active area of investigation in many disease settings including cardiovascular, cancer, neural networks, damage and repair mechanisms associated with traumatic injury, wound healing, host-pathogen interactions, nanotechnology, tissue engineering, and molecular therapeutics. The Japan Prize 2005 and cash award is slated to be given in presence of the Emperor of Japan in a week-long celebration beginning 20<sup>th </sup>April, 2005 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.japanprize.jp/English.htm"/>.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>K.K.W. wrote and edited the whole manuscript.</p></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The field of cell adhesion is somewhat matured. I apologize to my colleagues and authors whose works could not be cited here due to space constrains. KKW is a recipient of an award from American Heart Association (National Council) and a member of Mission Connect, TIRR, Houston, Texas, and a member of Cardiovascular Research Institute (CVRI) of the Texas A &#x00026; M University-System Health Science Center.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takeichi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional correlation between cell adhesive properties and some cell surface proteins</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>1977</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>464</fpage><lpage>474</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">264120</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.75.2.464</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takeichi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The cadherins: cell-cell adhesion molecules controlling animal morphogenesis</article-title><source>Development</source><year>1988</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>639</fpage><lpage>655</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3048970</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takeichi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cadherin cell adhesion receptors as a morphogenetic regulator</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1991</year><volume>251</volume><fpage>1451</fpage><lpage>1455</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2006419</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gumbiner</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epithelial morphogenesis</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1992</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>385</fpage><lpage>387</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1581959</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0092-8674(92)90440-N</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gumbiner</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cell adhesion: the molecular basis of tissue architecture and morphogenesis</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1996</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>345</fpage><lpage>357</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8608588</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(00)81279-9</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takeichi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cadherins in cancer: implications for invasion and metastasis</article-title><source>Curr Opin Cell Biol</source><year>1993</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>806</fpage><lpage>811</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8240824</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0955-0674(93)90029-P</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruoslahti</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fibronectin in cell adhesion and invasion</article-title><source>Cancer Metastasis Rev</source><year>1984</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>51</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6324988</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00047692</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hynes</surname><given-names>RO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Integrins: versatility, modulation, and signaling in cell adhesion</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1992</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1555235</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0092-8674(92)90115-S</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Springer</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Traffic signals for lymphocyte recirculation and leukocyte emigration: The multistep paradigm</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1994</year><volume>76</volume><fpage>301</fpage><lpage>314</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7507411</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0092-8674(94)90337-9</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hynes</surname><given-names>RO</given-names></name><name><surname>Bader</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Targeted mutations in integrins and their ligands: their implications for vascular biology</article-title><source>Thromb Haemost</source><year>1997</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>83</fpage><lpage>87</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9198133</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vasioukhin</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuchs</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Directed actin polymerization is the driving force for epithelial cell-cell adhesion</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2000</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>209</fpage><lpage>219</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10660044</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(00)81559-7</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruoslahti</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Pierschbacher</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New perspectives in cell adhesion: RGD and integrins</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1987</year><volume>238</volume><fpage>491</fpage><lpage>497</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2821619</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fibronectins: structure, functions and receptors</article-title><source>Curr Opin Cell Biol</source><year>1989</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>956</fpage><lpage>963</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2534045</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0955-0674(89)90065-3</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruoslahti</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The RGD story: a personal account</article-title><source>Matrix Biol</source><year>2003</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>459</fpage><lpage>465</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14667838</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0945-053X(03)00083-0</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruoslahti</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anchorage dependence, integrins, and apoptosis</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1994</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>477</fpage><lpage>478</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8187171</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0092-8674(94)90209-7</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giancotti</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruoslahti</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Integrin signaling</article-title><source>Science </source><year>1999</year><volume>285</volume><fpage>1028</fpage><lpage>1032</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10446041</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.285.5430.1028</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giancotti</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name><name><surname>Tarone</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Positional control of cell fate through joint integrin/receptor protein kinase signaling</article-title><source>Annu Rev Cell Dev Biol</source><year>2003</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>173</fpage><lpage>206</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14570568</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.cellbio.19.031103.133334</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patti</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>McGavin</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>H&#x000f6;&#x000f6;k</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MSCRAMM-mediated adherence of microorganisms to host tissues</article-title><source>Annu Rev Microbiol</source><year>1994</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>585</fpage><lpage>617</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7826020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.mi.48.100194.003101</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>



