<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Cell Biol</journal-id><journal-title>BMC Cell Biology</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2121</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15850493</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1090567</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1471-2121-6-21</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2121-6-21</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>S-Nitrosothiols modulate G protein-coupled receptor signaling in a reversible and highly receptor-specific manner</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kokkola</surname><given-names>Tarja</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>tarja.kokkola@uku.fi</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Savinainen</surname><given-names>Juha R</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>juha.savinainen@uku.fi</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>M&#x000f6;nkk&#x000f6;nen</surname><given-names>Kati S</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>kati.monkkonen@uku.fi</email></contrib><contrib id="A4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Retamal</surname><given-names>Montse Dur&#x000e1;n</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>monsdr@hotmail.com</email></contrib><contrib id="A5" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Laitinen</surname><given-names>Jarmo T</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>jarmo.laitinen@uku.fi</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Physiology, University of Kuopio, POB 1627, FIN-70211, Kuopio, Finland</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Department of Pharmaceutical Chemistry, University of Kuopio, POB 1627, FIN-70211 Kuopio, Finland</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2005</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>25</day><month>4</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2121/6/21"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>5</day><month>11</month><year>2004</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>4</month><year>2005</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2005 Kokkola et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2005</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Kokkola et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>
               Kokkola
               Tarja
               
               tarja.kokkola@uku.fi
            </dc:author><dc:title>
            S-Nitrosothiols modulate G protein-coupled receptor signaling in a reversible and highly receptor-specific manner
         </dc:title><dc:date>2005</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>BMC Cell Biology 6(1): 21-. (2005)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1471-2121(2005)6:1&#x0003c;21&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1471-2121</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Recent studies indicate that the G protein-coupled receptor (GPCR) signaling machinery can serve as a direct target of reactive oxygen species, including nitric oxide (NO) and S-nitrosothiols (RSNOs). To gain a broader view into the way that receptor-dependent G protein activation &#x02013; an early step in signal transduction &#x02013; might be affected by RSNOs, we have studied several receptors coupling to the G<sub>i </sub>family of G proteins in their native cellular environment using the powerful functional approach of [<sup>35</sup>S]GTP&#x003b3;S autoradiography with brain cryostat sections in combination with classical G protein activation assays.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>We demonstrate that RSNOs, like S-nitrosoglutathione (GSNO) and S-nitrosocysteine (CysNO), can modulate GPCR signaling via reversible, thiol-sensitive mechanisms probably involving S-nitrosylation. RSNOs are capable of very targeted regulation, as they potentiate the signaling of some receptors (exemplified by the M2/M4 muscarinic cholinergic receptors), inhibit others (P2Y<sub>12 </sub>purinergic, LPA<sub>1</sub>lysophosphatidic acid, and cannabinoid CB<sub>1 </sub>receptors), but may only marginally affect signaling of others, such as adenosine A<sub>1</sub>, &#x003bc;-opioid, and opiate related receptors. Amplification of M2/M4 muscarinic responses is explained by an accelerated rate of guanine nucleotide exchange, as well as an increased number of high-affinity [<sup>35</sup>S]GTP&#x003b3;S binding sites available for the agonist-activated receptor. GSNO amplified human M4 receptor signaling also under heterologous expression in CHO cells, but the effect diminished with increasing constitutive receptor activity. RSNOs markedly inhibited P2Y<sub>12 </sub>receptor signaling in native tissues (rat brain and human platelets), but failed to affect human P2Y<sub>12 </sub>receptor signaling under heterologous expression in CHO cells, indicating that the native cellular signaling partners, rather than the P2Y<sub>12 </sub>receptor protein, act as a molecular target for this action.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>These in vitro studies show for the first time in a broader general context that RSNOs are capable of modulating GPCR signaling in a reversible and highly receptor-specific manner. Given that the enzymatic machinery responsible for endogenous NO production is located in close proximity with the GPCR signaling complex, especially with that for several receptors whose signaling is shown here to be modulated by exogenous RSNOs, our data suggest that GPCR signaling in vivo is likely to be subject to substantial, and highly receptor-specific modulation by NO-derived RSNOs.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>G protein-coupled receptors (GPCRs) represent the largest group of integral membrane proteins involved in signal transduction and are the most important targets of clinically marketed drugs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. The known GPCRs mediate messages from ligands as diverse as neurotransmitters, lipid mediators, hormones, and sensory stimuli [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. The classical scheme of GPCR signaling implies that agonist-induced conformational changes in receptor molecule will result in activation of cognate G proteins and subsequently in the regulation of downstream effectors, second messengers, and the activation of protein kinases, for example [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. However, recent work has indicated that GPCR signaling is subject to complex, cell-type specific regulation, involving a plethora of kinases, as well as newly-identified signaling partners, such as regulators of G protein signaling (RGS) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>], and activators of G protein signaling (AGS) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>].</p><p>Nitric oxide (NO) is a unique gaseous messenger generated in vivo by three isoforms of NO synthases (NOS). The established mode of NO signaling is through the activation of the hemoprotein, soluble guanylyl cyclase, resulting in increased production of the second messenger cGMP. However, accumulating evidence points towards cGMP-independent mechanisms by which NO can react with proteins, forming covalent post-translational modifications [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. S-nitrosothiols (RSNOs) are biological metabolites of NO, that may prolong and spatially extend the in vivo actions of locally produced NO [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. NO and RSNOs can reversibly react with free SH-groups of target cysteine (Cys) residues, including those in proteins, leading to S-nitrosylation and/or S-thiolation (disulfide linkage of low-molecular weight thiols to proteins) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. A broad functional spectrum of potential S-nitrosylation target proteins is currently recognized. A growing list of targets include ion channels, transporters, transcription factors, signaling proteins, metabolic enzymes, as well as respiratory proteins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>]. Although individual components of the GPCR signaling machinery are implicated as potential targets of reactive oxygen species (ROS), including NO [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>], a broader view on how NO, and RSNOs in particular, might modulate GPCR signaling, has not been established.</p><p>To begin to address these issues, we have studied how exogenous RSNOs affect receptor-mediated G protein activity &#x02013; a very proximal step of GPCR signal transduction &#x02013; by studying the signaling of several receptors that couple to the G<sub>i </sub>family of heterotrimeric G proteins. This family consists of both pertussis toxin sensitive (G&#x003b1;<sub>i1-3</sub>, G&#x003b1;<sub>o</sub>, transducin, gustducin) and insensitive (G&#x003b1;<sub>z</sub>) members. We applied the powerful functional approach of [<sup>35</sup>S]GTP&#x003b3;S autoradiography in brain cryostat sections, as this technique allows selective detection of receptor-dependent G protein activity simultaneously in multiple brain regions with minimal disturbance of the GPCR microenvironment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>]. We anticipated that accessibility of target thiols would be minimally disturbed in cryostat sections. Moreover, it is increasingly recognized that specialized plasma membrane microdomains (variously described as detergent-resistant fractions, low-density fractions, lipid rafts, or caveolae) act as unique signaling platforms with specific enrichment of GPCRs, their cognate G proteins, as well as effectors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>]. Such an enrichment is thought to be well-preserved in cryostat sections, but might be compromised to a variable extent [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>], or even lost in bulk membrane preparations obtained using traditional protocols. To complement the autoradiography approach, we used membrane and lysate [<sup>35</sup>S]GTP&#x003b3;S binding assays to more systematically study the effects of RSNOs on a panel of G<sub>i</sub>-coupled receptors in native tissues. Signaling of selected receptors was further studied after their heterologous expression in Chinese hamster ovary (CHO) cells. Our studies reveal highly receptor-specific modulation of GPCR signaling by RSNOs, as signaling of some receptors can be amplified, or inhibited, whereas for others, the activity is only marginally affected by comparable treatments. The GPCR itself and/or its native signaling partners seem to act as potential targets of RSNO action, and therefore their modulation may be diminished, or even totally masked under heterologous expression.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>Exogenous RSNOs modulate GPCR signaling via mechanisms likely involving S-nitrosylation</title><p>We used the functional approach of [<sup>35</sup>S]GTP&#x003b3;S autoradiography, as this technique allows selective detection of receptor-stimulated G<sub>i </sub>protein activity simultaneously in multiple brain structures with minimal disturbance of the GPCR microenvironment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>]. We focused the initial experiments on three G<sub>i</sub>-linked receptors, namely M2/M4 AChRs, the P2Y<sub>12 </sub>purinoceptor, and the LPA<sub>1 </sub>receptor, as G protein activity upon stimulation of these receptors has been previously characterized using the autoradiography approach and each receptor shows a unique anatomical distribution pattern in the developing rat brain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>]. As depicted in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>, pretreatment of brain sections with freshly prepared GSNO (0.5 mM) had distinct effects on basal and receptor-stimulated [<sup>35</sup>S]GTP&#x003b3;S binding responses. In GSNO-treated sections, basal G protein activity was increased throughout the gray matter areas and this effect was fully reversed in the presence of excess thiol, either in the form of dithiotreitol (DTT) or reduced glutathione (GSH). The autoradiography images were quantified for selected brain regions and these results are shown in Supplementary Figures 1 and 2 [see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">additional file 1</xref>]. Consistent with the anatomical distribution of atropine-sensitive and M2/M4 AChR-dependent G protein activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>], the cholinergic agonist carbachol (CCh) stimulated [<sup>35</sup>S]GTP&#x003b3;S binding to multiple gray matter regions, including the striatum (Str), the thalamic structures, with the most intense responses in the superficial gray layer of the superior colliculus (SuG), as well as various brainstem (bs) nuclei. In all visible regions, CCh-stimulated G protein activity was robustly amplified by GSNO. This was particularly evident in the above-mentioned M2/M4 receptor-enriched anatomical loci. It is noteworthy that the GSNO effects were fully reversed in all regions in the presence of DTT or GSH (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>, Supplementary Figure 1 [see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">additional file 1</xref>]). As further illustrated in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>, the P2Y receptor agonist 2-methylthio-ADP (2MeSADP) activated G proteins both in gray and white matter regions, producing a heterogeneous activity pattern with characteristic "hot spot" appearance, as described earlier [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>]. Previous studies have established that the 2MeSADP-stimulated G protein activity in rat brain sections is mediated by a P2Y receptor subtype that pharmacologically corresponds to P2Y<sub>12 </sub>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>]. In contrast to the robust amplification of M2/M4 receptor-dependent G protein activity, GSNO clearly inhibited P2Y<sub>12 </sub>receptor signaling (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>, Supplementary Figures 1 and 2 [see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">additional file 1</xref>]). This inhibition was evident throughout the effective agonist concentration range (10<sup>-7 </sup>-10<sup>-4 </sup>M 2MeSADP), and responses to the endogenous agonist ADP (5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>-5 </sup>- 10<sup>-3 </sup>M) were similarly blunted (Supplementary Figure 2 [see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">additional file 1</xref>]). The GSNO-effect was fully reversible upon addition of DTT or GSH (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>, Supplementary Figure 1 [see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">additional file 1</xref>]). In the developing rat brain, LPA-stimulated G<sub>i </sub>protein activity is largely restricted to the myelinating white matter tracts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>] (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>), closely reflecting the anatomical distribution of LPA<sub>1 </sub>receptor subtype [Ref. 36, and references therein]. Similar to the P2Y<sub>12 </sub>responses, LPA<sub>1 </sub>receptor responses were suppressed in GSNO-treated sections throughout the white matter tracts. Also this effect was fully reversed in the presence of thiols (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>, Supplementary Figure 1 [see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">additional file 1</xref>]).</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>S-nitrosoglutathione (GSNO) reversibly modulates basal and receptor-dependent G protein activity in rat brain cryostat sections</bold>. [<sup>35</sup>S]GTP&#x003b3;S autoradiography of sagittal brain sections was conducted using a 3-step protocol with DPCPX (10<sup>-6 </sup>M) present throughout steps 2 and 3, as detailed in the <italic>Methods </italic>section. Where indicated, GSNO (0.5 mM) was present for 60 min during the GDP loading (step 2). When used, DTT (1 mM) or GSH (1 mM) were present during the [<sup>35</sup>S]GTP&#x003b3;S labeling (step 3). The muscarinic agonist, carbachol (CCh, 10<sup>-4 </sup>M), the P2Y receptor agonist 2-methylthio-ADP (2MeSADP, 10<sup>-5 </sup>M) or lysophosphatidic acid (LPA, 5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>-5 </sup>M in 0.1% fatty acid free BSA) were present in step 3. In the control panel (left), the anatomical loci where receptor agonists typically activate G proteins are indicated. Note GSNO-dependent overall increase in basal G protein activity, as well as robust amplification of CCh-stimulated G protein activity in several gray matter regions visible at this sagittal plane, most notably the brain stem (bs) nuclei, the striatum (Str), and the superficial gray layer of the superior colliculus (SuG). Note also clear attenuation of 2MeSADP-stimulated responses in all brain regions, and blunting of LPA-stimulated responses, especially in the white matter areas, including the corpus callosum (cc), the fimbria of the hippocampus (fi) and the cerebellar white matter (Cbw). Scale bar = 2 mm. For quantitative data on selected brain regions, see Supplementary Figs. 1 and 2 in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">additional file 1</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2121-6-21-1"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>GSNO modulates GPCR signaling in a dose-dependent manner</bold>. [<sup>35</sup>S]GTP&#x003b3;S autoradiography was conducted using a 3-step protocol with DPCPX (10<sup>-6 </sup>M) present throughout steps 2 and 3, as detailed in the <italic>Methods </italic>section. GSNO was present at the indicated concentrations for 60 min during the GDP loading (step 2). Carbachol (CCh, 10<sup>-4 </sup>M), 2MeSADP (10<sup>-6 </sup>M) or LPA (5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>-5 </sup>M in 0.1% fatty acid free BSA) were present in step 3. Note dose-dependent amplification of CCh-stimulated G protein activity, most evident at this coronal plane in the cerebral cortex (Cx), the striatum (Str), and the thalamus (Thal). Note also dose-related attenuation of 2MeSADP- and LPA-stimulated responses, especially in the white matter regions, including the corpus callosum (cc), the fimbria of the hippocampus (fi), and the striatal white matter (Sw). Scale bar = 2 mm. For quantitative data on selected brain regions, see Supplementary Figs. 1 and 2 in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">additional file 1</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2121-6-21-2"/></fig><p>GSNO is present in significant amounts (~15 pmol/mg protein) in the brain tissue and it is thought to act as a physiological carrier of NO for S-nitrosylation reactions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>]. As shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> and Supplementary Figure 1 [see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">additional file 1</xref>], GSNO modulated GPCR responses in a dose-dependent manner, being effective at the submillimolar concentration range. However, the threshold and maximal concentrations needed for the modulation of distinct receptors slightly varied. Potentiation of M2/M4 receptor signaling was evident already with 0.05 mM GSNO, but statistically significant responses were obtained using 0.2 &#x02013; 1 mM GSNO (Supplementary Figure 1 [see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">additional file 1</xref>]). P2Y<sub>12 </sub>receptor responses were inhibited with 0.2 mM GSNO and higher concentrations (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>, Supplementary Figure 1 [see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">additional file 1</xref>]). LPA<sub>1 </sub>receptor signaling was only marginally affected with 0.05 mM GSNO, but was severely blunted with 0.2 mM GSNO and higher concentrations (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>, Supplementary Figure 1 [see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">additional file 1</xref>]). Collectively, these experiments demonstrate that GSNO, a physiologically relevant RSNO, can modulate GPCR signaling in discrete brain regions in a receptor-specific and fully reversible manner.</p><p>Various RSNOs, including S-nitrosocysteine (CysNO) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>, Supplementary Table 1 [see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">additional file 1</xref>]), S-nitrosocysteamine, S-nitroso-L-cysteinylglycine (CysNO-Gly), L-&#x003b3;-glutamyl-S-nitrosocysteine (Glu-CysNO), and S-nitroso-N-acetyl-D,L-penicillamine (SNAP) &#x02013; a compound with a sterically hindered SNO group &#x02013; mimicked the effects of GSNO on the three studied receptors (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>, Supplementary Figure 2 [see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">additional file 1</xref>], and data not shown). When equimolar concentrations (0.5 mM) of GSNO and SNAP were compared, SNAP equally well suppressed P2Y<sub>12 </sub>receptor responses, whereas GSNO more efficiently modulated M2/M4 and LPA<sub>1 </sub>receptor responses (Supplementary Figure 3 [see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">additional file 1</xref>]). The modulatory effect of CysNO on the three receptors was reversed by addition of DTT or cysteine (Supplementary Figure 4 [see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">additional file 1</xref>]). However, when "aged" CysNO was used (the stock solution was left to stand for 2 days in ambient light, oxygen and temperature), receptor-stimulated G protein activity was almost completely abolished (Supplementary Figure 5 [see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">additional file 1</xref>]).</p><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>S-nitrosocysteine (CysNO) mimics the effects of GSNO in modulating GPCR signaling, whereas sodium nitroprusside (SNP) and 8-bromo cyclic GMP (8Br-cGMP) do not</bold>. [<sup>35</sup>S]GTP&#x003b3;S autoradiography was conducted using a 3-step protocol with DPCPX (10<sup>-6 </sup>M) present throughout steps 2 and 3, as detailed in the <italic>Methods </italic>section. Where indicated, CysNO (1 mM), SNP (0.5 mM), or 8Br-cGMP (0.25 mM) were present for 60 min during the GDP loading (step 2). Carbachol (10<sup>-4 </sup>M), 2MeSADP (10<sup>-6 </sup>M), or LPA (5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>-5 </sup>M in 0.1% fatty acid free BSA) were present in step 3. Note amplification of CCh-stimulated G protein activity by CySNO, most evident at this coronal plane in the cerebral cortex (Cx), the thalamus (Thal), including the superficial gray layer of the superior colliculus (SuG). Note also CysNO-dependent attenuation of 2MeSADP- and LPA-stimulated responses, most evident in the corpus callosum (cc) and the fimbria of the hippocampus (fi). Scale bar = 2 mm. For quantitative data on selected brain regions, see Supplementary Table 1 in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">additional file 1</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2121-6-21-3"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Effects of GSNO treatment on agonist dose-response parameters in [<sup>35</sup>S]GTP&#x003b3;S binding assays of various G<sub>i</sub>-coupled receptors in their native cellular environment. Membranes or lysates were preincubated in control conditions or in the presence of 0.5 mM GSNO for 30 min. Values are mean &#x000b1; SE from three to four independent experiments performed in duplicate. E<sub>max </sub>is expressed in percentage over basal with nonspecific binding subtracted.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td></td><td align="center" colspan="2">Control</td><td align="center" colspan="2">GSNO</td></tr><tr><td></td><td colspan="2"><hr></hr></td><td colspan="2"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Receptor (agonist)</td><td align="left">log(EC<sub>50</sub>)</td><td align="left">E<sub>max </sub>(%)</td><td align="left">log(EC<sub>50</sub>)</td><td align="left">E<sub>max </sub>(%)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><bold><italic>Rat forebrain membranes</italic></bold></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">M2/M4 mAChRs (CCh)</td><td align="left">-4.94 &#x000b1; 0.05</td><td align="left">176 &#x000b1; 2</td><td align="left">-5.55 &#x000b1; 0.11**</td><td align="left">207 &#x000b1; 4**</td></tr><tr><td align="left">LPA<sub>1 </sub>(LPA)</td><td align="left">-6.84 &#x000b1; 0.26</td><td align="left">140 &#x000b1; 7</td><td align="left">-6.53 &#x000b1; 0.40</td><td align="left">116 &#x000b1; 3*</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Cannabinoid CB<sub>1 </sub>(CP55940)</td><td align="left">-7.84 &#x000b1; 0.07</td><td align="left">223 &#x000b1; 3</td><td align="left">-7.69 &#x000b1; 0.08</td><td align="left">183 &#x000b1; 2***</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Adenosine A<sub>1 </sub>(2ClAdo)</td><td align="left">-6.90 &#x000b1; 0.04</td><td align="left">256 &#x000b1; 3</td><td align="left">-6.87 &#x000b1; 0.12</td><td align="left">234 &#x000b1; 7*</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x003bc;-opiate (DAMGO)</td><td align="left">-6.85 &#x000b1; 0.09</td><td align="left">167 &#x000b1; 3</td><td align="left">-7.31 &#x000b1; 0.19</td><td align="left">164 &#x000b1; 5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ORL1 (Nociceptin)</td><td align="left">-8.66 &#x000b1; 0.12</td><td align="left">173 &#x000b1; 3</td><td align="left">-8.78 &#x000b1; 0.10</td><td align="left">161 &#x000b1; 2*</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold><italic>CHO cell lysates</italic></bold></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">LPA (LPA)</td><td align="left">-7.37 &#x000b1; 0.11</td><td align="left">202 &#x000b1; 4</td><td align="left">-7.05 &#x000b1; 0.12</td><td align="left">176 &#x000b1; 4**</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold><italic>Human platelet membranes</italic></bold></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">P2Y<sub>12 </sub>(MeSADP)</td><td align="left">-8.19 &#x000b1; 0.03</td><td align="left">279 &#x000b1; 2</td><td align="left">-8.30 &#x000b1; 0.08</td><td align="left">195 &#x000b1; 3***</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x003b1;<sub>2A</sub>-adrenoceptor (NA)</td><td align="left">-5.33 &#x000b1; 0.08</td><td align="left">161 &#x000b1; 2</td><td align="left">-5.49 &#x000b1; 0.09</td><td align="left">182 &#x000b1; 3**</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>* Statistically different from control (P &#x0003c; 0.05)</p><p>** Statistically different from control (P &#x0003c; 0.01)</p><p>*** Statistically different from control (P &#x0003c; 0.001)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><bold>GSNO only marginally affect opiate related receptor (ORL1), &#x003bc; opioid receptor (MOR) and adenosine A<sub>1 </sub>(Ado A<sub>1</sub>) receptors signaling in brain sections</bold>. [<sup>35</sup>S]GTP&#x003b3;S autoradiography was conducted using a 3-step protocol with adenosine deaminase (ADA, 1 U/ml) present throughout steps 2 and 3, as detailed in the <italic>Methods </italic>section. Where indicated, GSNO (1 mM) was present for 60 min during the GDP loading (step 2). Protease inhibitor cocktail was included in step 2 for brain sections used for testing ORL1 and MOR responses. Receptor agonists nociceptin (ORL1), DAMGO (MOR), and 2-chloroadenosine (2ClAdo) (adenosine A<sub>1 </sub>receptor) were present at submaximal concentrations during step 3. Note wide distribution of nociceptin-responsive brain regions, including the cerebral cortex (Cx). Note also robust response to DAMGO in the MOR-enriched striatal patches (Sp), as well as the relatively GSNO-resistant, and widely distributed adenosine A<sub>1 </sub>receptor-dependent signal throughout the sagittal plane. Scale bar = 2 mm. For quantitative data on selected brain regions, see Supplementary Table 2 in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">additional file 1</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2121-6-21-4"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><bold>The P2Y<sub>12 </sub>receptor is not a direct target of RSNO action</bold>. Human P2Y<sub>12 </sub>receptor was stably expressed in CHO cells and agonist-stimulated G protein activity was determined in control conditions and in membranes pretreated for 30 min with 0.5 mM GSNO or CysNO, as detailed in the <italic>Methods </italic>section. There were no statistical differences in the agonist potency [log (EC<sub>50</sub>): control -9.20 &#x000b1; 0.09; GSNO -9.14 &#x000b1; 0.07; CysNO -9.27 &#x000b1; 0.14) or efficacy [E<sub>max </sub>(% basal): control 182 &#x000b1; 3 %; GSNO 180 &#x000b1; 2; CysNO 179 &#x000b1; 5%]. Values are mean &#x000b1; SE from three independent experiments performed in duplicate.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2121-6-21-5"/></fig><p>Previous studies have suggested that RSNOs can act as NO<sup>+</sup>, NO<sup>.</sup>, and NO<sup>- </sup>donors under physiological conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. The RSNO effects on GPCR responses were not mimicked by the NO donor sodium nitroprusside (SNP), when tested at similar (0.5 mM) concentrations (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>, Supplementary Table 1 [see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">additional file 1</xref>]). Furthermore, the NO<sup>+</sup>-releasing NO donor, nitrosodium tetrafluoroborate (NOBF<sub>4</sub>, 0.5 mM) (data not shown), hydrogen peroxide (1 mM H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2 </sub>+ 0.2 mM FeSO<sub>4</sub>) (data not shown), or the cyclic GMP analog 8-bromo-cyclic GMP (0.25 mM) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>, Supplementary Table 1 [see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">additional file 1</xref>]) were largely ineffective. For selected brain regions, quantitative autoradiography data on CysNO, SNP and 8-bromo-cyclic GMP are presented in the Supplementary Table 1 [see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">additional file 1</xref>].</p><p>The above results demonstrate that the effects of NO-related species was shared by -and restricted to &#x02013; different classes of RSNO compounds, suggesting that S-nitrosylation rather than other types of NO reactions, or cGMP-dependent mechanisms, were involved. According to the S-nitrosylation scheme, treatment with exogenous RSNOs should result in transnitrosylation of potential protein thiols (R-SNO + Protein-SH &#x02194; R-SH + Protein-SNO). To demonstrate the presence of SNO moieties in GSNO-treated brain section, we used the indirect approach where heterolytic cleavage of S-NO bond with HgCl<sub>2 </sub>generates nitrite which can be measured by a colorimetric method. To this end, brain sections were treated with GSNO (0.5 mM), and after thorough washes, the sections were incubated further in the absence or presence of HgCl<sub>2 </sub>(10<sup>-4 </sup>M). These experiments (shown in Supplementary Figure 6 [see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">additional file 1</xref>]) revealed that HgCl<sub>2</sub>-catalyzed nitrite formation was significantly higher in GSNO treated sections than that in control conditions (2.46 &#x000b1; 0.13 vs. 0.61 &#x000b1; 0.14 nmol NO<sub>2</sub><sup>- </sup>per four coronal brain sections, mean &#x000b1; SE, n = 3, P &#x0003c; 0.001). Collectively these experiments suggest that the RSNO-evoked and receptor-specific modulation of GPCR signaling in brain sections most likely involves S-nitrosylation mechanisms.</p><fig position="float" id="F6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><bold>GSNO accelerates the rate of M2/M4 AChR-stimulated [<sup>35</sup>S]GTP&#x003b3;S binding to rat forebrain membranes but has no effect on basal guanine nucleotide exchange rate</bold>. Membranes were preincubated for 30 min in control conditions or in the presence of 0.5 mM GSNO, and time-response for basal and CCh-stimulated (10<sup>-4 </sup>M] [<sup>35</sup>S]GTP&#x003b3;S binding was determined, as detailed in the <italic>Methods </italic>section. Values represent specific binding (mean &#x000b1; SD of duplicate determinations) from one representative experiment that was replicated three times with similar outcome.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2121-6-21-6"/></fig></sec><sec><title>RSNOs modulate GPCR signaling in native tissues in a highly receptor-specific manner</title><p>Although [<sup>35</sup>S]GTP&#x003b3;S autoradiography offers the advantage of monitoring G protein activity simultaneously in multiple brain regions with minimal disturbance of the GPCR microenvironment, generating quantitative data from the autoradiography images is relatively tedious. As a complementary approach, we tested the effect of RSNOs on agonist potency and efficacy for several additional G<sub>i</sub>-coupled receptors using classical membrane and lysate [<sup>35</sup>S]GTP&#x003b3;S binding assays. The results of these experiments are summarized in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>. There was one major difference from the situation with brain sections; in the rat forebrain membrane preparations GSNO did not significantly affect basal G protein activity (102 &#x000b1; 2 % control, mean &#x000b1; SE, n = 26, see also Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>). However, GSNO modulation of receptor-mediated responses was found to be highly receptor-specific. In line with the autoradiography data, M2/M4 receptor signaling was markedly amplified (both the potency and the efficacy of agonist increased) whereas LPA-evoked signaling efficacy (but not agonist potency) was significantly decreased in the rat forebrain membrane preparations. Moreover, the efficacy of cannabinoid CB<sub>1 </sub>receptor signaling was significantly inhibited with no concomitant change in agonist potency (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). [<sup>35</sup>S]GTP&#x003b3;S autoradiography studies further indicated that CB<sub>1 </sub>receptor signaling was similarly inhibited in various CB<sub>1 </sub>receptor-enriched brain regions, including the cerebral cortex, the hippocampus and the globus pallidus (Supplementary Figure 7 [see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">additional file 1</xref>]). On the other hand, signaling via other widely distributed receptors, such as adenosine A<sub>1</sub>, &#x003bc;-opioid (MOR) and opiate-related receptor (ORL1), was only marginally (A<sub>1 </sub>and ORL1), or not detectably (MOR), altered in bulk membrane preparations (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>) or in brain cryostat sections (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). For the three receptors, quantitative autoradiography data on selected brain regions are presented in Supplementary Table 2 [see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">additional file 1</xref>].</p><fig position="float" id="F7"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p><bold>GSNO increases the number of M2/M4 AChR interacting high-affinity [<sup>35</sup>S]GTP&#x003b3;S binding sites in rat forebrain membranes</bold>. Membranes were preincubated for 30 min in control conditions or in the presence of 0.5 mM GSNO, and incubated thereafter for 90 min with 0.15 nM [<sup>35</sup>S]GTP&#x003b3;S, 10<sup>-5 </sup>M GDP and indicated concentrations of unlabeled GTP&#x003b3;S in the presence and absence of CCh (10<sup>-4 </sup>M), as detailed in the <italic>Methods </italic>section. Statistical comparison of one- versus two-site competition curves (nonlinear regression) indicated that the one-site model best described GTP&#x003b3;S displacement in agonist-stimulated conditions. Note that GSNO significantly increased the number of high-affinity [<sup>35</sup>S]GTP&#x003b3;S binding sites in CCh-treated membranes (CCh-control 1.49 &#x000b1; 0.02; CCh-GSNO 1.75 &#x000b1; 0.02 pmol/mg protein, P &#x0003c; 0.001, unpaired T-test). There were no statistical differences in the potency for GTP&#x003b3;S in displacing radioligand in any condition [log (EC<sub>50</sub>): basal-control -8.10 &#x000b1; 0.07; basal-GSNO -8.11 &#x000b1; 0.12; CCh-control -8.06 &#x000b1; 0.06; CCh-GSNO -8.10 &#x000b1; 0.04). Values represent specific binding (mean &#x000b1; SE) from three independent experiments performed in duplicate.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2121-6-21-7"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Effects of GSNO treatment on agonist (CCh) dose-response parameters in [<sup>35</sup>S]GTP&#x003b3;S binding assays of hM4 cell line membranes. Membranes were preincubated in control conditions or in the presence of 0.5 mM GSNO for 30 min. Values are mean &#x000b1; SE from three to four independent experiments performed in duplicate. E<sub>max </sub>is expressed in percentage over basal with nonspecific binding subtracted.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td></td><td align="center" colspan="2">Control</td><td align="center" colspan="2">GSNO</td></tr><tr><td></td><td colspan="2"><hr></hr></td><td colspan="2"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left">CHO cell line</td><td align="left">log(EC<sub>50</sub>)</td><td align="left">E<sub>max </sub>(%)</td><td align="left">log(EC<sub>50</sub>)</td><td align="left">E<sub>max </sub>(%)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">hM4-WT-A1</td><td align="left">-4.87 &#x000b1; 0.14</td><td align="left">586 &#x000b1; 31</td><td align="left">-4.94 &#x000b1; 0.09</td><td align="left">674 &#x000b1; 23</td></tr><tr><td align="left">hM4-WT-E5</td><td align="left">-4.87 &#x000b1; 0.05</td><td align="left">213 &#x000b1; 3</td><td align="left">-4.98 &#x000b1; 0.13</td><td align="left">276 &#x000b1; 10**</td></tr><tr><td align="left">hM4-WT-C2</td><td align="left">-5.21 &#x000b1; 0.20</td><td align="left">134 &#x000b1; 3</td><td align="left">-5.27 &#x000b1; 0.20</td><td align="left">154 &#x000b1; 8*</td></tr><tr><td align="left">hM4-C133S-H2</td><td align="left">-5.13 &#x000b1; 0.10</td><td align="left">198 &#x000b1; 4</td><td align="left">-5.12 &#x000b1; 0.11</td><td align="left">235 &#x000b1; 6**</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>* Statistically different from control (P &#x0003c; 0.05)</p><p>** Statistically different from control (P &#x0003c; 0.01)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>CHO cells express endogenous G<sub>i</sub>-coupled LPA receptors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>], and similarly to the situation in brain membranes and cryostat sections, GSNO significantly inhibited LPA signaling in CHO cell lysates without affecting the agonist potency (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). Platelets offer another readily accessible model to study P2Y<sub>12</sub>-G<sub>i </sub>(specifically G&#x003b1;<sub>i2</sub>) signaling in native cellular environments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>]. In human platelet membranes, GSNO inhibited basal G protein activity by 22 &#x000b1; 4 % (mean &#x000b1; SE, n = 3). This effect was statistically significant. Similar to the situation with brain P2Y<sub>12 </sub>receptor signaling, GSNO inhibited P2Y<sub>12 </sub>receptor-dependent G protein activity in human platelet membranes, but had no effect on the agonist potency (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). To examine whether the receptor protein serves as a direct target of this action, human P2Y<sub>12 </sub>receptor was stably transfected into CHO cells. Several cell lines responding to 2MeSADP in [<sup>35</sup>S]GTP&#x003b3;S binding assays were established (our unpublished observations). However, neither GSNO nor CysNO affected the 2MeSADP dose-response curves of any of the hP2Y<sub>12</sub>-expressing cell lines (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref> and data not shown). These data rule out the P2Y<sub>12 </sub>receptor protein as a direct target of the RSNO action.</p><p>The inhibitory effect of GSNO on basal and P2Y<sub>12 </sub>receptor-dependent G protein activity was not due to a nonspecific action on platelet membranes, since the signaling of another G<sub>i</sub>-linked platelet receptor, the &#x003b1;<sub>2A</sub>-adrenoceptor, was significantly amplified in GSNO-treated membranes (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). This effect was not restricted to platelets, nor was it unique to the &#x003b1;<sub>2A</sub>-subtype, as signaling of the three human &#x003b1;<sub>2</sub>-adrenoceptor subtypes (&#x003b1;<sub>2A</sub>, &#x003b1;<sub>2B</sub>, and &#x003b1;<sub>2C</sub>) was potentiated by GSNO in CHO cell lines stably expressing these receptors (our unpublished observations).</p></sec><sec><title>RSNOs amplify muscarinic responses by increasing the rate of GDP/GTP exchange and the number of high-affinity GTP binding sites</title><p>The amplification of M2/M4 responses by RSNOs was clearly evident in native brain tissue. Further experiments were designed to address the mechanism of this action. Results of these studies are presented in Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>. A time-response study on basal and CCh-stimulated [<sup>35</sup>S]GTP&#x003b3;S binding responses in forebrain membranes revealed that GSNO accelerated the rate of [<sup>35</sup>S]GTP&#x003b3;S binding in agonist-stimulated conditions (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>). In contrast, GSNO had no effect on basal guanine nucleotide exchange. Given that GDP release is generally thought to be the rate-limiting step in receptor-driven G protein activation, these data indicate that the amplifying effect of GSNO on M2/M4 receptor-stimulated G protein activity is due to an accelerated rate of GDP/GTP exchange at the receptor-activated G protein &#x003b1; subunits. In line with this, GSNO significantly increased the number of high-affinity [<sup>35</sup>S]GTP&#x003b3;S binding sites available for M2/M4 receptor activation under agonist-stimulated conditions (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>) (Mean &#x000b1; SE: CCh-control 1.49 &#x000b1; 0.02 vs. CCh-GSNO 1.75 &#x000b1; 0.02 pmol/mg protein, P &#x0003c; 0.001, unpaired T-test). In contrast, there were no statistical differences in the potency of GTP&#x003b3;S to displace [<sup>35</sup>S]GTP&#x003b3;S in any of the tested conditions (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>) [log (EC<sub>50</sub>) &#x000b1; SE: basal-control -8.10 &#x000b1; 0.07; basal-GSNO -8.11 &#x000b1; 0.12; CCh-control -8.06 &#x000b1; 0.06; CCh-GSNO -8.10 &#x000b1; 0.04). These experiments indicate that RSNOs amplify muscarinic receptor-stimulated G protein activity in native brain tissue by accelerating the rate by which agonist-occupied receptors can activate their cognate G proteins.</p></sec><sec><title>RSNO amplification of M4 receptor responses are preserved under heterologous expression but the amplification is lost with constitutive receptor activity</title><p>To investigate the signaling of the human M4 receptor (hM4) under heterologous expression system, the receptor was stably transfected into CHO cells. The effects of GSNO on agonist-stimulated G protein activity were compared in rat forebrain membranes and three cell lines expressing the wild-type (WT) hM4 receptor with increasing capability to activate G proteins. The results of these experiments are shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>, and the potency and efficacy values are summarized in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>. In control conditions, CCh stimulated [<sup>35</sup>S]GTP&#x003b3;S binding in the three WT-hM4 cell lines at a similar potency but varying efficacy (E<sub>max </sub>ranging from 134 to 586 %) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>, Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). GSNO treatment significantly increased the E<sub>max </sub>in the two WT-hM4 cell lines (E5 and C2) that showed comparable maximal responses to the values obtained in rat forebrain membranes (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>, Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). In contrast, the potentiating effect of GSNO was lost in the WT-hM4-A1 cell line, where CCh robustly activated G proteins (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>, Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). In contrast to the situation in brain membranes and other hM4 cell lines of this study, WT-hM4-A1 cell line exhibited constitutive activity, i.e. significant G protein activation was evident in the absence of added agonist. In this cell line, the mAChR antagonist, atropine, significantly inhibited basal G protein activity by 13 &#x000b1; 3 % (mean &#x000b1; SE, n = 3, P &#x0003c; 0.05) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>, bottom panel middle). The effect was dose-dependent [log(IC<sub>50</sub>) -8.48 &#x000b1; 0.23 (mean &#x000b1; SE, n = 3)], indicating increased constitutive activation of WT-hM4 receptor in this cell line. Collectively these experiments indicate that the potentiating effect of GSNO on hM4 receptor responses was preserved under heterologous expression but that the effect was diminished with constitutive receptor activity.</p><fig position="float" id="F8"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p><bold>GSNO-evoked potentiation of muscarinic signaling is preserved under heterologus expression but the effect diminishes with increasing constitutive activity</bold>. The human M4 (hM4) receptor was stably transfected into CHO cells and wild type (WT) or mutant (C133S) cell lines with differential G protein activation capacity were compared with that in rat forebrain membranes. CCh-stimulated G protein activity was determined in control conditions and in membranes pretreated for 30 min with 0.5 mM GSNO, as detailed in the <italic>Methods </italic>section. Note that cell lines WT-C2, WT-E5 and C133S-H2 have maximal responses comparable to that in native brain tissue. Note also robust G protein activation in WT-A1 cell line, as well as its constitutive activity, as evidenced by the ability of the inverse agonist atropine to inhibit basal G protein activity in this cell line. Potency and efficacy values are summarized in Tables 1 (rat brain) and 2 (hM4 clones). Values are mean &#x000b1; SE from at least three independent experiments performed in duplicate.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2121-6-21-8"/></fig><p>The final experiments were intended to clarify whether cysteine 133 (C133), located adjacent to the G protein-interacting DRY-motif in the intracellular end of transmembrane helix 3 of the G<sub>i</sub>-coupled muscarinic receptors (M2/M4), could serve as the molecular target of RSNO action. To this end, C133 was mutated into serine to reveal if the C133S mutation would abolish the effect of GSNO on the efficacy of CCh. However, GSNO treatment significantly increased E<sub>max </sub>also in the mutant C133S-hM4 cell line (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>, bottom panel right, Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>), indicating that cysteine C133 of the hM4 receptor is not the specific target of RSNOs. The mutation did not affect the potency of CCh to activate G proteins via the hM4 receptor (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>[<sup>35</sup>S]GTP&#x003b3;S autoradiography of brain cryostat sections revealed a highly receptor-specific modulation of GPCR signaling by RSNOs in several receptor-enriched anatomical structures. This modulation was fully reversible upon addition of excess thiols. We have provided evidence indicating that S-nitrosylation, rather than other types of NO reactions or the NO &#x02013; guanylyl cyclase &#x02013; cGMP signaling pathway, was responsible for the observed effects. The RSNOs effects were receptor-specific, as signaling of some receptors was markedly potentiated (M2/M4 AChRs and &#x003b1;<sub>2</sub>-adrenoceptors), whereas that of others was clearly inhibited (P2Y<sub>12</sub>, LPA and cannabinoid CB<sub>1 </sub>receptors), while signaling of other receptors was only marginally affected (adenosine A<sub>1</sub>, MOR, and ORL1 receptors) by comparable treatments. We further demonstrated that RSNOs can amplify M2/M4 receptor responses by increasing the rate of GDP/GTP exchange as well as the number of high-affinity G protein &#x003b1; subunits capable of interacting with the agonist-activated receptors. The potentiating effect of RSNOs on hM4 receptor responses was preserved when this was studied in a heterologous expression system but was diminished in constitutively active hM4 receptors. We also demonstrated that the GPCR itself or its native signaling partners serve as potential targets of this modulation, as it was attenuated, or even lost, when receptor signaling was studied under heterologous expression. Our study suggests that GPCR signaling is subject to a highly receptor-specific modulation by NO-derived RSNOs.</p><sec><title>The GPCRs and their proximal signaling partners as likely targets of RSNO action</title><p>Since [<sup>35</sup>S]GTP&#x003b3;S binding assays monitor G protein activation, one of the earliest measurable steps in GPCR signal transduction, it is obvious that the molecular targets of RSNO action are the receptors, their cognate G proteins and/or additional signaling partners, whose thiol modification can directly regulate guanine nucleotide binding and hence G protein activation.</p><p>It is interesting that RSNO treatment of brain sections consistently resulted in thiol-sensitive increases in basal G<sub>i </sub>protein activity throughout the gray matter regions. However, no such effect was present in brain membrane [<sup>35</sup>S]GTP&#x003b3;S binding assays, nor was it detected in CHO cell membranes but in platelet membranes, RSNOs inhibited basal G protein activity by ~20%. As receptor input should be minimal in basal conditions, the differential behavior of RSNOs in cryostat sections and various membrane preparations likely reflects direct action on the G<sub>i </sub>proteins and/or their proximal regulatory partners. It has been known for some time that G proteins can serve as direct targets of ROS, including NO [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>]. Exogenous NO donors stimulate the monomeric G protein p21<sup>ras </sup>via S-nitrosylation to a single cysteine residue [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">53</xref>]. Furthermore, G&#x003b1;<sub>i </sub>and G&#x003b1;<sub>o </sub>serve as direct protein targets of ROS, and they can be activated in the absence of input from the GPCRs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>]. Specifically, ROS were shown to modify two cysteine residues of G&#x003b1;<sub>i/o </sub>and this modification accelerated GDP release from G&#x003b1; with a concomitant increase in the formation of the GTP-bound form of G&#x003b1; without receptor activation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>]. Furthermore, GSNO was reported to stimulate basal G protein activity in bovine aortic endothelial cells and human peripheral blood mononuclear cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]. The RSNO-elicited increase in basal G protein activity in brain sections is consistent with these findings. However, it is not clear why no such stimulation was detected in bulk membrane preparations. One explanation could be the differential accessibility of target thiol(s) in cryostat sections as compared to membrane preparations. It is reasonable to assume that thiol accessibility in the former situation is close to natural. It is also possible that some crucial regulatory component of the signaling machinery is lost in bulk membrane preparations. Since several high-speed centrifugation steps were employed to obtain the relatively pure membrane preparation used in our study, this possibility should not be underestimated. This could also explain why RSNOs had no effect on basal G protein activity in CHO cell membranes, although several members of the G<sub>i </sub>family, including G&#x003b1;<sub>i1/2</sub>, G&#x003b1;<sub>i3</sub>, and G&#x003b1;<sub>o</sub>, are endogenously present in these cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">54</xref>].</p><p>In platelet membranes, RSNOs inhibited both basal and P2Y<sub>12 </sub>receptor-dependent G protein activity, but clearly potentiated &#x003b1;<sub>2A</sub>-adrenoceptor responses. Platelet P2Y<sub>12 </sub>receptors couple to G&#x003b1;<sub>i2 </sub>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>], whereas &#x003b1;<sub>2A</sub>-adrenoceptors can communicate via G&#x003b1;<sub>z</sub>, at least in the mouse [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">55</xref>]. Collectively these data suggest that RSNOs inhibit both basal and receptor-stimulated G&#x003b1;<sub>i2 </sub>activity in the platelets. It is not yet known whether brain P2Y<sub>12 </sub>receptors couple to this particular G protein subtype. Further, it is unclear whether LPA receptors in brain and CHO cells communicate via G&#x003b1;<sub>i2</sub>. It is interesting that RSNOs inhibited the signaling of all three receptors in native tissues. In addition, we found that brain cannabinoid CB<sub>1 </sub>receptor signaling was inhibited by RSNOs. A previous study reported that pulmonary vasoconstriction by serotonin was also inhibited by GSNO [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>].</p><p>Although the basic module of GPCR signaling is traditionally considered to be the receptor, its cognate G protein, and the effector, recent studies have identified a wide range of proteins that can directly interact with the receptor and/or G proteins. These can modulate signaling efficiency, cellular localization, or the regulation of the GPCRs or G proteins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. One such recently-identified protein is the brain-enriched, Ras-related monomeric G protein Dexras1 (human counterpart is termed activator of G protein signaling 1, AGS1). Dexras1/AGS1 is physiologically activated upon NMDA receptor-stimulated NO synthesis and S-nitrosylation on cysteine C11 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">57</xref>]. Dexras1/AGS-1 also interacts with G&#x003b1;<sub>i</sub>/G&#x003b1;<sub>o</sub>, and can activate GPCR signaling systems independently of receptor input [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">58</xref>]. Interestingly, Dexras1/AGS-1 was shown to proximally antagonize the signaling of M2 AChRs and formyl peptide receptors, possibly by altering the pool of G proteins available for receptor coupling and/or disruption of a preformed signaling complex [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">59</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60">60</xref>]. It is currently unknown whether RSNOs and/or S-nitrosylation could alter the ability of Dexras1/AGS-1 to modify G protein function and/or input from the GPCRs. In light of the present findings, this should be an attractive hypothesis for future studies.</p><p>Most G&#x003b1; proteins are palmitoylated at a cysteine near the amino terminus and this modification is required for G protein targeting to lipid rafts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">61</xref>] and/or normal signaling [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B62">62</xref>]. Addition and removal of the palmitoyl group appear to be dynamic receptor-mediated processes that may contribute to recycling of G&#x003b1; between the membrane and cytosolic compartments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">63</xref>]. Since our experiments used only nonliving tissue, it is unlikely that the RSNO actions would achieve such extensive lipid modifications, although such alterations reportedly occur after exposure of living cells to NO [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B64">64</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Functional implications</title><p>Specialized plasma membrane microdomains act as unique platforms with specific enrichment of GPCRs, their signaling partners, and the enzymatic machinery for NO biosynthesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>]. Such close proximity of the GPCR signaling complex and NO source is particularly relevant for many of the receptors whose signaling was shown here to be reversibly modulated by RSNOs.</p><p>In the heart, endothelial NOS (eNOS) is localized n caveolin-enriched myocyte membrane fractions and it has been shown that lipid draft-disrupting agents severely compromise NO-dependent inhibition of adenylyl cyclase types 5 and 6 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>]. M2-mediated parasympathetic cardiac signaling also critically involves eNOS activation and NO production [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B65">65</xref>]. On the other hand, caveolar sequestration of M2 receptors and NO signaling was shown to be finely tuned in the myocytes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B66">66</xref>], suggesting a dynamic interplay between the M2 receptor and NO. In hM4 expressing CHO cells, SNP induced agonist-independent internalization of the receptor via atropine- and thiol-sensitive mechanisms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B67">67</xref>]. Furthermore, ROS including NO, potentiate cardiac M2 receptor signaling via poorly defined mechanisms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B68">68</xref>]. Consistent with these findings, our study revealed robust amplification of M2/M4 receptor signaling by RSNOs both in the brain and in CHO cells expressing the hM4 receptor. In CHO cells, however, the RSNO effect clearly diminished with increasing constitutive receptor activity, suggesting that RSNO action and constitutive receptor activity likely share common mechanisms, including accelerated GDP/GTP exchange in cognate G&#x003b1; subunits. As far as we are aware, this is the first study to show robust, and highly region-specific amplification of M2/M4 receptor signaling in discrete anatomical loci of the central nervous system. The functional consequences of these findings remain to be established.</p><p>The P2Y<sub>12 </sub>receptor plays a central role in platelet activation and aggregation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B69">69</xref>]. Previous studies have indicated that endothelial and platelet-derived NO, as well as exogenous RSNOs, are potent inhibitors of platelet aggregation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B70">70</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B73">73</xref>]. Both cGMP-dependent and -independent mechanisms and several potential molecular targets have been implicated in these effects [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B72">72</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B74">74</xref>]. A previous report provided evidence for cGMP-mediated signaling in the inhibition of platelet G<sub>i </sub>signaling [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B74">74</xref>]. The present study adds further dimensions to this scheme by demonstrating that RSNOs can inhibit platelet (and brain) P2Y<sub>12 </sub>receptor function via cGMP-independent mechanisms, likely involving S-nitrosylation. However, since the effect was lost in CHO cells stably expressing the hP2Y<sub>12 </sub>receptor, the native signaling partners, rather than the P2Y<sub>12 </sub>receptor, serve as obvious targets of this action.</p><p>One of the novel findings in this study was that RSNOs strongly inhibited G<sub>i</sub>-mediated LPA receptor signaling in the brain and in CHO cells. The relevance of this finding with respect to brain LPA<sub>1 </sub>receptor signaling remains to be established. In vivo, peripheral LPA receptor signaling is closely associated with NO. In bovine aortic endothelial cells, LPA stimulates endothelial NOS via G<sub>i</sub>-coupled LPA receptors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B75">75</xref>]. LPA is released from activated platelets and this stimulates other platelets to activate aggregation processes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B76">76</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B77">77</xref>]. Inhibition of LPA signaling via endogenous RSNOs could be one important mechanism by which endothelium-derived NO can suppress LPA-mediated athero- and thrombogenic signaling.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>In conclusion, this study revealed that G protein activation, an early step of GPCR signal transduction, is subject to a reversible and highly receptor-specific modulation by exogenous RSNOs at physiologically relevant concentrations. Since NOS synthases (and thus NO production) have been shown to reside in close proximity with the GPCR signaling machinery, especially for many of the receptors whose signaling is subject to modulation by exogenous RSNOs, these findings suggest that GPCR signaling in vivo is likely to be finely tuned by NO-derived RSNO species. Future studies should aim at pinpointing the precise molecular targets of these actions, and at understanding the specific modifications (S-nitrosylation and/or S-thiolation) involved, as well as revealing the physiological and/or pathophysiological relevance in vivo.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec sec-type="materials"><title>Materials</title><p>All drugs and chemicals were from Sigma (St. Louis, MO) or Merck (Darmstadt, Germany), unless otherwise stated. Cell culture media, sera, and antibiotics were from Euroclone (Pero, Italy). Protein concentrations were determined with Bio-Rad protein assay (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA, USA). Adenosine deaminase (ADA) was purchased from Roche (Mannheim, Germany) and guanosine-5'-O-(3-[<sup>35</sup>S]-thio)-triphosphate ([<sup>35</sup>S]GTP&#x003b3;S; initial specific activity 1250 Ci/mmol) from NEN (Boston, MA). CP55940, DAMGO, nociceptin, and SNAP were purchased from Tocris Cookson Ltd. (Bristol, UK).</p></sec><sec><title>DNA constructs</title><p>Human M4 muscarinic receptor (hM4, gift from Dr. Johnny N&#x000e4;sman, University of Kuopio) was subcloned from pBluescript into pcDNA3 mammalian expression vector and a triple hemagglutinin (HA) epitope tag was subcloned after the initiating Met codon of the hM4 gene. This construct was used to create a C133S mutant hM4 receptor with QuickChange Site Directed Mutagenesis Kit (Stratagene, La Jolla, CA). Human P2Y<sub>12 </sub>purinergic receptor (hP2Y<sub>12</sub>) was amplified from QuickClone human brain cDNA (Stratagene) using RT-PCR with gene-specific primers. The PCR product was ligated into pcDNA3 and a N-terminal hemagglutinin (HA) epitope tag was inserted in a PCR reaction with 5' primer containing the HA tag DNA sequence. All receptor constructs were confirmed by restriction analyses and DNA sequencing prior to transfections.</p></sec><sec><title>Cell culture and transfection</title><p>Recombinant plasmids were introduced into Chinese hamster ovary (CHO) cells with Lipofectamine 2000 transfection reagent (Gibco, Paisley, UK). Transfected cells were placed under G-418 selection (600 &#x003bc;g/ml) and several cell lines originating from single G-418 resistant cells were isolated. The G-418 resistant cell lines were cultured as monolayers with 100 &#x003bc;g/ml G-418 in Ham's F-12 nutrient mixture, containing 10% fetal calf serum, 100 U/ml penicillin and 100 &#x003bc;g/ml streptomycin at 37&#x000b0;C in a humidified atmosphere of 5% CO<sub>2 </sub>/ 95% air. Stable cell lines were analyzed for HA tag (and thus receptor) expression using receptor ELISA with mouse anti-HA primary antibody [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B78">78</xref>]. The cell lines that showed high receptor expression levels in receptor ELISA were maintained for subsequent experiments. From these, several hM4 and hP2Y<sub>12 </sub>cell lines were established that responded to carbachol (CCh) or 2-methylthio-ADP (2MeSADP), respectively. Nontransfected CHO cells did not respond to CCh (data not shown). CHO cells endogenously express G<sub>q</sub>-coupled P2Y receptors (P2Y<sub>1 </sub>and P2Y<sub>2</sub>). However, CHO cells that had not been transfected with the hP2Y<sub>12 </sub>receptor construct did not respond to 2MeSADP, indicating that activation of G<sub>q </sub>was not detected using [<sup>35</sup>S]GTP&#x003b3;S binding assays (data not shown).</p></sec><sec><title>Preparation of cryostat sections, membranes, and cell lysates</title><p>Na&#x000ef;ve, four-week-old male Wistar rats were used for the preparation of brain cryostat sections essentially as described earlier [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B79">79</xref>]. All animal protocols were approved by the local ethics committee. Platelet membranes were prepared from expired human platelets (Red Cross, Helsinki, Finland) as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>], except that protease inhibitor cocktail was omitted. CHO cells were harvested by scraping in PBS containing 5 mM EDTA. Membrane fractions (P2) from rat brains and hM4 cell lines were isolated with differential centrifugation using previously published protocols [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B80">80</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B81">81</xref>]. For membrane preparation from hP2Y<sub>12</sub>-expressing cell lines, the centrifugation method used for platelet membrane preparation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>] was used, with the modification of omitting the protease inhibitor cocktail. For the preparation of whole-cell lysates, the cells were harvested by trypsinization in normal growth medium. Cell density was counted in a hemocytometer and the cells were pelleted by centrifugation for 10 min at 250 &#x000d7; g at room temperature. The cell pellets were washed with PBS and centrifuged twice as above, after which the dry pellets were snap-frozen on dry ice. The frozen pellets were thawed for 1 min in a water bath at room temperature, after which snap-freezing was repeated. The final membrane and lysate preparations (1&#x02013;5 mg protein/ml) were stored as single-use aliquots in -75&#x000b0;C.</p></sec><sec><title>Preparation of S-nitrosothiols</title><p>S-nitroso-N-acetyl-D,L-penicillamine (SNAP) was purchased from Tocris Cookson Ltd. (Bristol, UK). All other RSNOs were synthesized from the respective thiols using acidified NaNO<sub>2</sub>. For example, S-nitrosoglutathione (GSNO) was prepared by mixing 100 &#x003bc;l sodium nitrite (100 mM) with 100 &#x003bc;l HCl (150 mM) and adding 100 &#x003bc;l reduced glutathione (100 mM). Reactions were allowed to proceed for 10 min at room temperature, protected from light. Reaction mixtures were neutralized with 150 &#x003bc;l NaOH (100 mM) and used immediately in the experiments. Millipore-quality water was used throughout and the assay buffer routinely contained 1 mM EDTA. The concentrations of RSNOs were determined by UV spectroscopy using previously published [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B70">70</xref>] values for the molar absorption coefficients (&#x003b5;) and absorption maxima (&#x003bb;<sub>max</sub>).</p></sec><sec><title>[<sup>35</sup>S]GTP&#x003b3;S autoradiography</title><p>The assay was conducted under optimized conditions, where basal noise due to tonic adenosine A<sub>1 </sub>receptor activity has been eliminated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B79">79</xref>]. Experiments were conducted in light-protected chambers and in the absence of dithiotreitol (DTT), unless indicated otherwise. Briefly, the assay consisted of preincubation for 20 min at 20&#x000b0;C in buffer A (50 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.4, 1 mM EDTA, 100 mM NaCl, 5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>), followed by GDP loading and RSNO treatment for 1 h at 20&#x000b0;C in buffer A, containing additionally 2 mM GDP and 8-cyclopentyl-1,3-dipropylxanthine (DPCPX, 10<sup>-6 </sup>M) or adenosine deaminase (ADA, 1 U/ml) to eliminate tonic adenosine A<sub>1 </sub>receptor activity. When peptide agonists were used, protease inhibitor cocktail (Sigma P-2714) was included in step 2 at the concentrations recommended by the manufacturer. For [<sup>35</sup>S]GTP&#x003b3;S binding, sections were incubated for 90 min at 20&#x000b0;C in buffer A, containing additionally 80 pM [<sup>35</sup>S]GTP&#x003b3;S, 2 mM GDP, DPCPX (10<sup>-6 </sup>M) or ADA (1 U/ml), and the receptor agonists and/or reduced thiols (DTT, GSH or cysteine), as detailed in the results section. Nonspecific binding (Nsb) was determined in the presence of 10 &#x003bc;M GTP&#x003b3;S. The sections were washed twice at 0&#x000b0;C for 5 min in washing buffer (50 mM Tris-HCl, 5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, pH 7.4), rinsed in ice-cold deionized water for 30 s, air dried and apposed to Biomax&#x02122; MR film (Kodak) for 6&#x02013;11 days. Autoradiography images were digitized and processed for figures, as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>[<sup>35</sup>S]GTP&#x003b3;S membrane binding assays</title><p>The incubations were carried with slight modifications to previously published protocols [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B80">80</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B81">81</xref>]. Membranes or lysates were preincubated for 30 min at room temperature in 50 mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.4), 1 mM EDTA, 100 mM NaCl, 5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 10 &#x003bc;M GDP and 0.5 U/ml ADA, under constant shaking and protected from light. RSNOs (usually GSNO or CysNO) were included in the preincubation at final concentrations of 0.5 mM. The assay was performed in duplicate in a final assay volume of 400 &#x003bc;l. The reaction was initiated by adding 40 &#x003bc;l of membrane or lysate preparation (5 &#x003bc;g protein or 50,000 cells / tube) to incubation tubes containing drug dilutions and binding cocktail. The final concentrations of the components in binding reaction were 50 mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.4), 1 mM EDTA, 100 mM NaCl, 5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 0.5% BSA, 10 &#x003bc;M GDP, 0.5 U/ml ADA and 150 pM [<sup>35</sup>S]GTP&#x003b3;S. Nsb was defined using 10 &#x003bc;M GTP&#x003b3;S. Reaction tubes were incubated for 90 min at 25&#x000b0;C under constant shaking. The reaction was quickly terminated by the addition of 4 ml ice-cold wash buffer (50 mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.4), 5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>) followed by rapid filtration through Whatman GF/B glass fiber filters (Whatman, Maidstone, UK) and two additional 4 ml washes with the buffer. In the time-response study (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>), initial reaction volume was 2 ml and aliquots (400 &#x003bc;l) from duplicate samples were draw at different time points (15, 30, 60 and 90 min), and the reaction was terminated as described above. Radioactivity in filters was counted with Wallac Rackbeta liquid scintillation counter (Wallac, Turku, Finland). It should be noted that RSNO treatment caused a small, yet consistent increase in Nsb (25 &#x000b1; 4 %, mean &#x000b1; SEM, n = 13). However, as Nsb represented &#x0003c;0.3 % of total radioactivity, this effect was considered negligible and did not contribute to the results and conclusions thereof.</p></sec><sec><title>Data analysis</title><p>[<sup>35</sup>S]GTP&#x003b3;S-membrane binding data were analyzed with GraphPad Prism software (GraphPad, San Diego, CA) using non-linear fitting for sigmoid dose-response curves. Statistical analyses were made with one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) followed by Tukey's multiple comparison test. When comparison was made between only two groups, unpaired T-test was used.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>List of abbreviations</title><p>2MeSADP, 2-methylthio-ADP; [<sup>35</sup>S]GTP&#x003b3;S, guanosine-5'-O-(3-[<sup>35</sup>S]-thio)-triphosphate; 5-HT, 5-hydroxytryptamine; ADA, adenosine deaminase; AGS, activator of G protein signaling; CCh, carbacholine; CHO, Chinese hamster ovary; CP-55940, (-)-3-[2-hydroxy-4-(1,1-dimethylheptyl)-phenyl]-4-[3-hydroxypropyl]cyclohexan-1-ol; CysNO, S-nitrosocysteine; CysNO-Gly, S-nitroso-cysteinyl-glycine; DAMGO, [D-Ala<sup>2</sup>, N-Me-Phe<sup>4</sup>, Gly<sup>5</sup>-ol]-enkephalin; DPCPX, 8-cyclopentyl-1,3-dipropylxanthine; DTT, dithiotreitol; Glu-CysNO, L-&#x003b3;-glutamyl-S-nitrosocysteine; GSH, glutathione; GPCR(s), G protein-coupled receptor(s); GSNO, S-nitrosoglutathione; HA, hemagglutinin; hM4, human muscarinic receptor subtype 4; hP2Y<sub>12</sub>, human P2Y<sub>12 </sub>purinergic receptor; LPA, lysophosphatidic acid; NA, noradrenaline; NO, nitric oxide; NOBF<sub>4</sub>, nitrosodium tetrafluoroborate; NOS, NO synthase; RGS, regulator of G protein signaling; RT, reverse transcriptase; SNAP, S-nitroso-N-acetyl-D,L-penicillamine; RSNO, S-nitrosothiol; SNP, sodium nitroprusside</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>TK carried out the cell culture, molecular biology and mutagenesis studies, participated in the membrane and lysate [<sup>35</sup>S]GTP&#x003b3;S binding assays, participated in the design of the study and drafted the manuscript. JRS and MDR carried out most of the membrane [<sup>35</sup>S]GTP&#x003b3;S binding assays and performed the statistical analyses for these. KSM carried out G protein activation assays with human platelets. JTL conceived of the study, its design and coordination and conducted [<sup>35</sup>S]GTP&#x003b3;S autoradiography experiments. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S1"><caption><title>Additional File 1</title><p>Supplementary material (Supplementary Figures 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7 and Supplementary Tables 1, 2) is provided as a single file. This pdf-file (size 0.75 MB) is readable using Adobe Acrobat.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2121-6-21-S1.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>MDR is a medical student from Madrid, Spain and participated in this study as an IFMSA (International Federation of Medical Students' Association) exchange student. We wish to thank Dr. Johny N&#x000e4;sman (University of Kuopio) for the hM4 receptor cDNA, and Prof. Mika Scheinin (University of Turku) for the CHO cell lines expressing &#x003b1;<sub>2</sub>-adrenoceptor subtypes. Reija Heikkinen (M.Sc.) is acknowledged for her contribution in the generation and functional testing of hM4 cell lines. Dr. Ewen MacDonald is acknowledged for the revision of the language of this paper. We are thankful to Mrs. Taina Vihavainen, Mrs. Tiina R&#x000e4;s&#x000e4;nen and Mrs. Taija Vaarala for skillful technical assistance and to Mrs. Merja Saastamoinen for secretarial help.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fredriksson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lagerstrom</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lundin</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name><surname>Schioth</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The G-protein-coupled receptors in the human genome form five main families. Phylogenetic analysis, paralogon groups, and fingerprints</article-title><source>Mol Pharmacol</source><year>2003</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>1256</fpage><lpage>1272</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12761335</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1124/mol.63.6.1256</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vassilatis</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Hohmann</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ranchalis</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Mortrud</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Weller</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergmann</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaitanaris</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The G protein-coupled receptor repertoires of human and mouse</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2003</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>4903</fpage><lpage>4908</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12679517</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0230374100</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wise</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gearing</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Rees</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Target validation of G-protein coupled receptors</article-title><source>Drug Discov Today</source><year>2002</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>235</fpage><lpage>246</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11839521</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1359-6446(01)02131-6</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pierce</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Premont</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name><surname>Lefkowitz</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Seven-transmembrane receptors</article-title><source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source><year>2002</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>639</fpage><lpage>650</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12209124</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrm908</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neubig</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Siderovski</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulators of G-protein signalling as new central nervous system drug targets</article-title><source>Nat Rev Drug Discov</source><year>2002</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>187</fpage><lpage>197</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12120503</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrd747</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blumer</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Lanier</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Accessory proteins for G protein-signaling systems: activators of G protein signaling and other nonreceptor proteins influencing the activation state of G proteins</article-title><source>Receptors Channels</source><year>2003</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>195</fpage><lpage>204</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12775339</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10606820308240</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Turko</surname><given-names>IV</given-names></name><name><surname>Murad</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Novel effects of nitric oxide</article-title><source>Annu Rev Pharmacol Toxicol</source><year>2001</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>203</fpage><lpage>236</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11264456</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.pharmtox.41.1.203</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Rudd</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Freedman</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Loscalzo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>S-Transnitrosation reactions are involved in the metabolic fate and biological actions of nitric oxide</article-title><source>J Pharmacol Exp Ther</source><year>1998</year><volume>284</volume><fpage>526</fpage><lpage>534</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9454793</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arnelle</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Stamler</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>NO+, NO, and NO- donation by S-nitrosothiols: implications for regulation of physiological functions by S-nitrosylation and acceleration of disulfide formation</article-title><source>Arch Biochem Biophys</source><year>1995</year><volume>318</volume><fpage>279</fpage><lpage>285</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7733655</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/abbi.1995.1231</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Akerboom</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name><surname>Sies</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>S-nitrosylation and S-glutathiolation of protein sulfhydryls by S-nitroso glutathione</article-title><source>Arch Biochem Biophys</source><year>1999</year><volume>362</volume><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>78</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9917330</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/abbi.1998.1013</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Konorev</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalyanaraman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hogg</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modification of creatine kinase by S-nitrosothiols: S-nitrosation vs. S-thiolation</article-title><source>Free Radic Biol Med</source><year>2000</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>1671</fpage><lpage>1678</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10938464</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0891-5849(00)00281-1</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibition of papain by S-nitrosothiols. Formation of mixed disulfides</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2000</year><volume>275</volume><fpage>20467</fpage><lpage>20473</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10779505</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M001054200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hess</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nudelman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Stamler</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>S-nitrosylation: spectrum and specificity</article-title><source>Nat Cell Biol</source><year>2001</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>E46</fpage><lpage>E49</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11175760</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35055152</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stamler</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nitrosylation. The prototypic redox-based signaling mechanism</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2001</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>675</fpage><lpage>683</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11572774</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(01)00495-0</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ahern</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Klyachko</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>cGMP and S-nitrosylation: two routes for modulation of neuronal excitability by NO</article-title><source>Trends Neurosci</source><year>2002</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>510</fpage><lpage>517</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12220879</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0166-2236(02)02254-3</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hogg</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The biochemistry and physiology of S-nitrosothiols</article-title><source>Annu Rev Pharmacol Toxicol</source><year>2002</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>585</fpage><lpage>600</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11807184</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.pharmtox.42.092501.104328</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>English</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Protein S-glutathiolation triggered by decomposed S-nitrosoglutathione</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>2004</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>4028</fpage><lpage>4038</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15049710</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/bi035924o</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lipton</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>YB</given-names></name><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Godzik</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bankston</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cysteine regulation of protein function &#x02013; as exemplified by NMDA-receptor modulation</article-title><source>Trends Neurosci</source><year>2002</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>474</fpage><lpage>480</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12183209</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0166-2236(02)02245-2</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>McMahon</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Stamler</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>S-nitrosylation in health and disease</article-title><source>Trends Mol Med</source><year>2003</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>160</fpage><lpage>168</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12727142</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1471-4914(03)00028-5</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hess</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SO</given-names></name><name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name><surname>Stamler</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Protein S-nitrosylation: purview and parameters</article-title><source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Bio</source><year>2005</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>150</fpage><lpage>166</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15688001</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ehret-Hilberer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nullans</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Aunis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Virmaux</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mono ADP-ribosylation of transducin catalyzed by rod outer segment extract</article-title><source>FEBS Lett</source><year>1992</year><volume>309</volume><fpage>394</fpage><lpage>398</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1516716</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0014-5793(92)80814-W</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lander</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sehajpal</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Novogrodsky</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nitric oxide signaling: a possible role for G proteins</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>1993</year><volume>151</volume><fpage>7182</fpage><lpage>7187</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8258718</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pozdnyakov</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Lloyd</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>VN</given-names></name><name><surname>Sitaramayya</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nitric oxide-regulated endogenous ADP-ribosylation of rod outer segment proteins</article-title><source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><year>1993</year><volume>192</volume><fpage>610</fpage><lpage>615</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8484771</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/bbrc.1993.1459</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hess</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Norden</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modification of cysteine residues within G(o) and other neuronal proteins by exposure to nitric oxide</article-title><source>Neuropharmacology</source><year>1994</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>1283</fpage><lpage>1292</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7870285</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0028-3908(94)90028-0</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pozdnyakov</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Margulis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sitaramayya</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Endogenous ADP-ribosylation of a G(alpha i) protein in bovine ciliary body is stimulated by nitric oxide</article-title><source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><year>1997</year><volume>235</volume><fpage>482</fpage><lpage>486</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9207181</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/bbrc.1997.6811</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miyamoto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Laufs</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Pardo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modulation of bradykinin receptor ligand binding affinity and its coupled G-proteins by nitric oxide</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1997</year><volume>272</volume><fpage>19601</fpage><lpage>19608</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9235967</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.272.31.19601</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McVey</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Howlett</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adenylyl cyclase, a coincidence detector for nitric oxide</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1999</year><volume>274</volume><fpage>18887</fpage><lpage>18892</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10383385</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.274.27.18887</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Naganuma</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Maekawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Murayama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nomura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of S-nitroso-cysteine on proteins that regulate exocytosis in PC12 cells: inhibitory effects on translocation of synaptophysin and ADP-ribosylation of GTP-binding proteins</article-title><source>Jpn J Pharmacol</source><year>2000</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>391</fpage><lpage>398</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11202610</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1254/jjp.84.391</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nishida</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Maruyama</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kontani</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagao</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurose</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>G alpha(i) and G alpha(o) are target proteins of reactive oxygen species</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2000</year><volume>408</volume><fpage>492</fpage><lpage>495</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11100733</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35044120</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Howlett</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nitric oxide selectively inhibits adenylyl cyclase isoforms 5 and 6</article-title><source>Cell Signal</source><year>2000</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>233</fpage><lpage>237</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10781930</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0898-6568(99)00082-0</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hudson</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name><name><surname>Corbett</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Howlett</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nitric oxide regulates adenylyl cyclase activity in rat striatal membranes</article-title><source>J Neurochem</source><year>2001</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>1279</fpage><lpage>1284</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11389178</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1471-4159.2001.00331.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Sand</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Batinik</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name><name><surname>Pfaffendorf</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>van Zwieten</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reactive oxygen species potentiate the negative inotropic effect of cardiac M2-muscarinic receptor stimulation</article-title><source>Naunyn-Schmiedebergs Arch Pharmacol</source><year>2001</year><volume>364</volume><fpage>166</fpage><lpage>171</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11534856</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s002100100442</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nishida</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schey</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Takagahara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kontani</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Katada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Urano</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagao</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurose</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Activation mechanism of Gi and Go by reactive oxygen species</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2002</year><volume>277</volume><fpage>9036</fpage><lpage>9042</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11781308</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M107392200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nozik-Grayck</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>McMahon</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name><surname>Dieterle</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Stamler</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Piantadosi</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pulmonary vasoconstriction by serotonin is inhibited by S-nitroso-glutathione</article-title><source>Am J Physiol Lung Cell Mol Physiol</source><year>2002</year><volume>282</volume><fpage>L1057</fpage><lpage>L1065</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11943671</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ostrom</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bundey</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Insel</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nitric oxide inhibition of adenylyl cyclase type 6 activity is dependent upon lipid rafts and caveolin signaling complexes</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2004</year><volume>279</volume><fpage>19846</fpage><lpage>19853</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15007069</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M313440200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laitinen</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>[35S]GTP&#x003b3;S Autoradiography: A powerful functional approach with expanding potential for neuropharmacological studies on receptors coupled to Gi family of G proteins</article-title><source>Current Neuropharmacology</source><year>2004</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>191</fpage><lpage>206</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/1570159043476819</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ostrom</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Head</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><name><surname>Gregorian</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Seasholtz</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Insel</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Localization of adenylyl cyclase isoforms and G protein-coupled receptors in vascular smooth muscle cells: expression in caveolin-rich and noncaveolin domains</article-title><source>Mol Pharmacol</source><year>2002</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>983</fpage><lpage>992</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12391260</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1124/mol.62.5.983</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bourova</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kostrnova</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hejnova</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Moravcova</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name><surname>Novotny</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Milligan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Svoboda</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>delta-Opioid receptors exhibit high efficiency when activating trimeric G proteins in membrane domains</article-title><source>J Neurochem</source><year>2003</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>34</fpage><lpage>49</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12641725</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B39"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>De Hoog</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Mann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Unbiased quantitative proteomics of lipid rafts reveals high specificity for signaling factors</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2003</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>5813</fpage><lpage>5818</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12724530</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0631608100</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B40"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Insel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Location, location, location</article-title><source>Trends Endocrinol Metab</source><year>2003</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>100</fpage><lpage>102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12670730</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1043-2760(03)00029-8</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B41"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laitinen</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Uri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Raidaru</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Miettinen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>[35S]GTP&#x003b3;S autoradiography reveals a wide distribution of Gi/o-linked ADP receptors in the nervous system: close similarities with the platelet P2YADP receptor</article-title><source>J Neurochem</source><year>2001</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>505</fpage><lpage>518</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11299313</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1471-4159.2001.00265.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B42"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vasiljev</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Uri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Laitinen</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>2-Alkylthio-substituted platelet P2Y12 receptor antagonists reveal pharmacological identity between the rat brain Gi-linked ADP receptors and P2Y12</article-title><source>Neuropharmacology</source><year>2003</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>145</fpage><lpage>154</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12814667</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0028-3908(03)00142-4</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B43"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Waeber</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vitro autoradiographic visualization of guanosine-5'-O-(3-[35S]thio)triphosphate binding stimulated by sphingosine 1-phosphate and lysophosphatidic acid</article-title><source>J Neurochem</source><year>1999</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>1212</fpage><lpage>1221</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10461914</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1471-4159.1999.0731212.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B44"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Capece</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Baghdoyan</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lydic</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Carbachol stimulates [35S]guanylyl 5'-(gamma-thio)-triphosphate binding in rapid eye movement sleep-related brainstem nuclei of rat</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>1998</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>3779</fpage><lpage>3785</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9570808</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B45"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Demarco</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Baghdoyan</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lydic</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential cholinergic activation of G proteins in rat and mouse brainstem: relevance for sleep and nociception</article-title><source>J Comp Neurol</source><year>2003</year><volume>457</volume><fpage>175</fpage><lpage>184</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12541317</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cne.10548</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B46"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gaston</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Reilly</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Drazen</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fackler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramdev</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Arnelle</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Mullins</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugarbaker</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chee</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Singel</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Endogenous nitrogen oxides and bronchodilator S-nitrosothiols in human airways</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>1993</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>10957</fpage><lpage>10961</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8248198</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B47"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kluge</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Gutteck-Amsler</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Zollinger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Do</surname><given-names>KQ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>S-nitrosoglutathione in rat cerebellum: identification and quantification by liquid chromatography-mass spectrometry</article-title><source>J Neurochem</source><year>1997</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>2599</fpage><lpage>2607</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9375694</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B48"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jalink</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hordijk</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Moolenaar</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Growth factor-like effects of lysophosphatidic acid, a novel lipid mediator</article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><year>1994</year><volume>1198</volume><fpage>185</fpage><lpage>196</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7819274</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B49"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Saffrich</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ansorge</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Just</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Receptor-mediated regulation of peroxisomal motility in CHO and endothelial cells</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>1999</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>5476</fpage><lpage>5485</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10523292</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/emboj/18.20.5476</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B50"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McAllister</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Stanton</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Salim</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Handford</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Beer</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Edg2 receptor functionality: gialpha1 coexpression and fusion protein studies</article-title><source>Mol Pharmacol</source><year>2000</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>407</fpage><lpage>412</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10908309</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B51"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ohlmann</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Laugwitz</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Nurnberg</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Spicher</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Cazenave</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Gachet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The human platelet ADP receptor activates Gi2 proteins</article-title><source>Biochem J</source><year>1995</year><volume>312</volume><fpage>775</fpage><lpage>779</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8554519</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B52"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jantzen</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Milstone</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Gousset</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Conley</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name><surname>Mortensen</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impaired activation of murine platelets lacking G alpha(i2)</article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><year>2001</year><volume>108</volume><fpage>477</fpage><lpage>483</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11489941</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI200112818</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B53"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lander</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hajjar</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Hempstead</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Mirza</surname><given-names>UA</given-names></name><name><surname>Chait</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Quilliam</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A molecular redox switch on p21(ras). Structural basis for the nitric oxide-p21(ras) interaction</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1997</year><volume>272</volume><fpage>4323</fpage><lpage>4326</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9020151</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.272.28.17810</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B54"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Selkirk</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Nahorski</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Challiss</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cell type-specific differences in the coupling of recombinant mGlu1alpha receptors to endogenous G protein sub-populations</article-title><source>Neuropharmacology</source><year>2001</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>645</fpage><lpage>656</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11311892</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0028-3908(00)00208-2</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B55"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kowalska</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dalvi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Prevost</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Brien</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Manning</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Poncz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucki</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Blendy</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Brass</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Loss of signaling through the G protein, Gz, results in abnormal platelet activation and altered responses to psychoactive drugs</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2000</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>9984</fpage><lpage>9989</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10954748</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.180194597</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B56"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaffrey</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Sawa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dexras1: a G protein specifically coupled to neuronal nitric oxide synthase via CAPON</article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>2000</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>183</fpage><lpage>193</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11086993</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0896-6273(00)00095-7</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B57"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jaffrey</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nitrosopeptide mapping: a novel methodology reveals s-nitrosylation of dexras1 on a single cysteine residue</article-title><source>Chem Biol</source><year>2002</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1329</fpage><lpage>1335</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12498886</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1074-5521(02)00293-4</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B58"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Qiao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Dorin</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dexras1 inhibits adenylyl cyclase</article-title><source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><year>2004</year><volume>316</volume><fpage>307</fpage><lpage>312</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15020218</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbrc.2004.02.049</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B59"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Prossnitz</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Dorin</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dexras1/AGS-1 inhibits signal transduction from the Gi-coupled formyl peptide receptor to Erk-1/2 MAP kinases</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2002</year><volume>277</volume><fpage>10876</fpage><lpage>10882</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11751935</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M110397200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B60"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takesono</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nowak</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Cismowski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Duzic</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Lanier</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Activator of G-protein signaling 1 blocks GIRK channel activation by a G-protein-coupled receptor: apparent disruption of receptor signaling complexes</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2002</year><volume>277</volume><fpage>13827</fpage><lpage>13830</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11842095</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M201064200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B61"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dunphy</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Greentree</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name><name><surname>Linder</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enrichment of G-protein palmitoyltransferase activity in low density membranes: in vitro reconstitution of Galphai to these domains requires palmitoyltransferase activity</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2001</year><volume>276</volume><fpage>43300</fpage><lpage>43304</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11557754</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M104275200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B62"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wedegaertner</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name><surname>Levis</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bourne</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Palmitoylation is required for signaling functions and membrane attachment of Gq alpha and Gs alpha</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1993</year><volume>268</volume><fpage>25001</fpage><lpage>25008</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8227063</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B63"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sprang</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>G proteins, effectors and GAPs: structure and mechanism</article-title><source>Curr Opin Struct Biol</source><year>1997</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>849</fpage><lpage>856</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9434906</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0959-440X(97)80157-1</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B64"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adam</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouvier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nitric oxide modulates beta(2)-adrenergic receptor palmitoylation and signaling</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1999</year><volume>274</volume><fpage>26337</fpage><lpage>26343</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10473590</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.274.37.26337</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B65"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Kubota</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Feron</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Opel</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Arstall</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Fishman</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Michel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Muscarinic cholinergic regulation of cardiac myocyte ICa-L is absent in mice with targeted disruption of endothelial nitric oxide synthase</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>1998</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>6510</fpage><lpage>6515</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9600997</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.95.11.6510</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B66"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dessy</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Balligand</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Feron</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dynamin mediates caveolar sequestration of muscarinic cholinergic receptors and alteration in NO signaling</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>2000</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>4272</fpage><lpage>4280</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10944110</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/emboj/19.16.4272</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B67"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maggio</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbier</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Toso</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Barletta</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Corsini</surname><given-names>GU</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sodium nitroprusside induces internalization of muscarinic receptors stably expressed in Chinese hamster ovary cell lines</article-title><source>J Neurochem</source><year>1995</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>943</fpage><lpage>946</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7616259</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B68"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abi-Gerges</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Szabo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Otero</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischmeister</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Mery</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>NO donors potentiate the beta-adrenergic stimulation of I(Ca,L) and the muscarinic activation of I(K,ACh) in rat cardiac myocytes</article-title><source>J Physiol</source><year>2002</year><volume>540</volume><fpage>411</fpage><lpage>424</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11956332</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/jphysiol.2001.012929</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B69"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dorsam</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name><surname>Kunapuli</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Central role of the P2Y12 receptor in platelet activation</article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><year>2004</year><volume>113</volume><fpage>340</fpage><lpage>345</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14755328</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI200420986</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B70"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tullett</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rees</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Shuker</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Gescher</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lack of correlation between the observed stability and pharmacological properties of S-nitroso derivatives of glutathione and cysteine-related peptides</article-title><source>Biochem Pharmacol</source><year>2001</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>1239</fpage><lpage>1247</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11705457</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0006-2952(01)00750-X</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B71"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Radomski</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Rees</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Dutra</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Moncada</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>S-nitroso-glutathione inhibits platelet activation in vitro and in vivo</article-title><source>Br J Pharmacol</source><year>1992</year><volume>107</volume><fpage>745</fpage><lpage>749</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1335336</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B72"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gordge M</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hothersall</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Noronha-Dutra</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence for a cyclic GMP-independent mechanism in the anti-platelet action of S-nitrosoglutathione</article-title><source>Br J Pharmacol</source><year>1998</year><volume>124</volume><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>148</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9630353</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.bjp.0701821</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B73"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Freedman</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Sauter</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Battinelli</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ault</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Knowles</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Loscalzo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Deficient platelet-derived nitric oxide and enhanced hemostasis in mice lacking the NOSIII gene</article-title><source>Circ Res</source><year>1999</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>1416</fpage><lpage>1421</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10381894</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B74"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aktas</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Honig-Liedl</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Geiger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibition of platelet P2Y12 and alpha2A receptor signaling by cGMP-dependent protein kinase</article-title><source>Biochem Pharmacol</source><year>2002</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>433</fpage><lpage>439</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12147294</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0006-2952(02)01113-9</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B75"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kou</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Igarashi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Michel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lysophosphatidic acid and receptor-mediated activation of endothelial nitric-oxide synthase</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>2002</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>4982</fpage><lpage>4988</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11939794</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/bi016017r</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B76"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karliner</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lysophospholipids and the cardiovascular system</article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><year>2002</year><volume>1582</volume><fpage>216</fpage><lpage>221</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12069831</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B77"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Siess</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Athero- and thrombogenic actions of lysophosphatidic acid and sphingosine-1-phosphate</article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><year>2002</year><volume>1582</volume><fpage>204</fpage><lpage>215</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12069830</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B78"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kokkola</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Foord</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Vakkuri</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Laitinen</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Important amino acids for the function of the human MT1 melatonin receptor</article-title><source>Biochem Pharmacol</source><year>2003</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>1463</fpage><lpage>1471</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12732358</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0006-2952(03)00113-8</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B79"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laitinen</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Selective detection of adenosine A1 receptor-dependent G-protein activity in basal and stimulated conditions of rat brain [35S]guanosine 5'-(gamma-thio)triphosphate autoradiography</article-title><source>Neuroscience</source><year>1999</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>1265</fpage><lpage>1279</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10338296</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0306-4522(98)00571-5</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B80"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kurkinen</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Koistinaho</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Laitinen</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gamma-35S]GTP autoradiography allows region-specific detection of muscarinic receptor-dependent G-protein activation in the chick optic tectum</article-title><source>Brain Res</source><year>1997</year><volume>769</volume><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>28</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9374269</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0006-8993(97)00663-X</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B81"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Savinainen</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>J&#x000e4;rvinen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Laine</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Laitinen</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Despite substantial degradation, 2-arachidonoylglycerol is a potent full efficacy agonist mediating CB(1) receptor-dependent G-protein activation in rat cerebellar membranes</article-title><source>Br J Pharmacol</source><year>2001</year><volume>134</volume><fpage>664</fpage><lpage>672</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11588122</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.bjp.0704297</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>



