<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="other"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">pmed</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosmed</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1549-1277</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1549-1676</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">16288553</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1297528</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.0020322</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Student Forum</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Other</subject><subject>Medical Education</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="System Taxonomy"><subject>Medical Education</subject><subject>Medical Careers</subject><subject>Academic Medicine</subject><subject>Medicine in Developing Countries</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Why Medical Students Are Crucial to the Future of Research in South Asia</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Student Forum</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Aslam</surname><given-names>Fawad</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="n3">&#x0002a;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shakir</surname><given-names>Murtaza</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Qayyum</surname><given-names>Muhammad Ahad</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><fn id="n1" fn-type="current-aff"><p>Fawad Aslam and Murtaza Shakir are final-year medical students at the Aga Khan University in Karachi, Pakistan. Fawad Aslam is also the vice president of Aga Khan University's Student Research Forum. Muhammad Ahad Qayyum is a final-year medical student at the Punjab Medical College in Faisalabad, Pakistan.</p></fn><fn id="n2" fn-type="COI-statement"><p>
<bold>Competing Interests:</bold> FA is the vice president of the Student Research Forum at Aga Khan University. MS and MAQ have declared that they have no competing interests.</p></fn><corresp id="n3">&#x0002a;To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <email>fawadaslam2&#x00040;hotmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>11</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>29</day><month>11</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><volume>2</volume><issue>11</issue><elocation-id>e322</elocation-id><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; 2005 Aslam et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2005</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract abstract-type="toc"><p>One long-term strategy for promoting health research in developing countries is to target medical students early in their careers.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><p>Health research is essential to improving health care [<xref rid="pmed-0020322-b1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Unfortunately, health research has a low priority in the developing world. In all disciplines of science and technology, India and Pakistan combined have 208 researchers per million citizens [<xref rid="pmed-0020322-b2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="pmed-0020322-b3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>], as compared to 4,526 researchers per million citizens in the United States [<xref rid="pmed-0020322-b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. The published research output from South Asia is small&#x02014;South Asian health researchers accounted for only 1.2&#x00025; of all papers within the Institute for Scientific Information database from 1992&#x02013;2001 [<xref rid="pmed-0020322-b5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Developing countries must therefore enhance their research capacity to efficiently address the growing burden of both communicable and non-communicable diseases [<xref rid="pmed-0020322-b6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>].</p><sec id="s2"><title>Engaging Medical Students in Health Research</title><p>One long-term strategy for promoting health research is to target medical students early in their careers. Most of the research to date on the effectiveness of such a strategy has been done in Western settings. This research has shown that research experience as a medical student is strongly associated with postgraduate research involvement [<xref rid="pmed-0020322-b7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="pmed-0020322-b8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].</p><p>Student research can also contribute to the published output of an institution. In Germany, for example, medical students authored 28&#x00025; of the publications of one institution, including first authorship in 7.8&#x00025; of papers [<xref rid="pmed-0020322-b9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Nothing can be more motivating for a student than to get published.</p><p>Even if the experience of doing research as a student does not lead to a later career in academic medicine, research experience can help improve students' skills in searching and critically appraising the medical literature, independent learning, and writing research papers [<xref rid="pmed-0020322-b10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="pmed-0020322-b11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Such exposure to research as a student can also help to identify future careers, establish important contacts, and secure better residency positions. Given the many benefits of doing a research project as a student, not surprisingly, 97&#x00025; of students considered research as a useful alternative to electives [<xref rid="pmed-0020322-b11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>].</p><p>Student research is not without its problems. Good mentorship, for example, is a vital component of effective student research, and inadequate mentoring can lead to discontentment with research. Other problems include lack of time, neglect of routine studies and deterioration of clinical skills due to more time being spent on research activities, and inadequate project management [<xref rid="pmed-0020322-b12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. The perceived competitiveness and greater demands of a career in academic medicine and lower salary compared to private practice may deter students from research. Another concern is that students may work simply as junior laborers with no role in designing the research or in critical thinking during the research process. For example, they may be told to review, say, 200 charts, and hand over the data to the principal investigator. Those who criticize medical student research would also argue that student papers are rarely cited, and thus are of limited utility.</p></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Student Research in South Asia</title><p>Student research is dependent on national research activity. Since there is still only a limited research infrastructure in many developing countries, this means that opportunities for medical student research are limited. Research is not considered a part of the medical curriculum in many of these countries.</p><p>In one Indian study, for example, 91&#x00025; of interns reported no research experience in medical school [<xref rid="pmed-0020322-b13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Thus, students in India rarely get exposed to research at this crucial stage in their academic development when such exposure could encourage further research after qualification. Faculty across South Asia themselves seldom engage in research owing to inadequate training in research, lack of incentives, work overload, poor pay, and minimal research demand in clinical practice from patients, fellow physicians, and policymakers. Consequently, students are deprived of mentors and role models. Medical training in general in South Asia does not emphasize the importance of research to medical practice. More than two-thirds of the postgraduate trainees at one Pakistani institution, for example, reported reading scientific journals only once in six months or more [<xref rid="pmed-0020322-b14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Taking Action</title><p>What can be done to increase medical students' involvement in research in South Asia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-0020322-g001">Figure 1</xref>)? First and foremost, the research infrastructure needs extensive improvement, and the meager funding for research must be boosted, so that there will be a healthier research culture in which students can participate. There also need to be effective international agreements to halt the &#x0201c;brain drain&#x0201d; of academic clinicians from low-income to high-income countries [<xref rid="pmed-0020322-b15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], since this migration robs medical students of role models.</p><fig id="pmed-0020322-g001" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Factors That Can Help Encourage South Asian Medical Students to Choose a Career in Academic Medicine</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pmed.0020322.g001"/></fig><p>In addition, students need to be &#x0201c;sensitized&#x0201d; to research&#x02014;that is, they should be made aware of why research is so crucial to health care. The medical curriculum must begin to incorporate and emphasize evidence-based medicine. To stimulate students' interest in research, we believe that they should undertake a mandatory course on research skills, along with a compulsory community project. Such projects undertaken in the primary-care setting will allow students to execute all the steps of a research project, from conception to final report writing, thereby narrowing the gap between theory and practice. Elective slots should be available to those students who are interested in pursuing further research. Young researchers need to be encouraged, for example, by being awarded scholarships. Prior research experience should be seen as valuable when recruiting postgraduate trainees. Only when students are sensitized in this way&#x02014;and provided that they also have sufficient flexibility and security to pursue a career in academic medicine&#x02014;will they choose career paths involving research.</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Conclusion</title><p>At our own medical schools, we believe that medical students are becoming more enthusiastic about getting involved in research, which is encouraging. Some efforts to promote student research are already underway in South Asia. For example, student conferences and research workshops are being held in major cities of Pakistan, and some medical journals, including the <italic>Journal of Postgraduate Medicine</italic> (India) and the <italic>Journal of the College of Physicians and Surgeons of Pakistan</italic>, have introduced student sections. The students at Aga Khan University in Pakistan, which has a well-established research infrastructure, have won awards for their projects at international student conferences and have published widely in indexed journals. Given the right amount of support, medical students' interest in research can be successfully nurtured.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>We are grateful to Fahim Jafary for critically reviewing the manuscript and being a worthy mentor. We are also thankful to our colleagues Abdul Waheed and Abdul Moiz Khan for providing valuable input.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="n4" fn-type="other"><p>
<bold>Citation:</bold> Aslam F, Shakir M, Qayyum MA (2005) Why medical students are crucial to the future of research in South Asia. PLoS Med 2(11): e322.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pmed-0020322-b1"><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>Global Forum for Health Research</collab><source>10/90 report on health research 2003&#x02013;2004</source><year>2004</year><publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Global Forum for Health Research</publisher-name><comment>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.globalforumhealth.org/site/002__What%20we%20do/005__Publications/001__10%2090%20reports.php">http://www.globalforumhealth.org/site/002__What%20we%20do/005__Publications/001__10%2090%20reports.php</ext-link>. Accessed 26 September 2005</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="pmed-0020322-b2"><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization Institute for Statistics</collab><source>Country profile: India</source><year>2005</year><publisher-loc>Quebec</publisher-loc><publisher-name>United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization Institute for Statistics</publisher-name><comment>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.uis.unesco.org/countryprofiles/html/EN/countryProfile_en.aspx?code=3560.htm">http://www.uis.unesco.org/countryprofiles/html/EN/countryProfile_en.aspx?code=3560.htm</ext-link>. Accessed 26 September 2005</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="pmed-0020322-b3"><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization Institute for Statistics</collab><source>Country profile: Pakistan</source><year>2005</year><publisher-loc>Quebec</publisher-loc><publisher-name>United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization Institute for Statistics</publisher-name><comment>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.uis.unesco.org/countryprofiles/html/EN/countryProfile_en.aspx?code=5860.htm">http://www.uis.unesco.org/countryprofiles/html/EN/countryProfile_en.aspx?code=5860.htm</ext-link>. Accessed 26 September 2005</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="pmed-0020322-b4"><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization Institute for Statistics</collab><source>Country profile: United States</source><year>2005</year><publisher-loc>Quebec</publisher-loc><publisher-name>United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization Institute for Statistics</publisher-name><comment>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.uis.unesco.org/countryprofiles/html/EN/countryProfile_en.aspx?code=8400.htm">http://www.uis.unesco.org/countryprofiles/html/EN/countryProfile_en.aspx?code=8400.htm</ext-link>. Accessed 26 September 2005</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="pmed-0020322-b5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sadana</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>D'Souza</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hyder</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Chowdhury</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Importance of health research in South Asia</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year>2004</year><volume>328</volume><fpage>826</fpage><lpage>830</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15070643</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pmed-0020322-b6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buddha</surname><given-names>Basnyat</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajapaksa</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cardiovascular and infectious diseases in South Asia: The double whammy</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year>2004</year><volume>328</volume><fpage>781</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15070612</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pmed-0020322-b7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Segal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lloyd</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Houts</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Stillman</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Jungas</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The association between students' research involvement in medical school and their postgraduate medical activities</article-title><source>Acad Med</source><year>1990</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>530</fpage><lpage>533</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2383337</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pmed-0020322-b8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reinders</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kropmans</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen-Schotanus</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Extracurricular research experience of medical students and their scientific output after graduation</article-title><source>Med Educ</source><year>2005</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>237</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15679693</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pmed-0020322-b9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cursiefen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Altunbas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Contribution of medical student research to the Medline-indexed publications of a German medical faculty</article-title><source>Med Educ</source><year>1998</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>439</fpage><lpage>440</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9743810</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pmed-0020322-b10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Houlden</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Raja</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Collier</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Waugh</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Medical students' perceptions of an undergraduate research elective</article-title><source>Med Teach</source><year>2004</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>659</fpage><lpage>661</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15763861</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pmed-0020322-b11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frishman</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Student research projects and theses: Should they be a requirement for medical school graduation?</article-title><source>Heart Dis</source><year>2001</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>140</fpage><lpage>144</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11975783</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pmed-0020322-b12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Diez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Arkenau</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer-Wentrup</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The German medical dissertation&#x02014;Time to change?</article-title><source>Acad Med</source><year>2000</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>861</fpage><lpage>863</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10965870</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pmed-0020322-b13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chaturvedi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Aggarwal</surname><given-names>OP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Training interns in population-based research: Learners' feedback from 13 consecutive batches from a medical school in India</article-title><source>Med Educ</source><year>2001</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>585</fpage><lpage>589</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11380862</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pmed-0020322-b14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aslam</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Qayyum</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahmud</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Qasim</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Haque</surname><given-names>IU</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Attitudes and practices of postgraduate medical trainees towards research&#x02014;A snapshot from Faisalabad</article-title><source>J Pak Med Assoc</source><year>2004</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>534</fpage><lpage>536</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15552293</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pmed-0020322-b15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dovlo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Taking more than a fair share? The migration of health professionals from poor to rich countries</article-title><source>PLoS Med</source><year>2005</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>e109</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.0020109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15916458</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
