<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Virol J</journal-id><journal-title>Virology Journal</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1743-422X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15801983</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1082913</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1743-422X-2-26</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1743-422X-2-26</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Ultrastructural studies on dengue virus type 2 infection of cultured human monocytes</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mosquera</surname><given-names>Jesus A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>mosquera99ve@yahoo.com</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hernandez</surname><given-names>Juan Pablo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>asisca_jph@cantv.net</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Valero</surname><given-names>Nereida</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>nere98@hotmail.com</email></contrib><contrib id="A4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Espina</surname><given-names>Luz Marina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>lmespina@hotmail.com</email></contrib><contrib id="A5" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>A&#x000f1;ez</surname><given-names>German J</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>ganezg@yahoo.com</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Seccion de Inmunologia y Biologia Celular, Instituto de Investigaciones Clinicas "Dr. Americo Negrette". Facultad de Medicina, Universidad del Zulia, Maracaibo, Venezuela</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Instituto de Investigaciones Biologicas. Facultad de Medicina, Universidad del Zulia, Maracaibo, Venezuela</aff><aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Seccion de Virologia, Instituto de Investigaciones Clinicas "Dr. Americo Negrette". Facultad de Medicina, Universidad del Zulia, Maracaibo, Venezuela</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2005</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>3</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><volume>2</volume><fpage>26</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.virologyj.com/content/2/1/26"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>5</day><month>3</month><year>2005</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>31</day><month>3</month><year>2005</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2005 Mosquera et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2005</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Mosquera et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>
               Mosquera
               A
               Jesus
               
               mosquera99ve@yahoo.com
            </dc:author><dc:title>
            Ultrastructural studies on dengue virus type 2 infection of cultured human monocytes
         </dc:title><dc:date>2005</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>Virology Journal 2(1): 26-. (2005)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1743-422X(2005)2:1&#x0003c;26&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1743-422X</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Early interaction of dengue virus and monocyte/macrophages could be an important feature for virus dissemination after its initial entry via the mosquito vector. Since ultrastructural analysis of this interaction has not been reported, dengue type 2 (DEN2) virus-infected human monocyte cultures were studied at 1, 2, 4 and 6 hours after infection.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Typical dengue particles and fuzzy coated viral particles were 35 to 42 nm and 74 to 85 nm respectively. Viruses were engulfed by phagocytosis and macropicnocytosis leading to huge vacuoles and phagosomes inside the monocytes. Interaction of monocytes with DEN2 virus induced apoptosis, characterized by nuclear condensation and fragmentation, cellular shrinkage, blebbing and budding phenomena and phagocytosis of apoptotic cells by neighboring monocytes. This finding was confirmed by TUNEL. Ultrastructural features associated to DEN2 virus replication were not observed.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>These data suggest that clearance of the virus by monocytes and cellular death are the main features during the initial interaction of DEN2 virus and monocytes and this could be important in the rapid elimination of the virus after infection by mosquito vector.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Monocyte/macrophages are one of the major target of dengue virus and responsible for virus dissemination after its initial entry via the mosquito vector [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. A detailed study of this early virus-monocyte interaction by electron microscopy has not been performed. Since ultrastructural study is one of the important analysis in the interaction virus-cell, we performed electron microscopy studies in DEN2 virus- infected human monocytes at 1, 2, 4 and 6 hours of culture, in order to get more information regarding to morphological aspects of virus, virus replication, cellular alterations and apoptosis.</p></sec><sec><title>Results and discussion</title><sec><title>Virus particles</title><p>After 1 hour of culture numerous virus particles were observed attached to plasma membrane, free in the extracellular space and in cytoplasmic vacuoles inside monocytes. The predominant viral particles in infected monocyte cultures were typical viral particles of 35 to 42 nm in diameter (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A, 1B, 1C</xref>). Small number of fuzzy coated viral particles (74 to 85 nm) showed a core similar to the usual dengue particles, but they had an envelope with projections, looking like a fuzzy coat (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1D, 1E</xref>). Typical DEN2 virus particles observed in this study were similar to those reported in mosquito cell cultures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. Similar fuzzy coated virus particles have been described by Barth et al [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>] in DEN2 Brazilian virus-infected C6/36 cell cultures. DEN2 virus used to infect monocytes was New Guinea C virus strain and isolated from virus-infected C6/36 cell cultures, suggesting that the fuzzy coated viral particles are a common feature of DEN2 virus. In addition, fuzzy coated virus particles have also been detected in other virus infections, but their significance remains obscure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. The presence of DEN2 virus antigens in the cytoplasm of infected monocytes was also investigated by direct immunofluorescence. Using a monoclonal antibody against DEN2 virus a diffuse and patchy patterns of fluorescence were observed in the cytoplasm (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1F</xref>). It was also observed small electron dense structures (75 to 105 nm) that we called in this report "dense particles" (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). In some instances, these dense particles showed a center similar to dengue virus nucleocapsid covered by membrane layers and an electron dense envelope (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2B, 2C</xref>). Dense particles could represent viral particles covered by a homogenous electron dense material. Since, it was not observe viral replication ultrastructural features in infected monocyte cultures, the contribution of monocytes to the formation of this viral envelope is unclear. However, electron dense material observed on the dense particles could represent a protein matrix obtained after virus replication on mosquito cells. In this regard, a range of variation in one virus after experimental isolation has been reported in other virus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. In general extracellular viral particles were found as single particles and viral particles forming aggregates were uncommon. Viruses attached to the cell surface and free in the extracellular space were engulfed by mechanisms of phagocytosis or macropicnocytosis via typical cytoplasmic processes (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). During phagocytosis or macropicnocytosis virus particles were engulfed alone or together with cellular debris, so that, intracytoplasmic vacuoles and vesicles containing viral particles or large phagosomes full of an electron dense matrix, cellular debris and viral particles may soon be found inside the cells (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). These data suggest a passive phase leading to virus inactivation. In this regard, previous reports have shown that human immunodeficiency virus entering human macrophages by phagocytosis is noninfectious [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. Infection of Kupffer cells by dengue virus resulted in no viral progeny [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>] and only a small proportion of the monocyte population supports replication of DEN2-virus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. Smooth membrane coated vacuoles containing viral particles, membrane fragments and moderated electron dense material were also observed (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref>). In some instances, cytoplasmic vesicles containing one or more viral particles showed disruption of the membrane leading to direct communication of viral particles with the cytoplasm (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1C</xref>), however, no morphological virus-related structures could be detected free in the cytoplasm. Features related to viral replication such as virus absorption by penetrating the cell membrane or by endocytosis by clathrin-coat vesicles, virion precursors on rough endoplasmic reticulum or its cisternae, inside Golgi complex, cytoplasm free viral cores or viral budding from cell membrane were not observed in monocytes. Previous report has shown that DEN2 virus can persistently infect transformed lymphoblastoid cells keeping an intact morphology without any indication of active viral replication [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. Our data show no indications of viral replication and the induction of apoptosis (see below) makes monocytes unlikely source of persistent dengue virus infection.</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Electron microscope morphological observations of DEN2 virus particles. A) Typical viral particle in the extracellular environment (arrow; bar: 200 nm). B) Viral particles engulfed in an intracytoplasmic vacuole (arrow; bar: 50 nm). C) Membrane disruption of a vesicle containing a virus (arrow; bar: 100 nm). D) Fuzzy coated viral particles occur in the extracellular space (arrows; bar: 200 nm) E) A fuzzy coated viral particle showing an envelope with projections (arrow; bar: 100 nm). F) Immunofluorescence staining of DEN2 viral antigens at 4 h of culture. A diffuse and patchy pattern of fluorescence was observed in the cytoplasm (arrows). &#x000d7; 1000.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1743-422X-2-26-1"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Electron microscope morphological observations of dense particles. A) Dense particles close to the cell surface (arrow; bar: 200 nm). B) Aggregated dense particles in the extracellular space (arrow). Note the nucleocapsid like center and the electron dense envelopes (bar: 100 nm). C) Dense particles showing a nucleocapsid like center surrounded by membrane layers and an electron dense material (arrow; bar: 100 nm).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1743-422X-2-26-2"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Ultrastructural features of DEN2 virus-infected monocytes. Prominent formation of cellular lamellipods (A) and engulfing of virus by macropicnocytosis (B) and phagocytosis (C) are observed 1 hour after infection. Note the presence of virus (arrows) and cellular debris in the extracellular space. (A and C bars: 1 &#x003bc;m; B bar: 500 nm).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1743-422X-2-26-3"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Ultrastructural features of DEN2 virus-infected monocytes. A) DEN2 virus-infected monocytes after 2 hours of infection. Observe the presence of virus particles in the extracellular space, on cellular plasma membrane and inside cytoplasmic vacuoles (arrows; bar: 1 &#x003bc;m). B) Monocyte showing huge empty vacuoles and vacuoles containing nuclear debris and myelin structures at 4 hours of culture (arrows; bar: 500 nm). C) Monocyte showing cytoplasmic phagosomes containing cellular debris and viral particles (arrow; bar: 200 nm). D) A huge vacuole containing numerous viral particles and cellular debris (arrow; bar: 500 nm).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1743-422X-2-26-4"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Monocyte cultures</title><p>As assessed by electron microscopy, monocytes showed high degree of activation after 1 hour of infection. One of the most prominent features in DEN2 virus-infected monocytes was the intense expression of short and long plasma membrane processes (lamellipods), in most of the cases engulfing virus particles, cellular debris and apoptotic cells (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). Engulfing of extracellular elements by pseudopods was also observed (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3C</xref>). As consequence of this activity, small and huge intracytoplasmic vacuoles and phagosomes containing cellular debris, virus particles and myelin like structures in various stages of digestion were observed (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). In some instances, phagosomes or vacuoles were surrounded by lysosomes. (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref>). Our data show similar ultrastructural findings than those obtained from DEN1 virus-infected Kupffer cells at 1 hour of culture [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>], suggesting a similar cellular response against DEN virus for monocytes and macrophages. In DEN2 virus- infected monocytes mitochondria increased in number and size (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>) and cytoplasmic structures resembling diverse degrees of mitochondrial alterations (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5C, 5D</xref>) were found. Mitochondria were observed in association with lysosomal granules and vacuoles containing membranous debris, consistent with mitochondrial digestion by lysosomes. Infected monocytes showed extensive proliferation of endoplasmic reticulum and lysosomal granules (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5E</xref>). Cytoplasmic projections associated with cellular movement (uropods) were also observed (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5F</xref>). It was not observed syncytia, however as shown in figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref> a curious distribution of monocytes in DEN2 virus-infected cultures was found. Empty spaces were surrounded by monocytes looking like "acinar" structures. In some instances, a linear electron dense material occurred between the empty space and monocytes, suggesting a previous presence of biological material in the lumen. These findings could represent a reactive response of monocytes around virus particles, cellular debris or virus-infected cells.</p><fig position="float" id="F5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Ultrastructural features of DEN2 virus-infected monocytes at 4 hours. A) Cytoplasmic vacuole containing cellular debris in close association with lysosomal granules (arrows; bar 200 nm). B) Increased number and size of mitochondria in the cytoplasm of monocyte (bar: 1 &#x003bc;m). C) Mitochondrial degeneration: normal mitochondria (1), early step of degeneration (2) and late step of degeneration (3). Lysosomal granule (large arrow; bar: 500 nm). D) Lysosomes (arrows) in association with mitochondria an autophagosome containing probably mitochondrial debris (bar: 200 nm). Intense lysosomal and vesicular accumulation in the cytoplasm (bar: 200 nm). F) Leukocyte locomotion; note the formation of uropods (arrows; bar: 2 &#x003bc;m).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1743-422X-2-26-5"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Ultrastructural features of DEN2 virus-infected monocytes. "Acinar" like structure. A and B show empty spaces surrounded by monocytes. (A bar 1 &#x003bc;m; B bar: 2 &#x003bc;m). C) In some instances, a moderated electron dense material also delimited the empty space (bar: 1 &#x003bc;m) D) Inset from C shows a lineal electron dense material (large arrow) delimiting the empty space, beyond viral particles (small arrow) and a monocyte are observed (bar: 200 nm).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1743-422X-2-26-6"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Cellular Death</title><p>After 1 hour of infection, electron microscopy revealed cells with morphological features of apoptosis, however, previous report has shown apoptosis in Kupffer cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>] after 24 hours of DEN-1 virus infection, suggesting different susceptibility of monocyte and macrophage to virus-induced apoptosis or different viral apoptotic effect depending of DEN virus strain. In this regard, the susceptibility to DEN virus infection depending of the differentiation state of monocytic cells has been reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. Apoptotic cells showed chromatin margination in nuclei, nuclear fragmentation, condensation and retraction of cytoplasm and blebbing and budding phenomena (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>). Numerous vesicles, some of which appeared to be releasing to the extracellular space were observed (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7D</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8E</xref>). The budding phenomenon observed on apoptotic cells led to the formation of apoptotic bodies containing several types of organelles, including nuclear fragments and high number of vesicles. This could represent a common aspect in virus-induced apoptosis, since the formation of vesicular apoptotic bodies has also been reported in monocytic/macrophage lineage infected with bovine leukaemia virus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. Blebbing of the plasma membrane was also observed in apoptotic cells. The surface blebbing has also been described in other viral infections and related to a role in the direct cell-to-cell spread of the virus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>] or associated with increased cellular permeability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. Some apoptotic cells showed long cisternae structures alongside with the plasma membrane suggesting cytoplasmic splitting (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8G</xref>). We have no explanation for this finding, but it could be due to the fusion of neighboring cytoplasmic vesicles. Apoptotic cells also showed bundles of intracellular microfibrils (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7G</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7H</xref>), which resembled the contractile structures observed in fibroblasts and some glomerular cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. These structures could be related to the apoptotic process, since, filamentous material, clumping of tonofilaments and MyD88 protein association with fibrillar aggregates containing beta-actin have been associated with apoptosis and apoptotic bodies formation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. Huge phagosomes were observed in the cytoplasm of apoptotic cells (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7E</xref>), and in some instances, vacuoles containing few viral particles associated with an electron dense material were observed (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8E</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8F</xref>). The presence of phagosomes in the cytoplasm of apoptotic cells suggests previous active phagocytosis. Contrarily to non apoptotic cell only scarce number of vacuoles containing virus and degraded material was observed in apoptotic cells, suggesting that the absorption of products of viral degradation could trigger cell death. Several apoptotic monocytes and apoptotic bodies were ingested by neighboring healthy monocytes leading to the formation of huge vacuolar compartments containing different grades of cellular digestion (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8D</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9</xref>). Apoptosis could avoid the release of viral particles [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>] and together with the phagocytosis and digestion of apoptotic cells represent mechanisms to prevent viral progeny [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]. The ultrastructural apoptosis finding was confirmed by detecting intrachromosomal DNA strand breaks using the TUNNEL assay. Untreated cultures showed low levels of TUNEL positive cells compared to higher levels observed in infected monocyte cultures (Control: 0.9 &#x000b1; 0.15. Infected at 1 h: 6.2 &#x000b1; 1.5; 2 h: 6.4 &#x000b1; 1.8; 4 h: 7.4 &#x000b1; 2.3; 6 h: 16.8 &#x000b1; 3.3; mean &#x000b1; SE) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8H</xref>). In addition to apoptosis, a cellular alteration accompanied by cellular swelling, plasma membrane disruption and karyolysis was observed (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10</xref>). Plasma membrane disruption led to increased amount of swelled organelles and cellular debris in the extracellular space and the formation of "ghost cells" (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10C</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10D</xref>), with further engulfing by monocytes (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10E</xref>). These lysed cells could represent nonphagocytized apoptotic cells that have lost the membrane integrity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>]. Since, noninfected controls or heat-inactivated DEN2 virus-infected monocytes showed scarce number of apoptotic cells, apoptosis seems to be linked to virus infection. We can not rule out the role of apoptosis inducer proteins in the apoptosis observed in this study. In this regard, increased production of Tumor Necrosis Factor has been reported in DEN2 virus-infected macrophages which could lead to apoptosis. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>].</p><fig position="float" id="F7"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Ultrastructural features of apoptotic cells in DEN2 virus-infected monocytes at 4 hours. A) The typical features of apoptosis are observed in several monocytes (arrows; bar: 2 &#x003bc;m). B) Apoptotic cell showing cellular shrinkage, nuclear condensation and bundles of microfibrils (arrows; bar: 500 nm). C) Monocyte with dense remnant nucleus and surface blebbing (arrow; bar 500 nm). D) Apoptotic cell showing intense cytoplasmic vacuolization (bar: 500 nm). E) Phagosome in the cytoplasm of apoptotic cell (arrow; bar: 200 nm). F) Nuclear fragmentation in apoptotic cell (arrow). Note beside a healthy monocyte (bar: 2 &#x003bc;m). G) Segment of apoptotic cell showing numerous bundles of cytoplasmic fibrils (bar: 200 nm). H) Bundles of microfibrils (arrow) in the cytoplasm of apoptotic cell (bar: 100 nm).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1743-422X-2-26-7"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F8"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>Ultrastructural features of apoptotic cells in DEN2 virus-infected monocytes. A) Apoptotic bodies containing nuclear fragments and several organelles (bar: 2 &#x003bc;m). B) Vesicular apoptotic body formation (bar: 1 &#x003bc;m). C) Vesicular apoptotic body in the extracellular space (arrow). Note a partial engulfing of the apoptotic body by monocyte processes (bar: 500 nm). D) Monocyte showing an engulfed vesicular apoptotic body (arrow) and intense accumulation of phagosomes containing cellular and viral material in several degrees of digestion (bar: 2 &#x003bc;m). E) Cytoplasm of apoptotic cell showing intense accumulation of vesicles and releasing of vesicular contents to the extracellular space (black arrows). Note the presence of a vacuole containing viral particles and electron dense material (white arrow; bar: 200 nm). F) Vacuole containing partial digested viral particles (arrow) in the cytoplasm of apoptotic cell (bar: 200 nm). G) Cisternae formation alongside the plasma membrane (arrows). Note a vesicle close to these formations (small arrow; bar: 200 nm). H) TUNEL staining for apoptosis in monocyte cultures infected for 4 hours with DEN-2 virus. Intense green fluorescence was observed in apoptotic nuclei (arrow). &#x000d7; 400.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1743-422X-2-26-8"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F9"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p>Ultrastructural features of apoptotic cells in DEN2 virus-infected monocytes. Different phases of phagocytosis and digestion of apoptotic cells. A) Engulfment of apoptotic cell (arrow) by a monocyte (bar: 2 &#x003bc;m). B) A huge phagosome containing a morphological intact apoptotic cell (arrow; bar: 1 &#x003bc;m). C and D show phagosomes (arrows) containing a partial digested apoptotic cells (C bar: 500 nm; D bar: 1 &#x003bc;m).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1743-422X-2-26-9"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F10"><label>Figure 10</label><caption><p>Ultrastructural features of apoptotic cells in DEN2 virus-infected monocytes at 6 hours. A) Swelling of organelles and membrane compartments in an apoptotic cell (bar: 1 &#x003bc;m). B) Release of cellular content from a swelling apoptotic cell. Note numerous viral particles (arrow) probably already present in the extracellular space (bar: 1 &#x003bc;m). C) Advance phase of cellular swelling (ghost cell) showing disruption of plasma membrane (arrow; bar: 1 &#x003bc;m). D) Ghost cell surrounding by numerous viral particles (arrow; bar: 500 nm). E) Monocyte engulfing cellular debris (arrow). Note the presence of a phagosome containing partial digested cellular material (bar: 1 &#x003bc;m).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1743-422X-2-26-10"/></fig></sec></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>This <italic>in vitro </italic>study indicates that the interaction of DEN2 virus with monocytes results in virus engulfment and apoptosis, suggesting that monocytes may protect against DEN2 virus infection by eliminating the virus particles and virus-infected apoptotic cells and this could be important in the rapid clearance of the initial virus input.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Preparation of virus stock and virus titration</title><p>DEN-2 virus strain New Guinea C was propagated in C6/36HT mosquito cells that were cultured in Eagle's MEM medium containing 10% FBS prior to viral monocyte infection. The virus culture medium was harvested after 5 days of incubation and after removal of cell debris by centrifugation, the virus supernatant was aliquoted and stored at -70&#x000b0;C until used. Virus was titrated by plaque formation assays on VERO cells. Cells were planted at 1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6 </sup>cells / well in 24-well plates and subsequently, serial dilutions of virus were added and the mixtures were incubated at 37&#x000b0;C for 7 days. Afterwards, the plaques were visualized by staining with a dye solution composed of 1% crystal violet. Virus concentrations are given as plaque-forming units (PFU) / ml. Virus stock was free of endotoxin as determined by limulus amebocyte lysate assay.</p></sec><sec><title>Monocyte cultures</title><p>Monocytes were isolated from heparinized peripheral blood obtained from human healthy volunteers (N = 5) by density centrifugation over 1.077 Histopaque (Sigma Chemical Co, St. Louis, MO). Healthy individuals were informed about the study procedures and their consents were obtained before enrollment in the investigation following the ethical committee guidelines of the bioethical committee of Medical School (Universidad del Zulia, Maracaibo, Venezuela). Total mononuclear leukocytes recovered from the interface were washed and resuspended in RPMI 1640, 10 % fetal bovine serum and penicillin/streptomycin. Afterwards, 300 &#x003bc;l / well of a cellular suspension (4 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6 </sup>cells / ml) were layered on 8 -well plastic chamber slides (Nunc, Roskilde, Denmark) or 10 ml on 75 cm<sup>3 </sup>tissue culture flasks and incubated for 3 hours at 37&#x000b0;C and 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. Non adherents cells were washed out with warm medium and adhered cells were used for experiments.</p></sec><sec><title>Infection of monocyte cultures</title><p>Monocytes were infected with a virus concentration of 4 &#x000d7; 10<sup>4 </sup>PFU / ml (MOI: 0.08) and incubated for 1, 2, 4 and 6 hours at 37&#x000b0;C and 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. Controls represent monocytes cultured with supplemented medium without virus. In addition, monocyte cultures were incubated with heat inactivated dengue virus (56&#x000b0;C, 30 min.) at 4 &#x000d7; 10<sup>4 </sup>PFU / ml for 6 hours.</p></sec><sec><title>Electron microscopy studies</title><p>Monocytes planted on 75 cm<sup>3 </sup>tissue culture flasks were incubated for 1, 2, 4 and 6 hours with DEN-2 virus (4 &#x000d7; 10<sup>4 </sup>PFU/ml). Afterwards, cells were detached by incubation with a solution of 0.01% EDTA and by using a cell scraper. After centrifugation, infected monocytes and controls were fixed with 2% glutaraldehyde in 0.1 M cacodylate buffer, pH 7.3. Cells were postfixed with 1% osmium tetraoxide, dehydrated in a series of ethanol and embedded in Epon 812. Samples were cut into ultrathin sections, stained with uranyl acetate followed by lead citrate and examined in an electron microscopy JEM 1010 (Jeol, Japan).</p></sec><sec><title>Direct immunofluorescence for DEN-2 antigens</title><p>Experiments were performed in 8-well plastic chamber slides. Monocytes were infected by incubation with DEN-2 virus as described above. Monocytes were washed in PBS and fixed with cold acetone for 5 minutes. Intracellular viral antigens were detected by a direct immunofluorescence assay using a fluorescein-conjugated DEN-2 virus-specific monoclonal antibody (CDC, Fort Collins, CO. USA).</p></sec><sec><title>TUNNEL assay</title><p>The method for nick end -labeling of apoptotic cells was adapted from that of Gavrieli et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>] with a commercial kit (Pharmigen, San Diego, CA). Adhered monocytes were treated according to the protocol provided with this kit. The assay is based on the preferential binding of the FITC-dUTP by terminal deoxynucleotidyl transferase to 3' OH ends of the DNA. Positive apoptotic nuclei were assessed by fluorescence microscopy (Axioskop, Zeiss, Germany).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors certify that they have not entered into any agreement that could interfere with their access to the data on the research, or upon their ability to analyze the data independently, to prepare manuscripts, and to publish them. Authors have not any conflicts of interest.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>JM designed, coordinated and draft the manuscript. JPH performed the ultrastructural procedures. NV, LME, GA performed TUNEL assay, virus isolation, monocytes cultures. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Dr. Dwane Gubler (Fort Collins, Centre for Disease Control, Colorado) for the monoclonal antibody anti-dengue virus type 2 that made the viral immunofluorescence studies reported here possible.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gubler</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dengue and dengue hemorrhagic fever</article-title><source>Clin Microbiol Rev</source><year>1998</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>480</fpage><lpage>496</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9665979</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Halstead</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pathogenesis of dengue: challenges to molecular biology</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1988</year><volume>239</volume><fpage>476</fpage><lpage>481</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3277268</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Halstead</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Rourke</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Allinson</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dengue virus and mononuclear phagocytes. II. Identity of blood and tissue leukocytes supporting in vitro infection</article-title><source>J Exp Med</source><year>1977</year><volume>146</volume><fpage>218</fpage><lpage>229</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">195000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.146.1.218</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barth</surname><given-names>OM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Replication of dengue viruses in mosquito cell cultures. A model from ultrastructural observation</article-title><source>Mem Inst Oswaldo Cruz</source><year>1992</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>565</fpage><lpage>574</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1343672</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barth</surname><given-names>OM</given-names></name><name><surname>de Castro-Cortes</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lampe</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>da Costa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Farias</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Filho</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ultrastructural aspects of viral replication in one fatal case and several other isolates from a dengue type 2 outbreak in Rio de Janeiro</article-title><source>Mem Inst Oswaldo Cruz</source><year>1994</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7823815</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name><surname>Goller</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Thormar</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Norrby</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fuzzy material surrounding measly virus nucleocapsids identified as matrix protein. Brief report</article-title><source>Arch Virol</source><year>1987</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>163</fpage><lpage>168</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3579607</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF01313735</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ohki</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A potvirus in nature: indistinct populations</article-title><source>Arch Virol Suppl</source><year>1992</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>217</fpage><lpage>219</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1450740</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pauza</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Human immunodeficiency virus infection of T cells and monocytes proceeds via receptor-mediated endocytosis</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>1988</year><volume>107</volume><fpage>959</fpage><lpage>968</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3262112</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.107.3.959</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marianneau</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Steffan</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Royer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Drouet</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaeck</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirn</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Deubel</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Infection of primary cultures of human Kupffer cells by dengue virus: No viral progeny synthesis, but cytokine production is evident</article-title><source>J Virol</source><year>1999</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>5201</fpage><lpage>5206</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10233989</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hotta</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiharta</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hotta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Homma</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dengue type 2 virus infection in human peripheral blood monocyte cultures</article-title><source>Microbiol Immunol</source><year>1984</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>1099</fpage><lpage>1109</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6521666</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takasaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Takada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurane</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Electron microscopic study of persistent dengue virus infection: analysis using a cell line persistently infected with Dengue-2 virus</article-title><source>Intervirology</source><year>2001</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>48</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11223720</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000050030</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O'Sullivan</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Killen</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The differentiation state of monocytic cells affects their susceptibility to infection and the effects of infection by dengue virus</article-title><source>J Gen Virol</source><year>1994</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>2387</fpage><lpage>2392</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8077937</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Domenech</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Goyache</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Llames</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Paya</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Suarez</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomez-Lucia</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vitro infection of cells of the monocytic/macrophage lineage with bovine leukaemia virus</article-title><source>J Gen Virol</source><year>2000</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>109</fpage><lpage>118</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10640548</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karimi</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name><surname>Schloemer</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilde</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Accumulation of chlamydial lipopolysaccharide antigen in the plasma membranes of infected cells</article-title><source>Infect Immun</source><year>1989</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>1780</fpage><lpage>1785</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2470679</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Papadimitriou</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Drachenberg</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Newkirk</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Trump</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name><name><surname>Silverberg</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>"Thanatosomes": a unifying morphogenetic concept for tumor hyaline globules related to apoptosis</article-title><source>Hum Pathol</source><year>2001</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>894</fpage><lpage>895</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11521238</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/hupa.2001.26453</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fish</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Michael</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Vernier</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Human glomerular cells in tissue culture</article-title><source>Lab Invest</source><year>1975</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>330</fpage><lpage>341</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">51134</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gebhart</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cytoid bodies in human</article-title><source>Wien Klin Wochenschr Suppl</source><year>1976</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1069406</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jaunin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Burns</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tschopp</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Fakan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ultrastructural distribution of the death-domain-containing MyD88 protein in HeLa cells</article-title><source>Exp Cell Res</source><year>1998</year><volume>243</volume><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>75</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9716450</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/excr.1998.4131</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kanerva</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Electron microscopic observations of dyskeratosis, apoptosis, colloid bodies and fibrillar degeneration after skin irritation with dithranol</article-title><source>J Cutan Pathol</source><year>1990</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2319038</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koyama</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukumori</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Irie</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Adachi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Physiological significance of apoptosis in animal virus infection</article-title><source>Microbes Infect</source><year>2000</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>1111</fpage><lpage>1117</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10967291</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1286-4579(00)01265-X</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Falasca</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergamini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Serafino</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Balabaud</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Dini</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Human Kuffer cell recognition and phagocytosis of apoptotic peripheral blood lymphocytes</article-title><source>Exp Cell Res</source><year>1996</year><volume>224</volume><fpage>152</fpage><lpage>162</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8612680</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/excr.1996.0123</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Persidsky</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Steffan</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gendrault</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hurtrel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Roger</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Stutte</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Muchmore</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Aubertin</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirn</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Permissiveness of Kupffer cell for simian immunodeficiency virus (SIV) and morphological changes in the liver of rhesus monkeys at different periods of SIV infection</article-title><source>Hepatology</source><year>1995</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>1215</fpage><lpage>1225</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7737626</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0270-9139(95)90040-3</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hockenbery</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Defining apoptosis</article-title><source>Am J Pathol</source><year>1995</year><volume>146</volume><fpage>16</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7856725</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carr</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hocking</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Bunting</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gamble</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Burrell</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Supernatants from dengue virus type-2 infected macrophages induce permeability changes in endothelial cell monolayers</article-title><source>J Med Virol</source><year>2003</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>521</fpage><lpage>528</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12601760</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jmv.10340</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gavriel</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ben-Sasson</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of programed cell death in situ via specific labeling of nuclear DNA fragmentation</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>1992</year><volume>119</volume><fpage>493</fpage><lpage>501</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1400587</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.119.3.493</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>



