<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="letter"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Environ Health Perspect</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Environ. Health Perspect</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Environmental Health Perspectives</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0091-6765</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1552-9924</issn><publisher><publisher-name>National Institue of Environmental Health Sciences</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1247596</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ehp0112-a0796b</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Perspectives</subject><subj-group><subject>Correspondence</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Conflicts of Interest: Gulson&#x02019;s Response</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gulson</surname><given-names>Brian</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Graduate School of the Environment Macquarie University Sydney, New South Wales, Australia E-mail:
<email>bgulson@gse.mq.edu.au</email></aff><author-notes><fn><p>The author declares he has no competing financial interests.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>10</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><volume>112</volume><issue>14</issue><fpage seq="b">A796</fpage><lpage>A796</lpage><permissions><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/" license-type="public-domain"><license-p>Publication of EHP lies in the public domain and is therefore without copyright. All text from EHP may be reprinted freely. Use of materials published in EHP should be acknowledged (for example, ?Reproduced with permission from Environmental Health Perspectives?); pertinent reference information should be provided for the article from which the material was reproduced. Articles from EHP, especially the News section, may contain photographs or illustrations copyrighted by other commercial organizations or individuals that may not be used without obtaining prior approval from the holder of the copyright. </license-p></license></permissions><related-article related-article-type="letter" id="d35e58" vol="112" page="A794b" ext-link-type="pmc"/></article-meta></front><body><p>We commend the Center for Science in the Public Interest (CSPI) for their investigation into conflicts of interest statements in leading scientific and medical journals, but we take exception to our inclusion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1-ehp0112-a0796b">Gulson et al. 2004</xref>) as an example of providing misinformation to <italic>EHP</italic>.</p><p>Goozner&#x02019;s sweeping statement that my colleague had previously received research funding, compensation, or stood to gain financially from Pasminco Ltd. is highly inaccurate. We received no research funding, compensation, or financial gain from the company to undertake this study. In fact, if Goozner had read even the abstract of our article, he would have noted that the findings were detrimental to the company, as the dominant source of lead in the environment and children probably derived from smelter emissions. Furthermore, the smelter closed in September 2003 and the company no longer exists. With respect to the association of my colleague, Karen Mizon, to her husband&#x02019;s company and the (consulting) work undertaken for Pasminco Ltd., the work [an International Organization for Standardization (ISO) Guide 25 accreditation assessment of the company&#x02019;s on-site laboratory (ISO/International <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2-ehp0112-a0796b">Electrotechnical Commission 1990</xref>)] was undertaken by the owner for the accreditation body while he was employed by a federal government research organization, and he was not paid for this audit.</p></body><back><ref-list><title>Reference</title><ref id="b1-ehp0112-a0796b"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Gulson</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Mizon</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Vimpani</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Identification of sources of lead in children in a primary zinc&#x02013;lead smelter environment</article-title><source>Environ Health Perspect</source><volume>112</volume><fpage>52</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14698931</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b2-ehp0112-a0796b"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>ISO/International Electrotechnical Commission</collab> 1990. ISO Guide 25: General Requirements for the Competence of Calibration and Testing Laboratories. 3rd ed. Geneva: International Organization for Standardization.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
