<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="letter"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Environ Health Perspect</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Environ. Health Perspect</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Environmental Health Perspectives</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0091-6765</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1552-9924</issn><publisher><publisher-name>National Institue of Environmental Health Sciences</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1247646</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ehp0112-a0866a</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Perspectives</subject><subj-group><subject>Correspondence</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Children&#x02019;s Exposure to OP Pesticides: Response to Fenske et al.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Coronado</surname><given-names>Gloria D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ehp0112-a0866a"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>Beti</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ehp0112-a0866a"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af1-ehp0112-a0866a">Cancer Prevention Research Program, Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center, Seattle, Washington, E-mail:
<email>gcoronad@fhcrc.org</email></aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Griffith</surname><given-names>William C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-ehp0112-a0866a"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af2-ehp0112-a0866a">Department of Environmental and Occupational Health Sciences, School of Public Health and Community Medicine, University of Washington, Seattle, Washington</aff><author-notes><fn><p>The authors declare they have no competing financial interests.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>11</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><volume>112</volume><issue>15</issue><fpage seq="a">A866</fpage><lpage>A866</lpage><permissions><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/" license-type="public-domain"><license-p>Publication of EHP lies in the public domain and is therefore without copyright. All text from EHP may be reprinted freely. Use of materials published in EHP should be acknowledged (for example, ?Reproduced with permission from Environmental Health Perspectives?); pertinent reference information should be provided for the article from which the material was reproduced. Articles from EHP, especially the News section, may contain photographs or illustrations copyrighted by other commercial organizations or individuals that may not be used without obtaining prior approval from the holder of the copyright. </license-p></license></permissions><related-article related-article-type="letter" id="d35e78" vol="112" page="A865c" ext-link-type="pmc"/></article-meta></front><body><p>In our article (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1-ehp0112-a0866a">Coronado et al. 2004</xref>), we reported a higher proportion of urine samples containing detectable levels of the organophosphate (OP) pesticide urinary metabolite dimethylthiophosphate (DMTP) from children of farmworkers who reported having thinned plants, compared with urine samples from children of non-thinners. We reported the detection frequency for individual dimethyl metabolites, not a composite score for the detection of multiple dimethyl metabolites. We thank Fenske et al. for their additional analyses showing slightly higher, though not significant, concentrations of urinary DMTP in children of thinners versus non-thinners.</p><p>We knew that assessing detection frequencies would provide only a preliminary view of a more complex pattern of exposure; thus, we specifically stated in the &#x0201c;Methods&#x0201d; section of our paper that the analysis was exploratory in nature. We examined job task as a factor possibly associated with high exposure to pesticides because job task is closely linked with regulatory policy. We understood that if substantial differences in the percentage of detectable samples existed between groups further exploration would be warranted.</p><p>This type of analysis follows the logic put forth by others in the field of exposure assessment. For example, Fenske et al. highlight that <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2-ehp0112-a0866a">Barr et al. (2004)</xref>&#x02014;in the same issue of <italic>EHP</italic> in which our article was published&#x02014;provided detection frequencies of OP pesticide urinary metabolites in older children (6&#x02013;11 years of age) from the general population. Barr et al. reported a detection frequency for DMTP of 69%, with a limit of detection of 0.18 &#x003bc;g/L. In our study we matched children (2&#x02013;6 years of age) with an adult agricultural worker in the same home. Among the children matched to farmworkers who reported thinning, we observed a detection frequency for urinary DMTP of 92%, with a limit of detection of 1.1 &#x003bc;g/L.</p><p>We agree with Fenske et al. that a more in-depth analysis is warranted and thank them for their interest and recommendations.</p></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="b1-ehp0112-a0866a"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Coronado</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Strong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffith</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name><surname>Islas</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Agricultural task and exposure to organophosphate pesticides among farmworkers</article-title><source>Environ Health Perspect</source><volume>112</volume><fpage>142</fpage><lpage>147</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14754567</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b2-ehp0112-a0866a"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Barr</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Bravo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Weerasekera</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Caltabiano</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitehead</surname><given-names>RD</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Olsson</surname><given-names>AO</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Concentrations of dialkyl phosphate metabolites of organophosphorus pesticides in the U.S. population</article-title><source>Environ Health Perspect</source><volume>112</volume><fpage>186</fpage><lpage>200</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14754573</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
