<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Bioinformatics</journal-id><journal-title>BMC Bioinformatics</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2105</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">16225682</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1280923</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1471-2105-6-254</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-6-254</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Prediction of &#x003b2;-barrel membrane proteins by searching for restricted domains</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mirus</surname><given-names>Oliver</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>mirus@lrz.uni-muenchen.de</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schleiff</surname><given-names>Enrico</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>schleiff@lrz.uni-muenchen.de</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Botanisches Institut der Ludwig-Maximilians-Universit&#x000e4;t M&#x000fc;nchen, Menzinger Str. 67, 80638 M&#x000fc;nchen, Germany</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2005</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>10</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><fpage>254</fpage><lpage>254</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2105/6/254"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>6</month><year>2005</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>10</month><year>2005</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2005 Mirus and Schleiff; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2005</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Mirus and Schleiff; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>
               Mirus
               Oliver
               
               mirus@lrz.uni-muenchen.de
            </dc:author><dc:title>
            Prediction of &#x003b2;-barrel membrane proteins by searching for restricted domains
         </dc:title><dc:date>2005</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>BMC Bioinformatics 6(1): 254-. (2005)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1471-2105(2005)6:1&#x0003c;254&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1471-2105</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>The identification of &#x003b2;-barrel membrane proteins out of a genomic/proteomic background is one of the rapidly developing fields in bioinformatics. Our main goal is the prediction of such proteins in genome/proteome wide analyses.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>For the prediction of &#x003b2;-barrel membrane proteins within prokaryotic proteomes a set of parameters was developed. We have focused on a procedure with a low false positive rate beside a procedure with lowest false prediction rate to obtain a high certainty for the predicted sequences. We demonstrate that the discrimination between &#x003b2;-barrel membrane proteins and other proteins is improved by analyzing a length limited region. The developed set of parameters is applied to the proteome of <italic>E. coli </italic>and the results are compared to four other described procedures.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Analyzing the &#x003b2;-barrel membrane proteins revealed the presence of a defined membrane inserted &#x003b2;-barrel region. This information can now be used to refine other prediction programs as well. So far, all tested programs fail to predict outer membrane proteins in the proteome of the prokaryote <italic>E. coli </italic>with high reliability. However, the reliability of the prediction is improved significantly by a combinatory approach of several programs. The consequences and usability of the developed scores are discussed.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Genomes of numerous organisms are sequenced. Computer-assisted assignment of coding regions of the organism of interest is the first important step for the understanding of the complex proteomic network [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Even though the quality of such predictions will be satisfying in future, the knowledge of the sequences of the gene products alone will not provide insight into their function or localization in the cell. In addition, the emphasis has switched from the study of individual molecules to a large-scale, high-throughput examination of genes and gene products of an organism with the aim of assigning their functions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>] and placing them into the complex biochemical networks. One kind of information comes from the structural classification of gene products. Since genome and proteome projects result in a rapid increase of information, the biochemical analysis has to be accomplished by <italic>in silico </italic>predictions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. One of the central questions is the localization of proteins since up to 50% of the proteins of a cell have to traverse at least one membrane in order to reach their place of function within organellar compartments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. In the past, several prediction programs have been developed for this purpose [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. However, the analysis of the intracellular localization of a protein is not only limited to the question to which organelle the protein is targeted. One important functional aspect is the distribution of the protein within this cell compartment. For some sub-organellar compartments like thylakoids predictions can be performed based on the targeting signal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>].</p><p>However, to date no differentiation of the signal is found for most sub-organellar localizations. So far, various approaches exist to identify helical transmembrane proteins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. More recently, however, the focus was shifted slightly to include the prediction of &#x003b2;-barrel membrane proteins. Initially, structure prediction was applied with reasonable success when proteins already known to form &#x003b2;-barrel structures were modeled [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. Now, four alternative directions are used in order to newly identify &#x003b2;-barrel proteins out of a genomic/proteomic data set. In the first approach, sequence profile based HMMs for predicting &#x003b2;-barrel membrane proteins were developed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. The second methodology is based on the alternating hydrophobicity as a measure for &#x003b2;-barrel transmembrane segments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. Thirdly, the structural data of the &#x003b2;-barrel membrane proteins were statistically analyzed and certain criteria developed for a linear prediction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. The fourth methodology is based on a modified k-nearest neighbor algorithm of the whole sequence amino acid composition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. Recently, the combination of several independent procedures for &#x003b2;-barrel membrane protein prediction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>] or their combination with other procedures, e.g. signal sequence prediction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>], was employed to improve the prediction quality.</p><p>To evaluate the performance of the developed procedures, test pools are commonly used to derive parameters that discriminate proteins of interest from those of structurally different classes. To avoid an overrepresentation of certain protein families, sequences are removed until each pair of proteins in the pool shares a degree of identity below a certain user defined threshold. Several algorithms have been published to solve this global optimization problem [e.g. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]]. Based on such test pools a comparison of the above mentioned strategies revealed a differential behavior. For example, Deng and co-workers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>] demonstrated that the linear predictor has a very low false positive but a high false negative rate. In contrast, a broader comparison of the predictors performed by Bagos and co-workers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>] manifested that the different predictors perform with a similar quality of about 25% false prediction.</p><p>We now improved the linear prediction by implementing new parameters and alterations of the previously established parameters based on test pools to increase the reliability and to avoid manual selection. Here, our main goals were to maintain a very low false positive rate and to reduce the high false negative rate of about 51% as reported by Deng and co-workers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>] for the original prediction method by Wimley [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. We present parameters for &#x003b2;-barrel membrane protein identification and their prediction performance on the proteome of the prokaryote <italic>E. coli</italic>.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>First, the published set of parameters (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>] was used to analyze proteomic data. The parameter set is defined as following (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>): the statistical values of the probability for an amino acid to be present in either the lipid tail or head group region and facing the membrane or channel interior in membrane-inserted &#x003b2;-strands were taken from Wimley [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. The &#x003b2;-strand length for the calculation of the exact &#x003b2;-strand score (EBSS, see Methods) and for the hairpin score (HPS) was chosen to be 10 amino acids following the original argumentation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. The loop length for calculation of the HPS was set to cover the range from the initial strand up to 14 amino acids distance. Previously, a minimal loop length of four [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>] or five amino acids [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>] was considered. For the calculation of the &#x003b2;-barrel score (BBS) of a protein the selection criterion for the HPS value was set to &#x0003e;6.0. For the calculation of the &#x003b2;-strand number (BSN) all independent EBSS peaks &#x0003e;2.0 were counted. For the final selection of &#x003b2;-barrel proteins, all proteins with a BBS of at least 0.7 and all proteins with a BSN above 13 were collected [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. For comparison, the amount of sequences predicted to be &#x003b2;-barrel membrane proteins of the <italic>E. coli </italic>proteome using this parameter set was analyzed. Employing the original proposed set &#x02013; selecting all proteins with a BBS greater than or equal to 1.0 &#x02013; about ~4% proteins of the <italic>E. coli </italic>proteome were selected [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. Applying the modified set [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>], about 12.2% of all sequences of the <italic>E. coli </italic>proteome were predicted to form a membrane inserted &#x003b2;-barrel. The larger number observed with the new criteria might represent an increase of the false positive prediction. Especially the introduction of the BSN criterion, even though essential for a reduction of the false negative rate of &#x003b2;-barrel membrane protein selection in eukaryotic background, revealed the prediction of soluble proteins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. As a consequence, we have focused on the BBS and BSN to refine the prediction procedure without altering the calculation of the EBSS.</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>The selection criteria</bold>. (A) Schematic view of the scores for prediction. (B) The amount of sequences in all test pools with 0 or 1 transmembrane helix (TMH) predicted by TMHMM. (C) The amount of sequences in the pools with NOM proteins (lane 1) greater than 79 amino acids (lane 2) and with less than 2 predicted transmembrane helices (lane 3).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2105-6-254-1"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Summary of the parameters for &#x003b2;-barrel prediction</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="center">score<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center">definition of the parameter<sup>b</sup></td><td align="center">value used<sup>c</sup></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center">EBSS</td><td align="center">&#x003b2;-strand length</td><td align="center">10 aa</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">Core region</td><td align="center">4 aa</td></tr><tr><td align="center">BSN<sup>d</sup></td><td align="center">Number of individual peaks</td><td align="center">EBSS &#x0003e;2.0</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">&#x003b2;-strand length</td><td align="center">10 aa</td></tr><tr><td align="center">HPS</td><td align="center">&#x003b2;-strand length</td><td align="center">10 aa</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">Loop length</td><td align="center">0&#x02013;14 aa<sup>d</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="center">BBS</td><td align="center">HPS cut off</td><td align="center">&#x0003e;6.0</td></tr><tr><td align="center">BBS275<sup>d</sup></td><td align="center">HPS cut off</td><td align="center">&#x0003e;6.0</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">Sliding window</td><td align="center">275 aa</td></tr><tr><td align="center">BSHS225<sup>d</sup></td><td align="center">EBSS cut off for strands</td><td align="center">&#x0003e;2.0</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">Sliding window</td><td align="center">225 aa</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>For detailed descriptions see text. <sup>a </sup>... The different intermediate scores necessary for final calculation of the &#x003b2;-barrel score; <sup>b </sup>... the scores are calculated by various physicochemical assumptions; <sup>c </sup>... the parameters for the different scores were used as suggested by Wimley, if not stated differently [14]; <sup>d </sup>... described in here</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><sec><title>Preceding parameters for selection</title><p>Three global rules were defined for all subsequent predictions. First, at least 8 transmembrane &#x003b2;-strands [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>] are required to form a &#x003b2;-barrel embedded in a lipid bilayer. In general, the average length of a single transmembrane &#x003b2;-strand is 10 amino acids [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. Therefore, a membrane inserted &#x003b2;-barrel contains at least 80 amino acids and consequently the first cut off defined is a rejection of all sequences below 80 amino acids (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1C</xref>, Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). Second, we found that a pre- or post-selection by TMHMM [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>] improves the performance. Previously was suggested, that two predicted transmembrane helices are an indication of a helical membrane protein [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]. Therefore, sequences with more than one predicted transmembrane helix are considered as helical anchored and rejected from the &#x003b2;-barrel prediction (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1C</xref>; Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). Here, the reliability of this step is defined by the false positive rate of TMHMM in regard to &#x003b2;-barrel membrane proteins. However, screening the PSort OM (outer membrane) test pool, PilQ, probably a &#x003b2;-barrel membrane protein involved in the assembly or modification of pili [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>], is &#x02013; besides two small cysteine-rich proteins &#x02013; the only protein with more than one predicted transmembrane helix. Third, in order to select a sequence as a &#x003b2;-barrel membrane protein all scores defined in the following have to be above zero.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>The new parameter set for linear prediction</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="center">Parameter</td><td align="center">old<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center">new<sup>b</sup></td><td align="center">new<sup>c</sup></td><td align="center">new<sup>d</sup></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center">aa</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center" colspan="3">&#x0003e;79</td></tr><tr><td align="center">TMHMM</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;1</td><td align="center" colspan="3">&#x0003c;2</td></tr><tr><td align="center">BSN</td><td align="center">&#x0003e;13</td><td align="center" colspan="3">&#x0003e;10</td></tr><tr><td align="center">BSN/aa</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center" colspan="3">&#x0003e;0.026</td></tr><tr><td align="center">BBS275</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">&#x0003e;2.5</td><td align="center">&#x0003e;1.35</td><td align="center">&#x0003e;1.35</td></tr><tr><td align="center">BSHS225</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">&#x0003e;0.12</td><td align="center">&#x0003e;0.11</td><td align="center">&#x0003e;0.04</td></tr><tr><td align="center">BBS</td><td align="center">&#x0003e;0.7</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Shown are the parameters used in here for linear prediction (new). They are compared to previously used parameters (old). <sup>a </sup>...values as previously described [15], <sup>b </sup>...values for a prediction with 0% false positive rate (BBS275 OR BSHS225), <sup>c </sup>...values for prediction with lowest false prediction rate considering independent selection by BBS275 and BSHS225 (OR), <sup>d </sup>...values for prediction with lowest false prediction rate considering dependent selection by BBS275 and BSHS225 (AND).</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Control of the incorporated &#x003b2;-strand number</title><p>One of the selection criteria for membrane &#x003b2;-barrel proteins was based on the &#x003b2;-strand number (BSN) of the proteins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. The previous BSN was calculated by selecting each individual region with EBSS values above 2.0. Hence, in a stretch of 10 amino acids considered as &#x003b2;-strand several counts can exist if values above 2.0 are separated by values equal or less than 2.0. We changed this algorithm as follows. The first predicted strand now starts at the amino acid with the highest EBSS. The preceding and succeeding nine amino acids are excluded from the search for the highest EBSS in the remaining values to account as starting amino acid of another strand. The &#x003b2;-strand selection procedure stops when no EBSS above 2.0 is left or all amino acids have been assigned to &#x003b2;-strand or pre-&#x003b2;-strand regions.</p><p>Hence, the number of counted strands is reduced in prokaryotic sequences (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A</xref>). In addition, analyzing the BSN in regard to the sequence length of the proteins revealed a clear dependence on the amino acid length (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2B</xref>). For most of the sequences of the <italic>E. coli </italic>proteome (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A</xref>, grey line, about 89%) at least one strand is proposed documenting that a selection by strand appearance alone is not possible. This might be understood as ~2% (2.001*10<sup>11</sup>) of all possible amino acid combinations (1.024*10<sup>13</sup>) analyzing a 10 amino acid window for the EBSS calculation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>] lead to a value above 2.0. Assuming a random distribution within an amino acid sequence, one peak exists about every 60 amino acids. Taking the previous result [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>] suggests an even higher number of selected strands leading to the over-representation of large proteins in the first selection, which had to be excluded manually. Analyzing the ratio between BSN and sequence length of the proteins revealed that for most of the sequences of the <italic>E. coli </italic>proteome (56%) one to three membrane inserted &#x003b2;-strands per 200 amino acids are predicted. As the amino acids within sequences are not entirely randomly distributed, the amino acid stretch is found to be a little longer than in the statistical calculation. However, the result is in line with the discussion above and further documents that BSN selection should be controlled by the statistical occurrence of &#x003b2;-strands.</p><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>The BSN selection</bold>. (A) The relationship between BSN calculated by the old and new procedure is shown for the sequences of <italic>E. coli </italic>(circle, bottom x-axis). The percentage of sequences with a certain BSN is shown as line plot (top x-axis). (B) The sequence length (in amino acids) dependence of the new BSN for sequences of <italic>E. coli </italic>is shown. (C-D) Sequences with a BSN value above 6 (solid), 8 (dashed), 10 (dashed-dotted) or 12 (dotted) were selected from the PDB (C) or PSort (D) pools. Subsequently, for the generated sequences pools the percentage of false positive selected sequences from NOM protein pools (black lines) and the false negative selected sequences from OM protein pools (grey lines) in relation to the BSN/aa cut off was determined. (E) The numbers of structurally determined strands and of predicted strands are shown; the line indicates a similar detection value. (F) The amount of strands predicted at identical position (maximum 1 amino acid mismatch; identical), of strands predicted at identical or overlapping position (maximum 5 amino acids mismatch; overlap) and the amount of false negative and false positive predicted strands (false) is shown.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2105-6-254-2"/></fig><p>To establish the selection criteria, we analyzed several test pools (described in Methods). First, the percentage of selected sequences from the sequence pools containing non-barrel proteins (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2C,D</xref>, black lines) with different BSN cut offs in relation to the BSN/aa cut off was determined. For these proteins, a BSN selection cut off of 10 in combination with a BSN/aa cut off of 0.026 results in a 0% false positive selection (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2C,D</xref>). This corresponds to one peak of the EBSS above 2.0 every 40 amino acids, which is above the calculated statistical expected frequency (see above). Previously, the existence of at least one transmembrane &#x003b1;-helix per 100 amino acids was defined as cut off for helical transporters [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>]. Comparing the length of the &#x003b2;-strand (10 amino acids on average) and of the membrane inserted helix (20&#x02013;24 amino acids) as well as the number of the inserted membrane segments (statistically membrane &#x003b2;-barrels contain at least twice as many membrane inserted segments compared to helical transporters) supports the defined BSN/aa score of 0.026. This set of parameters leads to a selection of all sequences in the PDB pool of &#x003b2;-barrel transmembrane proteins (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2C</xref>, grey). For the sequences in the PSort pool of OM proteins a false negative rate of at least 43% is achieved (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2D</xref>, grey dotted). However, the further selection by BBS reduces the false negative rate as described below.</p><p>We next analyzed whether the new algorithm for BSN calculation could be used for the generation of topological models of the analyzed proteins. As already discussed above, an over prediction of strands is obtained, especially for larger proteins (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2E</xref>). A detailed analysis of the strands predicted (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2F</xref>) revealed a 68% identical positioning allowing one amino acid mismatch and 80% overlapping positioning of the strands requiring at least five amino acids overlap between structural determined and predicted strands. However, the rate of false positioned strands (false negative and false positive selected strands) is 45%. This analysis suggests that the positioning is not as much the problem as the over prediction and the prediction should be combined with the analysis of other physicochemical parameters.</p></sec><sec><title>Development of a new criterion based on the localization of the pore-forming domain</title><p>Detailed analysis and topological modeling revealed that the pore-forming regions are mostly located within a compact domain (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref>). Prokaryotic pore-forming proteins/domains are typically of a size between 30 and 35 kDa. The topological models based on the solved structures of OmpF and Nalp are shown as examples (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref>). Guided by this observation, the scores were now calculated for a defined region of the sequences. We used different scanning windows starting with 75 amino acids as it is below the smallest possible pore unit as discussed above and incremented the window size in steps of 25 amino acids. This window is subsequently moved across the protein and the highest calculated score was selected. For sequences with less amino acids than the window size, the BBS value of the entire sequence is considered. The false positive rates for the combined pools of the non-&#x003b2;-barrel proteins and the false negative rates for the combined pools of &#x003b2;-barrel proteins for each BBS calculation window for different BBS-x (x reflects window size) cut off values were calculated.</p><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>Analysis of the BBS and BSHS</bold>. (A) The &#x003b2;-strand locations of a <italic>N. meningitidis </italic>(NalP) and an <italic>E. coli </italic>(OmpF) OM protein are shown. The window for calculating the BBS or a domain based BBS (BBS-x) is indicated. (B-C) The false prediction rate for BBS-x (B) or BSHS-x (C) calculation using different amino acid windows and different cut off scores is shown. The regions with the lowest false prediction rates (black) for the three times weighted pool of the NOM proteins is shown. (D) The percentage of sequences above a certain threshold value of BBS275 minus BBS is shown for the sequences of <italic>E. coli</italic>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2105-6-254-3"/></fig><p><italic>In vivo</italic>, a ratio between soluble and helical membrane proteins of at least 10:1 is expected [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]. It is further reasonable to assume that cells do not contain more &#x003b2;-barrel membrane proteins compared to helical membrane proteins. Indeed, other publications discuss a &#x003b2;-barrel membrane protein content within the entire proteome of 2 to 4% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. However, our pools represent a ratio of 3.8:1 of NOM (non-outer membrane) to OM proteins. To match the proteomic situation, the false positive prediction rate of the NOM proteins was weighted three times higher than the false negative prediction rate of the OM proteins (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref>). Hence, a region with lowest false prediction in windows of 250 to 375 amino acids and a BBS-x score of 0.6 to 1.0 could be obtained (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref>). The lowest false prediction rate was achieved utilizing a window of 275 amino acids with a cut off value of 0.8. Therefore, for the subsequent analysis the BBS is replaced by the BBS in a 275 amino acid window (BBS275). Analysis of the score performance when applied to sequences from <italic>E. coli </italic>(Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3D</xref>) shows, that about 70% of all sequences have a smaller BBS275 compared to the old BBS even though the highest value obtained for BBS275 of <italic>E. coli </italic>sequences is similar to the highest BBS value (not shown).</p><p>Guided by the development and performance of the new BSN score, we developed and analyzed a new score taking into account the alternating hydrophobicity for each predicted strand. Here, for each predicted transmembrane &#x003b2;-strand its alternating hydrophobicity according to equation 1 (E1) was calculated and multiplied with its EBSS value (E2). The final score BSHS (&#x003b2;-strand based hydrophobicity score) is calculated according to equation 3 (E3). The analysis of the performance of the score was performed as described for BBS275. Here, we identified a window of 225 amino acids as best performing (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3C</xref>). This is in line with a homo-oligomeric complex formation of most of the &#x003b2;-barrel membrane proteins, since strands on the protein-protein interface do not necessarily reveal an alternating hydrophobicity as the strands involved in complex formation are not exposed to the membrane lipids [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Development of scores for the linear predictor</title><p>After development of three scores for the linear predictor (BSN, BSHS225 and BBS275) we went on to establish selection procedures. They include the three discussed preceding steps by size, TMHMM [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>] prediction and score analysis as discussed above.</p><p>First, scores for the selection with a low false positive rate had to be established. Hence, the cut offs of BSN and BSN/aa, 10 and 0.026, warrant a low false positive selection according to the analysis of the test pools (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2C,D</xref>; Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). Analyzing the BBS275 and BSHS225 distribution of the NOM proteins in the test pools revealed cut off values of 2.5 and 0.12 (independent selection, BBS275 OR BSHS225, Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4A</xref>, Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>), respectively. This procedure selects 62.5% of the OM proteins of the test pools and therefore, the false negative prediction rate is 37.5%.</p><fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><bold>Score definition for the linear predictor</bold>. (A) The false positive rate for the NOM protein pool in dependence on the BBS275 cut off (grey) or BSHS225 cut off (black) was calculated. (B, C) The false positive selection rate for the NOM protein pool and the false negative rate of the OM protein pool was calculated for a sliding window for BBS275 and BSHS225 considering BSN&#x0003e;10 and BSN/aa&#x0003e;0.026 as preselection rule. The false prediction rate was calculated using a three times higher weight of the false positive rate of NOM proteins. In (B) the false prediction rates of the individual selection by BBS275 and BSHS225 is shown. In (C) the false prediction rate of the dependent selection by BBS275 and BSHS225 is shown.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2105-6-254-4"/></fig><p>However, a 0% false positive predictor does not perform with a low false negative prediction rate. We therefore went on to derive scores for the lowest false prediction rate as well. Since the BSN algorithm leads to an over-prediction of strands, we considered the BSN:BSN/aa selection as an initial step and did not alter the cut off values for selection. Subsequently, the selection by the two scores was performed individually by each score (OR selection) or in combination of both scores (AND selection). Again, we weighted the false positive rate of the NOM pools three times higher as the false negative rate of the OM proteins for the discussed reason. Analyzing the selection performance by the individual BBS275 and BSHS225 (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4B</xref>, Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>) revealed a score cut off combination of 1.35 and 0.11, respectively. BBS275 and BSHS225 in combination (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4C</xref>, Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>) result in cut off values of 1.35 and 0.04, respectively. For both procedures a false negative rate of 27.5% and a false positive rate of about 1.2% were obtained based on the analyzed test pools.</p></sec><sec><title>Comparison of predictors applied to proteome wide prediction</title><p>To further confirm the quality of the developed cut off values we analyzed their performance by prediction of &#x003b2;-barrel proteins from the prokaryotic <italic>E. coli </italic>proteome. Here, 108, 160 or 150 sequences were selected by the cut off values defined for 0%, OR or AND approach. This accounts for 2.1%, 3.1% or 2.9% of the entire proteome, respectively (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref>). For 83/111/106 sequences (0%, OR, AND) a (proposed) function could be assigned (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>). Hence, we found 15/32/27 (0%, OR, AND) sequences not encoding for OM proteins (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>). Interestingly, most of the selected NOM proteins are secreted proteins or proteins of the periplasmic space (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>, white section). Assuming a similar distribution of the localization of the hypothetical proteins as found for the annotated sequences, we obtain a false positive rate of 18% for the 0% selection, of 29% for the OR procedure and of 26% for the AND procedure (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5C</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><bold>Identification of &#x003b2;-barrel protein sequences from the <italic>E. coli </italic>proteome</bold>. (A) Sequences were selected from the <italic>E. coli </italic>proteome by the three parameter sets developed (Table 2). The percentage of selected sequences in comparison to the proteome size is shown (bars 1&#x02013;3). Also shown are the percentage of sequences selected by MCMBB (bar 4), MCMBB filtered by TMHMM (bar 5, MCMBB*), by BOMP (bar 6; please note, that only two sequences were selected by BOMP with &#x003b1;TM &#x0003e;1 according to TMHMM), by TMB-Hunt, BBTM protein score &#x0003e;0 and E-value &#x0003c;1 (TMB-Hunt&#x000b0;, bar 7), by TMB-Hunt, BBTM protein score &#x0003e;0 and E-value &#x0003c;1 controlled by TMHMM (TMB-HUNT&#x000b0;*, bar 8) and by the global procedure (bar 9). (B) The sequences selected by the three procedures proposed in here were analyzed for known or assigned function or localization. The percentage of the sequences either classified as hypothetical, outer membrane, extra-cellular or soluble intracellular is shown. (C) The false positive rate for the three in here generated sequence pools (bars 1&#x02013;3), for the sequence pool generated by MCMBB (bar 4), by MCMBB controlled by TMHMM (bar 5), by BOMP (bar 6), by TMB-Hunt, BBTM protein score &#x0003e;0 and E-value &#x0003c;1 (TMB-Hunt&#x000b0;, bar 7) or by TMB-Hunt, BBTM protein score &#x0003e;0 and E-value &#x0003c;1, controlled by TMHMM (TMB-Hunt&#x000b0;*, bar 8) is shown.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2105-6-254-5"/></fig><p>To achieve an impression of the performance quality, we compared our selection with the performance of MCMBB [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>], BOMP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>], TMB-Hunt [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>] and a predictor just based on the global amino acid distribution of &#x003b2;-barrel proteins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>]. MCMBB selects 10% of the <italic>E. coli </italic>proteome (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref>, MCMBB, 565 sequences). Application of the pre- or post-selection by TMHMM (see above) revealed only a slight reduction of the selected pool (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref>, MCMBB*, 530 sequences). For both selections we found a very high false positive rate of about 70% (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5C</xref>). Interestingly, for the predictor based on the global amino acid composition an even higher number of sequences was selected (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref>, Global), which was not drastically altered when post-screened with TMHMM (not shown). Even though it was estimated that about 30% of all proteins are helical membrane proteins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>], it is not considered to be likely that more than 10% of all proteins are &#x003b2;-barrel membrane proteins as discussed above. Therefore, these results raise the question, how reliable scores based on prediction performance on test pools are when transferred to proteome wide prediction.</p><p>Using BOMP (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref>) or TMB-Hunt controlled by the E-value (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref>, TMB-Hunt&#x000b0;) results in a similar pool size compared to the 0% selection established in here. At default settings BOMP selected 2.23% of the <italic>E. coli </italic>proteome (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref>, BOMP) with a false positive rate of 26.4% (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5C</xref>, BOMP) and only two proteins with more than one transmembrane helix according to TMHMM prediction (not shown). TMB-Hunt predicted 1.9% of the <italic>E. coli </italic>proteome as integral outer membrane proteins (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref>, TMB-Hunt&#x000b0;) with a false positive rate of 24.1% when requiring both a BBTM protein score &#x0003e;0 and an E-value &#x0003c;1 (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5C</xref>, TMB-Hunt&#x000b0;). A post-selection by TMHMM reduced the ratio of predicted sequences to 1.8% (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref>, TMB-Hunt&#x000b0;*) and the false positive rate to 19.2% (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5C</xref>, TMB-Hunt&#x000b0;*).</p><p>Previously, the combination of several predictors was suggested to improve the selection reliability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. This strategy allows an increase of the prediction quality as tested on proteomic data of the OM proteome of <italic>Nostoc </italic>sp. PCC7120 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]. We subsequently analyzed the overlap of our procedures with the output of the other programs. The amount of sequences selected in the overlap of our selection and that of the other programs depends on the size of the selected sequence pools by the individual programs (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6A</xref>). Therefore, this combinatory approach revealed the most sequences in combination with MCMBB and the least number of sequences in combination with TMB-Hunt after E-value selection (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6A</xref>). To see, whether an improvement of the selection quality was achieved, we have analyzed the false positive rate after the combinatory approach. The false positive rate is dependent on the number of sequences in the selected pool (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6B</xref>). Using BOMP, 91 sequences (OR) and 90 sequences (AND) were selected in combination with our procedure showing a false positive rate of 9.6 and 8.6%, respectively (Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6B</xref>, light grey bar). The lowest false positive rate of about 6% out of 60 selected sequences was achieved combining our AND or OR method with TMB-Hunt (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6B</xref>, dark grey bar). We next analyzed, whether the same result would be obtained increasing the threshold of BOMP or TMB-Hunt. Analyzing the overlap of the BOMP and the AND selection, we discovered that only sequences of the rank 1&#x02013;3 were omitted (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6C</xref>). The integral &#x003b2;-barrel score [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>] of these proteins is rather low (rank 1 and 3) or even below threshold (rank 2, proteins are only selected by pattern match [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]).</p><fig position="float" id="F6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><bold>The performance of the combinatory approach</bold>. (A) The percentage of sequences selected from the <italic>E. coli </italic>proteome by our three methods in combination with MCMBB (black bar), BOMP (light grey bar) and TMB-Hunt, BBTM protein score &#x0003e;0 and E-value &#x0003c;1 (dark grey bar) is given. (B) The false positive rate for combinatory approach performed as under (A) is shown. (C) The percentage of sequences selected by BOMP and our AND selection were analyzed in comparison to the BOMP selection sorted according to the BOMP rank (BR) assigned (top panel, grey). The percentage of the (putative) outer membrane &#x003b2;-barrel proteins (black bar) and (putative) non-outer membrane &#x003b2;-barrel proteins (white bar) in relation to the total amount of rejected sequences is given on the bottom. (D, E) The percentage of sequences selected by TMB-Hunt&#x000b0; and our AND selection were analyzed in comparison to the TMB-Hunt&#x000b0; selection sorted according to the BB score (D) or E-value (E) assigned ({explained in [17]} grey). In (E), the percentage of the (putative) outer membrane &#x003b2;-barrel proteins (black bar) and (putative) non-outer membrane &#x003b2;-barrel proteins (white bar) in relation to the total amount of rejected sequences sorted according to the E-value is given on the bottom. (F) The percentage of the <italic>E. coli </italic>proteome selected by the combinatory approach between TMB-Hunt&#x000b0; &#x00026; BOMP, TMB-Hunt&#x000b0; &#x00026; MCMBB, and BOMP &#x00026; MCMBB is given on the left side. The right side shows the false positive rate as explained in Fig. 5C.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2105-6-254-6"/></fig><p>However, simply rejecting all sequences of rank 1&#x02013;3 from the BOMP selection would not reveal the same result as the overlap procedure. Furthermore, analyzing the rejected sequences we found that most of the sequences rejected from the BOMP prediction are indeed non-&#x003b2;-barrel outer membrane proteins (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6C</xref>, bottom, white). Analyzing the overlap between TMB-Hunt and our AND prediction shows that the BB score [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>] does not show any clear preference for rejection (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6D</xref>), whereas all sequences with an E-value above 0.8 were rejected (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6E</xref>). Interestingly, sequences with very low E-values were rejected as well (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6E</xref>). Analysis of the rejected sequences shows that again mostly non-&#x003b2;-barrel proteins are rejected although the amount of &#x003b2;-barrel proteins removed from the selected pool seems to be increased. Finally, we went on to compare the combinatory approach including our predictor with the combinatory approach among the other programs. Again, utilizing MCMBB resulted in a larger number of selected sequences than the combination of TMB-Hunt and BOMP (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6F</xref>, left). However, to our surprise, the false positive rate was not significantly changed in comparison to the individual programs (compare Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6F</xref> right and Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5C</xref>). This might be explained as all other programs analyze the entire sequence as such, whereas our prediction is based on a defined region of the sequence.</p><p>Summarizing, the combination of our procedure with other predictors increased the quality of the performance. However, this improvement is only achieved by a consensus approach of a domain and a full length sequence based predictor.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>The aim of the presented work was to develop better tools or rules for the prediction of &#x003b2;-barrel membrane proteins. In a recent proposal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>] we obtained a significant false prediction of soluble proteins. First, we went on to optimize the developed scores by implementing a new definition of the BSN and a control parameter for this score (BSN/aa, Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> and Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). Further, we analyzed the domain size optimum for &#x003b2;-barrel discrimination (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). Here we learned that the best performance was achieved in a window below 300 amino acids. The latter result is in line with the observation that most porins are about 30&#x02013;35 kDa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. Furthermore, for &#x003b2;-barrel proteins of larger size, clustered pore regions were found. For example the structural modeling of FhaC [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>], ShlB [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>] or Toc75 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>] suggests a soluble domain or long loops in the N-terminal region, whereas only the C-terminal portion seems to be involved in pore formation. It might therefore be suggested that an evolutionary prolongation of the membrane &#x003b2;-barrel proteins occurred facilitating the interaction with other proteins or substrates as seen for Toc75 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>]. This result is interesting for the understanding of the evolutionary development of such proteins. It might point to the fact that a minimal structural unit was the starting seed for the development of larger pores as discussed for helical transporters ("hairpin theory") [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>]. Finally, we used a combination of an amino acid distribution based score and the theory that membrane facing strands should reveal an alternating hydrophobicity and calculated a combined score in a 225 amino acid window (BSHS). The window size might reflect that strands involved in homo-oligomerisation do not contain as many hydrophobic amino acids compared to those facing the exterior.</p><p>By visual inspection of the structures we determined the average sizes of the continuous region exposed to the lipid membrane and of the region containing the &#x003b2;-barrel. The obtained sizes are ~275 and ~325 amino acids on average, respectively. This corresponds quite well to the window sizes determined for BSHS225 and BBS275. Theoretically, the smallest possible &#x003b2;-barrel membrane domain, an 8-stranded &#x003b2;-barrel of about 80 aa length, should represent the optimal screening window size. But as we are not analyzing each protein separately but a whole pool of proteins, also the larger &#x003b2;-barrels &#x02013; mostly assembled into homo-oligomeric complexes &#x02013; have their influence. Here, three major factors contribute to the window sizes determined for BSHS225 and BBS275: (i) The &#x003b2;-barrel has a N-terminal and/or C-terminal extension, (ii) one or more long loops break the compact &#x003b2;-barrel domain into two or more parts and (iii) in homo-oligomeric complexes certain parts of the &#x003b2;-barrel domain are involved into protein-protein binding and therefore do not necessarily show an alternating hydrophobicity which results in a smaller scanning window for the BSHS225 compared to the BBS275. Remarkably, according to Wallin and von Heijne [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>] most of the in there investigated proteins of eubacterial organisms have a local maximum at six transmembrane helices within a segment of about 225 to 275 residues. The average domain sizes of &#x003b2;-barrel and above mentioned helical membrane proteins lie within the same range. Therefore, the best discrimination between the two structurally different classes might be possible within this domain. This finding further supports our approach to identify &#x003b2;-barrel membrane proteins by searching for the transmembrane domain only.</p><p>Subsequently, scores for &#x003b2;-barrel membrane protein prediction were developed using test pools (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>, Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>) and three preceding rules. First, a selected protein has to be larger than 80 amino acids, since the smallest monomeric transmembrane &#x003b2;-barrel structure consists of 8 strands [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>]. Second, if more than one transmembrane helix is identified by TMHMM, the current protein is not considered as a transmembrane &#x003b2;-barrel protein (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>) and finally, all scores calculated for a sequence have to be larger than zero, regardless of a performed individual or combined selection. In comparison to the previous procedure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>] we achieved a significant increase of the prediction performance of the <italic>E. coli </italic>proteome (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>). Certainly, a factor contributing to this achievement was the greater flexibility of the HPS calculation. Wimley [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>] originally set the loop length to a minimum of four amino acids. By this slight simplification, as Deng and co-workers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>] also noticed, some hairpins might be missed, because about 28% of the loops are up to three amino acids short [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. Thus, we kept the window of 25 amino acids for the HPS calculation, but searched for the start of the second &#x003b2;-strand from position 11 to 25, thereby allowing a loop length of 0 to up to 14 amino acids. However, the discriminative power of the linear predictor is limited by the availability of crystal structures of &#x003b2;-barrel membrane proteins. Although about 20 non-redundant structures of this type are currently available in the PDB, they only represent a few families of the diverse group of &#x003b2;-barrel membrane proteins. For example, the important family of &#x003b2;-barrel shaped polypeptide transporters [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>] is still missing. A crystal structure of a member of this family would certainly help to improve the predictive power.</p><p>In terms of the prediction performance on the sequence pools we have met our goal of reducing the high false negative rate reported by Deng and co-workers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>] for Wimley's [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>] original method. Deng and co-workers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>] developed a HMM for discriminating &#x003b2;-barrel membrane proteins. For screening proteomes they raised the threshold score in order to increase the chance of true positive hits. For our procedures we included in the development of the prediction parameters an optimization for a proteome wide scan by taking care of the proposed <italic>in vivo </italic>ratio of OM proteins to NOM proteins. Thus, a direct comparison of the performance on proteomes regarding the test pool derived parameters is not possible. This raises the question, if test pools alone are sufficient to receive an impression of the prediction performance on real proteomes. Regarding the generation of test pools not only a broad and diverse collection of proteins but especially the algorithm to reduce the redundancy of the gathered sequences is of central importance. To keep or not to keep a protein &#x02013; this is here the question. However, there is possibly still a need for improvement of such redundancy removal algorithms. As a consequence, we suggest testing &#x003b2;-barrel membrane protein prediction procedures also on a real proteome. The very well annotated proteome of the prokaryote <italic>E. coli </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>] is a good candidate for such a model proteome. This additional testing gives the user a better impression of the reliability of the predictions for prokaryotic proteomes and would allow a better comparison of the scores developed.</p><p>The combination of different independent procedures for &#x003b2;-barrel membrane protein prediction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>] was employed to improve the prediction quality. In here we have analyzed and compared several programs and program combinations. These programs can be classified according to their training sets, to the mathematical procedure taken as basis for the prediction or the size restriction for the sequence analysis window. Therefore, the combination of these programs could be achieved based on the difference of one of the named properties. However, we found that predicting sequences with programs differing in the size restriction for the sequence analysis window revealed the lowest false positive rate based on the <italic>E. coli </italic>proteome. We therefore speculate that the prediction of &#x003b2;-barrel membrane proteins could be further improved employing knowledge based limitations toward the domains, which have to be identified, and global selection approaches in combination.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Test pool generation</title><p>In order to evaluate the prediction, the following sequence pools were created with a redundancy of maximal 50%. From the TMPDB [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>] databank we retrieved the file TMPDB_alpha_nr_PR.dat [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>] which contains a set of &#x003b1;-helical transmembrane proteins. We further collected all OM proteins from the experimentally verified ePSortdb dataset v2.0 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>] and removed proteins that are clearly no integral OM proteins and proteins marked as hypothetical. From the same databank all available proteins of the cytoplasmic membrane and the cytoplasm of Gram-negative bacteria were downloaded.</p><p>From PDB [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>] (version 01/11/2005) we retrieved globular proteins. By SCOP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>] classification we downloaded from PDB proteins with transmembrane helices and all available transmembrane &#x003b2;-barrels.</p><p>As mentioned above, we removed all proteins with more than one transmembrane helix predicted by TMHMM and with less than 80 amino acids. Of the initially 1.235 proteins, 782 survived these steps.</p><p>All proteins that are not &#x003b2;-barrel membrane proteins and are not from PDB were accumulated in one sequence pool. They are referred to as PSort NOM protein pool. The OM proteins of PSort and PDB were kept each in separate pools.</p></sec><sec><title>Proteome</title><p>For testing our in here developed procedure on a real proteome, the genomic derived sequences deposited at [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>] (from 01/07/2005) for <italic>E. coli </italic>were used.</p></sec><sec><title>Definition of the scores</title><p>The algorithms for EBSS, HPS, BBS and BSN were previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. In brief: The <underline>EBSS</underline> gives the TM beta-strand probability within a 10 aa sliding window which corresponds to the average length of a TM beta-strand [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. Approximately 6 aa are required to cross the hydrophobic core of the membrane and further 3 aa for the lipid head group regions of each membrane leaflet [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. Collecting crystal structures of all &#x003b2;-barrel membrane proteins available in 2002 at a maximum sequence identity of 50% Wimley [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>] calculated the statistical occurrence of amino acids belonging to TM &#x003b2;-strands in the above mentioned membrane regions further differentiating between amino acids exposed to the membrane or oriented towards the interior of the pore. Taking into account the typical &#x003b2;-barrel architecture, the <underline>HPS</underline> is derived by applying a sliding window calculation to the EBSS values. The HPS is calculated by summing up the greatest EBSS of the first 10 and the following 15 residues. The <underline>BBS</underline> is calculated by adding all HPS values above 6 normalized to the amino acid number of the sequence.</p></sec><sec><title>Calculation of the scores</title><p>The BSHS value is derived by calculating the individual score for the &#x003b2;-strand starting at amino acid z. The &#x003b2;-strand position was assigned by the in here redesigned BSN algorithm.</p><p><inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="M1" name="1471-2105-6-254-i1" overflow="scroll"><mml:semantics definitionURL="" encoding=""><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>X</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>strand</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>aa</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mtext>z</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:munderover><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>&#x0003c;H&#x0003e;</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>aa</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>z</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>&#x0003c;H&#x0003e;</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>aa</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>z</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>E</mml:mtext><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:annotation encoding="MathType-MTEF">
 MathType@MTEF@5@5@+=feaafiart1ev1aaatCvAUfKttLearuWrP9MDH5MBPbIqV92AaeXatLxBI9gBaebbnrfifHhDYfgasaacH8akY=wiFfYdH8Gipec8Eeeu0xXdbba9frFj0=OqFfea0dXdd9vqai=hGuQ8kuc9pgc9s8qqaq=dirpe0xb9q8qiLsFr0=vr0=vr0dc8meaabaqaciGacaGaaeqabaqabeGadaaakeaacqqGybawdaWgaaWcbaGaee4CamNaeeiDaqNaeeOCaiNaeeyyaeMaeeOBa4MaeeizaqMaeiikaGIaeeyyaeMaeeyyaeMaeyypa0JaeeOEaONaeiykaKcabeaakiabg2da9maaqahabaGaeiikaGIaeeipaWJaeeisaGKaeeOpa4ZaaSbaaSqaaiabbggaHjabbggaHjabcIcaOiabbQha6jabgUcaRiabcIcaOiabbMgaPjabcQcaQiabikdaYiabgUcaRiabigdaXiabcMcaPiabcMcaPaqabaaabaGaeeyAaKMaeyypa0JaeGimaadabaGaeGinaqdaniabggHiLdGccqGHsislcqqG8aapcqqGibascqqG+aGpdaWgaaWcbaGaeeyyaeMaeeyyaeMaeiikaGIaeeOEaONaey4kaSIaeiikaGIaeeyAaKMaeiOkaOIaeGOmaiJaeiykaKIaeiykaKcabeaakiabcMcaPiabc+caViabigdaXiabicdaWiaaxMaacaWLjaWaaeWaaeaacqqGfbqrcqaIXaqmaiaawIcacaGLPaaaaaa@6E37@</mml:annotation></mml:semantics></mml:math></inline-formula></p><p>using the water/octanol transfer free energy scale [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>], multiplying the EBSS value</p><p>Y<sub>strand(aa=z) </sub>= |X<sub>strand (aa=z)</sub>| * EBSS<sub>(aa=z) </sub>&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0; (E2)</p><p>adding all values in a defined amino acid window (w) and normalize to that window</p><p><inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="M2" name="1471-2105-6-254-i2" overflow="scroll"><mml:semantics definitionURL="" encoding=""><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>w</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:munderover><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>aa</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>w</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>9</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>Y</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>strand</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>aa</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mtext>w</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>E</mml:mtext><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:annotation encoding="MathType-MTEF">
 MathType@MTEF@5@5@+=feaafiart1ev1aaatCvAUfKttLearuWrP9MDH5MBPbIqV92AaeXatLxBI9gBaebbnrfifHhDYfgasaacH8akY=wiFfYdH8Gipec8Eeeu0xXdbba9frFj0=OqFfea0dXdd9vqai=hGuQ8kuc9pgc9s8qqaq=dirpe0xb9q8qiLsFr0=vr0=vr0dc8meaabaqaciGacaGaaeqabaqabeGadaaakeaaieaacqWFcbGqcqWFtbWucqWFibascqWFtbWudaWgaaWcbaGaeiikaGIaee4DaCNaeiykaKcabeaakiabg2da9maaqahabaGaeeywaK1aaSbaaSqaaiabbohaZjabbsha0jabbkhaYjabbggaHjabb6gaUjabbsgaKjabcIcaOiabbggaHjabbggaHjabcMcaPaqabaaabaGaeeyyaeMaeeyyaeMaeyypa0JaeGymaedabaGaee4DaCNaeyOeI0IaeGyoaKdaniabggHiLdGccqGGVaWlcqqG3bWDcaWLjaGaaCzcamaabmaabaGaeeyrauKaeG4mamdacaGLOaGaayzkaaaaaa@54D1@</mml:annotation></mml:semantics></mml:math></inline-formula></p><p>All scores were described earlier [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. For transmembrane helix prediction TMHMM v. 2.0 was used [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Abbreviations</title><p>aa, amino acids; BBS, &#x003b2;-barrel score; BSN, &#x003b2;-strand number; EBSS, exact &#x003b2;-strand score; HPS, hairpin score; BSHS, &#x003b2;-strand based hydrophobicity score; HMM, Hidden Markov Model; MCM, Markov Chain Model; OM, outer membrane; NOM, non-outer membrane</p></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>Special thanks to L. Eichacker for helpful discussions. This work was supported by grants to E.S. from the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (SFB-TR01), from the Fonds der Chemischen Industrie and from the Volkswagenstiftung.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ashurst</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gene annotation: prediction and testing</article-title><source>Annu Rev Genomics Hum Genet</source><year>2003</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>88</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14527297</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.genom.4.070802.110300</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Drewes</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouwmeester</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global approaches to protein-protein interactions</article-title><source>Curr Opin Cell Biol</source><year>2003</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>199</fpage><lpage>205</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12648676</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0955-0674(03)00005-X</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gerstein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hegyi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparing genomes in terms of protein structure: surveys of a finite parts list</article-title><source>FEMS Microbiol Rev</source><year>1998</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>277</fpage><lpage>304</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10357579</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0168-6445(98)00019-9</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schatz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Dobberstein</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Common principles of protein translocation across membranes</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1996</year><volume>271</volume><fpage>1519</fpage><lpage>1526</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8599107</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Emanuelsson</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>von Heijne</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prediction of organellar targeting signals</article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><year>2001</year><volume>1541</volume><fpage>114</fpage><lpage>119</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11750667</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0167-4889(01)00145-8</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Westerlund</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>von Heijne</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Emanuelsson</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>LumenP &#x02013; a neural network predictor for protein localization in the thylakoid lumen</article-title><source>Protein Sci</source><year>2003</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>2360</fpage><lpage>2366</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14500894</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1110/ps.0306003</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>M&#x000f6;ller</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Croning</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Apweiler</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of methods for the prediction of membrane spanning regions</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2001</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>646</fpage><lpage>653</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11448883</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/17.7.646</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Melen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Krogh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>von Heijne</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reliability measures for membrane protein topology prediction algorithms</article-title><source>J Mol Biol</source><year>2003</year><volume>327</volume><fpage>735</fpage><lpage>744</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12634065</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0022-2836(03)00182-7</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jacoboni</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Martelli</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Fariselli</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>De Pinto</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Casadio</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prediction of the transmembrane regions of beta-barrel membrane proteins with a neural network-based predictor</article-title><source>Protein Sci</source><year>2001</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>779</fpage><lpage>787</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11274469</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1110/ps.37201</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martelli</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Fariselli</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Krogh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Casadio</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A sequence-profile-based HMM for predicting and discriminating beta barrel membrane proteins</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2002</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>46</fpage><lpage>53</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bigelow</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name><surname>Petrey</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Przybylski</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Rost</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Predicting transmembrane beta-barrels in proteomes</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>2566</fpage><lpage>2577</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15141026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkh580</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bagos</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Liakopoulos</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Spyropoulos</surname><given-names>IC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamdrakas</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A Hidden Markov Model method, capable of predicting and discriminating &#x003b2;-barrel outer membrane proteins</article-title><source>BMC Bioinformatics</source><year>2004</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>29</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15070403</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-5-29</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Saier</surname><given-names>MH</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group><article-title>The beta-barrel finder (BBF) program, allowing identification of outer membrane beta-barrel proteins encoded within prokaryotic genomes</article-title><source>Protein Sci</source><year>2002</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>2196</fpage><lpage>2207</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12192075</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1110/ps.0209002</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wimley</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Toward genomic identification of beta-barrel membrane proteins: composition and architecture of known structures</article-title><source>Protein Sci</source><year>2002</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>301</fpage><lpage>312</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11790840</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1110/ps.29402</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schleiff</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Eichacker</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Eckart</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mirus</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Stahl</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Soll</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prediction of the plant beta-barrel proteome: a case study of the chloroplast outer envelope</article-title><source>Protein Sci</source><year>2003</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>748</fpage><lpage>759</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12649433</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1110/ps.0237503</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garrow</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Agnew</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Westhead</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TMB-Hunt: a web server to screen sequence sets for transmembrane beta-barrel proteins</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>W188</fpage><lpage>192</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15980452</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gki384</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garrow</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Agnew</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Westhead</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TMB-Hunt: an amino acid composition based method to screen proteomes for beta-barrel transmembrane proteins</article-title><source>BMC Bioinformatics</source><year>2005</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>56</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15769290</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-6-56</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moslavac</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bredemeier</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Mirus</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Granvogl</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Eichacker</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Schleiff</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Proteomic analysis of the Outer Membrane of Anabaena sp. Strain PCC 7120</article-title><source>J Prot Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1330</fpage><lpage>1338</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/pr050044c</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berven</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name><name><surname>Flikka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name><name><surname>Eidhammer</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>BOMP: a program to predict integral beta-barrel outer membrane proteins encoded within genomes of Gram-negative bacteria</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>W394</fpage><lpage>399</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15215418</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hobohm</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Scharf</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sander</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Selection of representative protein data sets</article-title><source>Protein Sci</source><year>1992</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>409</fpage><lpage>417</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1304348</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holm</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sander</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Removing near-neighbour redundancy from large protein sequence collections</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>1998</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>423</fpage><lpage>429</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9682055</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/14.5.423</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>May</surname><given-names>ACW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Optimal classification of protein sequences and selection of representative sets from multiple alignments: application to homologous families and lessons for structural genomics</article-title><source>Protein Eng</source><year>2001</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>209</fpage><lpage>217</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11391012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/protein/14.4.209</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>YX</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Scoring hidden Markov models to discriminate beta-barrel membrane proteins</article-title><source>Comput Biol Chem</source><year>2004</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>189</fpage><lpage>194</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15261149</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.compbiolchem.2004.02.004</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bagos</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Liakopoulos</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Promponas</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamodrakas</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Topology prediction of &#x003b2;-barrel outer membrane proteins</article-title><source>PINSA-B</source><year>2004</year><comment></comment></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The structure of bacterial outer membrane proteins</article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><year>2002</year><volume>1565</volume><fpage>308</fpage><lpage>317</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12409203</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krogh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Larsson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>von Heijne</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonnhammer</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Predicting transmembrane protein topology with a hidden Markov model: application to complete genomes</article-title><source>J Mol Biol</source><year>2001</year><volume>305</volume><fpage>567</fpage><lpage>580</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11152613</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/jmbi.2000.4315</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wallin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>von Heijne</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide analysis of integral membrane proteins from eubacterial, archaean, and eukaryotic organisms</article-title><source>Protein Sci</source><year>1998</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1029</fpage><lpage>1038</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9568909</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Frye</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitmitto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>T&#x000f8;njum</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Derrick</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure of the Neisseria meningitides Outer Membrane PilQ Secretin Complex at 12 &#x000c5; Resolution</article-title><source>J Bio Chem</source><year>2004</year><volume>279</volume><fpage>39750</fpage><lpage>39756</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15254043</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M405971200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferro</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Salvi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Riviere-Rolland</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Vermat</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Seigneurin-Berny</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Grunwald</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Garin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Joyard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rolland</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Integral membrane proteins of the chloroplast envelope: identification and subcellular localization of new transporters</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2002</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>11487</fpage><lpage>11492</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12177442</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.172390399</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seshadri</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Garemyr</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>von Heijne</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Elofsson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Architecture of beta-barrel membrane proteins: analysis of trimeric porins</article-title><source>Protein Sci</source><year>1998</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>2026</fpage><lpage>2032</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9761484</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bagos</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Liakopoulos</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamodrakas</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Finding beta-barrel outer membrane proteins with a markov chain model</article-title><source>WSEAS Transactions on Biology and Biomedicine</source><year>2004</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>186</fpage><lpage>189</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gromiha</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Suwa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A simple statistical method for discriminating outer membrane proteins with better accuracy</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2005</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>961</fpage><lpage>968</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15531602</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bti126</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guedin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Willery</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Tommassen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fort</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Drobecq</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Locht</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacob-Dubuisson</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Novel topological features of FhaC, the outer membrane transporter involved in the secretion of the Bordetella pertussis filamentous hemagglutinin</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2000</year><volume>275</volume><fpage>30202</fpage><lpage>30210</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10906141</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M005515200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>K&#x000f6;nninger</surname><given-names>UW</given-names></name><name><surname>Hobbie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Benz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Braun</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The haemolysin-secreting ShlB protein of the outer membrane of Serratia marcescens: determination of surface-exposed residues and formation of ion-permeable pores by ShlB mutants in artificial lipid bilayer membranes</article-title><source>Mol Microbiol</source><year>1999</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>1212</fpage><lpage>1225</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10383762</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2958.1999.01433.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moslavac</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mirus</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Bredemeier</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Soll</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>von Haeseler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schleiff</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Conserved pore-forming regions in polypeptide-transporting proteins</article-title><source>FEBS J</source><year>2005</year><volume>272</volume><fpage>1367</fpage><lpage>1378</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15752354</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1742-4658.2005.04569.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ertel</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Mirus</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Bredemeier</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Moslavac</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Schleiff</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Evolutionary related &#x003b2;-barrel polypeptide transporters from P. sativum and Nostoc PCC7120 contain two distinct functional domains</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2005</year><volume>280</volume><fpage>28281</fpage><lpage>28289</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15951438</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M503035200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitsuke</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Noto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Arai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Internal gene duplication in the evolution of prokaryotic transmembrane proteins</article-title><source>J Mol Biol</source><year>2004</year><volume>339</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15123416</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jmb.2004.03.048</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wimley</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The versatile beta-barrel membrane protein</article-title><source>Curr Opin Struct Biol</source><year>2003</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>404</fpage><lpage>411</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12948769</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0959-440X(03)00099-X</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B39"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>From the Sequence to Cell Modeling: Comprehensive Functional Genomics in Escherichia coli</article-title><source>J Biochem Mol Biol</source><year>2004</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>83</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14761306</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B40"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ikeda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Arai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Okuno</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TMPDB: a database of experimentally-characterized transmembrane topologies</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2003</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>406</fpage><lpage>409</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12520035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkg020</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B41"><citation citation-type="other"><article-title>TMPDB FTP</article-title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="ftp://bioinfo.si.hirosaki-u.ac.jp/TMPDB/Release_6.3/"/></citation></ref><ref id="B42"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rey</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Acab</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gardy</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Laird</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>deFays</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lambert</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Brinkman</surname><given-names>FSL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PSORT-DB: A Database of Subcellular Localizations for Bacteria</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>164</fpage><lpage>168</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gki027</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B43"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berman</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Westbrook</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilliland</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhat</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name><name><surname>Weissig</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Shindyalov</surname><given-names>IN</given-names></name><name><surname>Bourne</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Protein Data Bank</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2000</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>235</fpage><lpage>242</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10592235</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/28.1.235</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B44"><citation citation-type="other"><article-title>RCSB Protein Data Bank</article-title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pdbbeta.rcsb.org/pdb"/></citation></ref><ref id="B45"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murzin</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hubbard</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Chothia</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SCOP: a structural classification of proteins database for the investigation of sequences and structures</article-title><source>J Mol Biol</source><year>1995</year><volume>247</volume><fpage>536</fpage><lpage>540</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7723011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/jmbi.1995.0159</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B46"><citation citation-type="other"><article-title>NCBI FTP</article-title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="ftp://ftp.ncbi.nih.gov/genbank/genomes/Bacteria/Escherichia_coli_O157H7"/></citation></ref><ref id="B47"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wimley</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hydrophobic interactions of peptides with membrane interfaces</article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><year>1998</year><volume>1376</volume><fpage>339</fpage><lpage>352</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9804985</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B48"><citation citation-type="other"><article-title>TMHMM Server v. 2.0</article-title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cbs.dtu.dk/services/TMHMM/"/></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>



