<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="letter"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Environ Health Perspect</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Environ. Health Perspect</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Environmental Health Perspectives</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0091-6765</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1552-9924</issn><publisher><publisher-name>National Institute of Environmental Health Sciences</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">16203225</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1281318</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ehp0113-a0657a</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Perspectives</subject><subj-group><subject>Correspondence</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Disease and &#x0201c;Broken Windows&#x0201d;</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mel&#x000e9;ndez</surname><given-names>Leo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ehp0113-a0657a"/></contrib><aff id="af1-ehp0113-a0657a">Public Health Seattle-King County Local Hazardous Waste Management Program, Seattle, Washington, E-mail:
<email>leo.melendez@metrokc.gov</email></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn><p>The author declares he has no competing financial interests.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>10</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><volume>113</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage seq="a">A657</fpage><lpage>A657</lpage><permissions><copyright-year>2005</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/" license-type="public-domain"><license-p>Publication of EHP lies in the public domain and is therefore without copyright. All text from EHP may be reprinted freely. Use of materials published in EHP should be acknowledged (for example, ?Reproduced with permission from Environmental Health Perspectives?); pertinent reference information should be provided for the article from which the material was reproduced. Articles from EHP, especially the News section, may contain photographs or illustrations copyrighted by other commercial organizations or individuals that may not be used without obtaining prior approval from the holder of the copyright. </license-p></license></permissions><related-article id="d35e61" related-article-type="commentary-article" xlink:href="15866747" ext-link-type="pubmed" vol="113" page="A290"/></article-meta></front><body><p>Frumkin&#x02019;s editorial in the May 2005 issue of <italic>EHP</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1-ehp0113-a0657a">Frumkin 2005</xref>) was very interesting and enlightening. On page A291, Frumkin cited several studies that endorse the &#x0201c;broken windows theory,&#x0201d; noting that</p><disp-quote><p>Part of this effect may well be due to the disorder and squalor of the environment. Poor people and people of color are disproportionately exposed to &#x0201c;broken windows.&#x0201d;</p></disp-quote><p>It is interesting that the &#x0201c;broken windows&#x0201d; are considered to cause disease and health inequity. What happened first: the &#x0201c;broken windows,&#x0201d; or the lack of social skills and the abandonment of the population who live in such places? As a scientist, I find it very difficult to accept that &#x0201c;broken windows&#x0201d; are associated with the number of cases of gonorrhea and are associated with causality. The cases of venereal diseases (VD) are more related to the social skills and social behaviors of the people living in the community. They also have a lack of respect for property, and destruction of property often occurs.</p><p>If we say the reverse is plausible, what would happen if we got a grant and fixed all of the &#x0201c;broken windows&#x0201d; in a particular community, with no other intervention, and observed the trend of VD? With the assumptions and inferences made in Frumkin&#x02019;s editorial, this would have a positive effect in reducing cases of VD. My instincts tell me that this would not be the case. The &#x0201c;broken windows&#x0201d; are a consequence of the behaviors of that particular community and they are not the cause of the behaviors. The &#x0201c;broken windows&#x0201d; are what I consider &#x0201c;collateral damage&#x0201d; of people lacking the necessary social skills to overcome certain challenges, such as socioeconomic stress and the lack of maintenance provided by building owners. These people show their frustration and anger many times against property, as well as other people.</p></body><back><ref-list><title>Reference</title><ref id="b1-ehp0113-a0657a"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Frumkin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Health, equity, and the built environment [Editorial]</article-title><source>Environ Health Perspect</source><volume>113</volume><fpage>A290</fpage><lpage>A291</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15866747</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
