<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Circadian Rhythms</journal-id><journal-title>Journal of Circadian Rhythms</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1740-3391</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15790406</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1079926</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1740-3391-3-4</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1740-3391-3-4</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Short Paper</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Time for sex: nycthemeral distribution of human sexual behavior</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Refinetti</surname><given-names>Roberto</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>refinetti@circadian.org</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Circadian Rhythm Laboratory, University of South Carolina, 807 Hampton Street, Walterboro, SC 29488, USA</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2005</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>24</day><month>3</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><volume>3</volume><fpage>4</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jcircadianrhythms.com/content/3/1/4"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>3</month><year>2005</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>24</day><month>3</month><year>2005</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2005 Refinetti; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2005</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Refinetti; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>
               Refinetti
               Roberto
               
               refinetti@circadian.org
            </dc:author><dc:title>
            Time for sex: nycthemeral distribution of human sexual behavior
         </dc:title><dc:date>2005</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>Journal of Circadian Rhythms 3(1): 4-. (2005)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1740-3391(2005)3:1&#x0003c;4&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1740-3391</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Nycthemeral (daily) oscillation has been documented in a variety of physiological and behavioral processes. The present study was carried out to evaluate the existence of a nycthemeral rhythm of human sexual behavior and to identify environmental factors responsible for the rhythmic pattern.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><p>Non-traditional university students (ages 18 to 51 years) recorded the times of day when they went to sleep, when they woke up, and when they had sex for 3 consecutive weeks. They also answered a questionnaire designed to identify the causes of their selection of time for sex.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>The majority of sexual encounters took place at bedtime (11 pm to 1 am). The most common explanations for this temporal pattern were the rigidity of the professional work schedule and family obligations and the availability of the partner, which reduced the opportunity for sexual encounters at other times of the day.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Most sexual encounters take place around bedtime. Although the presence of an endogenous component responsible for this temporal pattern cannot be excluded, the evidence indicates strong environmental forcing, particularly from the work/family schedule of the individuals and from partner availability.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Practically all physiological parameters in the animal and human body exhibit nycthemeral (daily) or circadian oscillation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. Epidemiological studies have documented nycthemeral oscillation in a variety of aggregate variables, such as heart attacks [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>], births [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>], and suicides [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. One study conducted in 1982 provided evidence of the existence of a nycthemeral rhythm of sexual activity in young married couples [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. The present study sought to verify this nycthemeral rhythmicity in a sample of human adults with a wider age range and to identify environmental factors responsible for the rhythmic pattern.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Part 1</title><p>The first part of the study, conducted during the winter of 2003, involved 15 non-traditional university students in South Carolina (6 males, 9 females, ages 18 to 51 years). The subjects participated in the study as partial fulfillment of course requirements. They were given a data sheet and were asked to record, each day for three weeks, the times of day when they went to sleep, when they woke up, and when they had sex. Subjects were allowed to use their own definition of sex, which did not necessarily involve vaginal intercourse. Complete forms were received from 11 subjects, anonymously. All subjects were married or were involved in a steady relationship with a partner.</p><p>The accumulated nycthemeral distribution of sexual encounters was analyzed in three ways. A Kolmogorov-Smirnov test [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>] was used to determine whether the experimental distribution differed significantly from a flat distribution. A Rayleigh test [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>] was used to determine whether the experimental distribution conformed to a sinusoidal pattern. A cosinor test [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>] was used to determine the acrophase (time of peak) of the nycthemeral oscillation.</p></sec><sec><title>Part 2</title><p>The second part of the study, conducted during the winter of 2005, involved a separate group of 38 university students (14 males, 24 females, ages 18 to 43 years). The subjects were given a brief survey containing two main questions: "What time of day do you usually have sex?" and "Why do you have sex at these times (as opposed to other times of day)?". Answers could be written in for both questions, but potential answers were provided for the second question, as follows:</p><p>__ I feel more sexual at these times.</p><p>__ These are the only times when my partner is available.</p><p>__ My work/family schedule does not allow me to have sex at other times.</p><p>__ I'm already in bed, so why not have sex?</p><p>__ Other. Specify: ________________________________</p><p>Ten subjects (4 males, 6 females, aged between 18 and 20 years) had never had sex and, therefore, were excluded from the study. The percentages of the answers to the second question were computed and compared by the Kolmogorov-Smirnov test.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results and Discussion</title><sec><title>Part 1</title><p>Although there were not enough data for the analysis of the distribution of sexual encounters according to day of the week, the mean number of sexual encounters per week (2.3) was comparable to that found in the broader adult population of the United States (twice a week) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>].</p><p>The nycthemeral distribution of sexual encounters is shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>. Of 71 recorded encounters, 17 took place at midnight, which was the average to-bed time for the subjects. A smaller peak occurred at 06:00, which was the average wake-up time for the subjects. The Kolmogorov-Smirnov test indicated that the distribution was significantly different from a flat distribution (<italic>D </italic>= 0.201, <italic>p </italic>&#x0003c; 0.01), and the Rayleigh test indicated that the distribution conformed to a sinusoidal pattern (<italic>nR</italic><sup>2 </sup>= 15.706, &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>(2) = 31.412, <italic>p </italic>&#x0003c; 0.0001). The cosinor test indicated an acrophase at 01:00.</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Nycthemeral distribution of sexual encounters. </bold>Of 71 recorded encounters, 17 took place at midnight, which was the average to-bed time for the subjects.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1740-3391-3-4-1"/></fig><p>The mean bedtime of 00:00 and mean waketime of 06:00 are within the range of bedtimes and waketimes observed in various societies around the world [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>]. The observed bedtime peak of sexual encounters is in agreement with a previous study of young married couples [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. The results are also in agreement with those obtained in a survey about the time of day of the first intercourse of young women, in which it was found that over 85% of the subjects had lost their virginity either in the evening or at night [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Part 2</title><p>Because the subjects in Part2 were asked only to recall their usual time of sex, the precision of the results was lower than in Part 1. The answers were categorized as "morning" (20%), "afternoon" (5%), "evening" (10%), and "night" (65%). This distribution is significantly different from a flat distribution (<italic>D </italic>= 0.400, <italic>p </italic>&#x0003c; 0.001) and is consistent with the results from Part 1.</p><p>The distribution of responses to the question "Why do you have sex at these times?" is shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>. Although the subjects were allowed to give multiple answers, most of them gave only one answer, and the few who chose "Other" actually wrote in one the four offered options. Consequently, the percentages of answers conveniently added up to 100%. Only 28% of the respondents gave an answer that would characterize an endogenous rhythm of sexual appetite ("I feel more sexual at these times"). In contrast, 33% of the respondents attributed the time selection to restrictions imposed by work/family schedule, and 23% attributed it to partner availability. The distribution of percentages does not differ significantly from a flat distribution (<italic>D </italic>= 0.090, <italic>p </italic>&#x0003e; 0.05), which indicates that none of the four responses was consistently chosen more frequently than the others. Thus, the response based on an endogenous rhythm of sexual appetite was chosen by only a quarter of the respondents. Even this relatively small fraction may be an overestimate, as the subjects may have failed to identify environmental factors other than those offered as potential answers.</p><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>Frequency distribution of answers to the question "Why do you have sex at these times?" </bold>Most subjects indicated that the selection of time for sex is determined by external factors, such as work schedule and partner availability.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1740-3391-3-4-2"/></fig><p>In addressing the issue of exogenous causation, it must be emphasized that this study was conducted under normal living conditions, where environmental factors can "mask" the expression of an endogenous rhythm of sexual appetite. In men, it is known that there is daily rhythmicity in plasma concentration of testosterone [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>], which likely has an endogenous source and could be responsible for rhythmicity in sexual appetite. However, the results of this study clearly indicate that, if there is an endogenous rhythm of sexual appetite, it is not the main determinant of the selection of time for sex in individuals living under normal societal conditions. Instead, the time for sex seems to be determined predominantly by environmental forcing.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Although human adults seem to find opportunities for sex at practically any time of the day, most sexual encounters occur around bedtime (11 pm to 1 am). A smaller peak in sexual activity occurs around wake time. Because the study was conducted in the presence of external time cues, the issue of the endogenous source of this nycthemeral variation cannot be directly addressed. However, self-reports indicate the presence of strong environmental forcing, particularly from the work/family schedule of the individuals and from partner availability.</p></sec><sec><title>Competing Interests</title><p>The author(s) declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dunlap</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Loros</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>DeCoursey</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><source>Chronobiology: Biological Timekeeping</source><year>2004</year><publisher-name>Sunderland, Mass: Sinauer</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Refinetti</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><source>Circadian Physiology</source><year>2005</year><edition>2</edition><publisher-name>Boca Raton, Fla: CRC Press</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fromm</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Pepe</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Circadian variation in the time of request for helicopter transport of cardiac patients</article-title><source>Ann Emerg Med</source><year>1992</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>1196</fpage><lpage>1199</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1416296</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spielberg</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Falkenhahn</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Willich</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Wegscheider</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>V&#x000f6;ller</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Circadian, day-of-week, and seasonal variability in myocardial infarction: comparison between working and retired patients</article-title><source>Am Heart J</source><year>1996</year><volume>132</volume><fpage>579</fpage><lpage>585</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8800028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0002-8703(96)90241-0</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>L&#x000f3;pez-Messa</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Garmendia-Leiza</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Aguilar-Garc&#x000ed;a</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Andr&#x000e9;s-de-Llano</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Alberola-L&#x000f3;pez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ardura-Fern&#x000e1;ndez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Factores de riesgo cardiovascular en el ritmo circadiano del infarto agudo de miocardio</article-title><source>Rev Esp Cardiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>850</fpage><lpage>858</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15373991</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name><surname>McLean</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name><name><surname>Usher</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diurnal variation in admission to hospital of women in labour</article-title><source>Can J Surg</source><year>1989</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>35</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2910377</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anderka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Declercq</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A time to be born</article-title><source>Am J Public Health</source><year>2000</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>124</fpage><lpage>126</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10630151</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goldstick</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Weissman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Drugan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The circadian rhythm of "urgent" operative deliveries</article-title><source>Isr Med Assoc J</source><year>2003</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>564</fpage><lpage>566</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12929294</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gallerani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Avato</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Dal Monte</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Caracciolo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fersini</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Manfredini</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The time for suicide</article-title><source>Psychol Med</source><year>1996</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>867</fpage><lpage>870</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8817723</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Preti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Miotto</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diurnal variations in suicide by age and gender in Italy</article-title><source>J Affect Disord</source><year>2001</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>253</fpage><lpage>261</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11511405</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0165-0327(00)00232-9</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Houwelingen</surname><given-names>CAJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Beersma</surname><given-names>DGM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Seasonal changes in 24-h patterns of suicide rates: a study on train suicides in The Netherlands</article-title><source>J Affect Disord</source><year>2001</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>215</fpage><lpage>223</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11578675</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0165-0327(00)00308-6</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Udry</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diurnal and weekly, but no lunar rhythm in human copulation</article-title><source>Hum Biol</source><year>1982</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>121</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7200945</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krauth</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><source>Distribution-Free Statistics: An Application-Oriented Approach</source><year>1988</year><publisher-name>New York: Elsevier</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mardia</surname><given-names>KV</given-names></name></person-group><source>Statistics of Directional Data</source><year>1972</year><publisher-name>New York: Academic Press</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Halberg</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Methods for cosinor rhythmometry</article-title><source>Chronobiologia</source><year>1979</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>305</fpage><lpage>323</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">548245</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laumann</surname><given-names>EO</given-names></name><name><surname>Gagnon</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Michael</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name><surname>Michaels</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><source>The Social Organization of Sexuality: Sexual Practices in the United States</source><year>1994</year><publisher-name>Chicago: University of Chicago Press</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Binkley</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tome</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Mosher</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Human daily rhythms measured for one year</article-title><source>Physiol Behav</source><year>1990</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>293</fpage><lpage>298</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2255734</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0031-9384(90)90316-V</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Refinetti</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Persistence of synchronization of the daily rhythms of body temperature and sleep-wake in college students</article-title><source>Biol Rhythm Res</source><year>1995</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>532</fpage><lpage>540</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinkoda</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Scores on morningness-eveningness and sleep habits of Korean students, Japanese students, and Japanese workers</article-title><source>Percept Mot Skills</source><year>1997</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>143</fpage><lpage>154</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9293571</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laberge</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Carrier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lesp&#x000e9;rance</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lambert</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Vitaro</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Tremblay</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Montplaisir</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sleep and circadian phase characteristics of adolescent and young adult males in a naturalistic summertime condition</article-title><source>Chronobiol Int</source><year>2000</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>489</fpage><lpage>501</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10908125</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1081/CBI-100101059</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Medeiros</surname><given-names>ALD</given-names></name><name><surname>Mendes</surname><given-names>DBF</given-names></name><name><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name><surname>Araujo</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The relationships between sleep-wake cycle and academic performance in medical students</article-title><source>Biol Rhythm Res</source><year>2001</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>263</fpage><lpage>270</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1076/brhm.32.2.263.1359</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Eastman</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sleep logs of young adults with self-selected sleep times predict the dim light melatonin onset</article-title><source>Chronobiol Int</source><year>2002</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>695</fpage><lpage>707</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12182497</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1081/CBI-120006080</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roenneberg</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Wirz-Justice</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Merrow</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Life between clocks: daily temporal patterns of human chronotypes</article-title><source>J Biol Rhythms</source><year>2003</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>80</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12568247</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0748730402239679</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barak</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ring</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ticher</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Elizur</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Patterns of first intercourse: a survey among Israeli women</article-title><source>Biol Rhythm Res</source><year>1997</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>36</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1076/brhm.28.1.36.12972</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reinberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lagoguey</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cesselin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Touitou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Legrand</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Delassalle</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Antreassian</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lagoguey</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Circadian and circannual rhythms in plasma hormones and other variables of five healthy young human males</article-title><source>Acta Endocrinol</source><year>1978</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>417</fpage><lpage>427</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">581015</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marrama</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Carani</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Baraghini</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name><name><surname>Volpe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zini</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Celani</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Montanini</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Circadian rhythm of testosterone and prolactin in the ageing</article-title><source>Maturitas</source><year>1982</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>131</fpage><lpage>138</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7121294</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>



