<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="letter"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Environ Health Perspect</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Environ. Health Perspect</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Environmental Health Perspectives</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0091-6765</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1552-9924</issn><publisher><publisher-name>National Institue of Environmental Health Sciences</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1253780</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ehp0113-a0150b</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Perspectives</subject><subj-group><subject>Correspondence</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Pesticides and Health Effects: Karpati et al. Respond</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Karpati</surname><given-names>Adam</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ehp0113-a0150b"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Perrin</surname><given-names>Mary C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ehp0113-a0150b"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Leighton</surname><given-names>Jessica</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ehp0113-a0150b"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Matte</surname><given-names>Tom</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ehp0113-a0150b"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af1-ehp0113-a0150b">New York City Department of Health and Mental Hygiene, New York, New York, E-mail:
<email>akarpati@health.nyc.gov</email></aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>Joel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-ehp0113-a0150b"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af2-ehp0113-a0150b">Division of Environmental Health, Harvard School of Public Health, Boston, Massachusetts</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Barr</surname><given-names>R. Graham</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3-ehp0113-a0150b"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af3-ehp0113-a0150b">Department of Medicine, Columbia University Medical Center, New York, New York</aff><author-notes><fn><p>The authors declare they have no competing financial interests.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>3</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><volume>113</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage seq="b">A150</fpage><lpage>A151</lpage><permissions><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/" license-type="public-domain"><license-p>Publication of EHP lies in the public domain and is therefore without copyright. All text from EHP may be reprinted freely. Use of materials published in EHP should be acknowledged (for example, ?Reproduced with permission from Environmental Health Perspectives?); pertinent reference information should be provided for the article from which the material was reproduced. Articles from EHP, especially the News section, may contain photographs or illustrations copyrighted by other commercial organizations or individuals that may not be used without obtaining prior approval from the holder of the copyright. </license-p></license></permissions><related-article id="d35e102" related-article-type="letter" xlink:href="15743698" ext-link-type="pubmed" vol="113" page="A150a"/></article-meta></front><body><p>In her letter, Ziem raises the issue of exacerbations of respiratory illness and other health effects of pesticide exposure that we did not measure in our study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1-ehp0113-a0150b">Karpati et al. 2004</xref>). Our analysis was designed to evaluate only whether a population-level effect on emergency department visits, specifically on asthma and other respiratory illnesses, was evident following pyrethroid pesticide spraying. Similar study designs, despite their limitations, have proven to be sensitive methods of identifying population-level health impacts from exposure to criteria air pollutants from exposure to unusual events, such as smoke from forest fires. Moreover, our analysis did identify adverse population-level health effects of elevated ozone and particulates. As we noted in our discussion, the results of the analysis for pesticide exposure do not rule out the possibility that certain individuals might have been affected by exposure to the agent. Also, our focus was on emergency department visits, which generally signify more serious illness, although in urban neighborhoods even milder illnesses are often treated in such settings. However, if, in fact, certain individuals experienced asthma exacerbations following exposure, we believe our study demonstrates that their number was small enough that it did not result in a population-level increase in emergency department visits for asthma and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease.</p><p>In our analysis we evaluated only respiratory complications of pesticide spraying to control West Nile virus, and we did not purport to measure possible neurotoxic or other nonrespiratory effects. Also, we did not evaluate the efficacy of pesticide spraying for mosquito control or its cost&#x02013;benefit ratio with regard to pesticide-related health effects.</p></body><back><ref-list><title>Reference</title><ref id="b1-ehp0113-a0150b"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Karpati</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Perrin</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Matte</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Leighton</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Barr</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Pesticide spraying for West Nile virus control and emergency department asthma visits in New York City, 2000</article-title><source>Environ Health Perspect</source><volume>112</volume><fpage>1183</fpage><lpage>1187</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15289164</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
