<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Genomics</journal-id><journal-title>BMC Genomics</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2164</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">16098230</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1198228</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1471-2164-6-108</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-6-108</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Comparative analysis of expression of histone H2a genes in mouse</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nishida</surname><given-names>Hiromi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>hnishida@gsc.riken.jp</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>Takahiro</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>t-suzuki@gsc.riken.jp</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ookawa</surname><given-names>Hiroki</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>hokawa@gsc.riken.jp</email></contrib><contrib id="A4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tomaru</surname><given-names>Yasuhiro</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>tomaru@gsc.riken.jp</email></contrib><contrib id="A5" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hayashizaki</surname><given-names>Yoshihide</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>yosihide@gsc.riken.jp</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Laboratory for Genome Exploration Research Group, RIKEN Genomic Sciences Center (GSC), RIKEN Yokohama Institute, 1-7-22 Suehiro-cho, Tsurumi-ku, Yokohama, Kanagawa 230-0045, Japan</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2005</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>13</day><month>8</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><fpage>108</fpage><lpage>108</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2164/6/108"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>2</month><year>2005</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>8</month><year>2005</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2005 Nishida et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2005</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Nishida et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>
               Nishida
               Hiromi
               
               
               hnishida@gsc.riken.jp
            </dc:author><dc:title>
            Comparative analysis of expression of histone H2a genes in mouse
         </dc:title><dc:date>2005</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>BMC Genomics 6(1): 108-. (2005)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1471-2164(2005)6:1&#x0003c;108&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1471-2164</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>At least 18 replication-dependent histone H2a genes are distributed in 3 <italic>Hist </italic>gene clusters on different chromosomes of the mouse genome. In this analysis we designed specific PCR primers for each histone H2a transcript and studied the expression levels and patterns using quantitative RT-PCR (qRT-PCR). In addition, we compared histone H3 K9 acetylation levels in the promoter regions of H2a genes by ChIP (chromatin immunoprecipitation) &#x02013; quantitative PCR (qPCR) analysis.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>RT-PCR analysis indicated that all 20 histone H2a genes assessed in this study are expressed. The replication-dependent histone H2a genes have different expression levels but similar expression patterns. Among the 20 histone H2a genes, the expression-level of <italic>H2afz</italic>, a replication-independent gene, was highest, and that of <italic>Hist1h2aa</italic>, a replication-dependent gene, was lowest. Among 18 replication-dependent H2a genes, the expression level of <italic>Hist3h2a </italic>was highest. The ChIP-qPCR analysis showed that histone H3 K9 acetylation levels in promoter regions of both <italic>H2afz </italic>and <italic>Hist3h2a </italic>are clearly higher than that in the promoter region of <italic>Hist1h2aa</italic>. The H3 K9 acetylation level in the promoter of <italic>Hist1h2aa </italic>is similar to that in the &#x003b3;-satellite region.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>These results strongly suggest that histone H3 K9 acetylation plays a role in the expression of histone genes.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Eukaryotic genomic DNA is packaged with chromosomal proteins, forming chromatin. The most fundamental repeating unit of chromatin is the nucleosome. The nucleosome core consists of 146 bp of DNA wrapped around an octamer of histone proteins made up of 2 copies each of histones H2A, H2B, H3, and H4, in 1.65 turns [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Replication of the eukaryotic chromosomes requires the synthesis of histones to package the newly replicated DNA into chromatin. Control of the level of histone mRNA accounts for much of the control of histone protein synthesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. It is still an open question as to how the expression of individual histone genes is controlled.</p><p>The variants and modifications of the histone proteins are related to chromatin structure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. Specific amino acids within histone tails are targets for a number of post-transcriptional modifications, i.e., acetylation, methylation, phosphorylation, and ubiquitination [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. In particular, the modification of histone H3 K9 affects chromatin structure. H3 K9 methylation is enriched in transcriptionally silent genes and heterochromatin. On the other hand, H3 K9 acetylation is enriched in transcriptionally active genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. Is this modification related to histone gene expression?</p><p>Eighteen replication-dependent histone H2a genes were identified in the mouse genome sequence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. Among these 18 genes, 13 are located in the <italic>Hist1 </italic>cluster on chromosome 13, 4 in the <italic>Hist2 </italic>cluster on chromosome 3, and 1 in the <italic>Hist3 </italic>cluster on chromosome 11 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. Thus, replication-dependent histone H2a genes are distributed in at least 3 <italic>Hist </italic>clusters. In addition, the mouse has 2 replication-independent histone H2a genes, <italic>H2afx </italic>on chromosome 9 and <italic>H2afz </italic>on chromosome 3. Recently we reported a novel replication-independent histone H2a gene (<italic>H2afj</italic>) on chromosome 6 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. <italic>H2afz </italic>and <italic>H2afj </italic>are typical replication-independent genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. The H2afz protein is enriched in euchromatic regions and acts synergistically with a boundary element to prevent the spread of heterochromatin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. On the other hand, <italic>H2afx </italic>mRNA has both a polyadenylated tail and a stem-loop structure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>], elements typical of, respectively, replication-independent and replication-dependent histone genes.</p><p>As cells progress from G1 to S phase, the rate of histone gene transcription increases 3- to 5-fold, and the efficiency of histone pre-mRNA processing increases 8- to 10-fold, resulting in a 35-fold increase in histone protein levels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. Most promoters of histone genes have CCAAT and TATA boxes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. Some promoters have an E2F binding motif between the CCAAT and TATA boxes. This E2F binding motif is recognized, and then the E2F transcription factor activates an H2a gene in early S-phase of the cell cycle [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. However, it is not known how transcription-related proteins cooperate to coordinately regulate histone gene transcription during the cell cycle.</p><p>The amino acid sequences of histone H2a proteins are very similar, except for that of H2afz protein [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. For example, <italic>Hist1h2ab</italic>, <italic>2ac</italic>, <italic>2ad</italic>, <italic>2ae</italic>, <italic>2ag</italic>, <italic>2ai</italic>, <italic>2an</italic>, and <italic>2ao </italic>encode the same structural protein. Among these 8 genes, <italic>Hist1h2ad </italic>and <italic>2ao </italic>have the same nucleotide sequence; however, the others have different nucleotide sequences. Quantitative RT-PCR analysis can be used to show the expression levels of different genes (for example [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]). Thus, in this study we designed the specific PCR primers for each histone H2a gene and studied the expression levels and patterns by qRT-PCR.</p></sec><sec><title>Results and discussion</title><p>Each product of the qRT-PCR gave a single band on the agarose gel, located in the expected position (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). This result indicates that all histone H2a genes are expressed in Hepa 1&#x02013;6 cells. The expression levels of 18 replication-dependent histone genes and <italic>H2afx </italic>increased along with cell cycle progression from the beginning (0 h) of S-phase to the middle (2&#x02013;4 h) of S-phase, and then decreased from the middle to the end (6 h) of S-phase (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). On the other hand, the expression level of the replication-independent gene <italic>H2afz </italic>lacked such a single peak during S-phase (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>RT-PCR products. </bold>Lanes 1 and 19, DNA ladder marker; 2, <italic>Hist1h2aa </italic>transcript; 3, <italic>Hist1h2ab </italic>transcript; 4, <italic>Hist1h2ac </italic>transcript; 5, <italic>Hist1h2ad/1h2ao </italic>transcripts; 6, <italic>Hist1h2ae </italic>transcript; 7, <italic>Hist1h2af </italic>transcript; 8, <italic>Hist1h2ag </italic>transcript; 9, <italic>Hist1h2ah </italic>transcript; 10, <italic>Hist1h2ai/1h2aj </italic>transcripts; 11, <italic>Hist1h2ak </italic>transcript; 12, <italic>Hist1h2an </italic>transcript; 13, <italic>Hist2h2aa1/2h2aa2 </italic>transcripts; 14, <italic>Hist2h2ab/2h2ac </italic>transcripts; 15, <italic>Hist3h2a </italic>transcript; 16, <italic>H2afj </italic>transcript [9]; 17, <italic>H2afx </italic>transcript; 18, <italic>H2afz </italic>transcript.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2164-6-108-1"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>Expression patterns and levels: results of a) first and b) second qRT-PCR analyses. </bold>X-axis, time (hours); Y-axis, expression level relative to <italic>H2afz </italic>expression level adjusted to 1.0 at 0 h in each experiment.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2164-6-108-2"/></fig><p><italic>H2afz </italic>is regulated in a replication-independent manner, but <italic>H2afx </italic>is regulated in a replication-dependent manner. This pattern is consistent with the results of a previous report that indicated that <italic>H2afx </italic>gives rise to a cell-cycle-regulated mRNA ending in the stem-loop during S-phase, and a polyadenylated mRNA during G1-phase [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. Therefore, <italic>H2afx </italic>is regulated in a replication-dependent manner (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). On the other hand, <italic>H2afz </italic>lacks regulation of a polyadenylated mRNA. Interestingly, expression levels of <italic>H2afz </italic>decreased at the end (6 h) of S-phase, similar to those of replication-dependent genes (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). This result suggests that the decrease at the end of S-phase is independent of the histone H2a mRNA structure.</p><p>We compared the sum of expression levels at 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, and 6 h (S-phase) from each histone H2a gene (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). Amino acid sequences from the proteins encoded by <italic>Hist1h2ab</italic>, <italic>2ac</italic>, <italic>2ad</italic>, <italic>2ae</italic>, <italic>2ag</italic>, <italic>2ai</italic>, <italic>2an</italic>, and <italic>2ao </italic>were identical. However, among these 8 genes, the expression level of <italic>Hist1h2ae </italic>was 10 to 30 times that of <italic>Hist1h2ag </italic>(Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). Thus, the expression levels of the genes encoding the same structural protein were different.</p><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>Sum of expression levels at 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, and 6 h (S-phase) in Fig. 2. </bold>Blue and red indicate a) and b) in Fig. 2, respectively. Y-axis, sum of expression levels.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2164-6-108-3"/></fig><p>Among the 13 genes in the <italic>Hist1 </italic>cluster, the expression level of <italic>Hist1h2ae </italic>was approximately 100 times that of <italic>Hist1h2aa </italic>(Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). In addition, the 4 genes in the <italic>Hist2 </italic>cluster had different expression levels. Thus, the expression level of <italic>Hist2h2aa1/2aa2 </italic>was approximately 10 times that of <italic>Hist2h2ab/2ac </italic>(Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). Therefore, the expression levels of genes belonging to the same gene cluster were different.</p><p>One possibility is that such different expression levels are caused by different promoters and different binding proteins bound to the promoters. For example, the promoters of <italic>Hist1h2ad</italic>, <italic>Hist1h2af</italic>, <italic>Hist1h2ag</italic>, and <italic>Hist1h2ah </italic>have the E2F binding motif (5'-TTTTCGCGCCC-3') between the CCAAT and TATA boxes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. Among these 4 replication-dependent genes, the expression level of <italic>Hist1h2ah </italic>was approximately 10 to 20 times that of <italic>Hist1h2ag </italic>(Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). In addition, compared among all 20 genes assessed in this paper, the expression levels of <italic>H2afz</italic>, <italic>Hist3h2a</italic>, <italic>Hist2h2aa1/2aa2</italic>, <italic>Hist1h2ae</italic>, and <italic>Hist1h2ai/aj </italic>were higher than that of <italic>Hist1h2ah</italic>, and those of <italic>Hist1h2ak </italic>and <italic>Hist1h2aa </italic>were lower than that of <italic>Hist1h2ag </italic>(Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). Thus, the relation between the E2F binding motif and the expression level is not clear. Unfortunately, we cannot determine here which structure of the promoters causes such different expression levels.</p><p>Next, we compared the histone H3 K9 acetylation levels in the promoter regions of <italic>H2afz </italic>(highest expression), <italic>Hist3h2a </italic>(highest expression among replication-dependent H2a genes), and <italic>Hist1h2aa </italic>(lowest expression). The ChIP-qPCR analysis showed that histone H3 K9 acetylation levels in the promoter regions of both <italic>H2afz </italic>and <italic>Hist3h2a </italic>were clearly higher than that in the promoter region of <italic>Hist1h2aa</italic>. The H3 K9 acetylation level in the promoter of <italic>Hist1h2aa </italic>was similar to that in the &#x003b3;-satellite heterochromatin region (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). This result indicates that the expression of histone H2a genes is related to the acetylation of histone H3 K9 in the promoter region.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>C<sub>T </sub>values of quantitative PCR for pull-down DNA fragments in ChIP analysis.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td></td><td align="center" colspan="2"><italic>Hist1h2aa </italic>promoter</td><td align="center" colspan="2"><italic>Hist3h2a </italic>promoter</td><td align="center" colspan="2"><italic>H2afz </italic>promoter</td><td align="center" colspan="2">&#x003b3;-satellite</td></tr><tr><td></td><td colspan="8"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">1st</td><td align="center">2nd</td><td align="center">1st</td><td align="center">2nd</td><td align="center">1st</td><td align="center">2nd</td><td align="center">1st</td><td align="center">2nd</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">A: No antibody</td><td align="center">26.9</td><td align="center">26.95</td><td align="center">27.46</td><td align="center">27.15</td><td align="center">29.45</td><td align="center">30.58</td><td align="center">8.2</td><td align="center">8.17</td></tr><tr><td align="left">B: Antibody of H3 K9 acetylated</td><td align="center">27.61</td><td align="center">27.06</td><td align="center">24.14</td><td align="center">23.59</td><td align="center">26.47</td><td align="center">26.68</td><td align="center">8.81</td><td align="center">8.57</td></tr><tr><td align="left">A &#x02013; B</td><td align="center">-0.71</td><td align="center">-0.11</td><td align="center">3.32</td><td align="center">3.56</td><td align="center">2.98</td><td align="center">3.9</td><td align="center">-0.61</td><td align="center">-0.4</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>This study strongly suggests that histone H3 K9 acetylation plays a role in the expression of histone genes.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Cell cycle synchronization</title><p>The cell cycle of mouse Hepa 1&#x02013;6 cells was synchronized at the end of G1-phase by the addition of thymidine-hydroxyurea. The cell cycle arrest was released by washing out the thymidine-hydroxyurea, then the cells were harvested at intervals of 1 h from 0 to 13 h.</p></sec><sec><title>RNA extraction</title><p>Total RNA was extracted by using the RNeasy mini kit (Qiagen) according to the instructions in the manual for the cell line. After that, each sample was treated with DNase I.</p></sec><sec><title>cDNA synthesis</title><p>RNA (approximately 0.5 &#x003bc;g) and random hexamer primers were heated to 70&#x000b0;C for 10 min, followed by cooling on ice for 5 min. The cDNA was synthesized in Superscript III First Strand buffer (Invitrogen) according to the manual. The reverse transcriptase was inactivated by a 15-min incubation at 70&#x000b0;C.</p></sec><sec><title>Quantitative PCR</title><p>The primers used in this analysis are shown in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>. Quantification of GAPDH (glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase) mRNA (primers 5'-TGTGTCCGTCGTGGATCTGA-3' and 5'-CCTGCTTCACCACCTTCTTGA-3' ; product size 76 bp) was used as a control for data normalization. PCR amplification was performed on an ABI PRISM 7700 Sequence Detection System (Applied Biosystems). The PCR conditions were an initial step of 30 s at 95&#x000b0;C, followed by 40 cycles of 5 s at 95&#x000b0;C and 30 s at 60&#x000b0;C. The SYBR premix Ex <italic>Taq </italic>(Takara) was used according to the manual. Each amplification curve was checked [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. Expression was assessed by evaluating threshold cycle (C<sub>T</sub>) values. The relative amount of expressed RNA was calculated by using Livak and Schmittgen's method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. The qRT-PCR analyses were performed twice. In each analysis, we adjusted the <italic>H2afz </italic>expression level to 1 at 0 h.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Primers used in this analysis.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="left">Transcript</td><td align="left">Sequences (5' to 3'), forward and reverse</td><td align="left">Product size (bp)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Hist1h2aa</td><td align="left">cggcagtgctagaatacttgaca, gcaggtggcgaggagta</td><td align="left">96</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Hist1h2ab</td><td align="left">gcctgcagttccccgta, atctcggccgtcaggtactc</td><td align="left">121</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Hist1h2ac</td><td align="left">ggctgctccgcaagggt, cttgttgagctcctcgtcgtt</td><td align="left">191</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Hist1h2ad/2ao</td><td align="left">tggacgcggcaagcagggt, agcacggccgccaggtag</td><td align="left">162</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Hist1h2ae</td><td align="left">accggctgctccgcaaa, tgatgcgcgtcttcttgttgt</td><td align="left">144</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Hist1h2af</td><td align="left">cgaggagctcaacaagctgt, ttgggcttatggtggctct</td><td align="left">111</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Hist1h2ag</td><td align="left">tggacgcggcaaacagggc, cagcacggccgccaggtaga</td><td align="left">162</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Hist1h2ah</td><td align="left">atatgtctggacgcggt, acgcgctccgagtagttg</td><td align="left">133</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Hist1h2ai/2aj</td><td align="left">tcgcgccaaggccaagact, cccacgcgctccgagtagtt</td><td align="left">102</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Hist1h2ak</td><td align="left">tacctggcagccgtgcta, cagcttgttgagctcctcgtc</td><td align="left">141</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Hist1h2an</td><td align="left">gaggagctcaacaagctgct, ggtggctctcggtcttcttc</td><td align="left">100</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Hist2h2aa1/2aa2</td><td align="left">aactgtagcccggcccg, ttcgtctgtttgcgcttt</td><td align="left">100</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Hist2h2ab/2ac</td><td align="left">ggcaaagtgacgatcgca, gtggctctcggtcttcttgg</td><td align="left">78</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Hist3h2a</td><td align="left">agcagggcggcaaagctcgt, ttacccttacggagaaggcg</td><td align="left">100</td></tr><tr><td align="left">H2afx</td><td align="left">aaggccaagtcgcgctctt, tcggcgtagtggcctttc</td><td align="left">86</td></tr><tr><td align="left">H2afz</td><td align="left">actccggaaaggccaagaca, gttgtcctagatttcaggtg</td><td align="left">100</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Chromatin immunoprecipitation</title><p>A total of 2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>7 </sup>cells were cross-linked with 1% formaldehyde for 10 min at room temperature. First, genomic DNA was cut by micrococcal nuclease. Then it was cut by sonication. The precleared extract was divided into 2 equal portions. One was used for control lacking antibody, and the other was incubated with acetylated histone H3 K9 antibody (Upstate Biotechnology). Following immunoprecipitation, beads were washed in low salt, then high salt, then LiCl, then TE buffers. The qPCR analyses were performed two times. Primers used in quantitative PCR were the <italic>Hist1h2aa </italic>promoter (5'-TTATAGGCGTGGACATT-3' and 5'-CACAGCTTGAATTCCCC-3'), the <italic>Hist3h2a </italic>promoter (5'-CCGCGTTCTTTTCTGAT-3' and 5'-AATTCGTAAGCGCCAGC-3'), and the <italic>H2afz </italic>promoter (5'-GCGCCAATCATCGCTCG-3' and 5'-TCGGGACGCGTCCTTGA-3'). We used &#x003b3;-satellite as a constitutive heterochromatin. The &#x003b3;-satellite PCR primers have been reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>HN designed this study and carried out the molecular biological studies. TS and HO carried out the ChIP experiment and qPCR. YT carried out synchronization of cells. YH helped design the study.</p></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This work was supported in part by a Research Grant for the RIKEN Genome Exploration Research Project, a Research Grant for Advanced and Innovational Research Programs in Life Sciences, and a Research Grant for the Genome Network Project from the Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology (MEXT) of the Japanese Government; in part by a Research Grant for CREST of Japan Science and Technology Corporation to Y.H; and in part by grant 15770055 from the MEXT to H.N.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luger</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000e4;der</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Richmond</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Sargent</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Richmond</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crystal structure of the nucleosome core particle at 2.8 &#x000c5; resolution</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1997</year><volume>389</volume><fpage>251</fpage><lpage>260</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9305837</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/38444</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marzluff</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name><name><surname>Duronio</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Histone mRNA expression: multiple levels of cell cycle regulation and important developmental consequences</article-title><source>Curr Opin Cell Biol</source><year>2002</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>692</fpage><lpage>699</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12473341</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0955-0674(02)00387-3</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Allis</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Histone methylation versus histone acetylation: new insights into epigenetic regulation</article-title><source>Curr Opin Cell Biol</source><year>2001</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>263</fpage><lpage>273</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11343896</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0955-0674(00)00208-8</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sims</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name><name><surname>Mandal</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Reinberg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recent highlights of RNA-polymerase-II-mediated transcription</article-title><source>Curr Opin Cell Biol</source><year>2004</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>263</fpage><lpage>271</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15145350</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ceb.2004.04.004</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ehrenhofer-Murray</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chromatin dynamics at DNA replication, transcription and repair</article-title><source>Eur J Biochem</source><year>2004</year><volume>271</volume><fpage>2335</fpage><lpage>2349</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15182349</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1432-1033.2004.04162.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meneghini</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Madhani</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Conserved histone variant H2A.Z protects euchromatin from the ectopic spread of silent heterochromatin</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2003</year><volume>112</volume><fpage>725</fpage><lpage>736</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12628191</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(03)00123-5</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roh</surname><given-names>T-Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Cuddapah</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Active chromatin domains are defined by acetylation islands revealed by genome-wide mapping</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>2005</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>542</fpage><lpage>552</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15706033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.1272505</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marzluff</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name><name><surname>Gongidi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Woods</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Maltais</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The human and mouse replication-dependent histone genes</article-title><source>Genomics</source><year>2002</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>487</fpage><lpage>498</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12408966</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0888-7543(02)96850-3</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nishida</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomaru</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayashizaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A novel replication-independent histone H2a gene in mouse</article-title><source>BMC Genetics</source><year>2005</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>10</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15720718</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2156-6-10</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hatch</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonner</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The human histone H2A.Z gene. Sequence and regulation</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1990</year><volume>265</volume><fpage>15211</fpage><lpage>15218</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1697587</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mannironi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonner</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hatch</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>H2A.X. a histone isoprotein with a conserved C-terminal sequence, is encoded by a novel mRNA with both DNA replication type and polyA 3' processing signals</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1989</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>9113</fpage><lpage>9126</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2587254</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x000f6;hni</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneiderman</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramamurthy</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sch&#x000fc;mperli</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Marzluff</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of histone mRNA in the unperturbed cell cycle: evidence suggesting control at two posttranscriptional steps</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>1991</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>2416</fpage><lpage>2424</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2017161</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Osley</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The regulation of histone synthesis in the cell cycle</article-title><source>Annu Rev Biochem</source><year>1991</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>827</fpage><lpage>861</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1883210</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.bi.60.070191.004143</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oswald</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Dobner</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipp</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The E2F transcription factor activates a replication-dependent human H2A gene in early S phase of the cell cycle</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>1996</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>1889</fpage><lpage>1895</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8628255</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crechowski</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Bari</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Stitt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheible</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><name><surname>Udvardi</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Real-time RT-PCR profiling of over 1400 <italic>Arabidopsis </italic>transcription factors: unprecedented sensitivity reveals novel root- and shoot-specific genes</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2004</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>366</fpage><lpage>379</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15078338</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2004.02051.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nishida</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomaru</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Oho</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayashizaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Naturally occurring antisense RNA of histone H2a in mouse cultured cell lines</article-title><source>BMC Genetics</source><year>2005</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>23</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15892893</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2156-6-23</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Livak</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmittgen</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of relative gene expression data using real-time quantitative PCR and the 2<sup>-&#x00394;&#x00394;CT </sup>method</article-title><source>Methods</source><year>2001</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>402</fpage><lpage>408</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11846609</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/meth.2001.1262</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shestakova</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mansuroglu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Mokrani</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghinea</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonnefoy</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transcription factor YY1 associates with pericentromeric &#x003b3;-satellite DNA in cycling but not in quiescent (G<sub>0</sub>) cells</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>4390</fpage><lpage>4399</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15316102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkh737</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>



