<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cytojournal</journal-id><journal-title>CytoJournal</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1742-6413</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">16174298</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1253525</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1742-6413-2-17</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1742-6413-2-17</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Fine needle aspiration biopsy diagnosis of metastatic neoplasms of the breast. A three-case report</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Raquel</surname><given-names>Garza-Guajardo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>rgguajardo@yahoo.com</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nora</surname><given-names>Mendez-Olvera</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>patologiacutanea@yahoo.com.mx</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pablo</surname><given-names>Flores-Gutierrez Juan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>jufloresmx@hotmail.com</email></contrib><contrib id="A4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Silvia</surname><given-names>Hernandez-Martinez</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>silivi36@hotmail.com</email></contrib><contrib id="A5" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Michelle</surname><given-names>Candanosa-Mc Cann</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>michellecandanosa@hotmail.com</email></contrib><contrib id="A6" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jes&#x000fa;s</surname><given-names>Ancer-Rodriguez</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>jancer@ccr.dsi.uanl.mx</email></contrib><contrib id="A7" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Oralia</surname><given-names>Barboza-Quintana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>oralibarboza@hotmail.com</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Anatomical Pathology and Cytopathology department, University Hospital "Dr. Jos&#x000e9; E.Gonzalez", UANL, Monterrey, Mexico</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2005</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>9</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><volume>2</volume><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cytojournal.com/content/2/1/17"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>31</day><month>3</month><year>2005</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>20</day><month>9</month><year>2005</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2005 Raquel et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2005</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Raquel et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>
               Raquel
               Garza-Guajardo
               
               rgguajardo@yahoo.com
            </dc:author><dc:title>
            Fine needle aspiration biopsy diagnosis of metastatic neoplasms of the breast. A three-case report
         </dc:title><dc:date>2005</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>CytoJournal 2(1): 17-. (2005)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1742-6413(2005)2:1&#x0003c;17&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1742-6413</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><p>Metastases to the breast are unusual lesions that make up approximately 2% of all malignant mammary neoplasms and may mimic both benign and malignant primary neoplasms from a clinical point of view, as well as in imaging studies. Arriving at a correct diagnosis is therefore essential in order to establish appropriate management.</p><p>We present three cases of metastatic neoplasms diagnosed through fine needle aspiration biopsy and immunocytochemistry. The cytological diagnoses were: medulloblastoma in an 18-year-old woman, melanoma in a 26-year-old man, and an exceptional case of ovarian sarcoma originating from a granulosa cell tumor with metastases to both breasts. A metastatic disease should be considered in the differential diagnosis of a palpable mass in the breast, especially if there is a history of an extramammary malignant neoplasm. Fine needle aspiration biopsy is the method of choice for the management of these cases.</p><p>Whenever possible the exam of the material obtained should be compared to the previous biopsy, which is usually enough to arrive at a correct diagnosis, thus preventing unnecessary surgical procedures.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Metastatic neoplasms of the breast are very rare [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. They may mimic benign and malignant primary neoplasms both clinically and radiologically [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>], and the clinical diagnosis often goes unsuspected, especially when the first manifestation of the clinical picture is a breast tumor and the existence of a primary neoplasm is unknown or not taken into consideration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. In most cases, management through fine needle aspiration biopsy (FNAB) permits the correct diagnosis of a metastatic neoplasm, which prevents unnecessary radical surgeries and allows us to start appropriate systemic treatment promptly [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>].</p><p>For FNAB evaluation it is necessary to know the patient's clinical history. It will usually be easier to achieve a definitive diagnosis when the history of extramammary malignant neoplasm is known. Therefore, metastatic lesions should be considered in the differential diagnosis of tumors of the breast, particularly in those cases presenting unusual clinical, radiological, or cytological characteristics. For the latter, it is very useful to perform immunocytochemistry stains on the smears or cell blocks to arrive at a definitive diagnosis.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><p>Three cases of metastatic neoplasms of the breast were identified through FNAB, from a total 639 aspirates of breast tumors performed between January 2001 and December 2003 at the Aspiration Room of the Anatomical Pathology and Cytopathology Service of the Hospital Universitario. The pathologist performed all the procedures by using a gauge 22 needle in a 10 ml syringe. One or two punctures were performed in each case, with an average of four smears per patient. An air-dried smear was stained with Diff-Quik for immediate evaluation of the sample, and the rest were fixed with 95&#x000b0; alcohol and stained by Papanicolau's method. Additionally, immunohistochemistry stains were performed on the cytological material [Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>].</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Immunochemical markers used:</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td align="left">Antibody</td><td align="left">Company</td><td align="left">Dilution</td><td align="left">HIER</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CD 45</td><td align="left">DAKO</td><td align="left">1:100</td><td align="left">yes</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ENE</td><td align="left">DAKO</td><td align="left">1:200</td><td align="left">no</td></tr><tr><td align="left">S-100 Protein</td><td align="left">DAKO</td><td align="left">1:200</td><td align="left">yes</td></tr><tr><td align="left">HMB 45</td><td align="left">DAKO</td><td align="left">1:50</td><td align="left">yes</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Vimentin</td><td align="left">DAKO</td><td align="left">1:200</td><td align="left">yes</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Cytokeratin AE1</td><td align="left">DAKO</td><td align="left">1:200</td><td align="left">yes</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CA 15-3</td><td align="left">DAKO</td><td align="left">1:250</td><td align="left">yes</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>HIER: Heat induce epitope retrieval</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Out of a total 639 aspiration biopsies of the breast, 3 cases (0.4%) were diagnosed as metastatic neoplasms. In the three cases, immunochemistry was performed on the smears to corroborate the diagnosis, and the histological slides of the primary tumor were reviewed in order to compare them with the original morphology.</p><sec><title>Case description</title><sec><title>Case 1</title><p>An 18-year-old female patient with a history of cerebellar medulloblastoma diagnosed 18 months before admission. At the time she was treated with subtotal surgical resection and the placement of a ventricular peritoneal shunt, in addition to radiotherapy. This time she presented with a tumor of the right breast and bone pain.</p><p>The physical examination revealed a lobulated tumor of the breast, approximately 3 cm in diameter, with poorly defined margins, no changes in the overlying skin and no axillary or supraclavicular adenopathies. An FNAB procedure was performed on the tumor, which yielded abundant material consisting of a population of non-cohesive, small, round cells with scant cytoplasm and a high nucleus-cytoplasm ratio. The nuclei were rounded and some of them were elongated, with lumpy chromatin and small nucleoli.</p><p>Immunocytochemistry was performed, which was positive for neuron-specific enolase and negative for the common leukocyte antigen. The cytological diagnosis was metastatic medulloblastoma. Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref></p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>a y b: Papamicolaou; c: biopsy; d: CD45; e: neuron specific enolase; f: vimentin.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1742-6413-2-17-1"/></fig></sec></sec><sec><title>Case 2</title><p>A 26-year-old man with a history of being diagnosed with a skin melanoma three years earlier, he presents with a firm, poorly-defined, multinodular retroareolar mass, approximately 5 cm in diameter. The smears showed numerous cells, predominantly epithelioid-looking, forming slightly cohesive groups, as well as isolated polygonal cells with cytoplasmic elongations and nuclei with acidophilic macronucleoli and pseudoinclusions. Scant cells with melanotic pigment were identified.</p><p>Immunohistochemistry was performed, with the following results: negative for cytokeratin, positive for vimentin, S-100 protein, and HMB45. A metastatic melanoma was diagnosed. Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref></p><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>a, b, c: Papanicolaou; d: HMB-45; e: skin biopsy; f, g, h: breast tumor.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1742-6413-2-17-2"/></fig><sec><title>Case 3</title><p>A 55-year-old woman who was diagnosed with a granulosa cell tumor of the ovary with sarcomatous differentiation a year prior to her admission, at present she shows several fastgrowing nodular tumors in both breasts, as well as imaging suggesting metastasis to the liver. FNAB of both breasts was performed.</p><p>The smears showed numerous neoplastic cells, predominantly spindle-shaped cells forming small groups, intermingled with other pleomorphic and isolated polygonal cells with large nuclei and no nucleoli. Immunohistochemistry was negative for cytokeratin and CA 15-3, and positive for vimentin. A metastatic sarcoma was diagnosed. Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>.</p><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>a: Papanicolaou; b: cytokeratin; c: CA 15-3; d: vimentin; e, f: ovarian tumor; g: inhibin; h: WT1.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1742-6413-2-17-3"/></fig></sec></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>Metastases to the breast of neoplasms originating in organs other than the breast are very rare. In a series of 2529 breast aspiration biopsies, 666 were diagnosed as malignant neoplasms, and only 18 (2.7%) were of extramammary origin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. The identification of a secondary neoplasm in the breast is clinically complicated because secondary neoplasms appear as well-circumscribed rounded masses, most often located in the upper outer quadrant, and without the spiculations or microcalcifications of primary carcinomas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. On the other hand, the presence of well-circumscribed multiple or bilateral nodules may suggest a benign process in the mammography [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>].</p><p>Since metastatic neoplasms may mimic primary tumors, it is important to know the patient's clinical history when interpreting the FNAB. However, for patients with unknown primary neoplasms the metastatic nature of the lesion should be suspected when we find unusual cytological patterns. Immunocytochemistry techniques are undoubtedly of great use in the latter cases.</p><p>Some clinical characteristics help us identify neoplasms of the breast that have a metastatic origin: the time span for the development of metastasis in patients with previously treated cancers is approximately two years. Metastases are usually to other sites or are detected simultaneously; by contrast, isolated metastases limited to the breast are infrequent [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>].</p><p>Although virtually any malignant neoplasm can metastasize to the breast, this is most common for melanomas, carcinomas of the lung, neuroendrocrine and carcinoid carcinomas, ovarian carcinomas, and lymphoid and hematopoietic neoplasms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. Extracranial metastases of medulloblastoma occur in 5% to 7% of cases, and they are mainly related to ventricular peritoneal shunts. Most frequently affected sites are the bones, the lymphatic nodes, the liver, and the lungs, with isolated cases reported for other organs, such as the breast, for which only five cases have been described in the literature. Three of these cases were diagnosed through fine needle aspiration biopsy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>].</p><p>The cytological differential diagnosis includes lobular carcinoma, small-cell carcinoma, carcinoid tumor, lymphoma, and leukemic infiltration. Melanomas are some of the neoplasms that most often metastasize to the breast. Such metastases may be hard to recognize if the primary tumor is hiding or if there is no history of this tumor [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>].</p><p>In addition, there is only one reported case of granulosa cell ovarian tumor metastatic to the breast diagnosed through a biopsy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>], and there are no previous reports of cases diagnosed with FNAB.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Metastatic disease should be taken into consideration in the differential diagnosis of a tumor of the breast, especially if there is a history of an extramammary malignant neoplasm. FNAB, in combination with Immunohistochemistry, is the method of choice for the initial management of these cases. On the other hand, comparing the cytological findings with the previous biopsy will be usually enough to arrive at a correct diagnosis, thus preventing unnecessary radical surgical procedures and allowing us to establish the treatment of choice promptly and safely.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Georgianos</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Chin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Goode</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheaff</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Secondary neoplasms of the breast: a survey of the 20th century</article-title><source>Cancer</source><year>2001</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>2259</fpage><lpage>2266</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11745279</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/1097-0142(20011101)92:9&#x0003c;2259::AID-CNCR1571&#x0003e;3.0.CO;2-O</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alvarado</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name><name><surname>Carrera</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Perez</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Tavassoli</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Met&#x000e1;stases to the breast</article-title><source>Eur J Surg Oncol</source><year>2003</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>854</fpage><lpage>855</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14624777</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0748-7983(03)00123-9</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Domanski</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metastases to the breast from extramammary neoplasms. A report of six cases with diagnosis by fine needle aspiration cytology</article-title><source>Acta Cytol</source><year>1996</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>1293</fpage><lpage>1300</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8960043</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akcay</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metastatic disease in the breast</article-title><source>Breast</source><year>2002</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>526</fpage><lpage>528</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14965721</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1054/brst.2002.0467</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silverman</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Feldman</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Covell</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Frable</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fine needle aspiration cytology of neoplasms metastatic to the breast</article-title><source>Acta Cytol</source><year>1987</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>291</fpage><lpage>300</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3473862</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vergier</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Trojani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>de Mascarel</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Coindre</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Treut</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metastases to the breast : differential diagnosis from primary breast carcinoma</article-title><source>J Surg Oncol</source><year>1991</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>112</fpage><lpage>116</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1921396</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chaignaud</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Powers</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Subramony</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott-Conner</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diagnosis and natural history of extramammary tumors metastatic to the breast</article-title><source>J Am Coll Surg</source><year>1994</year><volume>179</volume><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8019724</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosen</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Paul Peter Rosen</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Metastases in the breast from nonmammary malignant neoplasms</article-title><source>Rosen's breast pathology</source><year>2001</year><publisher-name>Philadelphia, PA: Lippincott Williams &#x00026; Wilkins</publisher-name><fpage>689</fpage><lpage>701</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>David</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Gattuso</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Razan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Moroz</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Dhurandhar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Unusual cases of metastases to the breast. A report of 17 cases diagnosed by fine needle aspiration</article-title><source>Acta Cytol</source><year>2002</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>377</fpage><lpage>385</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11917589</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sneige</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Zachariah</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fanning</surname><given-names>TV</given-names></name><name><surname>Dekmezian</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ordo&#x000f1;ez</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fine-needle aspiration cytology of metastatic neoplasms in the breast</article-title><source>Am J Clin Pathol</source><year>1989</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>35</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2750705</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Henriksen</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kristensen</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name><surname>Lorentzen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ravn</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Schiodt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Thorborg</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name><surname>Ornvold</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metastases to the breast from extramammary carcinomas</article-title><source>Acta Pathol Microbiol Scand</source><year>1981</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>251</fpage><lpage>256</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lamovec</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pogaenik</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metastatic medulloblastoma to the breast</article-title><source>Virchows Arch</source><year>2001</year><volume>439</volume><fpage>201</fpage><lpage>205</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11561762</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s004280100448</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baliga</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmquist</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Espinoza</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Medulloblastoma metastatic to breast, diagnosed by fine-needle aspiration biopsy</article-title><source>Diagn Cytopathol</source><year>1994</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8005039</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kapila</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarkar</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detection of metastatic medulloblastoma in a fine needle breast aspirate</article-title><source>Acta Cytol</source><year>1996</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>384</fpage><lpage>385</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8629434</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brutschin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Culver</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Extracranial metastases from medulloblastomas</article-title><source>Radiology</source><year>1973</year><volume>107</volume><fpage>359</fpage><lpage>362</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4695903</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brydon</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Carey</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Medulloblastoma metastasizing to a breast fibroadenoma: a case report</article-title><source>Br J Neurosurg</source><year>1991</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2021436</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Filie</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Simsir</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fetsch</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Abati</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Melanoma metastatic to the breast: utility of fine needle aspiration and immunohistochemistry</article-title><source>Acta Cytol</source><year>2002</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11843553</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hejmadi</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Day</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Extramammary metastatic neoplasms in the breast: a cytomorphological study of 11 cases</article-title><source>Cytopathology</source><year>2003</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>191</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12873311</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2303.2003.00073.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harwood</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metastatic carcinoma to the breast</article-title><source>JAMA</source><volume>218</volume><fpage>97</fpage><comment>1971 Oct 4</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5109929</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.218.1.97b</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>



