<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Behav Brain Funct</journal-id><journal-title>Behavioral and brain functions : BBF</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1744-9081</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">16212663</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1262690</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1744-9081-1-17</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1744-9081-1-17</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Short Paper</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Branching projections of ventrolateral reticular neurons to the medial preoptic area and lumbo-sacral spinal cord</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Russo</surname><given-names>Antonella</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>antrusso@unict.it</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pellitteri</surname><given-names>Rosalia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>r.pellitteri@isn.cnr.it</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Romeo</surname><given-names>Rosa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>romeros@unict.it</email></contrib><contrib id="A4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Stanzani</surname><given-names>Stefania</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>stanzani@unict.it</email></contrib><contrib id="A5" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jean</surname><given-names>Andr&#x000e9;</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I4">4</xref><email>andre.jean@univ.u-3mrs.fr</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Physiological Sciences, University of Catania, Catania, Italy</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Institute of Neurological Science, Research National Council, Catania, Italy</aff><aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Department of Anatomy, Diagnostic Pathology, Phorens Medicine, Hygiene and Public Health, University of Catania, Catania, Italy</aff><aff id="I4"><label>4</label>Laboratoire de Physiologie Neurov&#x000e9;g&#x000e9;tative, UMR 6153-CNRS 1147-INRA, Universit&#x000e9; Aix-Marseille III, Facult&#x000e9; des Sciences St. Jer&#x000f4;me, Marseille, France</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2005</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>7</day><month>10</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><volume>1</volume><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.behavioralandbrainfunctions.com/content/1/1/17"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>6</month><year>2005</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>7</day><month>10</month><year>2005</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2005 Russo et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2005</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Russo et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>
               Russo
               Antonella
               
               antrusso@unict.it
            </dc:author><dc:title>
            Branching projections of ventrolateral reticular neurons to the medial preoptic area and lumbo-sacral spinal cord
         </dc:title><dc:date>2005</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>Behavioral and Brain Functions 1(1): 17-. (2005)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1744-9081(2005)1:1&#x0003c;17&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1744-9081</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><p>Different findings indicate that rostral ventrolateral reticular nucleus (RVL) is neuronal substrate of integration and regulation of the cardiovascular functions. Some efferent RVL neurons project to the thoraco-lumbar spinal cord and excite preganglionic sympathetic neurons, to the spinal phrenic motor neurons involved in inspiratory function and increase the activity of vasoconstrictor fibres innervating blood vessels in the skin and skeletal muscle. Our study was aimed at revealing presence of neurons within RVL supplying branching collateral input to the medial preoptic area (MPA) and to the lumbo-sacral spinal cord (SC-L) in the rat. All animal experiments were carried out in accordance with current institutional guidelines for the care and use of experimental animals. We have employed double fluorescent-labelling procedure: the projections were defined by injections of two retrograde tracers: Rhodamine Labelled Bead (RBL) and Fluoro Gold (FG) in the MPA and SC-L, respectively. Our results showed the presence of few single FG neurons and single RBL neurons in the RVL. The size of FG-neurons and RBL-neurons was medium (25&#x02013;30 &#x003bc;m) and large (50 &#x003bc;m).</p><p>Few double-projecting neurons were distributed in the middle third of RVL nucleus, their size was 30&#x02013;40 &#x003bc;m. The results demonstrate that pools of neurons in the RVL have collateral projections to the MPA and SC-L and they are involved in ascending and descending pathway. These data suggest that these neurons could play a role in maintaining activity of central and peripheral blood flow.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>ventrolateral reticular nucleus (RVL)</kwd><kwd>retrograde fluorescent tracer</kwd><kwd>medial preoptic area</kwd><kwd>spinal cord</kwd><kwd>rat.</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Several findings indicate that rostral ventrolateral reticular medulla (RVL) is the fundamental neuronal substrate of the regulation of circulation and cardiovascular functions, that mediates vasomotor reflexes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. Different methods permitted to identify afferent projections to RVL, from the hypothalamic paraventricular nucleus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>], the lateral hypothalamic area [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>], the dorsal raphe nucleus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>] and from other regions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. Some efferent RVL neurons project to the intermediolateral cell column of the thoraco-lumbar spinal cord and excite preganglionic sympathetic neurons [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>], spinal phrenic motor neurons involved in inspiratory function [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>] and increase the activity of vasoconstrictor fibres innervating blood vessels in the skin and skeletal muscle [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. Ascending RVL efferent projections convey informations from RVL to diencephalic nuclei [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>] and collateralized fibres were found in RVL, after injections within the cerebellar fastigial nucleus and the superior colliculus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. In fact, electrical stimulation of RVL in rats elicits an excitatory response on the renal sympathetic nerve activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. The MPA is also involved in controlling of numerous functions: neuroendocrine, sexual, maternal behaviour and other activities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. The aim of the present study is to demonstrate the existence of direct projections from RVL to the MPA and, <italic>via </italic>collaterals, the existence of direct projections to MPA and SC-L. In addition, previous work has shown that RVL adrenergic (C1) and non-adrenergic neurons were found to participate in these projections [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. The brainstem neurons may be involved in simultaneous transmission of autonomic-related signals, in fact catecholaminergic and non-catecholaminergic neurons were found to provide branching collaterals to the central nucleus of the amygdala and to the hypothalamic paraventricular nucleus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>].</p><p>In the present study we have used two retrograde tracers to determine the distribution of RVL neurons that project <italic>via </italic>collaterals to the MPA and SC-L.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Only those cases (8 rats) where microscopic analysis of the injection sites revealed that the tracer deposits were correctly positioned were included in the study. Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref> shows the injection sites of the retrograde tracers RLB in the MPA (A) and FG in the SC-L (B). The results showed a large number of retrogradely-labelled neurons in the whole ipsi- and contralateral RVL (stereotaxic planes: -11.60/-11.96). FG-labelled neurons from the ipsilateral and contralateral RVL were numerous (39.42 &#x000b1; 3.3); moreover, these neurons ranged in size from medium (20&#x02013;30 &#x003bc;m) to large (50 &#x003bc;m) and were rather sparse within RVL. RLB-labelled neurons were mostly packed within the boundaries of the field examined, consistently of medium size (20&#x02013;35 &#x003bc;m) and uniformly distributed in ipsi- and contralateral RVL (38.2 &#x000b1; 2.85). The fluorescence microscopy revealed a substantial number of RVL double-labelled neurons (18.6 &#x000b1; 3.13), evidencing the presence of collateralization to the MPA and SC-L. These neurons generally were of medium to large size (30&#x02013;40 &#x003bc;m) and were localized in the middle third of RVL.</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Microphotographs show injection zones: in (A) RLB injection site and drawing in MPA (black area); Scale bar: 400 &#x003bc;m. In (B) FG injection site and drawing in SC-L (black area). Scale bar: 90 &#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1744-9081-1-17-1"/></fig><p>Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> shows schematic drawing of frontal brain section including RVL region with different symbol (circle, triangle and star) indicating the labelled neurons presence.</p><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Schematic drawing atlas of frontal brain section including RVL region: circle indicates FG labelled neurons; triangle indicates RLB labelled neurons; star indicates FG-RLB labelled neurons.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1744-9081-1-17-2"/></fig><p>A relatively low number of FG/RLB (4.6 &#x000b1; 1.49 neurons) double-labelled neurons (30&#x02013;40 &#x003bc;m) were scattered mainly at the ipsilateral RVL level; an example is showed in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>.</p><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Microphotographs of double-labelled neurons FG-RLB in reticular ventrolateral nucleus (RVL). (A) cells stained positively to FG (excitation wavelength 330 nm); (B) the same cells stained positively to RLB (excitation wavelength 560 nm) indicating the existence of a collateral axon. Scale bar: 50 &#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1744-9081-1-17-3"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>The present study provides direct evidence, based on retrograde tracing technique, that: 1) RVL single neurons directly project to the medial preoptic area; 2) RVL single neurons directly project to spinal cord, confirming previous results [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]; 3) RVL neurons supply, <italic>via </italic>collaterals, branching inputs to the MPA and SC-L. Sympatho-excitatory neurons of the RVL, like in rostral ventromedial medulla [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>] and in caudal ventrolateral medulla [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>], are important for the maintenance of tonic levels of arterial pressure they are intrinsic pacemaker activity and discharge continuously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. In conclusion, after the injections of FG and RLB, we show a cluster of branching RVL neurons in the rat brain. The fact that RVL contains neurons with a collateral fibers to both the spinal cord and to hypothalamic MPA, suggests that these neurons might play a role in maintaining activity of central and peripheral blood flow simultaneously.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><p>All experiments were carried out in accordance with current institutional guidelines for the care and use of experimental animals. Experiments were performed on 10 adult male Wistar rats weighing 250&#x02013;300 g (Morini, Italy), maintained under controlled conditions of room temperature (23 &#x000b1; 1&#x000b0;C) and lighting (lights on 07:00 &#x02013; 19:00 h); laboratory chow diet and water were available <italic>ad libitum</italic>; the <italic>in vivo </italic>experimental procedure was performed during daytime (10:00 &#x02013; 13:00 a.m.).</p><p>Animals were anaesthetized with chloral hydrate (400 mg/Kg, i.p.). Two fluorescent tracers were injected to the same rat: Fluoro Gold (FG) was injected into the lumbo-sacral spinal cord on one side, Rhodamine Labeled Bead (RLB) into the medial preoptic area of the same side. Rats were placed in a Kopf stereotaxic frame and injected with 0.08 &#x003bc;l of undiluted RLB in the MPA, at the following coordinates (0.30; L = 0.5; V = -8.5) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]; freshly dissolved FG (0.15 &#x003bc;l at 6% in saline) was injected into the SC-l. Both tracers were pressure-injected at a rate of 50 nl/min. using 1 &#x003bc;l Hamilton microsyringes.</p><p>Seven days after the injections, the animals were reanaesthetized and perfused through the ascending aorta with saline (60 ml), followed by ice-cold 4% paraformaldehyde phosphate buffer (300 ml; pH 7.4). The brains were removed, immersed in the same fixative for 3&#x02013;4 h and cryoprotected overnight in phosphate-buffered with 20% sucrose solution.</p><p>Coronal sections (40 &#x003bc;m) were cut on a cryostat (Reichert), mounted on slides and observed under fluorescent microscope (Polyvar Reichert) for identification of injection zones. The sections were air-dried, mounted and observed with a Reichert fluorescence microscope equipped with filter combinations revealing red (RLB), yellow (FG). For each animal, three non-adjacent sections were evaluated and the labelled cells plotted onto schematic drawings of the RVL region level (stereotaxic planes: -11.60 / -11.96) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. Thus, cell numbers were expressed as the average number/section calculated from these three sections.</p></sec><sec><title>Competing interests</title><p>The author(s) declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>AR, RP, RR, SS and AJ jointly conceived and executed this study and helped draft the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Mr. S. Bentivegna for helping with the photographic work. This study was supported by MIUR.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aicher</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Milner</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pickel</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name><name><surname>Reis</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anatomical substrates for baroreflex sympathoinhibition in the rat</article-title><source>Brain Res Bull</source><year>2000</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>107</fpage><lpage>110</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10709955</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0361-9230(99)00233-6</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reis</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Golanov</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruggiero</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sympatho-excitatory neurons of the rostral ventrolateral medulla are oxygen sensors and essential elements in the tonic and reflex control of the systemic and cerebral circulations</article-title><source>J Hypertens</source><year>1994</year><fpage>S159</fpage><lpage>180</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Coote</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of the hypothalamic paraventricular nucleus on cardiovascular in the rostral ventrolateral medulla of the rat</article-title><source>J Physiol (Lond)</source><year>1998</year><volume>531</volume><fpage>521</fpage><lpage>530</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9807000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-7793.1998.521bb.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dampney</surname><given-names>RAL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional organization of central pathways regulating the cardiovascular system</article-title><source>Physiol Rev</source><year>1994</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>323</fpage><lpage>364</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8171117</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Underwood</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Arango</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Bakalian</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruggiero</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mann</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dorsal raphe nucleus serotonergic neurons innervate the rostral ventrolateral medulla in rat</article-title><source>Brain Res</source><year>1999</year><volume>824</volume><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10095041</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0006-8993(99)01181-6</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Minson</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Arnolda</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name><name><surname>Llewellyn-Smith</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neurochemistry of nerve fibers apposing sympathetic preganglionic neurons activated by sustained hypotension</article-title><source>J Comp Neurol</source><year>2002</year><volume>449</volume><fpage>307</fpage><lpage>318</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12115667</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cne.10282</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Comer</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibbons</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Win</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detenction of mRNA species in bulbospinal neurons isolated from the rostral ventrolateral medulla using single-cell RT-PCR</article-title><source>Brain Res Brain Res Prot</source><year>1999</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>367</fpage><lpage>377</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1385-299X(99)00042-2</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rajakumar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hrycyshyn</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Flumerfelt</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Afferent organization of the lateral reticular nucleus in the rat: an anterograde tracing study</article-title><source>Anat and Embryol (Berl)</source><year>1992</year><volume>185</volume><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>37</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1736682</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00213598</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Reis</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Excitatory amino acid-mediated chemoreflex excitation of respiratory neurones in rostral ventrolateral medulla in rats</article-title><source>J Physiol</source><year>1996</year><volume>492</volume><fpage>559</fpage><lpage>571</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9019550</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dampney</surname><given-names>RAL</given-names></name><name><surname>McAllen</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential control of sympathetic fibres supplying hindlimb skin and muscle by subretrofacial neurones in the cat</article-title><source>J Physiol (Lond)</source><year>1998</year><volume>395</volume><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>56</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2900889</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petrov</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Krukoff</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Jhamandas</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Branching projections of catecholaminergic brainstem neurons to the paraventricular hypotalamic nucleus and the central nucleus of the amygdala in the rat</article-title><source>Brain Res</source><year>1993</year><volume>609</volume><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8099526</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0006-8993(93)90858-K</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stanzani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Russo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pellitteri</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Storaci</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Cataudella</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Branching projections of catecholaminergic ventrolateral reticular neurons to the fastigial nucleus and superior colliculus in the rat: triple labelling procedure</article-title><source>Neurosci Lett</source><year>2001</year><volume>307</volume><fpage>135</fpage><lpage>138</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11438382</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0304-3940(01)01899-7</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Granata</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Denavit-Saubie</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bulbospinal sympathoexcitatory pathways in the rat</article-title><source>Brain Res Bull</source><year>1994</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>601</fpage><lpage>605</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7922604</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0361-9230(94)90146-5</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>YQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Jun-Qing</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Direct projections from the medial preoptic area to spinally- projecting neurons in Barrington's nucleus: an electron microscope study in the rat</article-title><source>Neurosci Lett</source><year>1999</year><volume>271</volume><fpage>175</fpage><lpage>178</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10507697</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0304-3940(99)00562-5</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dominguez</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hul</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stimulation of the medial amygdala enhances medial preoptic dopamine release: implications for male rat sexual behavior</article-title><source>Brain Res</source><year>2001</year><volume>917</volume><fpage>225</fpage><lpage>229</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11640908</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0006-8993(01)03031-1</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grattan</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Rocca</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Sagrillo</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Selmanoff</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antiandrogen microimplants into rostral medial preoptic area decrease gamma-aminobutyric acidergic neuronal activity and increase luteinizing hormone secretion in the intact male rat</article-title><source>Endocrinology</source><year>1996</year><volume>137</volume><fpage>4167</fpage><lpage>4173</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8828473</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/en.137.10.4167</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aicher</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Milner</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>N-methyl-D-aspartate-type glutamate receptors are found in post-synaptic targets of adrenergic terminals in the thoracic spinal cord</article-title><source>Brain Res</source><year>2000</year><volume>856</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10677605</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0006-8993(99)02145-9</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Callaway</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Milner</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Reis</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rostral ventrolateral medulla: a source of the glutamatergic innervation of the sympathetic intermediolateral nucleus</article-title><source>Brain Res</source><year>1991</year><volume>562</volume><fpage>126</fpage><lpage>135</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1724740</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0006-8993(91)91196-8</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hackett</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Guyenet</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rostral ventrolateral medullary neurons with intrinsic pacemaker properties are not catecholaminergic</article-title><source>Brain Res</source><year>1988</year><volume>451</volume><fpage>345</fpage><lpage>349</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2908028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0006-8993(88)90781-0</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Babic</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ciriello</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Medullary and spinal cord projections from cardiovascular responsive sites in the rostral ventromedial medulla</article-title><source>J Comp Neurol</source><year>2004</year><volume>469</volume><fpage>391</fpage><lpage>412</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14730590</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cne.11024</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Panneton</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Defining projections from the caudal pressor area of the caudal ventrolateral medulla</article-title><source>J Comp Neurol</source><year>2005</year><volume>482</volume><fpage>273</fpage><lpage>93</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15690490</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cne.20434</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paxinos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><source>The rat brain in sterotaxis coordinates</source><year>1986</year><publisher-name>Academic Press: Sydney</publisher-name></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>



