<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="letter"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Environ Health Perspect</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Environ. Health Perspect</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Environmental Health Perspectives</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0091-6765</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1552-9924</issn><publisher><publisher-name>National Institue of Environmental Health Sciences</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">16002357</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1257672</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ehp0113-a0442a</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Perspectives</subject><subj-group><subject>Correspondence</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Urinary Creatinine and Arsenic Metabolism</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gamble</surname><given-names>Mary V.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Xinhua</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Department of Environmental Health Sciences, Department of Biostatistics, Mailman School of Public Health, Columbia University, New York, New York, E-mail:
<email>mvg7@columbia.edu</email></aff><author-notes><fn><p>The authors declare they have no competing financial interests.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>7</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><volume>113</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage seq="a">A442</fpage><lpage>A442</lpage><permissions><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/" license-type="public-domain"><license-p>Publication of EHP lies in the public domain and is therefore without copyright. All text from EHP may be reprinted freely. Use of materials published in EHP should be acknowledged (for example, ?Reproduced with permission from Environmental Health Perspectives?); pertinent reference information should be provided for the article from which the material was reproduced. Articles from EHP, especially the News section, may contain photographs or illustrations copyrighted by other commercial organizations or individuals that may not be used without obtaining prior approval from the holder of the copyright. </license-p></license></permissions><related-article id="d35e66" related-article-type="commentary-article" xlink:href="15687057" ext-link-type="pubmed" vol="113" page="192"/></article-meta></front><body><p>Urinary creatinine is almost universally employed to adjust concentrations of urinary analytes for variations in hydration status. In the February 2005 issue of <italic>EHP</italic>, Barr et al. used data from the Third National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey (NHANES III) to establish reference ranges for urinary creatinine for specific age and demographic categories (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1-ehp0113-a0442a">Barr et al. 2005</xref>). They reported that the significant predictors of urinary creatinine concentrations include age, sex, race/ethnicity, body mass index, and fat-free mass. Although these indicators have been known for many years, the unintentional adjustment for these covariates when urinary metabolites are expressed per gram creatinine can have profound effects on the interpretation of data. The fact that these effects are often under-appreciated or even unnoticed renders this paper highly relevant to exposure assessment and well worth revisiting. In our studies of arsenic methylation and one-carbon metabolism, we have noted several additional complications when expressing urinary arsenic as micrograms per gram creatinine. Note that one-carbon metabolism refers to the folate-dependent biochemical pathway responsible for methylation of DNA, arsenic, and hundreds of other substrates.</p><p>Our study in Bangladesh on 1,650 adults revealed that urinary creatinine concentrations are significantly correlated with plasma folate concentrations&#x02014;particularly among males, who had a higher prevalence of folate deficiency than females in Bangladesh (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2-ehp0113-a0442a">Gamble et al. 2005</xref>). Although this association had not been previously reported, it is not surprising considering that the formation of creatine from methylation of guanidino-acetate accounts for approximately 75% of all folate-dependent transmethylation reactions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3-ehp0113-a0442a">Mudd and Poole 1975</xref>) and that creatine is the direct precursor of creatinine. In some analyses, adjusting urinary arsenic for creatinine obscured correlations between folate and arsenic metabolism. In other analyses, correlations between folate and arsenic/creatinine were due in part to the associations between folate and creatinine. Correct interpretation of the data would not be possible without considering the impact of the correlation between urinary creatinine and plasma folate. As did <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1-ehp0113-a0442a">Barr et al. (2005)</xref>, we decided to include urinary creatinine in the statistical models as a separate independent variable. However, because of the intimate link between creatine metabolism and one-carbon metabolism, inclusion of urinary creatinine in some models resulted in overcontrolling for the effects of folate and homocysteine, our variables of interest. Thus, expression of total urinary arsenic per gram creatinine runs the risk of confounding relationships between total urinary arsenic and arsenic metabolism. Adjusting for the specific gravity of urine was not useful because it is so highly correlated with urinary creatinine.</p><p>In summary, we concur with <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1-ehp0113-a0442a">Barr et al. (2005)</xref> that urinary creatinine should be included in multiple regression models as a separate independent variable; in addition, the role of one-carbon metabolism as a predictor of urinary creatinine should also be considered in interpreting results. Specifically, we routinely test if urinary creatinine itself is a predictor of the outcomes of interest.</p></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="b1-ehp0113-a0442a"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Barr</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilder</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Caudill</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonzalez</surname></name><name><surname>AJ</surname></name><name><surname>Needham</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Pirkle</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Urinary creatinine concentrations in the U.S. population: implications for urinary biologic monitoring measurements</article-title><source>Environ Health Perspect</source><volume>113</volume><fpage>192</fpage><lpage>200</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15687057</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b2-ehp0113-a0442a"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Gamble</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahsan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Factor-Litvak</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ilievski</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Slavkovich</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Folate and cobalamin deficiencies and hyperhomocysteinemia in Bangladesh</article-title><source>Am J Clin Nutr</source><volume>81</volume><fpage>1372</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15941889</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b3-ehp0113-a0442a"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Mudd</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Poole</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><year>1975</year><article-title>Labile methyl balances for normal humans on various dietary regimens</article-title><source>Metabolism</source><volume>24</volume><fpage>721</fpage><lpage>735</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1128236</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
