<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="letter"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Environ Health Perspect</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Environ. Health Perspect</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Environmental Health Perspectives</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0091-6765</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1552-9924</issn><publisher><publisher-name>National Institue of Environmental Health Sciences</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1247595</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ehp0112-a0796a</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Perspectives</subject><subj-group><subject>Correspondence</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Conflicts of Interest: Ayotte&#x02019;s Response</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ayotte</surname><given-names>Pierre</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Public Health Research Unit, CHUQ-Laval University Medical Center, Quebec, Canada, E-mail:
<email>pierre.ayotte@inspq.qc.ca</email></aff><author-notes><fn><p>The author declares he has no competing financial interests.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>10</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><volume>112</volume><issue>14</issue><fpage seq="a">A796</fpage><lpage>A796</lpage><permissions><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/" license-type="public-domain"><license-p>Publication of EHP lies in the public domain and is therefore without copyright. All text from EHP may be reprinted freely. Use of materials published in EHP should be acknowledged (for example, ?Reproduced with permission from Environmental Health Perspectives?); pertinent reference information should be provided for the article from which the material was reproduced. Articles from EHP, especially the News section, may contain photographs or illustrations copyrighted by other commercial organizations or individuals that may not be used without obtaining prior approval from the holder of the copyright. </license-p></license></permissions><related-article related-article-type="letter" id="d35e58" vol="112" page="A794b" ext-link-type="pmc"/></article-meta></front><body><p>Goozner contacted me by e-mail on 24 June 2004, and I promptly, honestly, and to the best of my knowledge answered questions regarding his claim that I did not disclose a conflict of interest while publishing our article (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1-ehp0112-a0796a">Bilrha et al. 2003</xref>) in <italic>EHP</italic>. Although I thought I made it clear that he was wrong in his allegations, he nevertheless chose to go ahead and include my name in a report published on the Center for Science in the Public Interest&#x02019;s (CSPI) website (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3-ehp0112-a0796a">CSPI 2004</xref>) and in his letter to <italic>EHP</italic>. Here are the facts.</p><p>In our 2003 manuscript (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1-ehp0112-a0796a">Bilrha et al. 2003</xref>), we acknowledged funding from the Canadian Network of Toxicology Centers (CNTC). As the corresponding author, I read the conflict of interest statement and indicated that I had nothing to declare, neither for me nor for the coauthors. I did not know at that time that the Canadian Chemical Producer Association was partly funding the CNTC. On their website (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2-ehp0112-a0796a">CNTC 2004</xref>), the CNTC indicates being funded mostly by public sources (90%) and does not mention the identity of private sources. In any case, had I known this at the time of publication, it would not have changed anything, because I never personally received any funds (or compensation of any sort, or stood to gain financially) from the Canadian Chemical Producer Association or the Canadian Chlorine Coordinating Committee. Goozner is wrong when he mentions that several of my previous studies were funded by these interest groups. I was a coauthor on two articles published previously in <italic>EHP</italic>, in which funding from these interest groups was acknowledged, along with other sources of funding (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4-ehp0112-a0796a">Sandau et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5-ehp0112-a0796a">2002</xref>). I collaborated in the work, but I was not the recipient of funds obtained from the Canadian Chemical Producer Association or the Canadian Chlorine Coordinating Committee. Funds from these organizations went to the principal investigator at Carleton University, and not a penny was transferred to me.</p><p>I truly believe that the authors of scientific manuscripts should disclose relevant conflicts of interest, and I support enforcing disclosure by appropriate means. However, because Goozner elected to choose the easy way by conducting an Internet-based research, without actually talking to me, he wrongly associated my name with scientific misconduct. I am presently seeking legal advice on this matter.</p></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="b1-ehp0112-a0796a"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Bilrha</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreau</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Belles-Isles</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dewailly</surname><given-names>&#x000c9;</given-names></name><name><surname>Ayotte</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title><italic>In vitro</italic> activation of cord blood mononuclear cells and cytokine production in a remote coastal population exposed to organochlorines and methyl mercury</article-title><source>Environ Health Perspect</source><volume>111</volume><fpage>1952</fpage><lpage>1957</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14644672</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b2-ehp0112-a0796a"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>CNTC</collab> 2004. Canadian Network of Toxicology Centres. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.uoguelph.ca/cntc/">http://www.uoguelph.ca/cntc/</ext-link> [accessed21 July 2004].</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b3-ehp0112-a0796a"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>CSPI</collab> 2004. Unrevealed: Non-Disclosure of Conflicts of Interest in Four Leading Medical and Scientific Journals. Washington, DC:Center for Science in the Public Interest. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cspinet.org/new/pdf/unrevealed_final.pdf">http://cspinet.org/new/pdf/unrevealed_final.pdf</ext-link> [accessed 15 July 2004].</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b4-ehp0112-a0796a"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Sandau</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Ayotte</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Dewailly</surname><given-names>&#x000c9;</given-names></name><name><surname>Duffe</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Norstrom</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Analysis of hydroxylated metabolites of PCBs (OH-PCBs) and other chlorinated phenolic compounds in whole blood from Canadian Inuit</article-title><source>Environ Health Perspect</source><volume>108</volume><fpage>611</fpage><lpage>616</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10903613</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b5-ehp0112-a0796a"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Sandau</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Ayotte</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Dewailly</surname><given-names>&#x000c9;</given-names></name><name><surname>Duffe</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Norstrom</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Pentachlorophenol and hydroxylated polychlorinated biphenyl metabolites in umbilical cord plasma of neonates from coastal populations in Qu&#x000e9;bec</article-title><source>Environ Health Perspect</source><volume>110</volume><fpage>411</fpage><lpage>417</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11940460</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
