<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Cardiovasc Disord</journal-id><journal-title>BMC Cardiovascular Disorders</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2261</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15972103</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1166544</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1471-2261-5-15</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2261-5-15</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Commentary</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Peripheral arterial disease: A high risk &#x02013; but neglected &#x02013; disease population</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tomson</surname><given-names>Joseph</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>G.Y.H.LIP@bham.ac.uk</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lip</surname><given-names>Gregory YH</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>G.Y.H.LIP@bham.ac.uk</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>University Department of Medicine, City Hospital, Birmingham B18 7QH, England, UK</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2005</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>6</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2261/5/15"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>6</month><year>2005</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>6</month><year>2005</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2005 Tomson and Lip; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2005</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Tomson and Lip; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>
               Tomson
               Joseph
               
               G.Y.H.LIP@bham.ac.uk
            </dc:author><dc:title>
            Peripheral arterial disease: A high risk &#x02013; but neglected &#x02013; disease population
         </dc:title><dc:date>2005</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>BMC Cardiovascular Disorders 5(1): 15-. (2005)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1471-2261(2005)5:1&#x0003c;15&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1471-2261</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><p>Peripheral arterial disease (PAD) is a common, progressive manifestation of atherothrombotic vascular disease, which should be managed no different to cardiac disease. Indeed, there is growing evidence that PAD patients are a high risk group, although still relatively under-detected and under treated. This is despite the fact that PAD patients are an increased mortality rate comparable to those with pre-existing or established cardiovascular disease [myocardial infarction, stroke]. With a holistic approach to atherothrombotic vascular disease, our management of PAD can only get better.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><p>Peripheral arterial disease (PAD) results from the narrowing of the blood vessels of the lower limbs, predominantly secondary to atherosclerotic vascular disease leading to compromised blood flow to the lower limbs. Risk factors associated with PAD include typical cardiovascular risk factors, such as older age, cigarette smoking, diabetes mellitus, hypercholesterolemia, and hypertension [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. PAD is also very common in the western world &#x02013; based on symptoms of intermittent claudication, PAD has a prevalence of up to 5%, but a higher prevalence is estimated in the general population [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. As with much of cardiovascular disease, PAD can be progressive, which about a third report worsening symptoms and require surgical interventions over 5 to 10 years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>] as well as suffer a higher cardiovascular mortality risk [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. One could argue that compared to the large publicity and public health initiatives on heart attacks and strokes, public recognition on the risks, morbidity and mortality associated with PAD has been relatively neglected.</p><p>Given that the pathology in PAD arises secondary to atherosclerosis (or atherothrombosis) affecting the vascular tree, PAD would be a very useful, subtle and early indicator of a high risk population. The realisation that the majority of those with PAD remain asymptomatic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>], and that they can be more effectively identified by simple non-invasive techniques warrants new hope for the primary prevention of cardiovascular risk.</p><p>In their recent article published in <italic>BMC Cardiovascular Disorders</italic>, Caro et al [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>] embark upon estimating the burden of cardiovascular risk in terms of mortality, morbidity and associated risk factors in patients with PAD. Of note, they compared outcomes between the PAD cohort to those with reference populations with a first diagnosis of myocardial infarction and stroke. They report that the mortality rate amongst those with PAD was higher when compared to those who had an index myocardial infarction but lower than those who had suffered stroke. Importantly, the rates were comparable to the other high risk cohorts, with the crude five year death rate standing at 33.2% [26.6% for index myocardial infarction; 41.8% for index stroke]. Furthermore, at the end of the follow-up period, half of the patients with PAD were alive, compared to 59.6% of those in the myocardial infarction group and 51.3% of those with stroke, respectively[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. Broadly similar findings have also been reported in previous studies involving patients with PAD symptoms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>].</p><p>As expected, risk factor analyses revealed that men with PAD were more likely to have atherothrombotic complications, angina, myocardial infarction, stroke, and death [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. Also, the risk of myocardial infarction was significantly increased with in those aged over 65 years, especially with concomitant angina, diabetes mellitus, heart failure, and hypertension &#x02013; the increase in cardiovascular risk in those with PAD was dependent on the number of additional risk factors at the time of diagnosis in comparison to those who did not have any other risk factors at baseline, illustrating how risk factors are additive to each other, resulting in a 'cumulative' cardiovascular risk[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. The parallels with cardiac disease are uncanny.</p><p>The study by Caro et al [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>] does merit some scrutiny. As it is a database/registry-type study, and there are limitations to the data presented. For instance, temporal changes in blood pressures and laboratory values are not available for further analyses, as well as detailed information on optimization of medical therapies. Data on concomitant risk factors such as atrial fibrillation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>] could have helped in further understanding their long term impact on PAD and outcome. Case ascertainment also remains an issue, as the PAD cohort in the study by Caro et al [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>] was identified based on the ICD codes used in case records. Though different methods with varying complexities are used currently [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>], the ankle brachial pressure index seems a simple effective and noninvasive solution and the best mode for diagnosis. However, it would be a daunting task to ensure confirmatory evidence in a standardized detailed population examination of this magnitude. One may argue that the patients with prior stroke and myocardial infarction were at a better advantage, making them a 'more scrutinized' cohort with better provisions for active secondary risk factor modification.</p><p>The conclusion that having PAD puts you at a much higher risk which is comparable to the reference populations is therefore a justified one, and a message that needs to be emphasized. Eventhough the majority of PAD subjects remain asymptomatic, they remain a high-risk population &#x02013; probably even higher than those with single cardiovascular risk factors. Of concern, risk factor reduction by lipid modifying therapy and antiplatelet therapy in those with a diagnosis of PAD is less frequently applied [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>] in comparison to those with cardiac disease. Thus, PAD patients may have had a less intensive risk reduction, leading to a high cardiovascular event rate.</p><p>Should we be surprised? Cynical cardiologists would argue that these aspects are well-known for heart disease, but as PAD commonly presents to vascular surgeons (at least in the UK) the onus is on them to initiate full cardiovascular risk prevention therapies (a 'best medical therapy' strategy), such as smoking cessation and the aggressive treatment of hypertension and lipids. However, many PAD patients also have cardiac problems, and may attend blood pressure and lipid clinics. Perhaps the time has come to organize vascular clinics jointly run by vascular surgeons and vascular physicians (even cardiologists!), as one possible solution. The approach to the PAD patient should not be simply surgery (or a stent) but should include focus on aggressive risk factor modification [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>].</p><p>However, cardiac patients are blessed with many well conducted large randomized controlled clinical trials, which PAD patients often have to depend on subgroup analyses from these studies to inform their management. Though clinical trials of lipid-lowering therapy for patients with PAD per se are not available, a systematic review by the Cochrane collaboration of seven clinical trials [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>] which included 698 patients with PAD, showed a substantial but not statistically significant reduction in total mortality (odds ratio 0.21; 95% confidence interval [CI], 0.03&#x02013;1.17), with lipid-lowering therapy. Furthermore, there are new studies indicating atherosclerosis regression with aggressive lipid-lowering therapy and with antihypertensive therapy, offering an effective interventional target [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>], again emphasising the role for aggressive risk factor modification. Antiplatelet therapy with aspirin or thienopyridine drugs (ticlopidine and clopidogrel) reduces the risk of cardiovascular events in patients with established atherosclerosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>], but in PAD patients included in the Antithrombotic Trialists Collaboration metaanalysis, there was no significant difference in cardiovascular outcomes. As in cardiac disease, blockade of the renin-angiotensin system may offer another therapeutic target. For example, in the Heart Outcomes Prevention Evaluation (HOPE) study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>], 44% of the study population had PAD and an impressive reduction in cardiovascular events was seen in the ACE inhibitor (ramipril) group, the reduction being independent of blood pressure reduction.</p><p>In conclusion, Caro et al [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>] allows us to take stock of our approach to managing PAD. PAD should be managed no different to cardiac disease. Indeed, there is now growing evidence that PAD patients are a high risk group, although still relatively under-detected and under treated. This is despite the fact that PAD patients are an increased mortality rate comparable to those with pre-existing or established cardiovascular disease [myocardial infarction, stroke]. With a holistic approach to atherothrombotic vascular disease, our management of PAD can only get better.</p><sec><title>Pre-publication history</title><p>The pre-publication history for this paper can be accessed here:</p><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2261/5/15/prepub"/></p></sec></body><back><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meijer</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name><name><surname>Grobbee</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunink</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>Determinants of peripheral arterial disease in the elderly: the Rotterdam study</article-title><source>Arch Intern Med</source><year>2000</year><volume>160</volume><fpage>2934</fpage><lpage>2938</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11041900</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archinte.160.19.2934</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reunanen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Takkunen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Aromaa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of intermittent claudication and its effect on mortality</article-title><source>Acta Med Scand</source><year>1982</year><volume>211</volume><fpage>249</fpage><lpage>256</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7102362</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jelnes</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaardsting</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Hougaard Jensen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Baekgaard</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Tonnesen</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Schroeder</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fate in intermittent claudication: outcome and risk factors</article-title><source>Br Med J</source><year>1986</year><volume>293</volume><fpage>1137</fpage><lpage>1140</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3094806</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Criqui</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Fronek</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Barrett-Connor</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Klauber</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Gabriel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The prevalence of peripheral arterial disease in a defined population</article-title><source>Circulation</source><year>1985</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>510</fpage><lpage>515</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3156006</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caro</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Migliaccio-Walle</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishak</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Proskorovsky</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The morbidity and mortality following a diagnosis of peripheral arterial disease: Long-term follow-up of a large database</article-title><source>BMC Cardiovascular Disorders</source><year>2005</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>14</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15972099</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2261-5-14</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dormandy</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rutherford</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><collab>for the TransAtlantic Inter-Society Consensus (TASC) Working Group</collab></person-group><article-title>Management of peripheral arterial disease (PAD)</article-title><source>J Vasc Surg</source><year>2000</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>S1</fpage><lpage>S296</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10666287</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Criqui</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Langer</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Fronek</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>Mortality over a period of 10 years in patients with peripheral arterial disease</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>1992</year><volume>326</volume><fpage>381</fpage><lpage>386</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1729621</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Conway</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lip</surname><given-names>GY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of outcomes of patients with symptomatic peripheral artery disease with and without atrial fibrillation (the West Birmingham Atrial Fibrillation Project)</article-title><source>Am J Cardiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>1422</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15165931</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.amjcard.2004.02.047</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weitz</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><name><surname>Byrne</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Clagett</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>Diagnosis and treatment of chronic arterial insufficiency of the lower extremities: a critical review</article-title><source>Circulation</source><year>1996</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>3026</fpage><lpage>3049</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8941154</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hirsch</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Criqui</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Treat-Jacobson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>Peripheral arterial disease detection, awareness, and treatment in primary care</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2001</year><volume>286</volume><fpage>1317</fpage><lpage>1324</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11560536</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.286.11.1317</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hiatt</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Medical treatment of peripheral arterial disease and claudication</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2001</year><volume>344</volume><fpage>1608</fpage><lpage>1621</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11372014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJM200105243442108</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Belch</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Topol</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Agnelli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bertrand</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Califf</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Clement</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><collab>Prevention of AtherothromboticDisease Network</collab><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>Critical issues in peripheral arterial disease detection and management: a call to action</article-title><source>Arch Intern Med</source><year>2003</year><volume>163</volume><fpage>884</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12719196</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archinte.163.8.884</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leng</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Jepson</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lipid-lowering for lower limb atherosclerosis</article-title><source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source><year>2000</year><fpage>CD000123</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10796489</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>LaRosa</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Grundy</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Waters</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Shear</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Barter</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Fruchart</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>the Treating to New Targets (TNT) Investigators</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2005</year><volume>352</volume><fpage>1425</fpage><lpage>1435</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15755765</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa050461</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nissen</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Tuzcu</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Libby</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghali</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Garza</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><collab>for the CAMELOT Investigators</collab></person-group><article-title>Effect of Antihypertensive Agents on Cardiovascular Events in Patients With Coronary Disease and Normal Blood Pressure: The CAMELOT Study: A Randomized Controlled Trial</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2004</year><volume>292</volume><fpage>2217</fpage><lpage>2225</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15536108</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.292.18.2217</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Antiplatelet Trialists' Collaboration</collab></person-group><article-title>Collaboration overview of randomised trials of antiplatelet therapy: I. Prevention of death, myocardial infarction, and stroke by prolonged anti-platelet therapy in various categories of patients</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year>1994</year><volume>308</volume><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>106</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8298418</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>The Heart Outcomes Prevention Evaluation Study Investigators</collab></person-group><article-title>Effects of an angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitor, ramipril, on cardiovascular events in high-risk patients</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2000</year><volume>342</volume><fpage>145</fpage><lpage>153</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10639539</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJM200001203420301</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>



