<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="other"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">pmed</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosmed</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1549-1277</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1549-1676</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">16187734</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1240053</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.0020327</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Perspectives</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Immunology</subject><subject>Infectious Diseases</subject><subject>Other</subject><subject>Allergy/Immunology</subject><subject>Epidemiology/Public Health</subject><subject>Vaccines</subject><subject>Parasitology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="System Taxonomy"><subject>Infectious Diseases</subject><subject>Microbiology</subject><subject>Medicine in Developing Countries</subject><subject>Immunology and allergy</subject><subject>International health</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The End of the Line for Hookworm? An Update on Vaccine Development</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Perspectives</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Devaney</surname><given-names>Eileen</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><fn id="n1" fn-type="current-aff"><p>Eileen Devaney is Professor of Parasite Immunobiology, Parasitology Group, Institute of Comparative Medicine, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, University of Glasgow, Glasgow, United Kingdom. E-mail: <email>e.devaney&#x00040;vet.gla.ac.uk</email>
</p></fn><fn id="n2" fn-type="COI-statement"><p>
<bold>Competing Interests:</bold> The author is on the Board of Directors of the Moredun Research Institute (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.moredun.org.uk">http://www.moredun.org.uk</ext-link>), a grant-aided public body. A group at the institute is working on vaccine development against nematodes of livestock.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>10</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>4</day><month>10</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><volume>2</volume><issue>10</issue><elocation-id>e327</elocation-id><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; 2005 Eileen Devaney.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2005</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><related-article id="d35e108" related-article-type="companion" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1371/journal.pmed.0020295" xlink:title="research article" vol="2" page="e295">
<article-title>Vaccination with Recombinant Aspartic Hemoglobinase Reduces Parasite Load and Blood Loss after Hookworm Infection</article-title>
</related-article><abstract abstract-type="toc"><p>Gut-associated molecules of human hookworms have been the focus of recent interest as potential vaccine candidates.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><p>Human hookworms are parasitic nematodes infecting about 700 million individuals, largely in tropical regions of the world [<xref rid="pmed-0020327-b1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. In endemic areas, most infected people carry a mixed worm burden, including <named-content content-type="genus-species">Ascaris lumbricoides</named-content> (roundworms), <named-content content-type="genus-species">Trichuris trichuria</named-content> (whipworms), and <named-content content-type="genus-species">Ancylostoma duodenale</named-content> and/or <named-content content-type="genus-species">Necator americanus</named-content> (both hookworms). Of these soil-transmitted helminths, hookworms are the most pathogenic because of their propensity to feed on blood, resulting in anaemia, particularly in those with low iron reserves such as children and women of reproductive age.</p><sec id="s2"><title>The Pathogenesis of Hookworm Infection</title><p>Hookworms' blood-feeding (hematophagous) habits cause pathology in humans and animals. The worms attach to the wall of the small intestine using their mouthparts and feed on blood from ruptured capillaries. Each female worm is estimated to ingest a minimal 0.1 ml of blood per day. However, actual blood loss can be significantly greater; the worms change their feeding sites several times a day, and the secretion of anti-coagulants means that the vacated sites continue to bleed, contributing greatly to blood loss.</p><p>Hookworms do not kill, but they can cause subclinical disease, most notably anaemia and impaired physical and cognitive development in children. As hookworm infection is associated with low socioeconomic status, it adds significantly to the burden of disease in such areas [<xref rid="pmed-0020327-b1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Natural Infection Elicits Poor Immunity</title><p>Hookworms have a simple life cycle in which the third-stage larvae (L3) infect humans, generally by skin penetration, although some species are also infective via oral ingestion. The parasites enter the bloodstream and migrate to the lungs; from there, they are coughed and swallowed to the small intestine (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-0020327-g001">Figure 1</xref>). The adult parasites mature in the intestine, and following mating, the female worm produces many thousands of eggs that pass out in the faeces and develop on the ground to infective L3.</p><fig id="pmed-0020327-g001" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Life Cycle of the Human Hookworm <named-content content-type="genus-species">N. americanus</named-content>
</title><p>(Illustration: Sapna Khandwala, reproduced from [<xref rid="pmed-0020327-b13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>])</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pmed.0020327.g001"/></fig><p>Hookworms can be treated using anthelmintic drugs such as albendazole, but treated people soon become reinfected. Additionally, recent epidemiological studies from China and Brazil show the highest worm burden and the highest prevalence of infection in the elderly [<xref rid="pmed-0020327-b2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>], contrasting with the intensity/prevalence curves for other soil-transmitted helminths, which typically peak in mid-to-late childhood. These data suggest that under natural conditions of exposure, little immunity is evoked. Given this immuno-epidemiological picture, developing a vaccine is a significant challenge.</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>The Search for a Vaccine</title><p>Recent studies suggest that the hematophagous lifestyle of hookworms may prove their downfall. Hookworms are armed with an array of molecules that are essential for blood feeding and digestion; these include anticoagulants and a variety of proteases that digest haemoglobin (Hb) and other serum proteins. In a new article in <italic>PLoS Medicine</italic>, Loukas et al. [<xref rid="pmed-0020327-b3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] now describe a vaccination schedule using one such protease&#x02014;an aspartic haemoglobinase&#x02014;from the hookworm <named-content content-type="genus-species">Ancylostoma caninum</named-content> (<italic>Ac</italic>-APR-1). In their study, the schedule protected against blood loss in an animal model of hookworm infection.</p><p>As with other parasitic nematodes, hookworms are complex multicellular organisms that have evolved an array of mechanisms for suppressing or avoiding host immune responses. The only commercially available vaccine against a parasitic nematode is Huskvac (an oral lungworm vaccine for calves), a preparation of radiation-attenuated L3 of <named-content content-type="genus-species">Dictyocaulus viviparus</named-content>, which protects against parasitic bronchitis [<xref rid="pmed-0020327-b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. In the 1960s, a similar approach was adopted to controlling hookworm infection in dogs using irradiated L3 of <named-content content-type="genus-species">A. caninum</named-content> [<xref rid="pmed-0020327-b5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. While this vaccine was efficacious, it was a commercial failure. However, these older vaccines established the principle that protective immunity can be elicited. The challenge now is to identify protective antigens and present them to the immune system in an appropriate manner.</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Proteases as Potential Vaccine Candidates</title><p>Hookworms express a range of proteases, including cysteine, aspartic, and metallo-proteases, several of which have been characterised in detail. These enzymes are localised to the brush border of the worm intestine and have been shown to function in a multi-enzyme cascade to digest Hb and other serum proteins [<xref rid="pmed-0020327-b6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Some of these molecules show an exquisite specificity; for example, <italic>Na</italic>-APR-2, an aspartic protease from <named-content content-type="genus-species">N. americanus</named-content>, cleaves Hb from the permissive host (human) with twice the efficiency of Hb from a non-permissive host (dog) [<xref rid="pmed-0020327-b7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>].</p><p>These gut-associated molecules of the parasite have been the focus of recent interest as potential vaccine candidates. The rationale behind this approach is that the induction of antibodies to molecules that function in parasite feeding will neutralise their activity and effectively &#x0201c;starve&#x0201d; the worm. A similar approach has previously been trialled against nematode parasites of livestock such as <named-content content-type="genus-species">Haemonchus contortus</named-content> [<xref rid="pmed-0020327-b8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], and some important lessons have been learned. One of these is the requirement for expression of recombinant molecules in a eukaryotic system [<xref rid="pmed-0020327-b9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. In general, bacterial-expressed antigens do not stimulate protection, presumably because they are improperly folded and/or modified and catalytically inactive.</p><p>Under the auspices of the Human Hookworm Vaccine Initiative and the Sabin Vaccine Institute (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sabin.org/hookworm.htm">http://www.sabin.org/hookworm.htm</ext-link>), which supported Loukas and colleagues' study [<xref rid="pmed-0020327-b3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>], the drive to develop a hookworm vaccine has gained significant momentum. A number of candidate antigens have been tested in the <named-content content-type="genus-species">A. caninum</named-content> dog model with varying degrees of success. Ideally, vaccination would protect against infection with L3. The same team of researchers have previously identified one such secreted molecule of the L3 of <named-content content-type="genus-species">N. americanus</named-content>, <italic>Na</italic>-ASP-2 (for abundant secreted protein-2), and have shown it to partially protect dogs against infection [<xref rid="pmed-0020327-b10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Phase 1 safety trials are now underway with this antigen.</p><p>Other candidate molecules are the cysteine and aspartic haemoglobinases from the adult worm. In another study by Loukas and colleagues, vaccination with a catalytically active cathepsin-B-like protease from <named-content content-type="genus-species">A. caninum</named-content> (<italic>Ac</italic>-CP-2) produced in the yeast <named-content content-type="genus-species">Pischia pastoris</named-content> resulted in worms that were stunted and produced fewer eggs but did not produce a reduction in number of worms or protect against anaemia [<xref rid="pmed-0020327-b11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. The current study from the same group tested an active aspartic haemoglobinase (<italic>Ac</italic>-APR-1) in the same model [<xref rid="pmed-0020327-b3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. A modest reduction in worm burden was observed in immunised animals, but a highly significant reduction in worm fecundity was observed (up to 85&#x00025; reduction in mean egg output between vaccinated and adjuvant-only controls), emphasising the nutritional demand of the parasite for egg laying and presumably reflecting an accumulation of neutralising antibodies. Most importantly, four of five vaccinated animals showed a reduction in Hb loss. Thus <italic>Ac</italic>-APR-1 could represent a pathology-limiting component of a future multivalent vaccine [<xref rid="pmed-0020327-b3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. In addition, by restricting worm fecundity it would, in essence, also act as a &#x0201c;transmission blocking&#x0201d; vaccine.</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>The Challenges Ahead</title><p>Despite these achievements, significant challenges remain, such as the selection of appropriate adjuvants for use in humans, the production of the vaccine at low cost and high yield, its distribution in the tropics, and the possible requirement to de-worm individuals prior to vaccination. However, the Human Hookworm Vaccine Initiative is progressing on many of these fronts and is an excellent example of what can be achieved with proper funding and good collaborations. It has the potential to become a 21st-century paradigm for a control programme aimed at a neglected tropical disease and should also provide renewed impetus to control programmes aimed at vaccine development against other hematophagous helminths of humans and domestic animals.</p><p>Finally, it is somewhat ironic to note that as attempts are made to eradicate worm infection in tropical regions of the world, worms are being used in the developed countries to regulate pathogenic proinflammatory immune responses. For example, patients with ulcerative colitis have shown an encouraging amelioration of pathology following infection with the pig whipworm <named-content content-type="genus-species">Trichuris suis</named-content> [<xref rid="pmed-0020327-b12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. These studies demonstrate the capacity of helminth parasites to induce regulatory immune networks in their hosts, and they emphasise the scale of the challenge facing the development of vaccines against worms.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn id="n3" fn-type="other"><p>
<bold>Citation:</bold> Devaney E (2005) The end of the line for hookworm? An update on vaccine development. PLoS Med 2(10): e327.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pmed-0020327-b1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Silva</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name><surname>Brooker</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hotez</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Montresor</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Engels</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Soil-transmitted helminth infections: Updating the global picture</article-title><source>Trends Parasitol</source><year>2003</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>547</fpage><lpage>551</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14642761</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pmed-0020327-b2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bethony</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Emerging patterns of hookworm infection: Influence of aging on the intensity of Necator infection in Hainan province, People's Republic of China</article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source><year>2002</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>1336</fpage><lpage>1344</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12439796</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pmed-0020327-b3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Loukas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bethony</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mendez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujiwara</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name><surname>Goud</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Vaccination with recombinant aspartic hamoglobinase reduces parasite load and blood loss after hookworm infection</article-title><source>PLoS Med</source><year>2005</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>e295</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.0020295</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16231975</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pmed-0020327-b4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jarrett</surname><given-names>WFH</given-names></name><name><surname>Jennings</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name><name><surname>McIntyre</surname><given-names>WIM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mulligan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharp</surname><given-names>NCC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A pasture trial using two immunising doeses of a parasitic bronchitis vaccine</article-title><source>Am J Vet Res</source><year>1961</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>492</fpage><lpage>494</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13789594</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pmed-0020327-b5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Industrial development and field use of the canine hookworm vaccine</article-title><source>Adv Parasitol</source><year>1978</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>333</fpage><lpage>332</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">364958</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pmed-0020327-b6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lecchi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Turk</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name><surname>Choe</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hotez</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A multi-enzyme cascade of hemoglobin proteolysis in the intestine of blood-feeding hookworms</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2004</year><volume>279</volume><fpage>35950</fpage><lpage>35957</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15199048</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pmed-0020327-b7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Brindley</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Abbenante</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Prociv</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cleavage of hemoglobin by hookworm cathepsin D aspartic proteases and its potential contribution to host specificity</article-title><source>FASEB J</source><year>2002</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>1458</fpage><lpage>1460</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12205047</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pmed-0020327-b8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knox</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vaccination against gastro-intestinal nematode parasites of ruminants using gut-expressed antigens</article-title><source>Vet Parasitol</source><year>2001</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11522403</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pmed-0020327-b9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hotez</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Bethony</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Loukas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Progress in the development of a recombinant vaccine for human hookworm disease: The Human Hookworm Vaccine Initiative</article-title><source>Int J Parasitol</source><year>2003</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>1245</fpage><lpage>1258</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13678639</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pmed-0020327-b10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bethony</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Loukas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Smout</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Brooker</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mendez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antibodies against a secreted protein from hookworm larvae reduce the intensity of hookworm infection in humans and vaccinated laboratory animals</article-title><year>2005</year><comment>FASEB J. E-pub ahead of print</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="pmed-0020327-b11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Loukas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bethony</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Goud</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><name><surname>Mendez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Vaccination of dogs with a recombinant cysteine protease from the intestine of canine hookworms diminishes the fecundity and growth of worms</article-title><source>J Infect Dis</source><year>2004</year><volume>189</volume><fpage>1952</fpage><lpage>1961</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15122534</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pmed-0020327-b12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Summers</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Urban</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Weinstock</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>
<named-content content-type="genus-species">Trichuris suis</named-content> therapy for active ulcerative colitis: A randomized controlled trial</article-title><source>Gastroenterology</source><year>2005</year><volume>128</volume><fpage>825</fpage><lpage>832</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15825065</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pmed-0020327-b13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hotez</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bethony</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bottazzi</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Brooker</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Buss</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hookworm: &#x0201c;The great infection of mankind&#x0201d;</article-title><source>PLoS Med</source><year>2005</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>e67</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.0020067</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15783256</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>Hb</term><def><p>haemoglobin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>L3</term><def><p>third-stage larvae</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></back></article>
