<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Genomics</journal-id><journal-title>BMC Genomics</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2164</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15854223</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1112591</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1471-2164-6-58</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-6-58</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Investigating hookworm genomes by comparative analysis of two <italic>Ancylostoma </italic>species</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" equal-contrib="yes" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mitreva</surname><given-names>Makedonka</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>mmitreva@watson.wustl.edu</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" equal-contrib="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>McCarter</surname><given-names>James P</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>jmccarte@watson.wustl.edu</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Arasu</surname><given-names>Prema</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>prema_arasu@ncsu.edu</email></contrib><contrib id="A4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hawdon</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I4">4</xref><email>mtmjmh@gwumc.edu</email></contrib><contrib id="A5" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>jmartin@watson.wustl.edu</email></contrib><contrib id="A6" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dante</surname><given-names>Mike</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>mdante@watson.wustl.edu</email></contrib><contrib id="A7" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wylie</surname><given-names>Todd</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>twylie@watson.wustl.edu</email></contrib><contrib id="A8" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Jian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>jxu@watson.wustl.edu</email></contrib><contrib id="A9" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Stajich</surname><given-names>Jason E</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I5">5</xref><email>jason@cgt.duhs.duke.edu</email></contrib><contrib id="A10" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kapulkin</surname><given-names>Wadim</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I6">6</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I7">7</xref><email>bgywjk@leeds.ac.uk</email></contrib><contrib id="A11" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Clifton</surname><given-names>Sandra W</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>sclifton@watson.wustl.edu</email></contrib><contrib id="A12" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Waterston</surname><given-names>Robert H</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I8">8</xref><email>waterston@gs.washington.edu</email></contrib><contrib id="A13" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>Richard K</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>rwilson@watson.wustl.edu</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Genome Sequencing Center, Department of Genetics, Washington University School of Medicine, St. Louis, MO 63108, USA</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Divergence Inc., St. Louis, MO 63141, USA</aff><aff id="I3"><label>3</label>College of Veterinary Medicine, Department of Molecular Biomedical Sciences, North Carolina State University, Raleigh, NC 27606, USA</aff><aff id="I4"><label>4</label>Department of Microbiology and Tropical Medicine, George Washington University Medical Center, Washington, DC 20037, USA</aff><aff id="I5"><label>5</label>Department of Molecular Genetics and Microbiology, Duke University, Durham, NC 27710, USA</aff><aff id="I6"><label>6</label>Department of Infectious Diseases, Microbiology and Parasitology, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Warsaw Agricultural University, Warszawa, Poland</aff><aff id="I7"><label>7</label>School of Biology, University of Leeds, LEEDS LS2 9JT, UK</aff><aff id="I8"><label>8</label>Department of Genome Sciences, University of Washington, Seattle, WA 98195, USA</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2005</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>26</day><month>4</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><fpage>58</fpage><lpage>58</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2164/6/58"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>12</month><year>2004</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>26</day><month>4</month><year>2005</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2005 Mitreva et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2005</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Mitreva et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>
               Mitreva
               Makedonka
               
               mmitreva@watson.wustl.edu
            </dc:author><dc:title>
            Investigating hookworm genomes by comparative analysis of two Ancylostoma species
         </dc:title><dc:date>2005</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>BMC Genomics 6(1): 58-. (2005)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1471-2164(2005)6:1&#x0003c;58&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1471-2164</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Hookworms, infecting over one billion people, are the mostly closely related major human parasites to the model nematode <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic>. Applying genomics techniques to these species, we analyzed 3,840 and 3,149 genes from <italic>Ancylostoma caninum </italic>and <italic>A. ceylanicum</italic>.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Transcripts originated from libraries representing infective L3 larva, stimulated L3, arrested L3, and adults. Most genes are represented in single stages including abundant transcripts like hsp-20 in infective L3 and <italic>vit-3 </italic>in adults. Over 80% of the genes have homologs in <italic>C. elegans</italic>, and nearly 30% of these were with observable RNA interference phenotypes. Homologies were identified to nematode-specific and clade V specific gene families. To study the evolution of hookworm genes, 574 <italic>A. caninum </italic>/ <italic>A. ceylanicum </italic>orthologs were identified, all of which were found to be under purifying selection with distribution ratios of nonsynonymous to synonymous amino acid substitutions similar to that reported for <italic>C. elegans </italic>/ <italic>C. briggsae </italic>orthologs. The phylogenetic distance between <italic>A. caninum </italic>and <italic>A. ceylanicum </italic>is almost identical to that for <italic>C. elegans </italic>/ <italic>C. briggsae</italic>.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>The genes discovered should substantially accelerate research toward better understanding of the parasites' basic biology as well as new therapies including vaccines and novel anthelmintics.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Comparative sequence analysis is an approach proven to aid in recognition of genes and defining of their function, especially when comparing genomes of close evolutionary distance. In addition, when partial genomes are placed in a context of a well-studied and fully sequenced model organism they can greatly facilitate the understanding of the less studied organisms' biology.</p><p>Hookworms are blood-feeding nematodes that infect one billion people causing iron deficiency anemia and retarded physical and cognitive development in children [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. The two major species infecting humans are <italic>Necator americanus </italic>and <italic>Ancylostoma duodenale</italic>. The closely related hookworm species of canids, <italic>Ancylostoma caninum</italic>, and canines and felines, <italic>A. ceylanicum</italic>, are minor parasites of humans, but are important as laboratory models for hookworm infection and disease. Other hookworms infect raccoons, sheep, seals and a variety of other mammals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]</p><p>Adult (Ad) hookworms inhabit the small intestine and produce eggs that pass in the feces and hatch in the soil. The first stage larva (L1) feeds on bacteria and molts twice to form the non-feeding, infective third stage (iL3). iL3 enters the host by penetrating the skin, or orally in the case of <italic>Ancylostoma </italic>species, molts twice, and matures to Ad in the small intestine. <italic>A. duodenale </italic>and <italic>A. caninum </italic>L3s can also infect a host, temporarily abort maturation and enter an arrested state (hypobiosis) within the host's somatic tissues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>], reactivating in response to host physiological changes such as pregnancy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>].</p><p>Current hookworm control strategies are limited to de-worming of infected people using anthelmintic drugs. However, rapid re-infection in endemic areas and the lack of sterile immunity necessitates repeated treatments and can in turn result in resistance. Additionally, tissue-arrested stages are relatively resilient to the effects of anthelmintics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. The Human Hookworm Vaccine Initiative is beginning clinical trials of a larval hookworm antigen, ASP-2, from <italic>N. americanus</italic>, as a vaccine antigen [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. There is a critical need for further research to identify new vaccine and drug targets as well as to better understand hookworm biology. Lack of sequence information has been a major hindrance to hookworm molecular studies. High throughput sequencing of expressed sequence tags (ESTs; sequences derived from randomly selected cDNA clones) has proven a cost-effective tool for discovering genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. Because the hookworm superfamily (Ancylostomatoidea) falls within nematode Clade V [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>], which also contains the well-studied model nematode <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>], predictions may be made and tested based on their close relatedness. Previous genome-based characterization of hookworms has been limited to sampling of few hundred ESTs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>] and molecular studies of individual genes of interest (eg. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]; reviewed in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]). EST approaches have also been initiated for other Strongylid parasites including <italic>Haemonchus contortus </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>] and <italic>Nippostrongylus brasiliensis </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>].</p><p>In this report we describe the comparative analyses of almost 20,000 ESTs from 7 different cDNA libraries representing pre-parasitic and parasitic larval through adult stages of the hookworms <italic>A. caninum </italic>and <italic>A. ceylanicum</italic>. The dataset defined nearly 7,000 hookworm genes, including a number of putative developmentally expressed genes and candidates for further study as drug target or vaccine components.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Nearly 20,000 <italic>Ancylostoma </italic>derived ESTs were submitted to GenBank between 1999 and 2003 [see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Additional file 1</xref>]. For simplicity, the results and analysis described are presented in the same order beginning with <italic>A. caninum </italic>and followed by <italic>A. ceylanicum</italic>, except where specified.</p><sec><title>EST acquisition and NemaGene organization</title><p>ESTs originated from 7 cDNA libraries, representing three and two life-cycle stages respectively (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). Clustering, implemented to reduce data redundancy and improve sequence quality and length, grouped ESTs into contigs which were further organized into clusters (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>), providing a non-redundant catalog of represented genes. ESTs within a contig derive from nearly identical transcripts while contigs within a cluster may arise from splice isoforms, alleles, or closely related paralogs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. Fifty-one potentially chimeric ESTs were discarded. Clusters ranged in size from a single EST to 203 and 323 for <italic>A. caninum </italic>and <italic>A. ceylanicum </italic>respectively (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). Most clusters for each species (72% and 55%) have ten or fewer ESTs. GC content for coding sequences was similar in the two species (44% and 48%) and consistent with other Clade V nematodes like <italic>C. elegans </italic>and <italic>C. briggsae </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>].</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><italic>Ancylostoma </italic>libraries sequenced and their properties</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td></td><td align="left">Nematode stage (vector or SL1 based)</td><td align="center">ESTs Submitted</td><td align="center">Nucleotides (million)</td><td align="center">Mean read length (bp)</td><td align="center">StDev</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><italic>A. caninum</italic></td><td align="left">Infective L3 (UniZap)</td><td align="right">5,679</td><td align="center">2,632</td><td align="center">358</td><td align="center">109</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">Tissue arrested L3 (SL1)</td><td align="right">820</td><td align="center">0,318</td><td align="center">344</td><td align="center">151</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">Serum stimulated L3 (pAMP)</td><td align="right">2,832</td><td align="center">1,273</td><td align="center">441</td><td align="center">150</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">Overall</td><td align="right">9,331</td><td align="center">4,223</td><td align="center">381</td><td align="center">137</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">Contigs &#x02013; 5,484 (4,020 clusters)</td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">502</td><td align="center">168</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>A. ceylanicum</italic></td><td align="left">Infective L3 (&#x003bb;ZAP II)</td><td align="right">3,359</td><td align="center">2,021</td><td align="center">500</td><td align="center">127</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">Infective L3 (SL1)</td><td align="right">3,306</td><td align="center">1,550</td><td align="center">400</td><td align="center">143</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">Adult (M1 SL1)</td><td align="right">629</td><td align="center">0,319</td><td align="center">460</td><td align="center">134</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">Adult (M2 SL1)</td><td align="right">480</td><td align="center">0,255</td><td align="center">467</td><td align="center">131</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">Adult (&#x003bb;ZAP II)</td><td align="right">2,817</td><td align="center">1,646</td><td align="center">500</td><td align="center">139</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">Overall</td><td align="right">10,591</td><td align="center">5,791</td><td align="center">465</td><td align="center">135</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">Contigs &#x02013; 4,953 (3,369 clusters)</td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">572</td><td align="center">179</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><italic>Ancylostoma </italic>NemaGene v2.0 clustering showing the distribution of ESTs by cluster size. For example, there are three <italic>A. caninum </italic>cluster of size 22 containing a sum of 66 ESTs and there were eight <italic>A. ceylanicum </italic>clusters of size 22 containing a sum of 176 ESTs. Cluster size (x-axis) is shown to scale for 1&#x02013;75 members, with the size of larger clusters indicated.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2164-6-58-1"/></fig><p>The number of clusters may overestimate gene discovery, as one gene may be represented by multiple non-overlapping clusters (fragmentation). By using <italic>C. elegans </italic>as a reference genome (19,522 genes; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]) and discounting for fragmentation calculated as 4.5% and 6.5 % respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>], the estimated gene numbers were reduced to 3,840 for <italic>A. caninum </italic>and 3,149 for <italic>A. ceylanicum </italic>giving a gene discovery rate of 41% (3,840 &#x000d7; 100/9,283) and 30% (3,149 &#x000d7; 100/10,588). These numbers also indicate 20% and 16% representation of all genes for each species respectively. The number of genes in common for more stage-specific <italic>Ancylostoma </italic>libraries analysed was as low as 9% and 11% (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). This may reflect the EST sample size or stage-specific expression, as will be discussed. In either case, the results clearly show the advantage gained for gene discovery in <italic>Ancylostoma </italic>by including diverse life stages in the analysis.</p><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Venn diagram of <italic>A. caninum </italic>(A) and <italic>A. ceylanicum </italic>(B) clusters, based on stage of origin of each cluster's EST members. The majority of clusters are represented by only one stage in this investigation, though greater depth of sampling would likely increase representation by multiple stages.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2164-6-58-2"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Functional classification based on Gene Ontology and KEGG assignments</title><p>Thirty-four percent of <italic>A. caninum </italic>and 54% of <italic>A. ceylanicum </italic>clusters align to InterPro domains and 21% and 36% map to Gene Ontology (GO) respectively. Following this same pattern, <italic>A. caninum </italic>also had fewer BLAST matches (see below). Seven of the ten most abundantly represented InterPro domains were common to both species (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). GO representation is shown by biological process, cellular component, and molecular function (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>). Among the most common GO categories are protein metabolism (GO:0019538) and catalytic activity (GO:0003824).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Most abundantly represented protein domains in <italic>A. caninum </italic>and <italic>A. ceylanicum </italic>datasets</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="left">Species</td><td align="left">InterPro ID</td><td align="center">Clusters #</td><td align="left">Domain descriptor</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><italic>A. caninum</italic></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">IPR001230</td><td align="center">141</td><td align="left">Prenyl group, CAAX box, attachment site</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">IPR001687</td><td align="center">66</td><td align="left">ATP/GTP-binding site motif A (P-loop)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">IPR000694</td><td align="center">62</td><td align="left">Proline-rich region</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">IPR001472</td><td align="center">51</td><td align="left">Bipartite nuclear localization signal</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">IPR000345</td><td align="center">29</td><td align="left">Cytochrome c heme-binding site</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">IPR001283</td><td align="center">25</td><td align="left">Allergen V5/Tpx-1 related</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">IPR002048</td><td align="center">24</td><td align="left">Calcium-binding EF-hand</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">IPR000504</td><td align="center">21</td><td align="left">RNA-binding region RNP-1 (RNA recognition motif)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">IPR000719</td><td align="center">19</td><td align="left">Protein kinase</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">IPR007087</td><td align="center">17</td><td align="left">Zn-finger, C2H2 type</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>A. ceylanicum</italic></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">IPR000694</td><td align="center">214</td><td align="left">Proline-rich region</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">IPR001230</td><td align="center">153</td><td align="left">Prenyl group, CAAX box, attachment site</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">IPR001687</td><td align="center">125</td><td align="left">ATP/GTP-binding site motif A (P-loop)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">IPR000345</td><td align="center">50</td><td align="left">Cytochrome c heme-binding site</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">IPR006209</td><td align="center">48</td><td align="left">EGF-like domain</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">IPR000504</td><td align="center">37</td><td align="left">RNA-binding region RNP-1 (RNA recognition motif)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">IPR001283</td><td align="center">34</td><td align="left">Allergen V5/Tpx-1 related</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">IPR001472</td><td align="center">32</td><td align="left">Bipartite nuclear localization signal</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">IPR000169</td><td align="center">32</td><td align="left">Eukaryotic thiol (cysteine) protease</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">IPR001534</td><td align="center">27</td><td align="left">Transthyretin-like</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>GO mappings for <italic>A. caninum </italic>and <italic>A. ceylanicum </italic>clusters</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="center" colspan="2"><italic>A. caninum</italic></td><td align="center" colspan="2"><italic>A. ceylanicum</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">Categories and subcategories</td><td align="center">Representation</td><td align="center">% Representation of total</td><td align="center">Representation</td><td align="center">% Representation of total</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">biological process</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;cellular process</td><td></td><td align="center">192</td><td align="center">4.80</td><td align="center">238</td><td align="center">4.36</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;&#x02003;cell communication</td><td></td><td align="center">62</td><td align="center">1.55</td><td align="center">66</td><td align="center">1.21</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;&#x02003;cell motility</td><td></td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">0.03</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;&#x02003;cell death</td><td></td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">0.03</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">0.02</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x02003;&#x02003;cell growth and/or maintaince</td><td align="center">140</td><td align="center">3.50</td><td align="center">180</td><td align="center">3.30</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">transport</td><td align="center">119</td><td align="center">2.98</td><td align="center">153</td><td align="center">2.80</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">cell organization and biogenesis</td><td align="center">21</td><td align="center">0.53</td><td align="center">32</td><td align="center">0.59</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">cell proliferation</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">0.10</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">0.11</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">cell homeostasis</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">0.03</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">0.07</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;physiological process</td><td></td><td align="center">579</td><td align="center">14.48</td><td align="center">785</td><td align="center">14.38</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x02003;&#x02003;response to endogenous stimulus</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">0.03</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">0.09</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x02003;&#x02003;response to external stimulus</td><td align="center">12</td><td align="center">0.30</td><td align="center">16</td><td align="center">0.29</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;&#x02003;response to stress</td><td></td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">0.20</td><td align="center">14</td><td align="center">0.26</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;&#x02003;death</td><td></td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">0.03</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">0.02</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;&#x02003;metabolism</td><td></td><td align="center">466</td><td align="center">11.65</td><td align="center">653</td><td align="center">11.96</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;&#x02003;hemostasis</td><td></td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">0.03</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;&#x02003;homeostasis</td><td></td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">0.08</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">0.07</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;&#x02003;secretion</td><td></td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0.00</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">0.02</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;development</td><td></td><td align="center">11</td><td align="center">0.28</td><td align="center">18</td><td align="center">0.33</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left">cellular component</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;cell</td><td></td><td align="center">327</td><td align="center">8.18</td><td align="center">385</td><td align="center">7.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;&#x02003;intracellular</td><td></td><td align="center">212</td><td align="center">5.30</td><td align="center">277</td><td align="center">5.08</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">cytoplasm</td><td align="center">166</td><td align="center">4.15</td><td align="center">181</td><td align="center">3.32</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">nucleus</td><td align="center">45</td><td align="center">1.13</td><td align="center">84</td><td align="center">1.54</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">ribonucleoprotein complex</td><td align="center">102</td><td align="center">2.55</td><td align="center">102</td><td align="center">1.87</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">respiratory chain complex</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">0.10</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">0.09</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">chromosome</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">0.20</td><td align="center">13</td><td align="center">0.24</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">thylakoid</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0.00</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">0.02</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;&#x02003;membrane</td><td></td><td align="center">146</td><td align="center">3.65</td><td align="center">146</td><td align="center">2.67</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;extracellular</td><td></td><td align="center">33</td><td align="center">0.83</td><td align="center">50</td><td align="center">0.92</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Unlocalized</td><td></td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">0.03</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">0.13</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left">molecular function</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;binding</td><td></td><td align="center">323</td><td align="center">8.08</td><td align="center">521</td><td align="center">9.55</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;&#x02003;carbohydrate binding</td><td></td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">0.15</td><td align="center">20</td><td align="center">0.37</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;&#x02003;lipid binding</td><td></td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">0.15</td><td align="center">12</td><td align="center">0.22</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;&#x02003;metal ion binding</td><td></td><td align="center">56</td><td align="center">1.40</td><td align="center">72</td><td align="center">1.32</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;&#x02003;nucleic acid binding</td><td></td><td align="center">109</td><td align="center">2.73</td><td align="center">201</td><td align="center">3.68</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;&#x02003;nucleotide binding</td><td></td><td align="center">133</td><td align="center">3.33</td><td align="center">214</td><td align="center">3.92</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;&#x02003;protein binding</td><td></td><td align="center">11</td><td align="center">0.28</td><td align="center">22</td><td align="center">0.40</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x02003;apoptosis regulator activity</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">0.03</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">0.02</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;chaperone activity</td><td></td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">0.13</td><td align="center">10</td><td align="center">0.18</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x02003;cell adhesion molecule activity</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">0.05</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">0.02</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;catalytic activity</td><td></td><td align="center">293</td><td align="center">7.33</td><td align="center">445</td><td align="center">8.15</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x02003;enzyme regulator activity</td><td align="center">24</td><td align="center">0.60</td><td align="center">35</td><td align="center">0.64</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x02003;molecular function unknown</td><td align="center">38</td><td align="center">0.95</td><td align="center">46</td><td align="center">0.84</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;motor activity</td><td></td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">0.08</td><td align="center">12</td><td align="center">0.22</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x02003;signal transducer activity</td><td align="center">55</td><td align="center">1.38</td><td align="center">61</td><td align="center">1.12</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x02003;structural molecule activity</td><td align="center">107</td><td align="center">2.68</td><td align="center">127</td><td align="center">2.33</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x02003;transcription regulator activity</td><td align="center">19</td><td align="center">0.48</td><td align="center">33</td><td align="center">0.60</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x02003;translation regulator activity</td><td align="center">14</td><td align="center">0.35</td><td align="center">17</td><td align="center">0.31</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;transporter activity</td><td></td><td align="center">128</td><td align="center">3.20</td><td align="center">180</td><td align="center">3.30</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Within <italic>Ancylostoma spp</italic>. clusters that had extracellular mappings, 70% and 56% respectively were in the category of Allergen V5/Tpx-1 proteins (IPR001283) related to the secreted venom proteins from hymenopteran insects (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). The <italic>Ancylostoma </italic>secreted proteins (ASPs) belong to this large gene family [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>], members of which been shown to play roles in host-parasite interactions for both mammalian [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>] and plant parasitic nematodes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>], and to induce protective responses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. ASP-1 is one of the major proteins secreted by serum-stimulated <italic>A. caninum </italic>iL3 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. In addition, four <italic>A. ceylanicum </italic>clusters were classified in extracellular matrix (GO:0005578) as tissue inhibitor of metalloprotease (TIMP) domain proteins. A TIMP homolog is reported as the most abundant protein in adult hookworm excretory/secretory products and may inhibit host metalloproteases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>].</p><p>Ten % and 15% unique clusters for <italic>A. caninum </italic>and <italic>A. ceylanicum </italic>respectively, mapped to 89 metabolic pathways grouped in 11 categories (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref>). Complete listings and graphical representations of the KEGG mappings are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nematode.net"/>. Pathways well represented by both species include glycolysis/gluconeogenesis, citrate cycle, oxidative phosphorylation and fatty acid biosynthesis and metabolism. KEGG analysis (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref>) also suggests specific biochemical differences among <italic>Ancylostoma </italic>stages. For example, while serum stimulated L3-specific clusters make up to 27% of all AC clusters, they account for 40% of all KEGG pathway mappings. In contrast, iL3-specific clusters that account for 55% of all AC clusters make-up only 38% of KEGG pathway mappings. It is unclear whether the predominance of enzyme mappings from the ssL3 stage versus iL3 stage is indicative of greater metabolic activity, greater metabolic complexity, differences in library construction methods, or other differences.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Kegg Biochemical pathway mappings for <italic>A. caninum </italic>and <italic>A. ceylanicum </italic>clusters</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td></td><td align="center">AC</td><td align="center" colspan="4">Clusters per library</td><td></td><td align="center">AE</td><td align="center" colspan="3">Clusters per library</td><td></td><td align="center">Total # of enzymes in KEGG</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td colspan="4"><hr></hr></td><td></td><td colspan="3"><hr></hr></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">KEGG CATEGORY REPRESENTED<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center">Cl<sup>b</sup></td><td align="center">iL3</td><td align="center">taL3</td><td align="center">ssL3</td><td align="center">Mixed</td><td align="center">Enz<sup>c</sup></td><td align="center">Cl<sup>b</sup></td><td align="center">iL3</td><td align="center">Ad</td><td align="center">Mixed</td><td align="center">Enz<sup>c</sup></td><td></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">1. Carbohydrate metabolism</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;1.1 Glycolysis / Gluconeogenesis</td><td align="center">23</td><td align="center">13</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">22</td><td align="center">25</td><td align="center">10</td><td align="center">11</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">23</td><td align="center">40</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;1.2 Citrate cycle (TCA cycle)</td><td align="center">17</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">16</td><td align="center">15</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">15</td><td align="center">23</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;1.3 Pentose phosphate pathway</td><td align="center">9</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">9</td><td align="center">12</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">34</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;1.4 Pentose and glucuronate interconversions</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">9</td><td align="center">9</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">53</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;1.5 Fructose and mannose metabolism</td><td align="center">14</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">15</td><td align="center">20</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">11</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">15</td><td align="center">61</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;1.6 Galactose metabolism</td><td align="center">10</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">12</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">12</td><td align="center">37</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;1.7 Ascorbate and aldarate metabolism</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">29</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;1.8 Pyruvate metabolism</td><td align="center">25</td><td align="center">11</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">11</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">23</td><td align="center">27</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">17</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">26</td><td align="center">67</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;1.9 Glyoxylate and dicarboxylate metabolism</td><td align="center">13</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">14</td><td align="center">9</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">17</td><td align="center">58</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;1.10 Propanoate metabolism</td><td align="center">22</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">10</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">20</td><td align="center">25</td><td align="center">11</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">22</td><td align="center">46</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;1.11 Butanoate metabolism</td><td align="center">22</td><td align="center">9</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">23</td><td align="center">29</td><td align="center">14</td><td align="center">14</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">26</td><td align="center">52</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;1.12 C5-Branched dibasic acid metabolism</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">20</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;1.13 Inositol metabolism</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2. Energy metabolism</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;2.1 Oxidative phosphorylation</td><td align="center">24</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">11</td><td align="center">11</td><td align="center">33</td><td align="center">10</td><td align="center">14</td><td align="center">9</td><td align="center">13</td><td align="center">14</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;2.2 ATP synthesis</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">11</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;2.4 Carbon fixation</td><td align="center">11</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">11</td><td align="center">11</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">13</td><td align="center">23</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;2.5 Reductive carboxylate cycle (CO2 fixation)</td><td align="center">12</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">9</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">13</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;2.6 Methane metabolism</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">26</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;2.7 Nitrogen metabolism</td><td align="center">11</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">14</td><td align="center">12</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">15</td><td align="center">64</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;2.8 Sulfur metabolism</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">9</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">9</td><td align="center">30</td></tr><tr><td align="left">3. Lipid metabolism</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;3.1 Fatty acid biosynthesis (path 1)</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">11</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">14</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;3.2 Fatty acid biosynthesis (path 2)</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;3.3 Fatty acid metabolism</td><td align="center">14</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">17</td><td align="center">21</td><td align="center">13</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">16</td><td align="center">28</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;3.4 Synthesis and degradation of ketone bodies</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">6</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;3.5 Sterol biosynthesis</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">9</td><td align="center">35</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;3.6 Bile acid biosynthesis</td><td align="center">11</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">11</td><td align="center">11</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">10</td><td align="center">27</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;3.8 Androgen and estrogen metabolism</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">9</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">26</td></tr><tr><td align="left">4. Nucleotide metabolism</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;4.1 Purine metabolism</td><td align="center">27</td><td align="center">11</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">11</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">28</td><td align="center">32</td><td align="center">14</td><td align="center">11</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">32</td><td align="center">99</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;4.2 Pyrimidine metabolism</td><td align="center">16</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">15</td><td align="center">22</td><td align="center">9</td><td align="center">12</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">22</td><td align="center">61</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;4.3 Nucleotide sugars metabolism</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">30</td></tr><tr><td align="left">5. Amino acid metabolism</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;5.1 Glutamate metabolism</td><td align="center">11</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">14</td><td align="center">16</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">18</td><td align="center">36</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;5.2 Alanine and aspartate metabolism</td><td align="center">14</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">15</td><td align="center">14</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">15</td><td align="center">38</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;5.3 Glycine, serine and threonine metabolism</td><td align="center">19</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">9</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">14</td><td align="center">21</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">10</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">24</td><td align="center">56</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;5.4 Methionine metabolism</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">9</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">24</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;5.5 Cysteine metabolism</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">11</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">9</td><td align="center">23</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;5.6 Valine, leucine and isoleucine degradation</td><td align="center">16</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">16</td><td align="center">22</td><td align="center">11</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">18</td><td align="center">32</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;5.7 Valine, leucine and isoleucine biosynthesis</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">9</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">15</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;5.8 Lysine biosynthesis</td><td align="center">11</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">10</td><td align="center">9</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">31</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;5.9 Lysine degradation</td><td align="center">19</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">14</td><td align="center">19</td><td align="center">12</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">17</td><td align="center">47</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;5.10 Arginine and proline metabolism</td><td align="center">18</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">20</td><td align="center">22</td><td align="center">11</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">20</td><td align="center">71</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;5.11 Histidine metabolism</td><td align="center">10</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">10</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">39</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;5.12 Tyrosine metabolism</td><td align="center">18</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">19</td><td align="center">19</td><td align="center">11</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">19</td><td align="center">67</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;5.13 Phenylalanine metabolism</td><td align="center">13</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">11</td><td align="center">14</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">12</td><td align="center">40</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;5.14 Tryptophan metabolism</td><td align="center">17</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">15</td><td align="center">22</td><td align="center">16</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">18</td><td align="center">61</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;5.15 Phenylalanine, tyrosine and tryptophan biosynthesis</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">31</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;5.16 Urea cycle and metabolism of amino groups</td><td align="center">10</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">14</td><td align="center">10</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">11</td><td align="center">35</td></tr><tr><td align="left">6. Metabolism of other amino acids</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;6.1 beta-Alanine metabolism</td><td align="center">14</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">13</td><td align="center">11</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">10</td><td align="center">32</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;6.2 Taurine and hypotaurine metabolism</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">14</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;6.3 Aminophosphonate metabolism</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">15</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;6.4 Selenoamino acid metabolism</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">12</td><td align="center">12</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">15</td><td align="center">22</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;6.5 Cyanoamino acid metabolism</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">19</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;6.6 D-Glutamine and D-glutamate metabolism</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">12</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;6.7 D-Arginine and D-ornithine metabolism</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">10</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;6.9 Glutathione metabolism</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">9</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">27</td></tr><tr><td align="left">7. Metabolism of complex carbohydrates</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;7.1 Starch and sucrose metabolism</td><td align="center">18</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">13</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">18</td><td align="center">20</td><td align="center">13</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">20</td><td align="center">75</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;7.2 N-Glycans biosynthesis</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">9</td><td align="center">27</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;7.3 O-Glycans biosynthesis</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;7.5 Aminosugars metabolism</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">10</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">10</td><td align="center">39</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;7.8 Glycosaminoglycan degradation</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">13</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;7.9 Chondroitin / Heparan sulfate biosynthesis</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">18</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;7.10 Keratan sulfate biosynthesis</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">6</td></tr><tr><td align="left">8. Metabolism og complex lipids</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;8.1 Glycerolipid metabolism</td><td align="center">24</td><td align="center">10</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">9</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">22</td><td align="center">25</td><td align="center">10</td><td align="center">13</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">22</td><td align="center">80</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;8.3 Inositol phosphate metabolism</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">25</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;8.4 Sphingophospholipid biosynthesis</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;8.5 Phospholipid degradation</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">11</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;8.6 Sphingoglycolipid metabolism</td><td align="center">11</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">9</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">10</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">20</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;8.9 Globoside metabolism</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">12</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;8.11 Prostaglandin and leukotriene metabolism</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">19</td></tr><tr><td align="left">9. Metabolism of cofactors and vitamins</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;9.2 Riboflavin metabolism</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">13</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;9.3 Vitamin B6 metabolism</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">23</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;9.4 Nicotinate and nicotinamide metabolism</td><td align="center">11</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">15</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">32</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;9.5 Pantothenate and CoA biosynthesis</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">9</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">27</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;9.7 Folate biosynthesis</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">25</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;9.8 One carbon pool by folate</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">10</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">24</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;9.10 Porphyrin and chlorophyll metabolism</td><td align="center">18</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">10</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">12</td><td align="center">27</td><td align="center">15</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">13</td><td align="center">56</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;9.11 Ubiquinone biosynthesis</td><td align="center">19</td><td align="center">10</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">13</td><td align="center">28</td><td align="center">11</td><td align="center">14</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">14</td><td align="center">22</td></tr><tr><td align="left">10. Biosynthesis of secondary metabolites</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;10.1 Terpenoid biosynthesis</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">12</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;10.3 Flavonoids, stilbene and lignin biosynthesis</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">39</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;10.4 Alkaloid biosynthesis I</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">36</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;10.8 Streptomycin biosynthesis</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">14</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;10.9 Erythromycin biosynthesis</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">6</td></tr><tr><td align="left">11. Biodegradation of xenobiotics</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;11.4 Nitrobenzene degradation</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">17</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;11.9 Tetrachloroethene degradation</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;11.10 Styrene degradation</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">18</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;11.1 gamma-Hexachlorocyclohexane degradation</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">12</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;11.1 Fluorene degradation</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">13</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;11.2 Benzoate degradation via CoA ligation</td><td align="center">22</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">10</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">18</td><td align="center">25</td><td align="center">14</td><td align="center">10</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">18</td><td align="center">38</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;11.2 Benzoate degradation via hydroxylation</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">45</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup><italic>A. caninum </italic>&#x02013; 839 multiple and 786 unique mappings; <italic>A. ceylanicum </italic>&#x02013; 957 multiple and 840 unique mappings. <sup>b </sup>Cluster, <sup>c </sup>Enzymes</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Homologs in other organisms, orthologs within <italic>Ancylostoma spp</italic>. and estimates of selective pressure</title><p>Within <italic>A. ceylanicum </italic>clusters, 83% had homology to proteins from other organisms as compared to only 66% for <italic>A. caninum </italic>(Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). To investigate why contigs from closely related species would show a difference in identified homologies, we compared sequence lengths and the open reading frame (ORF) lengths of contigs with and without homologies in both species. EST lengths and contig lengths, respectively, were shorter for <italic>A. caninum </italic>(410 and 549 nucleotides) than for <italic>A. ceylanicum </italic>(490 and 637 nucleotides). The differences were even more striking for ORFs (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). Hence, <italic>A. caninum </italic>contigs very likely identify fewer homologs because these sequences are shorter, contain smaller ORFs, and probably include more 3' UTR versus the superior quality dataset from <italic>A. ceylanicum</italic>. Most likely, differences in library construction and sampling rather than intrinsic differences between the species explain this discrepancy. Accounting for such differences is important as it keeps analysis focused upon interesting features of the dataset related to the organisms' biology rather than artifactual differences arising from data collection.</p><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Venn diagram showing distribution of <italic>A. caninum </italic>(A) and <italic>A. ceylanicum </italic>(B) cluster BLAST matches by database. Amino acid level homologies (&#x02265; e-05) were identified to non-<italic>Ancylostoma </italic>sequences for 65.8% (2,646/4,020) of <italic>A. caninum </italic>and 83.1% (2,801/3,369) of <italic>A. ceylanicum </italic>clusters. Databases used are: for <italic>C. elegans</italic>, Wormpep v.97 and mitochondrial protein sequences; for other nematodes, all GenBank nucleotide data for nematodes except <italic>C. elegans </italic>and <italic>Ancylostoma</italic>; for non-nematodes, nrGenBank (3/20/2003) with all nematode sequences removed.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2164-6-58-3"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Distribution of <italic>A. caninum </italic>and <italic>A. ceylanicum </italic>contigs with and without database amino acid level homology by size of the longest predicted open reading frame (ORF).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2164-6-58-4"/></fig><p>The distribution of identified homologs (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>) was consistent with earlier observations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. Besides <italic>C. elegans</italic>, one of the more informative nematode datasets for this study is a collection of 4,780 ESTs from the human hookworm <italic>Necator americanus </italic>to which homologies were commonly found (42% and 38% respectively). Within <italic>Ancylostoma </italic>itself homologies were common with 34% of total <italic>A. caninum </italic>clusters matching the <italic>A. ceylanicum </italic>dataset and 44% of total <italic>A. ceylanicum </italic>clusters matching <italic>A. caninum</italic>. Searching for putative orthologs between all <italic>A. caninum </italic>and <italic>A. ceylanicum </italic>contigs resulted in 1,304 reciprocal best TBLASTX hits. The ortholog pair members were very similar in GC composition (46% and 47%) and the average length of alignment was 327 bp. All ortholog pairs (574) were under purifying selection (dN/dS &#x0003c; 1; Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>) and the average dS was 0.65 &#x000b1; 0.83 and dN was 0.11 &#x000b1; 0.2. The average dN/dS ratio (~0.17) is higher than that reported for <italic>C. briggsae/C. elegans </italic>(~0.06; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]), and closer to that for mouse/human (0.115; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>]), indicating that the levels of purifying selection are somewhat different. In addition, to examine if this purifying selection is more frequently detected in genes with essential function, we cross-referenced the <italic>C. elegans </italic>genes matched by <italic>Ancylostoma </italic>orthologs with a list of <italic>C. elegans </italic>genes with available RNA interference (RNAi) information (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org"/>; eg. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]). Of the 67% of the orthologous genes matching <italic>C. elegans </italic>genes with available RNAi data, 45% had an observable phenotype after transcript knock-down. A vast majority of the observed phenotypes were severe (88% sterility and embryonic lethality). <italic>Ancylostoma </italic>orthologs matching <italic>C. elegans </italic>genes that had phenotypes showed a somewhat lower dN/dS ratio than those matching genes that remained wild type after RNAi treatment, though the difference was not statistically significant at P &#x0003c; 0.05 (0.09 vs. 0.14; sign. diff. at P &#x0003c; 0.2).</p><fig position="float" id="F5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Distribution of dN/dS ratios among <italic>Ancylostoma </italic>ortholog pairs. dN and dS are the rates of nonsynonymous and synonymous amino acid substitutions, respectively.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2164-6-58-5"/></fig><p>In a 4-way comparison of orthologs in <italic>C. elegans, C. briggsae, A. caninum</italic>, and <italic>A. ceylanicum</italic>, the phylogenetic distance between <italic>A. caninum </italic>and <italic>A. ceylanicum </italic>is almost identical to that between <italic>C. elegans </italic>and <italic>C. briggsae </italic>and the distance between the two genera is just over four times the within genera distance (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>). Average branch lengths for the set of 452 orthologous proteins did not show a significant difference in relative rate of molecular change. Maximum likelihood trees [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>] were constructed for each 4-way ortholog and relative branch lengths compared between <italic>Ancylostoma spp</italic>. for both the protein and nucleotide sequences. For protein sequences, 109 trees had equal branch lengths for the hookworm species while 175 trees had longer <italic>A. caninum </italic>branches and 168 had longer <italic>A. ceylanicum </italic>branches. To look for differences between genes in the <italic>Ancylostoma </italic>species, we constructed a distribution of branch length differences between each of the sister species pairs in our tree. Because some genes may be rapidly evolving in all nematode lineages we evaluated a subset of the trees where the difference in branch lengths between <italic>C. briggsae </italic>and <italic>C. elegans </italic>were less than one standard deviation from the mean but which had significantly different branch lengths in the two <italic>Ancylostoma </italic>species. This final dataset had 23 genes with significantly longer branch lengths in <italic>A. ceylanicum </italic>and 16 in <italic>A. caninum </italic>(1 SD, P &#x0003c; 0.05). However the set did not show any significant bias towards either species (p &#x0003c; 0.34, sign test). This suggests there is no significant rate difference in protein evolution between the two hookworms, although some of these genes are relatively rapidly evolving. Repeating the analysis for nucleotide sequences we find marginally significant differences (p &#x0003c; 0.08; sign test).</p><fig position="float" id="F6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Relative distance based upon protein maximum likelihood. <italic>A. ceylanicum </italic>to <italic>A. cananum </italic>distance is similar to <italic>C. elegans </italic>to <italic>C. briggsae </italic>distance. <italic>Ancylostoma </italic>to <italic>Caenorhabditis </italic>distance for any species is 4.3X the <italic>Ancylostoma </italic>to <italic>Ancylostoma </italic>distance and 4.1X the <italic>Caenorhabditis </italic>to <italic>Caenorhabditis </italic>distance. The length of each line segment is proportional to the calculated branch length between the species.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2164-6-58-6"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Using the <italic>C. elegans </italic>genome to interpret hookworm sequences</title><p>As expected, the <italic>C. elegans </italic>genome provides the best source of information for interpreting hookworm sequences as a majority of <italic>A. caninum </italic>and <italic>A</italic>. <italic>ceylanicum </italic>clusters with BLAST homologies outside <italic>Ancylostoma </italic>had <italic>C. elegans </italic>homologs (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>; 25 most conserved nematode genes between each <italic>Ancylostoma </italic>species and <italic>C. elegans </italic>are available online; [see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">Additional file 2</xref>]). Furthermore, <italic>C. elegans </italic>orthologs of hookworm genes with available RNAi or other data provide information that may be relevant to understanding the role of the parasite genes. Of all the <italic>Ancylostoma </italic>clusters with <italic>C. elegans </italic>homology, 97% and 92% matched <italic>C. elegans </italic>genes with available RNA interference knock-down information <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org"/>, and in turn 33% and 37% of these <italic>C. elegans </italic>genes produce RNAi phenotypes (versus a rate of only ~15% phenotypes for all <italic>C. elegans </italic>genes). Phenotype classification [see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S3">Additional file 3</xref>] showed that <italic>C. elegans </italic>genes with expressed <italic>Ancylostoma </italic>homologs were somewhat more likely to have severe phenotypes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. Hence, certain genes in the <italic>Ancylostoma </italic>datasets encode proteins if disabled may disrupt survival of the parasite. Some examples include abundant clusters (AC00023.cl, AE01104.cl; Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">5</xref> and Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T6">6</xref>). A group of particular interest is proteins that are required for nematode survival and lack strong homologies outside of the phyla (nematode-specific), since these targets could provide for nematode control without toxicities to the host or other non-target organisms. Of the <italic>Ancylostoma </italic>nematode-specific clusters (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>), 85 and 91 respectively had <italic>C. elegans </italic>matches with RNAi phenotypes. Among these, AC04398.cl and AE00474.cl matched hypothetical protein F42A8.1 (1e-65, 2e-76 respectively), a gene without a mammalian homolog yet likely involved in multiple developmental processes based on observed mutant phenotypes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. Homologs are found in at least 13 nematode species to date including free-living species (3), and parasites of mammals (8) and plants (1). Further analysis will identify additional genes which warrant detailed investigation.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>The most abundantly represented transcripts in the <italic>A. caninum </italic>cDNA libraries</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center" colspan="2">non-redundant GenBank</td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td colspan="2"><hr></hr></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>A. caninum </italic>cluster id</td><td align="center">ESTs per cluster</td><td align="center" colspan="3"><underline>ESTs from library</underline></td><td></td><td align="center">Accession</td><td></td><td align="center"><italic>C. elegans </italic>gene</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="center">iL3</td><td align="center">taL3</td><td align="center">ssL3</td><td align="left">Best identity descriptor</td><td align="center">SW / TR<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center">E-value</td><td align="center">Wormpep97<sup>b</sup></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">AC00932.cl</td><td align="center">203</td><td align="center">186</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">17</td><td align="left"><italic>Ancylostoma duodenale </italic>cytochrome oxidase subunit I</td><td align="center">CAD10437</td><td align="center">2e &#x02013; 304</td><td align="center">C06G4.2b</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AC00471.cl</td><td align="center">120</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">118</td><td align="left"><italic>C. elegans </italic>CMP-sialic acid transporter</td><td align="center">O02345</td><td align="center">2e &#x02013; 83</td><td align="center">ZK896.9<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">AC00048.cl</td><td align="center">114</td><td align="center">100</td><td align="center">11</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="left"><italic>C. elegans </italic>hsp-12.6 alpha-B-crystallin</td><td align="center">Q20165</td><td align="center">6e &#x02013; 40</td><td align="center">F38E11.2<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">AC01032.cl</td><td align="center">104</td><td align="center">104</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="left"><italic>Ancylostoma duodenale </italic>cytochrome oxidase subunit II</td><td align="center">AAL50814</td><td align="center">1e &#x02013; 09</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AC01031.cl</td><td align="center">93</td><td align="center">90</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="left"><italic>Ancylostoma duodenale </italic>cytochrome oxidase subunit III</td><td align="center">CAD10435</td><td align="center">2e &#x02013; 143</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AC00807.cl</td><td align="center">69</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">63</td><td align="left"><italic>Necator americanus </italic>ancylostoma secreted protein 1 precursor</td><td align="center">AAD13340</td><td align="center">3e &#x02013; 28</td><td align="center">F33A8.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AC00205.cl</td><td align="center">65</td><td align="center">51</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">13</td><td align="left"><italic>Ancylostoma duodenale </italic>COX2, cytochrome c oxidase subunit II</td><td align="center">NP_579953</td><td align="center">4e &#x02013; 125</td><td align="center">F26E4.12</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AC00967.cl</td><td align="center">54</td><td align="center">9</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">45</td><td align="left"><italic>Ancylostoma ceylanicum </italic>cathepsin D-like aspartic protease</td><td align="center">AAO22152</td><td align="center">8e &#x02013; 174</td><td align="center">R12H7.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AC00134.cl</td><td align="center">44</td><td align="center">44</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="left"><italic>C. elegans </italic>putative protein, nematode specific</td><td align="center">NP_497272</td><td align="center">9e &#x02013; 53</td><td align="center">K02F3.9<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">AC01029.cl</td><td align="center">39</td><td align="center">37</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="left"><italic>C. elegans </italic>stress associated endoplasmic reticulum protein</td><td align="center">NP_510604</td><td align="center">9e &#x02013; 37</td><td align="center">F59F4.2<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">AC00137.cl</td><td align="center">38</td><td align="center">37</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="left"><italic>C. elegans </italic>RNA recognition motif</td><td align="center">CAB03222</td><td align="center">4e &#x02013; 35</td><td align="center">R06C1.4<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">AC00023.cl</td><td align="center">38</td><td align="center">36</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="left"><italic>C. elegans </italic>rpl-2 Ribosomal Proteins L2</td><td align="center">Q9XVF7</td><td align="center">3e &#x02013; 148</td><td align="center">B0250.1<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">AC00060.cl</td><td align="center">36</td><td align="center">36</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="left"><italic>Ancylostoma caninum </italic>secreted protein ASP-2 precursor</td><td align="center">AAC35986</td><td align="center">2e &#x02013; 134</td><td align="center">F11C7.3b</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AC01400.cl</td><td align="center">32</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">31</td><td align="left"><italic>C. elegans </italic>ham-2 zinc finger protein</td><td align="center">NP_508781</td><td align="center">1e &#x02013; 20</td><td align="center">C07A12.1<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">AC00976.cl</td><td align="center">32</td><td align="center">29</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="left"><italic>Tetrahymena pigmentosa </italic>metallothionein MT-2</td><td align="center">AAL87687</td><td align="center">6e &#x02013; 12</td><td align="center">K11G9.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AC00193.cl</td><td align="center">31</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">24</td><td align="left"><italic>Pisum sativum </italic>putative senescence-associated protein</td><td align="center">BAB33421</td><td align="center">2e &#x02013; 61</td><td align="center">F58H1.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AC00931.cl</td><td align="center">29</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">23</td><td align="left">novel</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AC00079.cl</td><td align="center">28</td><td align="center">25</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="left"><italic>Ostertagia ostertagi </italic>unknown protein</td><td align="center">AAC08432</td><td align="center">8e &#x02013; 06</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AC00980.cl</td><td align="center">27</td><td align="center">11</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">16</td><td align="left"><italic>C. elegans </italic>Glycerol kinase</td><td align="center">AAA79749</td><td align="center">8e &#x02013; 70</td><td align="center">R11F4.1<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">AC00971.cl</td><td align="center">26</td><td align="center">9</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">17</td><td align="left"><italic>C. elegans </italic>rpl-1 Ribosomal Protein Large subunit</td><td align="center">NP_491061</td><td align="center">5e &#x02013; 116</td><td align="center">Y71F9AL.13a<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">AC01023.cl</td><td align="center">25</td><td align="center">22</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="left"><italic>Ostertagia ostertagi </italic>putative ES protein F7</td><td align="center">CAD20464</td><td align="center">9e &#x02013; 87</td><td align="center">F02A9.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AC00913.cl</td><td align="center">25</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">17</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="left"><italic>C. elegans </italic>ribosomal protein L37</td><td align="center">O62388</td><td align="center">2e &#x02013; 50</td><td align="center">W01D2.1<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">AC02930.cl</td><td align="center">24</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">24</td><td align="left"><italic>C. elegans </italic>calponin-like protein</td><td align="center">NP_504712</td><td align="center">4e &#x02013; 119</td><td align="center">T25F10.6<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">AC00252.cl</td><td align="center">24</td><td align="center">12</td><td align="center">12</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="left"><italic>C. elegans </italic>rpl-43</td><td align="center">CAB54440</td><td align="center">4e &#x02013; 49</td><td align="center">Y48B6A.2<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">AC01020.cl</td><td align="center">23</td><td align="center">20</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="left"><italic>C. elegans rps-15 </italic>Ribosomal Protein Small subunit RPS-15</td><td align="center">NP_492384</td><td align="center">1e &#x02013; 88</td><td align="center">F36A2.6<sup>b</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a </sup>SW/TR is Swiss-prot and TrEMBL Proteinknowledgebase <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://us.expasy.org/sprot/"/>.</p><p><sup>b </sup><italic>C. elegans </italic>homolog has higher probability match than the best GenBank descriptor.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T6"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>The most abundantly represented transcripts in the <italic>A. ceylanicum </italic>cDNA libraries</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center" colspan="2">non-redundant GenBank</td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td colspan="2"><hr></hr></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>A. ceylanicum </italic>cluster id</td><td align="center">ESTs Per cluster</td><td align="center" colspan="2"><underline>ESTs from Library</underline></td><td></td><td align="center">Accession</td><td></td><td align="center"><italic>C. elegans </italic>gene</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="center">iL3</td><td align="center">Ad</td><td align="left">Best identity descriptor</td><td align="center">SW / TR<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center">E-value</td><td align="center">Wormpep97<sup>b</sup></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">AE00908.cl</td><td align="center">323</td><td align="center">320</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="left"><italic>C. elegans </italic>stress associated endoplasmic reticulum protein</td><td align="center">NP_510604</td><td align="center">9e &#x02013; 37</td><td align="center">F59F4.2<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">AE00787.cl</td><td align="center">205</td><td align="center">205</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="left"><italic>C. elegans </italic>hsp-12.6 alpha-B-crystallin</td><td align="center">Q20165</td><td align="center">7e &#x02013; 39</td><td align="center">F38E11.2<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">AE01104.cl</td><td align="center">155</td><td align="center">155</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="left"><italic>C. elegans </italic>microsomal signal peptidase 25 kDa subunit</td><td align="center">Q9XWW1</td><td align="center">8e &#x02013; 80</td><td align="center">Y37D8A.10<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">AE00463.cl</td><td align="center">119</td><td align="center">118</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="left"><italic>C. elegans </italic>dlc-1 dynein light chain (10.3 kD)</td><td align="center">NP_498422</td><td align="center">9e &#x02013; 56</td><td align="center">T26A5.9<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">AE00121.cl</td><td align="center">110</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">110</td><td align="left"><italic>C. elegans </italic>vit-3 Vitellogenin 3 precursor</td><td align="center">NP_508613</td><td align="center">7e &#x02013; 121</td><td align="center">F59D8.1<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">AE00890.cl</td><td align="center">84</td><td align="center">84</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="left"><italic>C. elegans </italic>spp-4 SaPosin-like Protein family</td><td align="center">NP_509237</td><td align="center">5e &#x02013; 16</td><td align="center">T08A9.8<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">AE00065.cl</td><td align="center">84</td><td align="center">84</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="left"><italic>C. elegans </italic>putative endoplasmic reticulum protein</td><td align="center">NP_508656</td><td align="center">1e &#x02013; 35</td><td align="center">F47B7.1<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">AE00360.cl</td><td align="center">74</td><td align="center">74</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="left">novel</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AE00048.cl</td><td align="center">72</td><td align="center">72</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="left"><italic>C. elegans </italic>rpl-29 60S ribosomal protein L29</td><td align="center">NP_502671</td><td align="center">6e &#x02013; 25</td><td align="center">B0513.3<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">AE00003.cl</td><td align="center">70</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">67</td><td align="left">novel</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AE01410.cl</td><td align="center">63</td><td align="center">60</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="left"><italic>Ostertagia ostertagi </italic>putative ES protein F7</td><td align="center">CAD20464</td><td align="center">3e &#x02013; 86</td><td align="center">F02A9.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AE00056.cl</td><td align="center">62</td><td align="center">56</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="left"><italic>C. elegans </italic>hypothetical protein</td><td align="center">AAK77617</td><td align="center">5e &#x02013; 39</td><td align="center">M01H9.3a<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">AE00464.cl</td><td align="center">61</td><td align="center">61</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="left">novel</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AE00227.cl</td><td align="center">59</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">59</td><td align="left"><italic>Zea mays </italic>extensin-like protein</td><td align="center">S49915</td><td align="center">2e &#x02013; 31</td><td align="center">ZK84.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AE00746.cl</td><td align="center">54</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">54</td><td align="left"><italic>C. elegans </italic>protein contains chitin binding peritrophin-A domain</td><td align="center">AAA19083</td><td align="center">3e &#x02013; 54</td><td align="center">B0280.5<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">AE00750.cl</td><td align="center">50</td><td align="center">36</td><td align="center">14</td><td align="left"><italic>C. elegans </italic>far-7 fatty Acid/Retinol binding protein</td><td align="center">NP_493708</td><td align="center">7e &#x02013; 45</td><td align="center">K01A2.2a<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">AE00072.cl</td><td align="center">47</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">47</td><td align="left"><italic>Beta vulgaris </italic>chitinase</td><td align="center">S51939</td><td align="center">6e &#x02013; 12</td><td align="center">C34D4.11</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AE00591.cl</td><td align="center">45</td><td align="center">45</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="left"><italic>C. elegans </italic>hypothetical protein</td><td align="center">AAF99918</td><td align="center">7e &#x02013; 26</td><td align="center">F29B9.11<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">AE01221.cl</td><td align="center">44</td><td align="center">44</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="left"><italic>Volvox carteri </italic>hydroxyproline-rich glycoprotein DZ-HRGP</td><td align="center">CAB62280</td><td align="center">1e &#x02013; 29</td><td align="center">Y59A8B.19</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AE01407.cl</td><td align="center">41</td><td align="center">41</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="left"><italic>C. elegans </italic>elt-3 GATA-binding transcription factor like</td><td align="center">CAA93510</td><td align="center">5e &#x02013; 18</td><td align="center">K02B9.4<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">AE00033.cl</td><td align="center">41</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">41</td><td align="left"><italic>Nippostrongylus brasiliensis </italic>hsp-20 Nbhsp20</td><td align="center">CAA50655</td><td align="center">8e &#x02013; 56</td><td align="center">T27E4.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AE01361.cl</td><td align="center">40</td><td align="center">39</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="left"><italic>C. elegans </italic>ICD-1 inhibitor of cell death</td><td align="center">AAA68776</td><td align="center">1e &#x02013; 75</td><td align="center">C56C10.8<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">AE00322.cl</td><td align="center">39</td><td align="center">37</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="left"><italic>C. elegans </italic>hypothetical protein</td><td align="center">CAB54416</td><td align="center">7e &#x02013; 28</td><td align="center">Y38E10A.24<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">AE00536.cl</td><td align="center">36</td><td align="center">34</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="left"><italic>Homo sapiens </italic>unnamed protein product</td><td align="center">BAB71316</td><td align="center">4e &#x02013; 134</td><td align="center">F25B5.4a</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AE00503.cl</td><td align="center">35</td><td align="center">13</td><td align="center">22</td><td align="left"><italic>C. elegans </italic>eft-3 elongation factor 1-alpha</td><td align="center">NP_498520</td><td align="center">3e &#x02013; 283</td><td align="center">F31E3.5<sup>b</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a </sup>SW/TR is Swiss-prot and TrEMBL Proteinknowledgebase <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://us.expasy.org/sprot/"/>.</p><p><sup>b </sup><italic>C. elegans </italic>homolog has higher probability match than the best GenBank descriptor.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Repeating the analysis in Stein et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>] indicates that 6&#x02013;7% of <italic>C. elegans </italic>and <italic>C. briggsae </italic>proteins are candidate "orphans", lacking homologs outside of the species. We examined whether these genes are truly orphans that have arisen in a <italic>Caenorhabditis </italic>sub-lineage or are instead genes present in an ancestral nematode that have been lost or evolved beyond recognition in one species. Of candidate orphan proteins, ten from <italic>C. elegans </italic>(Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T7">7</xref>) and 27 from <italic>C. briggsae </italic>[see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S4">Additional file 4</xref>] match <italic>A. caninum </italic>and/or <italic>A. ceylanicum </italic>clusters, with three and eight, respectively, having matches in both species. Most of the <italic>C. elegans </italic>orphans are hypothetical proteins of unknown function though some had functional information from InterPro domains (R10E9.3) or mutant phenotypes (ZK686.1). Therefore, at least a portion of the genes identified in either <italic>C. elegans </italic>or <italic>C. briggsae </italic>as "orphans" are actually ancestral nematode genes with homologs found in other clade V species and further clade V sequencing will likely reveal more such cases.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T7"><label>Table 7</label><caption><p><italic>C. elegans </italic>candidate orphans (1,358 out of 21,437) matching <italic>Ancylostoma </italic>clusters</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="left"><italic>C. elegans </italic>gene<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">Descriptor</td><td align="left"><italic>Ancylostoma </italic>cluster id<sup>b</sup></td><td align="center">ESTs <italic>per </italic>cluster</td><td align="center">E-value</td><td align="center">C. elegans <italic>gene </italic>length (aa)</td><td align="center">Matched region length (%)</td><td align="center">%ID</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">F31E8.1</td><td align="left">Hypothetical protein</td><td align="left">AC05087.cl</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">1e &#x02013; 07</td><td align="center">249</td><td align="center">14.5</td><td align="center">45</td></tr><tr><td align="left">F57B10.14</td><td align="left">Hypothetical protein</td><td align="left">AE02023.cl</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">3e &#x02013; 20</td><td align="center">56</td><td align="center">75.0</td><td align="center">69</td></tr><tr><td align="left">R10E9.3</td><td align="left">Contains Cytochrome C heme-binding site</td><td align="left">AC02329.cl</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">2e &#x02013; 10</td><td align="center">149</td><td align="center">79.2</td><td align="center">32</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">AE00556.cl</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">5e &#x02013; 19</td><td align="center">149</td><td align="center">97.3</td><td align="center">31</td></tr><tr><td align="left">T07A9.13</td><td align="left">Putative nuclear encoded protein</td><td align="left">AE02236.cl</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">4e &#x02013; 31</td><td align="center">111</td><td align="center">91.9</td><td align="center">49</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Y35H6.1</td><td align="left">Hypothetical protein</td><td align="left">AE03902.cl</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">6e &#x02013; 23</td><td align="center">161</td><td align="center">47.2</td><td align="center">48</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Y41C4A.3</td><td align="left">Hypothetical protein</td><td align="left">AE00269.cl</td><td align="center">14</td><td align="center">1e &#x02013; 05</td><td align="center">162</td><td align="center">49.4</td><td align="center">37</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Y54G2A.27</td><td align="left">Hypothetical protein</td><td align="left">AC04390.cl</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">2e &#x02013; 05</td><td align="center">229</td><td align="center">14.4</td><td align="center">38</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">AE01938.cl</td><td align="center">9</td><td align="center">8e &#x02013; 07</td><td align="center">229</td><td align="center">11.4</td><td align="center">48</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ZC487.3</td><td align="left">Hypothetical protein</td><td align="left">AC04655.cl</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">2e &#x02013; 08</td><td align="center">79</td><td align="center">81.0</td><td align="center">38</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ZK686.1</td><td align="left">Nuclear transition protein</td><td align="left">AC00867.cl</td><td align="center">16</td><td align="center">2e &#x02013; 07</td><td align="center">44</td><td align="center">68.2</td><td align="center">62</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">AE01651.cl</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">3e &#x02013; 07</td><td align="center">44</td><td align="center">68.2</td><td align="center">62</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ZK84.5</td><td align="left">Hypothetical protein</td><td align="left">AC00410.cl</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">6e &#x02013; 11</td><td align="center">84</td><td align="center">70.2</td><td align="center">46</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a </sup>Of 21,437 proteins 1,358 were candidate orphans</p><p><sup>b </sup>AC, <italic>Ancylostoma caninum; </italic>AE, <italic>A. ceylanicum</italic></p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Abundant transcripts expressed in <italic>Ancylostoma </italic>species</title><p>The 25 most abundantly represented clusters account for 14% and 19% of ESTs for <italic>A. caninum </italic>and <italic>A. ceylanicum </italic>respectively. The representation of the abundant transcripts varied from shared to stage-specific (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">5</xref> and Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T6">6</xref>). Hookworm developmental stages differ in habitat, morphology and behavior, hence highly represented gene transcripts may identify functions that are important to the parasites at various stages. Differences in gene expression between <italic>A. ceylanicum </italic>stages have been demonstrated previously for several genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>]. Our comparison of iL3 and adult suggests additional examples (see Discussion). In fact, only 9% of the <italic>A. ceylanicum </italic>clusters are shared between iL3 and adult (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>) and of the 25 largest clusters, 23 were biased toward one of the developmental stages (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T6">6</xref>). While representation in EST collections generally correlates with source expression level [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>], artifacts can occur [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>]. Differences in expression are most likely to be accurate when comparing the most abundant transcripts in each stage. Therefore, while follow-up work is needed to confirm expression levels, examination of ESTs provides a list of candidates for various expression profiles.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><sec><title>Overview</title><p>We have taken a genomics approach to the study of hookworm species, key parasites of humans and domestic animals that are related to the model nematode <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic>. Nearly 20,000 ESTs from <italic>Ancylostoma caninum </italic>and <italic>A. ceylanicum </italic>identified approximately 7,000 genes including over 1,300 likely orthologs represented in both species. Close to 900 genes encode putative enzymes involved in 88 metabolic pathways. Over 3,100 genes contain recognizable protein domains many of which have been categorized in the Gene Ontology hierarchy. 4,600 genes have homologs in <italic>C. elegans </italic>including numerous nematode-specific genes and hundreds with observable RNAi phenotypes. ESTs originated from libraries representing infective L3 larva, stimulated L3, tissue arrested L3, and adults resulting in an improved rate of gene discovery and allowing the identification of transcripts abundant in various stages.</p></sec><sec><title>Gene expression in iL3 and dauers</title><p>Infective L3 (iL3) are developmentally-arrested, non-feeding pre-parasitic stages, which when triggered by the infection process and host-specific signals reactivate, molt and complete development. A similar stage in <italic>C. elegans </italic>is called the dauer larva. In <italic>Ancylostoma </italic>species host factors such as dog serum stimulate feeding and an activation response in serum stimulated L3 (ssL3) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>] that approximates the transition to parasitism in the host [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>]. <italic>A. caninum </italic>tissue-arrested L3 (taL3) recovered from infected mice are a distinct population that potentially share properties with the arrested iL3. Developmentally arrested, non-feeding larvae would be expected to be dependent on stored energy reserves and lipid metabolic pathways; accordingly, the KEGG biochemical pathway mappings show a substantive number of clusters for fatty acid metabolism especially with the <italic>A. ceylanicum </italic>iL3 clusters (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref>).</p><p><italic>C. elegans </italic>microarray experiments identified 540 dauer-enriched genes along with genes involved in dauer-recovery [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]. <italic>C. elegans </italic>SAGE experiments identified 358 candidate dauer-specific genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>]. Genes shown to be abundantly expressed in <italic>C. elegans </italic>dauers include a variety of genes that may play roles in extended survival including heat shock protein encoding genes like <italic>hsp-12.6 </italic>and <italic>daf-21 </italic>(Hsp90), <italic>ctl-1 </italic>(cytosolic catalase), <italic>sod-3 </italic>(superoxide dismutase), and <italic>hil-1 </italic>and <italic>hil-3 </italic>(Histone H1's). A number of genes identified both in <italic>Ancylostoma </italic>L3s and <italic>C. elegans </italic>dauers are discussed below.</p><sec><title>Heat-shock Proteins</title><p>hsp-12.6, a member of the <italic>hsp-20 </italic>family, was one of the most highly represented clusters in <italic>A. caninum </italic>iL3 and taL3 as well as <italic>A. ceylanicum </italic>iL3 (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">5</xref> and Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T6">6</xref>). Among a <italic>Strongyloides stercoralis </italic>EST collection, the gene is also found in iL3 but not L1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. <italic>C. elegans </italic>hsp-12.6 is upregulated in dauer and starved L1s [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>] and is a transcriptional target of the FOXO transcription factor DAF-16 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>]. Unlike other HSPs, <italic>C. elegans hsp-12.6 </italic>is not stress-induced and does not prevent aggregation of unfolded proteins, suggesting a novel role. AE00033.cl, found exclusively in adult ESTs, encodes an ortholog of the <italic>Nippostrongylus brasiliensis </italic>HSP-20 protein. <italic>Nb-hsp-20 </italic>is more similar to the HSP-16 group of the HSP-20 family of small HSPs in <italic>C. elegans</italic>, is also expressed in the adult [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>], and is not stress regulated, suggesting that it may function as an adult version of <italic>hsp-12.6</italic>.</p></sec><sec><title>Candidate stress-response proteins</title><p><italic>A. caninum </italic>iL3 showed abundant clusters encoding homologs of the mitochondrial cytochrome oxidase subunits I, II, III and a stress associated endoplasmic reticulum protein not seen in ssL3 (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">5</xref>). One <italic>A. ceylanicum </italic>iL3 abundant cluster encoded a ribosome-associated membrane 4 protein (RAMP4) involved in ER protein translocation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>] which is over-expressed in hypoxia and suppresses degradation of ER membrane proteins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>]. A homolog of <italic>C. elegans spp-4 </italic>was also expressed at high levels in <italic>A. ceylanicum </italic>iL3. <italic>spp-4 </italic>encodes an amoebapore, a member of the saposin-like protein superfamily that kill bacteria by forming membrane ion channels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>]. Amoebapore proteins are one of a number of putative stress response proteins regulated by DAF-16 in <italic>C. elegans </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>]. These proteins, also including lysozyme and thaumatin, may provide a defense against worm pathogens and contribute to dauer longevity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>]. Hookworm free-living stages are also soil dwelling microbiverous organisms exposed to soil pathogens, so it is possible that <italic>spp-4 </italic>plays an antibacterial role in <italic>A. ceylanicum</italic>.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Gene expression in ssL3, adults, and multiple stages</title><p>In contrast to iL3, <italic>A. caninum </italic>ssL3 showed a CMP-sialic acid transporter, cathepsin D-like aspartic protease, calponin-like protein, and ham-2 zinc finger protein among the abundant transcripts. While the significance of these molecules is unknown, upregulation of an aspartic protease during the transition to parasitism and tissue penetration/migration is consistent with its role in degradation of serum proteins and collagens [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>].</p><p>Abundant adult-specific clusters are likely to be involved in reproduction. For example, <italic>A. ceylanicum </italic>(Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T6">6</xref>) encodes an ortholog of the <italic>C. elegans </italic>VIT-3 protein, a lipid binding protein and major yolk component [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>]. VIT-3 is expressed exclusively in the <italic>C. elegans </italic>adult hermaphrodite intestine, secreted, and taken up by oocytes. Two clusters encode genes involved in metabolism of chitin, an important constituent of the nematode eggshell [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>]. One encodes a protein similar to <italic>C. elegans </italic>protein C34D4.11, and shows some similarity to a beet chitinase; the other encodes an ortholog of <italic>C. elegans </italic>B0280.5, a protein required for early embryonic development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>]. B0280.5 mRNA is expressed specifically in the adult hermaphrodite germ line and is a target of GLD-1, an RNA binding protein required for oocyte meiotic cell cycle progression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>].</p><sec><title>ASP's</title><p>While there are differences in the cluster profiles among <italic>Ancylostoma </italic>stages, there are shared transcripts as well. For example, the <italic>Ancylostoma </italic>secreted protein ASP-1 and ASP-like cDNAs are present in abundance in both <italic>A. caninum </italic>iL3 and ssL3. The secretion of ASP-1 protein by ssL3s was noted as a marker of the transition to parasitism [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. These results support conclusions made by Wang and Kim [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>] that arrested larvae are transcriptionally prepared for dauer exit and upon receipt of appropriate stimulatory signals, exit from the arrested state is accompanied by a burst of translational activity in addition to further transcriptional activity. In contrast to ASP-1, ESTs for ASP-2 were exclusively detected in <italic>A. caninum </italic>iL3.</p></sec><sec><title>FAR Proteins</title><p>Two of the most abundant <italic>A. ceylanicum </italic>transcripts encode fatty acid/retinol binding (FAR) proteins (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T6">6</xref>). FAR proteins are novel fatty acid and retinol binding proteins described in nematodes including <italic>A. caninum</italic>, other Strongylida, filarial, and plant parasitic species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>]. In <italic>C. elegans </italic>8 FAR members are divided into 3 groups. All the parasitic nematodes FARs described to date are most similar to the <italic>C. elegans </italic>A group containing <italic>Ce-far-1</italic>, -<italic>2</italic>, and -<italic>6</italic>. Seven <italic>A. ceylanicum </italic>clusters encode FAR proteins. Four of which (9 ESTs) were found in the adult cDNA library; clusters AE00748.cl and AE03203.cl were nearly identical to <italic>Ac-far-1 </italic>and <italic>Ac-far-2 </italic>(98% and 99% nucleotide identity) whereas cluster AE02490.cl showed the highest similarity to <italic>Ce-far-1 </italic>and AE01700.cl to <italic>Ac-far-2</italic>. The iL3 specific clusters AE01410.cl (60/63 ESTs from iL3) and AE03983.cl (2/2 ESTs from iL3) were both most closely related to a FAR protein from <italic>Ostertagia ostertagi </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>], and more distantly to <italic>Ac-far-1 </italic>and <italic>-2</italic>. Therefore, as seen in other parasitic nematodes, most <italic>A. ceylanicum </italic>FAR proteins are related to <italic>C. elegans </italic>group A FAR proteins. However, the <italic>A. ceylanicum </italic>cluster AE00750 was most similar to group C FAR protein <italic>Ce-far-7</italic>. Group C proteins differ from the other FARs in important ways including lacking an N-terminal signal peptide (suggesting an intracellular location), containing several cysteines, and failing to bind DAUDA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">53</xref>]. AE00750.cl represents the first report of a FAR-7 like protein from a parasitic nematode. The function of FAR proteins is unknown but may represent a lipid acquisition system in which released FARs bind to lipids followed by uptake of the complex by a specific receptor mediated process. Retinoids are required for nematode growth and development, but are not synthesized by the worms. In parasitic nematodes, release of FAR proteins may also modify local inflammatory and immunological responses by delivering or sequestering biochemically important lipids [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">54</xref>].</p></sec></sec></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>The application of genomic approaches to hookworms has resulted in more than a 100-fold increase in available sequence data from <italic>Ancylostoma </italic>species thereby allowing an initial bioinformatic analysis of transcripts from these important parasites and establishing a foundation for the eventual completion of a hookworm genome. Semi-automated informatic approaches that are now being applied to all nematode sequences [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">55</xref>] allow uniform comparisons across many genomes and provide databases for further exploration. Transcripts in <italic>A. caninum </italic>and <italic>A. ceylanicum </italic>include clear candidates for stage specific expression representing the very different biological processes underway in different points of the lifecycle. The availability of the <italic>C. elegans </italic>and <italic>C. briggsae </italic>genomes has allowed highly informative comparisons to the two hookworm species showing extensive overlap in gene complements, including genes demonstrated to be essential in <italic>C. elegans </italic>and numerous genes specific to nematodes. As the most closely related major human pathogen to <italic>C. elegans</italic>, hookworms provide an attractive near-term application for using a model organism to better understand and eventually control a key disease-causing species. Beyond categorization of hookworm genes, clear research avenues are available to apply this information to improved methods for hookworm control including anthelmintic and vaccine development, diagnostics, population studies, as well as better understanding of fundamental aspects of hookworm biology, such as host immune system modulation.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Nematode extraction</title><p>A Shanghai strain of <italic>A. caninum </italic>was maintained in beagles as described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>]. Infective L3 (iL3) were recovered from 7&#x02013;10 day old coprocultures using a modified Baermann technique, washed clean of debris with BU buffer (50 mM Na<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>/22 mM KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>/70 mM NaCl, pH 6.8; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">57</xref>]), and snap-frozen by immersion in liquid N<sub>2</sub>. Frozen larvae were stored at -80&#x000b0;C until used for library construction. Serum stimulated larvae (ssL3) were generated by incubating iL3s harvested from a North Carolina strain of <italic>A. caninum </italic>in 5% normal dog serum for 20&#x02013;24 h at 37&#x000b0;C, 5% carbon dioxide. Tissue-arrested L3 larvae (taL3) were recovered from BALB/c mice infected with 1,000&#x02013;1,500 iL3 (North Carolina strain) and euthanized at 10&#x02013;14 days post-infection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">58</xref>].</p><p>A Warsaw strain of <italic>A. ceylanicum </italic>was maintained in Syrian hamsters as described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">59</xref>], and L<sub>3 </sub>recovered, washed, and frozen as above. For the recovery of adult stage <italic>A. ceylanicum</italic>, infected hamsters with patent infections were sacrificed and the small intestine removed. The intestine was cut into 3 sections, opened longitudinally, and hung in 50 ml centrifuge tubes containing phosphate buffered saline at 37&#x000b0;C for 2&#x02013;3 hrs. Following incubation, adult worms were recovered from the sediment, washed free of debris, and snap-frozen as above. All animals were housed and treated in accordance with institutional care and use committee guidelines.</p></sec><sec><title>Preparation of <italic>A. caninum </italic>staged RNA and cDNA libraries</title><p>Pulverization for the ssL3 and taL3 was performed using an Alloy Tool Steel Set (Fisher Scientific International). Total RNA from adult and larval parasites was prepared using TRIzol Reagent (GibcoBRL, Life Technologies or Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA).</p><p>SMART based serum stimulated L3 library &#x02013; Library construction was based on the SMART cDNA library construction system (Clontech Laboratories; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60">60</xref>]). mRNA was extracted from 10 &#x003bc;g of total RNA using a Dynabeads mRNA Purification kit (Dynal Biotech) with some modifications. First strand synthesis was performed with the mRNA bound to the oligo-dT of the Dynabeads using Superscript II RT (Invitrogen, Life Technologies) and the primer smart T7_3G_5. Concatemers were digested with Not I on the bead. Second strand synthesis was performed with the smartT7_5 and the smartCDSII primer. Amplification of the cDNA was performed with the smartT7_5 and smartT7_3 primers with cycling parameters of 95&#x000b0;C for 5 minutes, seven cycles of 95&#x000b0;C for 5 seconds, 60&#x000b0;C for 5 seconds and 68&#x000b0;C for 6 minutes followed by a 4 minute extension at 68&#x000b0;C. Following amplification, the cDNA was purified using the High Pure PCR Product Purification Kit (Roche). The final 5 cycles of PCR introduced the deoxy-UMP primers needed for cloning into the pAMP1 vector (Invitrogen, Life Technologies). cDNA fragments &#x0003e;1 kb were size selected on a 0.8% TAE agarose gel and cloned into the pAMP1 vector following the CloneAMP pAMP1 System (Invitrogen, Life Technologies). The ligation mix introduced into <italic>E. coli </italic>DH10B chemically competent cells (GibcoBRL, Life Technologies) resulted in 4.36 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5 </sup>primary transformants.</p><p>SL1-PCR-based tissue arrested L3 library &#x02013; mRNA was extracted from 2 &#x003bc;g of total RNA using a Dynabeads mRNA Purification kit (Dynal Biotech) and eluted with 10 &#x003bc;l 10 mM Tris-HCl. First strand synthesis was performed using linker primer (GAGAGAGAGAGAGAGAGAGAACTAGTCTCGAGTTTTTTTTTTTTT) and Superscript II RT (Invitrogen, Life Technologies). Amplification with Taq Polymerase used the SL1 (GGGTTTAATTACCCAAGTTTGA) and Xhop (GAGAGAGAACTAGTCTCGA) primers and 5 &#x003bc;l of the first strand reaction. Cycling parameters were 95&#x000b0;C for 5 minutes, 30 cycles of 95&#x000b0;C for 1 minute, 47&#x000b0;C for 1 minute, 72&#x000b0;C for 3 minutes followed by 5 minutes at 72&#x000b0;C. cDNA fragments &#x0003e;1 kb were size selected on a 0.8% TAE agarose gel and cloned into the pCRII-TOPO vector following the TOPO TA protocol (Invitrogen). The ligation mix was introduced into <italic>E. coli </italic>DH10B chemically competent cells (GibcoBRL, Life Technologies).</p><p>Hawdon infective L<sub>3 </sub>library &#x02013; Frozen <italic>A. caninum </italic>L3 pellets were ground to powder on a mortar pre-chilled with liquid nitrogen. Total RNA was isolated from the powder using Trizol reagent (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA). Poly (A)+ RNA was isolated from total RNA using the Oligotex mRNA isolation kit (Qiagen, Chatsworth, CA). Approximately 5 &#x003bc;g of mRNA was used to construct a directional cDNA library in Lambda ZAP II (Stratagene, La Jolla, CA) as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">61</xref>]. pBluescript phagemid were mass excised prior to sequencing. The library had &#x0003e;95% recombinants, and insert size varied from 700&#x02013;3,000 bp. The library was amplified once (10<sup>6 </sup>pfu).</p></sec><sec><title>Preparation of <italic>A. ceylanicum</italic> staged RNA and cDNA libraries</title><p>Hawdon adult and infective L3 <italic>A. ceylanicum </italic>libraries &#x02013; Total RNA and poly (A)+ mRNA were isolated from the appropriate <italic>A. ceylanicum </italic>life-cycle stage using Trizol reagent and the Oligotex mRNA isolation kit as described above. Approximately 5 &#x003bc;g of mRNA was used to construct directional cDNA libraries in Lambda ZAP II (Stratagene, La Jolla, CA) as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">61</xref>]. Both libraries had 99% recombinants with inserts ranging from 500&#x02013;2500 bp (average 1500 bp), and each underwent one round of amplification (10<sup>6 </sup>pfu). Inserts were mass excised as described above.</p><p>SL1-PCR-based infective L3 and adult libraries &#x02013; cDNA was PCR amplified, using SL1-EcoRI primer on the 5' end and oligo(dT)-XhoI on 3' end, gel fractionated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B62">62</xref>], and non-directionally cloned into pCR-TOPO-XL (Invitrogen), following XL-Topo TA cloning protocol. The cDNA inserts were excised with EcoRI.</p></sec><sec><title>Sequencing and clustering</title><p>Sequencing, EST processing and clustering were performed as described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. Information for clone requests and sequence trace files are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nematode.net"/>. The completed cluster assemblies, NemaGene <italic>Ancylostoma caninum </italic>v 2.0 and <italic>A. ceylanicum </italic>v 2.0, were used as the basis for all subsequent analyses and are available for searching and acquisition by FTP at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nematode.net"/>. "Fragmentation", defined as the representation of a single gene by multiple non-overlapping clusters, was estimated by examining <italic>Ancylostoma </italic>clusters with homology to <italic>C. elegans </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. Overall representation of <italic>Ancylostoma </italic>genes is based on a theoretical gene number of 21,437, comparable to <italic>C. elegans </italic>wormpep97.</p></sec><sec><title>Analysis and functional assignments</title><p>Homology assignments &#x02013; WU-BLAST sequence comparisons [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">63</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B64">64</xref>] were performed using <italic>A. caninum </italic>and <italic>A. ceylanicum </italic>contig consensus sequences which were further organized into clusters. Consensus sequences were used to search multiple databases, including the non-redundant GenBank (3/20/2003) and Wormpep v.97 <italic>C. elegans </italic>(Wellcome Trust Sanger Institute, unpublished) protein databases. Internally constructed databases using intersections of data from Genbank, allowed examination of sequences in specific phylogenetic distributions. Homologies were reported for E (expect) value scores of &#x02265; 1e -05.</p><p>To identify cases where <italic>Ancylostoma </italic>homologs in <italic>C. elegans </italic>have been surveyed for knock-down phenotypes using RNA interference, Wormpep BLAST matches were cross-referenced to a list of 17,042 <italic>C. elegans </italic>genes with available RNAi information (20<sup>th </sup>February 2005) <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org"/>. For each <italic>Ancylostoma </italic>cluster, only the best <italic>C. elegans </italic>match was considered.</p><p>Functional classification &#x02013; Clusters were assigned putative functional categorization using two methods. First, InterProScan v.3.1 <ext-link ext-link-type="ftp" xlink:href="ftp://ftp.ebi.ac.uk/pub/software/unix/iprscan"/> was used to search contig translations versus InterPro domains (11/08/02) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B65">65</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B66">66</xref>]. Using InterPro, clusters were mapped to the three organizing principles of the Gene Ontology (GO_200211_assocdb.sql) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B67">67</xref>]. Mappings are stored by MySQL database, displayed using AmiGo (11/25/02) <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.godatabase.org/cgi-bin/go.cgi"/>, and are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nematode.net"/>. Second, clusters were assigned by enzyme commission number to metabolic pathways using the Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) database (2/24/2004)[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B68">68</xref>]. All matches better than 1e-10 were taken into consideration.</p><p>Orthologs and dN/dS ratio &#x02013; <italic>A. caninum </italic>/ <italic>A. ceylanicum </italic>orthologs were determined by reciprocal best TBLASTX match using a threshold of E value &#x02265; 10<sup>-5</sup>. In addition, the ORFs accepted to be the correct translation were required to have the best <italic>C. elegans </italic>gene match in the same frame as the TBLASTX matches. Only continuous alignments longer than 30 amino acids were accepted. 'Suboptimal alignment program' (Jason Stajich, unpublished), scripted using tools in Bioperl [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B69">69</xref>] and utilizing 'yn00' from PAML [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B70">70</xref>], calculated the synonymous (dS) and non-synonymous substitutions (dN) per ortholog pair. A 4-way orthologs were assigned by using SSEARCH [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B71">71</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B72">72</xref>] to find the best <italic>C. elegans </italic>and <italic>C. briggsae </italic>homolog for each ortholog pair of <italic>A. caninum </italic>and <italic>A. ceylanicum</italic>. Orthologs were assigned if both sequences agreed on the best hits. Multiple sequence alignments were performed with MUSCLE [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B73">73</xref>]. Trees were built using the programs 'protml' and 'nucml' for protein and nucleotide sequences respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]. An exhaustive search was used first to enumerate the possible topologies and then -R rearrangement search was used to identify the most likely branch lengths and bootstrap values. Only genes for which well supported topologies where <italic>A. caninum </italic>and <italic>A. ceylanicum </italic>appeared as sisters were used in subsequent analysis. Tree branch lengths were parsed and processed with Perl scripts written using modules from the Bioperl package and statistical tests were applied with the R package [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B74">74</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec><title>List of abbreviations used</title><p>Ad, adult parasite stage; BLAST, basic local alignment search tool; dN, non-synonymous substitutions; dS, synonymous substitutions; EST, expression sequence tag; GO, gene ontology; iL3, infective third larval stage; KEGG, Kyoto encyclopedia of genes and genomes; PCR, polymerase chain reaction; ssL3, serum-stimulated L3; taL3, tissue-arrested L3.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>MM, JPM, SWC, RKW, and RHW conceived and designed the research plan and participated in all aspects of data collection and analysis. MM, JPM, MD, TW, JX, and JES analyzed and interpreted the data. PA, JH, and WK contributed material and constructed cDNA libraries. MM, JPM, PA, and JH drafted the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S1"><caption><title>Additional File 1</title><p>Accession numbers.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2164-6-58-S1.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S2"><caption><title>Additional File 2</title><p>Most conserved nematode genes between <italic>A. caninum </italic>and <italic>C. elegans</italic>.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2164-6-58-S2.xls" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S3"><caption><title>Additional File 3</title><p>Classification of <italic>C. elegans </italic>RNAi phenotypes for genes with <italic>A. caninum </italic>and <italic>A. ceylanicum </italic>homologs.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2164-6-58-S3.xls" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S4"><caption><title>Additional File 4</title><p><italic>C. briggsae </italic>candidate orphans matching <italic>Ancylostoma </italic>clusters.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2164-6-58-S4.xls" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>Ancylostoma EST sequencing at Washington University was supported by NIH-NIAID research grant AI 46593 to RHW. The authors would like to thank B. Chiapelli, C. Murphy, D. Pape, Bin Zhan, Adriana Magalska and E. Janecka for technical assistance, Reshad Dobardzic, Halina Wedrychowicz and Jerzy Behnke, for providing larval strains, and Peter Hotez and the Human Hookworm Initiative from the Sabin Vaccine Institute for their support. JPM was supported by a Helen Hay Whitney/Merck Fellowship. JES is supported by an NSF pre-doctoral fellowship. JPM is employee and equity holder of Divergence Inc; this research was not company funded.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Silva</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name><surname>Brooker</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hotez</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Montresor</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Engels</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Savioli</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Soil-transmitted helminth infections: updating the global picture</article-title><source>Trends Parasitol</source><year>2003</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>547</fpage><lpage>551</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14642761</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pt.2003.10.002</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group><source>Nematode Parasites of Vertebrates, Their Development and Transmission</source><year>2000</year><publisher-name>New York: CABI Publishing</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schad</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Schad GA, Warren KS</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Hypobiosis and related phenomena in hookworm infection</article-title><source>Hookworm Disease Current Status and New Directions</source><year>1990</year><publisher-name>London: Taylor and Francis</publisher-name><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>88</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Girardeau</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transmammary passage of <italic>Ancylostoma caninum </italic>larvae in dogs</article-title><source>J Parasitol</source><year>1968</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>426</fpage><lpage>429</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5761146</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arasu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anthelmintic efficacy against tissue-arrested larvae of <italic>Ancylostoma caninum </italic>in murine hosts</article-title><source>J Parasitol</source><year>1998</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>1263</fpage><lpage>1267</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9920326</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hotez</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Bethony</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Loukas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Goud</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawdon</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Dobardzic</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dobardzic</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>Progress in the development of a recombinant vaccine for human hookworm disease: the Human Hookworm Vaccine Initiative</article-title><source>Int J Parasitol</source><year>2003</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>1245</fpage><lpage>1258</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13678639</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0020-7519(03)00158-9</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boguski</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Tolstoshev</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bassett</surname><given-names>DEJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gene discovery in dbEST</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1994</year><volume>265</volume><fpage>1993</fpage><lpage>1994</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8091218</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blaxter</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>De Ley</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Garey</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>LX</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheldeman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Vierstraete</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanfleteren</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Mackey</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name><name><surname>Dorris</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Frisse</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>A molecular evolutionary framework for the phylum Nematoda</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1998</year><volume>392</volume><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>75</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9510248</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/32160</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blaxter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genes and genomes of <italic>Necator americanus </italic>and related hookworms</article-title><source>Int J Parasitol</source><year>2000</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>347</fpage><lpage>355</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10731559</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0020-7519(99)00198-8</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>The C.elegans Sequencing Consortium</collab></person-group><article-title>Genome Sequence of the Nematode <italic>C. elegans</italic>: A Platform for Investigating Biology</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1998</year><volume>282</volume><fpage>2012</fpage><lpage>2018</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9851916</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.282.5396.2012</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Daub</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Loukas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pritchard</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name><name><surname>Blaxter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A survey of genes expressed in adults of the human hookworm, <italic>Necator americanus</italic></article-title><source>Parasitology</source><year>2000</year><volume>120</volume><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>184</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10726278</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0031182099005375</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hawdon</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hotez</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cloning and characterization of Ancylostoma-secreted protein. A novel protein associated with the transition to parasitism by infective hookworm larvae</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1996</year><volume>271</volume><fpage>6672</fpage><lpage>6678</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8636085</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.271.12.6672</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gasser</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Newton</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genomic and genetic research on bursate nematodes: significance, implications and prospects</article-title><source>Int J Parasitol</source><year>2000</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>509</fpage><lpage>534</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10731573</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0020-7519(00)00021-7</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoekstra</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Visser</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Otsen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tibben</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenstra</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>EST sequencing of the parasitic nematode <italic>Haemonchus contortus </italic>suggests a shift in gene expression during transition to the parasitic stages</article-title><source>Mol Biochem Parasitol</source><year>2000</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>68</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10989145</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0166-6851(00)00255-3</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jasmer</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Dautova Mitreva</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>McCarter</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>mRNA sequences for <italic>Haemonchus contortus </italic>intestinal cathepsin B-like cysteine proteases display an extreme in abundance and diversity compared with other adult mammalian parasitic nematodes</article-title><source>Mol Biochem Parasitol</source><year>2004</year><volume>137</volume><fpage>297</fpage><lpage>305</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15383300</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molbiopara.2004.06.010</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harcus</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name><surname>Parkinson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernandez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Daub</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Selkirk</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>ML</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Maizels</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Signal sequence analysis of expressed sequence tags from the nematode <italic>Nippostrongylus brasiliensis </italic>and the evolution of secreted proteins in parasites</article-title><source>Genome Biol</source><year>2004</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>R39</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15186490</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2004-5-6-r39</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mitreva</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>McCarter</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dante</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wylie</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiapelli</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Pape</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Clifton</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Nutman</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name><name><surname>Waterston</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative Genomics of Gene Expression in the Parasitic and Free-living Nematodes <italic>Strongyloides stercoralis </italic>and <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic></article-title><source>Genome Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>209</fpage><lpage>220</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14762059</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.1524804</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Blasiar</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Blumenthal</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Brent</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Chinwalla</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Clee</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Coghlan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>The Genome Sequence of <italic>Caenorhabditis briggsae</italic>: A Platform for Comparative Genomics</article-title><source>PLoS Biol</source><year>2003</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>E45</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14624247</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.0000045</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bin</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawdon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Qiang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hainan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Huiqing</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Shu-Hua</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Tiehua</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Hotez</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ancylostoma secreted protein 1 (ASP-1) homologues in human hookworms</article-title><source>Mol Biochem Parasitol</source><year>1999</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>143</fpage><lpage>149</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10029316</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0166-6851(98)00157-1</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hotez</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawdon</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cappello</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name><name><surname>Pritchard</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular pathobiology of hookworm infection</article-title><source>Infect Agents Dis</source><year>1995</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>75</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7613730</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tawe</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Pearlman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Unnasch</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lustigman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Angiogenic activity of <italic>Onchocerca volvulus </italic>recombinant proteins similar to vespid venom antigen 5</article-title><source>Mol Biochem Parasitol</source><year>2000</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>99</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10960168</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0166-6851(00)00231-0</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Shields</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hussey</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular cloning and characterisation of a venom allergen AG5-like cDNA from <italic>Meloidogyne incognita</italic></article-title><source>Int J Parasitol</source><year>2001</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10675748</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0020-7519(99)00165-4</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Badamchian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Meihua</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashcom</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawdon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Shuhua</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Hotez</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular cloning and purification of Ac-TMP, a developmentally regulated putative tissue inhibitor of metalloprotease released in relative abundance by adult <italic>Ancylostoma </italic>hookworms</article-title><source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source><year>2002</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>238</fpage><lpage>244</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12139214</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Waterston</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindblad-Toh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Birney</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Abril</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Agarwal</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Agarwala</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ainscough</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Alexandersson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>An</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>Initial sequencing and comparative analysis of the mouse genome</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2002</year><volume>420</volume><fpage>520</fpage><lpage>562</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12466850</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature01262</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kamath</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Poulin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Durbin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gotta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanapin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Bot</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sohrmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>Systematic functional analysis of the <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans </italic>genome using RNAi</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2003</year><volume>421</volume><fpage>231</fpage><lpage>237</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12529635</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature01278</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B26"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adachi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasegawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><source>MOLPHY version 23: Programs for Molecular Phylogenetics based on Maximum Likelihood</source><year>1996</year><publisher-name>Tokyo: Institute of Statistical Mathematics</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hawdon</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Narasimhan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hotez</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ancylostoma secreted protein 2: cloning and characterization of a second member of a family of nematode secreted proteins from <italic>Ancylostoma caninum</italic></article-title><source>Mol Biochem Parasitol</source><year>1999</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>165</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10340481</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0166-6851(99)00011-0</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hotez</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawdon</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A developmentally regulated metalloprotease secreted by host-stimulated <italic>Ancylostoma caninum </italic>third-stage infective larvae is a member of the astacin family of proteases</article-title><source>Mol Biochem Parasitol</source><year>2002</year><volume>120</volume><fpage>291</fpage><lpage>296</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11897134</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0166-6851(01)00453-4</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Audic</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Claverie</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Significance of Digital Gene Expression Profiles</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><year>1997</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>986</fpage><lpage>995</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9331369</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mitreva</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jasmer</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Appleton</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dante</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wylie</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Clifton</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Waterston</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>McCarter</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gene discovery in the adenophorean nematode <italic>Trichinella spiralis</italic>: an analysis of transcription from three life cycle stages</article-title><source>Mol Biochem Parasitol</source><year>2004</year><volume>137</volume><fpage>277</fpage><lpage>291</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15383298</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molbiopara.2004.05.015</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Munoz</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name><name><surname>Bogarad</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Deem</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microarray and EST database estimates of mRNA expression levels differ: the protein length versus expression curve for <italic>C. elegans</italic></article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2004</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>30</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15134588</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-5-30</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arasu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwak</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Developmental arrest and pregnancy-induced transmammary transmission of <italic>Ancylostoma caninum </italic>larvae in the murine model</article-title><source>J Parasitol</source><year>1999</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>779</fpage><lpage>784</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10577710</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s004360050631</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brand</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawdon</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phosphoinositide-3-OH-kinase inhibitor LY294002 prevents activation of <italic>Ancylostoma caninum </italic>and <italic>Ancylostoma ceylanicum </italic>third-stage infective larvae</article-title><source>Int J Parasitol</source><year>2004</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>909</fpage><lpage>914</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15217729</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijpara.2004.04.003</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global analysis of dauer gene expression in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic></article-title><source>Development</source><year>2003</year><volume>130</volume><fpage>1621</fpage><lpage>1634</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12620986</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.00363</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Riddle</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Pouzyrev</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Velculescu</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hillier</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Eddy</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Stricklin</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Baillie</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Waterston</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Marra</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Changes in Gene Expression Associated with Developmental Arrest and Longevity in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic></article-title><source>Genome Res</source><year>2001</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1346</fpage><lpage>1352</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11483575</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.184401</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leroux</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Batelier</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Melki</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Candido</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Unique structural features of a novel class of small heat shock proteins</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1997</year><volume>272</volume><fpage>12847</fpage><lpage>12853</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9139746</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.272.19.12847</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name><surname>McCarroll</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bargmann</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name><name><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamath</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahringer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kenyon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genes that act downstream of DAF-16 to influence the lifespan of <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic>. [see comment]</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2003</year><volume>424</volume><fpage>277</fpage><lpage>283</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12845331</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature01789</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tweedie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Grigg</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Ingram</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Selkirk</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The expression of a small heat shock protein homologue is developmentally regulated in <italic>Nippostrongylus brasiliensis</italic></article-title><source>Mol Biochem Parasitol</source><year>1993</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>153</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8259127</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0166-6851(93)90168-W</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B39"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hori</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Stern</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartmann</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tohyama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stress-associated endoplasmic reticulum protein 1 (SERP1)/Ribosome-associated membrane protein 4 (RAMP4) stabilizes membrane proteins during stress and facilitates subsequent glycosylation</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>1999</year><volume>147</volume><fpage>1195</fpage><lpage>1204</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10601334</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.147.6.1195</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B40"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Dobberstein</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oligomeric complexes involved in translocation of proteins across the membrane of the endoplasmic reticulum</article-title><source>FEBS Letters</source><year>1999</year><volume>457</volume><fpage>316</fpage><lpage>322</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10471800</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0014-5793(99)01075-3</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B41"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leippe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Andra</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nickel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Tannich</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Muller-Eberhard</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Amoebapores, a family of membranolytic peptides from cytoplasmic granules of <italic>Entamoeba histolytica</italic>: isolation, primary structure, and pore formation in bacterial cytoplasmic membranes</article-title><source>Mol Microbiol</source><year>1994</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>895</fpage><lpage>904</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7715451</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B42"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nicholas</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hodgkin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Responses to infection and possible recognition strategies in the innate immune system of <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic></article-title><source>Mol Immunology</source><year>2004</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>479</fpage><lpage>493</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molimm.2004.03.037</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B43"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garsin</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Villanueva</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Begun</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Sifri</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Calderwood</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruvkun</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ausubel</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long-lived <italic>C.elegans </italic>daf-2 mutants are resistant to bacterial pathogens</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2003</year><volume>300</volume><fpage>1921</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12817143</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1080147</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B44"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Brindley</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Loukas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hookworm cathepsin D aspartic proteases: contributing roles in the host-specific degradation of serum proteins and skin macromolecules</article-title><source>Parasitology</source><year>2003</year><volume>126</volume><fpage>179</fpage><lpage>185</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12636356</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0031182002002706</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B45"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spieth</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Blumenthal</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans </italic>vitellogenin gene family includes a gene encoding a distantly related protein</article-title><source>Mol Cellular Biology</source><year>1985</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>2495</fpage><lpage>2501</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B46"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spindler</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Spindler-Barth</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Londershausen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chitin metabolism: a target for drugs against parasites</article-title><source>Parasitol Res</source><year>1990</year><volume>76</volume><fpage>283</fpage><lpage>288</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2186405</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00928180</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B47"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Schedl</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of in vivo mRNA targets of GLD-1, a maxi-KH motif containing protein required for <italic>C. elegans </italic>germ cell development</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>2001</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>2408</fpage><lpage>2420</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11562350</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.915901</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B48"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson-Berry</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Dang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Schedl</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Control of the proliferation versus meiotic development decision in the <italic>C. elegans </italic>germline through regulation of GLD-1 protein accumulation</article-title><source>Development</source><year>2004</year><volume>131</volume><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>104</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14660440</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.00916</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B49"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Basavaraju</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawdon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hotez</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ac-FAR-1, a 20 kDa fatty acid- and retinol-binding protein secreted by adult <italic>Ancylostoma caninum </italic>hookworms: gene transcription pattern, ligand binding properties and structural characterisation</article-title><source>Mol Biochem Parasitol</source><year>2003</year><volume>126</volume><fpage>63</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12554085</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0166-6851(02)00253-0</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B50"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garofalo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Klager</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Rowlinson</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Nirmalan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Klion</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The FAR proteins of filarial nematodes: secretion, glycosylation and lipid binding characteristics</article-title><source>Mol Biochem Parasitol</source><year>2002</year><volume>122</volume><fpage>161</fpage><lpage>170</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12106870</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0166-6851(02)00097-X</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B51"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prior</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Blok</surname><given-names>VC</given-names></name><name><surname>Beauchamp</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>McDermott</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A surface-associated retinol- and fatty acid-binding protein (Gp-FAR-1) from the potato cyst nematode <italic>Globodera pallida</italic>: lipid binding activities, structural analysis and expression pattern</article-title><source>Biochem J</source><year>2001</year><volume>356</volume><fpage>387</fpage><lpage>394</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11368765</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/0264-6021:3560387</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B52"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vercauteren</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Geldhof</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Peelaers</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Claerebout</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Berx</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Vercruysse</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of excretory-secretory products of larval and adult <italic>Ostertagia ostertagi </italic>by immunoscreening of cDNA libraries</article-title><source>Mol Biochem Parasitol</source><year>2003</year><volume>126</volume><fpage>201</fpage><lpage>208</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12615319</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0166-6851(02)00274-8</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B53"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garofalo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rowlinson</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Amambua</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The FAR protein family of the nematode <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic>. Differential lipid binding properties, structural characteristics, and developmental regulation</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2003</year><volume>278</volume><fpage>8065</fpage><lpage>8074</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12502713</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M206278200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B54"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Nirmalan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Klager</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Faulkner</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>River blindness: a role for parasite retinoid-binding proteins in the generation of pathology?</article-title><source>Trends Parasitol</source><year>2001</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>471</fpage><lpage>475</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11587960</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1471-4922(01)02036-0</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B55"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parkinson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitreva</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitton</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Daub</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Barrell</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Waterston</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>McCarter</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Blaxter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A transcriptomic analysis of the phylum Nematoda</article-title><source>Nature Genetics</source><year>2004</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>1259</fpage><lpage>1267</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15543149</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng1472</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B56"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hawdon</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Datu</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The second messenger cyclic GMP mediates activation in <italic>Ancylostoma caninum </italic>infective larvae</article-title><source>Int J Parasitol</source><year>2003</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>787</fpage><lpage>793</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12865078</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0020-7519(03)00088-2</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B57"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hawdon</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Schad</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long-term storage of hookworm infective larvae in buffered saline solution maintains larval responsiveness to host signals</article-title><source>J Helm Soc Wash</source><year>1991</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>140</fpage><lpage>142</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B58"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arasu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vitro reactivation of <italic>Ancylostoma caninum </italic>tissue-arrested third-stage larvae by transforming growth factor-beta</article-title><source>J Parasitol</source><year>2001</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>733</fpage><lpage>738</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11534634</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B59"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hawdon</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Volk</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Pritchard</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name><name><surname>Schad</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Resumption of feeding in vitro by hookworm third-stage larvae: a comparative study</article-title><source>J Parasitol</source><year>1992</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>1036</fpage><lpage>1040</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1491295</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B60"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ciavatta</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Cairney</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation of full-length cDNA clones using SMART cDNA and a biotin-streptavidin bead system</article-title><source>Biotechniques</source><year>2000</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>444</fpage><lpage>446</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10997256</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B61"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawdon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Shan</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Qiang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Hotez</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Construction and analysis of cDNA library of <italic>Necator americanus </italic>third stage larvae</article-title><source>J Parasitol Paras Dis</source><year>2000</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>26</fpage><lpage>28</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B62"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Osoegawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Woon</surname><given-names>PY</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Frengen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Tateno</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Catanese</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>de Jong</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An improved approach for construction of bacterial artificial chromosome libraries</article-title><source>Genomics</source><year>1998</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9740665</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/geno.1998.5423</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B63"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Altschul</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Gish</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipman</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Basic local alignment search tool</article-title><source>J Mol Biol</source><year>1990</year><volume>215</volume><fpage>403</fpage><lpage>410</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2231712</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/jmbi.1990.9999</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B64"><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gish</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blast.wustl.edu."/><comment>1996&#x02013;2002</comment></citation></ref><ref id="B65"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Apweiler</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Attwood</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name><name><surname>Bairoch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bateman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Birney</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Biswas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bucher</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Cerutti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Corpet</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Croning</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>The InterPro database, an integrated documentation resource for protein families, domains and functional sites</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2001</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11125043</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/29.1.37</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B66"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zdobnov</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Apweiler</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>InterProScan &#x02013; an integration platform for the signature-recognition methods in InterPro</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2001</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>847</fpage><lpage>848</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11590104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/17.9.847</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B67"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>The Gene Ontology Consortium</collab></person-group><article-title>Gene ontology: tool for the unification of biology</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2000</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10802651</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/75556</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B68"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kanehisa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Goto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>KEGG: kyoto encyclopedia of genes and genomes</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2000</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10592173</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/28.1.27</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B69"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stajich</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Block</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Boulez</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Chervitz</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dagdigian</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuellen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilbert</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Korf</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Lapp</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>The Bioperl toolkit: Perl modules for the life sciences</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><year>2002</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1611</fpage><lpage>1618</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12368254</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.361602</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B70"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PAML: A program package for phylogenetic analysis by maximum likelhood</article-title><source>Comput Appl Biosci</source><year>1997</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>555</fpage><lpage>556</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9367129</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B71"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Searching protein sequence libraries: comparison of the sensitivity and selectivity of the Smith-Waterman and FASTA algorithms</article-title><source>Genomics</source><year>1991</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>635</fpage><lpage>650</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1774068</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0888-7543(91)90071-L</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B72"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name><name><surname>Waterman</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of common molecular subsequences</article-title><source>J Mol Biol</source><year>1981</year><volume>147</volume><fpage>195</fpage><lpage>197</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7265238</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0022-2836(81)90087-5</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B73"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Edgar</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MUSCLE: multiple sequence alignment with high accuracy and high throughput</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>1792</fpage><lpage>1797</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15034147</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkh340</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B74"><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>R Development Core team</collab></person-group><source>R: A language and environment for statistical computing</source><year>2004</year><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.r-project.org/."/></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>



