<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Health Qual Life Outcomes</journal-id><journal-title>Health and Quality of Life Outcomes</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1477-7525</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">16153294</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1215504</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1477-7525-3-56</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1477-7525-3-56</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Health-related quality of life is related to COPD disease severity</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>St&#x000e5;hl</surname><given-names>Elisabeth</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>elisabeth.stahl@astrazeneca.com</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lindberg</surname><given-names>Anne</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I4">4</xref><email>anne.lindberg@nll.se</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jansson</surname><given-names>Sven-Arne</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I5">5</xref><email>svenarne.jansson@holmsund.nu</email></contrib><contrib id="A4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>R&#x000f6;nmark</surname><given-names>Eva</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I5">5</xref><email>eva.ronmark@telia.com</email></contrib><contrib id="A5" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Svensson</surname><given-names>Klas</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>klas.sv@telia.com</email></contrib><contrib id="A6" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>Fredrik</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>fredrik.l.andersson@astrazeneca.com</email></contrib><contrib id="A7" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>L&#x000f6;fdahl</surname><given-names>Claes-G&#x000f6;ran</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>claes-goran.lofdahl@lung.lu.se</email></contrib><contrib id="A8" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lundb&#x000e4;ck</surname><given-names>Bo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I5">5</xref><email>bo.lundback@telia.com</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Respiratory Medicine and Allergology, University Hospital, SE-221 85 Lund, Sweden</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>AstraZeneca R&#x00026;D Lund, SE-221 87 Lund, Sweden</aff><aff id="I3"><label>3</label>The OLIN Studies, Department of Medicine, Sunderby Central Hospital of Norrbotten, SE-971 80 Lule&#x000e5;, Sweden</aff><aff id="I4"><label>4</label>Department of Respiratory Medicine and Allergy, University Hospital, SE-901 85 Ume&#x000e5;, Sweden</aff><aff id="I5"><label>5</label>Lung and Allergy Research, National Institute of Environmental Medicine, the Karolinska Institute, SE-171 77 Stockholm, Sweden</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2005</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>9</day><month>9</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><volume>3</volume><fpage>56</fpage><lpage>56</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.hqlo.com/content/3/1/56"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>13</day><month>7</month><year>2005</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>9</day><month>9</month><year>2005</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2005 St&#x000e5;hl et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2005</copyright-year><copyright-holder>St&#x000e5;hl et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>
               St&#x000e5;hl
               Elisabeth
               
               
               elisabeth.stahl@astrazeneca.com
            </dc:author><dc:title>
            Health-related quality of life is related to COPD disease severity
         </dc:title><dc:date>2005</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>Health and Quality of Life Outcomes 3(1): 56-. (2005)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1477-7525(2005)3:1&#x0003c;56&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1477-7525</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>The aim of this study was to evaluate the association between health-related quality of life (HRQL) and disease severity using lung function measures.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><p>A survey was performed in subjects with COPD in Sweden. 168 subjects (70 women, mean age 64.3 years) completed the generic HRQL questionnaire, the Short Form 36 (SF-36), the disease-specific HRQL questionnaire; the St George's Respiratory Questionnaire (SGRQ), and the utility measure, the EQ-5D. The subjects were divided into four severity groups according to FEV<sub>1 </sub>per cent of predicted normal using two clinical guidelines: GOLD and BTS. Age, gender, smoking status and socio-economic group were regarded as confounders.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>The COPD severity grades affected the SGRQ Total scores, varying from 25 to 53 (GOLD p = 0.0005) and from 25 to 45 (BTS p = 0.0023). The scores for SF-36 Physical were significantly associated with COPD severity (GOLD p = 0.0059, BTS p = 0.032). No significant association were noticed for the SF-36, Mental Component Summary scores and COPD severity. Scores for EQ-5D VAS varied from 73 to 37 (GOLD I-IV p = 0.0001) and from 73 to 50 (BTS 0-III p = 0.0007). The SGRQ Total score was significant between age groups (p = 0.0047). No significant differences in HRQL with regard to gender, smoking status or socio-economic group were noticed.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>The results show that HRQL in COPD deteriorates with disease severity and with age. These data show a relationship between HRQL and disease severity obtained by lung function.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Health-related quality of life</kwd><kwd>COPD</kwd><kwd>disease severity</kwd><kwd>epidemiological, Global Initiative for Chronic Obstructive Lung Disease (GOLD)</kwd><kwd>St George's Respiratory Questionnaire (SGRQ)</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) is a major cause of morbidity and mortality worldwide and is currently the fourth leading cause of death in the US [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. It is a slowly progressive disease, characterized by lung function impairment with airway obstruction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. Common symptoms are cough, sputum production and shortness of breath. Smoking and different air pollutants, such as are well-known risk factors for COPD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>].</p><p>The prevalence of COPD varies considerably between countries and areas, from 3% in India [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>] to 23% in the inner-city population of Manchester, UK [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. The US National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey (NHANES) III survey puts the prevalence of COPD in the US at 7% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. The figure in Spain is similar, 9% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. In Sweden, the prevalence of COPD in those aged above 45 years was estimated to be 8% according to the British Thoracic Society (BTS) criteria and 14% according to the Global Initiative for Chronic Obstructive Lung Disease (GOLD) guidelines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. However, there are a considerable number of subjects with COPD who have not been diagnosed as such. In Europe and also in Sweden only one-quarter to one-third of those with COPD have been diagnosed as having COPD or with different labelling of the disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>].</p><p>Over the past decade, more and more research on the development and validation of questionnaires has been undertaken to quantify the impact of disease on daily life and well-being from the COPD subject's point of view [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. Health-related quality of life (HRQL), and preference-based HRQL instruments (utility instruments) are increasingly used in clinical studies. Although their use is established in many fields, such as oncology and gastrointestinal disease, questionnaires are rarely used as primary endpoints in randomised clinical studies of respiratory disease. One possible reason may be the lack of information about the patients' deterioration in HRQL when the disease progresses. The Medical Outcomes Study Short Form 36 (SF-36) and St George's Respiratory Questionnaire (SGRQ) are generic and disease-specific HRQL questionnaires, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. The SF-36 has been used in a number of therapeutic areas, including COPD, while the SGRQ has been widely used in both COPD and asthma research. The EQ-5D is a generic, preference-based utility measure and has been used in a number of therapeutic areas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>].</p><p>The aim of the present study was to evaluate the association between HRQL and COPD stages using forced expiratory volume in one second as a percentage of predicted normal values (FEV<sub>1 </sub>% predicted) by means of two clinical guidelines for COPD, taking into account the influence on HRQL of age, gender, smoking status and socio-economic background. The association between HRQL and forced vital capacity as a percentage of predicted normal values (FVC % predicted) was also evaluated.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Study sample</title><p>A total of 202 subjects with COPD, recruited from a representative sample of the general population in northern Sweden, were invited; 176 subjects took part in this survey and data from 168 subjects were available [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. The study cohort was derived from the Obstructive Lung Disease in Northern Sweden (OLIN) Studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>], which has previously been described in detail [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Procedure</title><p>After initial instruction from the administrator, a qualified nurse, the questionnaires were completed unaided by subjects in the order SF-36, SGRQ and EQ-5D. A few subjects did not complete all questionnaires.</p><sec><title>Definition and severity of COPD</title><p>The subjects were divided into four severity groups according to FEV<sub>1</sub>% predicted (pre-bronchodilator) using two different guidelines: the updated version (not yet published) of the GOLD guidelines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>] and the BTS guidelines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. The definition and severity criteria are described in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>. Calculation of FEV<sub>1</sub>predicted normal values for FEV<sub>1 </sub>was based on the reference values from ERS guidelines. In addition, levels of FVC % predicted were also used in the analysis instead of COPD severity stages.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Severity criteria of COPD</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="left" colspan="3"><bold>Global Initiative for Chronic Obstructive Lung Disease, GOLD [3]: FEV<sub>1</sub>/FVC &#x0003c; 70%</bold></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">I:</td><td align="left">Mild COPD</td><td align="left">FEV<sub>1 </sub>&#x02265; 80% predicted</td></tr><tr><td align="left">II:</td><td align="left">Moderate COPD</td><td align="left">FEV<sub>1 </sub>50- &#x0003c; 80% predicted</td></tr><tr><td align="left">III:</td><td align="left">Severe COPD</td><td align="left">FEV<sub>1 </sub>30- &#x0003c; 50% predicted</td></tr><tr><td align="left">IV:</td><td align="left">Very severe COPD</td><td align="left">FEV<sub>1 </sub>&#x0003c; 30% predicted</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3"><bold>British Thoracic Society, BTS [2]: FEV<sub>1</sub>/VC &#x0003c; 70% and FEV<sub>1 </sub>&#x0003c; 80% predicted</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="3"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left">I:</td><td align="left">Mild COPD</td><td align="left">FEV<sub>1 </sub>60- &#x0003c; 80% predicted</td></tr><tr><td align="left">II:</td><td align="left">Moderate COPD</td><td align="left">FEV<sub>1 </sub>40-59% predicted</td></tr><tr><td align="left">III:</td><td align="left">Severe COPD</td><td align="left">FEV<sub>1 </sub>&#x0003c; 40% predicted</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>A group labelled BTS stage 0 was created for subjects with FEV<sub>1 </sub>&#x02265; 80% predicted: i.e. identical with mild COPD according to the GOLD criteria.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec><title>HRQL questionnaires</title><sec><title>Short Form 36</title><p>The most widely used generic questionnaire, the Medical Outcomes Study Short Form 36 (SF-36), has been widely accepted in recent years as the best generic HRQL measurement. It contains 36 items divided into eight domains: Physical Functioning (PF), Role-Physical (RP), Bodily Pain (BP), General Health (GH), Vitality (VT), Social Functioning (SF), Role-Emotional (RE) and Mental Health (MH). These domains create a profile of the subject. Two summary scores can also be aggregated, the Physical Component Summary (PCS) and the Mental Component Summary (MCS). Scores range from 0 to 100, with higher scores representing better HRQL.</p></sec><sec><title>St George's Respiratory Questionnaire</title><p>The best-known and most frequently used disease-specific HRQL questionnaire for respiratory diseases, is the St George's Respiratory Questionnaire (SGRQ) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. The SGRQ is a standardized, self-administered questionnaire for measuring impaired health and perceived HRQL in airways disease. It contains 50 items, divided into three domains: Symptoms, Activity and Impacts. A score is calculated for each domain and a total score, including all items, is also calculated. Each item has an empirically derived weight. Low scores indicate a better HRQL. Recent publications by the developer (PW Jones) have confirmed that the minimal important difference relevant to the patients (MID) is 4 on a scale of 0 to 100 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>EQ-5D</title><p>The EQ-5D is a generic, preference-based utility questionnaire and consists of two parts, the EQ-5D VAS and the EQ-5D index. The EQ-5D has been used in a number of therapeutic areas and contains a vertical rating scale from 0 to 100 (EQ-5D VAS), with 0 = death/worst possible health and 100 = best possible health. The EQ-5D index is a five-item questionnaire ranging from 0 to 1. The items consist of mobility, self-care, usual activity, pain/discomfort and anxiety/depression. Each item has three levels: no problem, some problem and severe problem [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. For the EQ-5D index, 0.03 has been regarded as the MID [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Statistical analysis was performed using an analysis of covariance model with HRQL scores as dependent variable. Three different approaches to analysis were performed using different classification of severity of COPD from GOLD and BTS guidelines. This classification was used as factor in the analysis. In all cases age, gender, smoking status and socio-economic background was used as covariates. These variables showed sign of influence on the HRQL measures and for the sake of comparability a unified model was selected for the analysis. An additional classification of severity based on FVC % predicted normal was also investigated with the same model with classification into four groups: stage I: &#x0003e; 95%, stage II: 95-81%, stage 3: 80-66% and stage IV; &#x0003c; 66%. These levels were chosen to have approximately equal number of patients in each group. Data presented in tables are adjusted least-square means from the adopted model.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>Subject characteristics</title><p>The mean age of the 168 subjects (70 women) was 64.3 years (range: 28&#x02013;80 years). In the six age groups (the lowest &#x0003c; 45 and the highest &#x0003e; 79 years), 57 of the subjects were smokers and 85 were ex-smokers. Three socio-economic groups were identified (manual employees, non-manual employees and unemployed including housewives). Of the 138 'employees', 65 were still working and 73 had retired, and of these, 40 had retired before the normal age of retirement. Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref> shows the subjects' characteristics.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Subject characteristics</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="left"><bold>Characteristic</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>Mean data (range)</bold></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">n, total number agreed</td><td align="left">176</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Men/women n = 168</td><td align="left">98/70</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Mean age, years (range) n = 168</td><td align="left">64.3 (28&#x02013;80)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">FEV<sub>1</sub>, L (range) n = 159</td><td align="left">1.76 (0.46&#x02013;4.12)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">FEV<sub>1 </sub>% predicted (range) n = 159</td><td align="left">62 (18&#x02013;118)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Smoking status n = 171</td><td align="left">Smoker, n = 57 Non-smoker, n = 29 Ex-smoker, n = 85</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Socioeconomic group n = 174</td><td align="left">Manual employees, n = 78 Non-manual employees, n = 60 Unemployed incl. housewives, n = 36</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>HRQL in relation to COPD severity according to GOLD</title><p>The differences in SF-36 PCS between the four severity groups were statistically significant (p = 0.0059). The scores for SF-36 (PCS) were 42 in the stage I group and 29 in the stage IV group. The corresponding scores for SF-36 MCS were 55 and 48 in stages I and IV respectively (p = 0.19) (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Health-related quality of life scores, adjusted mean values (&#x000b1; SD) &#x02013; GOLD criteria</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="left"><bold>Scale</bold></td><td align="center" colspan="5"><bold>FEV<sub>1 </sub>% predicted</bold></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center"><bold>&#x02265; 80% Stage I n = 26</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>79-50% Stage II n = 91</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>49-30% Stage III n = 33</bold></td><td align="center"><bold> &#x0003c; 30% Stage IV n = 9</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>p-value (all stages)</bold></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">SF-36 PCS</td><td align="center">42(12)</td><td align="center">42(12)</td><td align="center">40(10)</td><td align="center">29(12)</td><td align="center">0.0059</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SF-36 MCS</td><td align="center">55(8)</td><td align="center">51(11)</td><td align="center">52(12)</td><td align="center">48(18)</td><td align="center">0.19</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SGRQ Total</td><td align="center">25(20)</td><td align="center">32(20)</td><td align="center">36(20)</td><td align="center">53(23)</td><td align="center">0.0005</td></tr><tr><td align="left">EQ-5D VAS</td><td align="center">73(21)</td><td align="center">65(24)</td><td align="center">62(21)</td><td align="center">37(28)</td><td align="center">0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">EQ-5D index</td><td align="center">0.84(0.15)</td><td align="center">0.73(0.23)</td><td align="center">0.74(0.25)</td><td align="center">0.52(0.26)</td><td align="center">0.0008</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>There was also a statistically significant difference in the SGRQ scores between the severity groups (p = 0.0005). The severity grades affected the level of SGRQ Total as follows: stage I: 25, stage II: 32, stage III: 36 and stage IV: 53 (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>, Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>SGRQ, Total score (adjusted mean values) in GOLD and BTS stages. </bold>p-values by test for trend.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1477-7525-3-56-1"/></fig><p>The scores for EQ-5D VAS were 73 in stage I and 37 in stage IV (p = 0.0001). EQ-5D index showed the following scores: stage I: 0.84 and stage IV: 0.52 (p = 0.0008) (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>HRQL in relation to COPD severity according to BTS</title><p>The scores for SF-36 (PCS) were 42 in the group labelled stage 0 and 35 in stage III (p = 0.032). The corresponding scores for SF-36 MCS were 55 and 50 in stages 0 and III, respectively (p = 0.29) (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Health-related quality of life scores, adjusted mean values (&#x000b1; SD) &#x02013; BTS criteria</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="left"><bold>Scale</bold></td><td align="center" colspan="5"><bold>FEV<sub>1 </sub>% predicted</bold></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center"><bold>&#x02265; 80% Stage 0 n = 26</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>79-60% Stage I n = 63</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>59-40% Stage II n = 47</bold></td><td align="center"><bold> &#x0003c; 40%Stage III n = 23</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>p-value (all stages)</bold></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">SF-36 PCS</td><td align="center">42(12)</td><td align="center">43(11)</td><td align="center">40(13)</td><td align="center">35(11)</td><td align="center">0.032</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SF-36 MCS</td><td align="center">55(8)</td><td align="center">50(10)</td><td align="center">54(11)</td><td align="center">50(15)</td><td align="center">0.29</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SGRQ Total</td><td align="center">25(20)</td><td align="center">32(20)</td><td align="center">34(19)</td><td align="center">45(22)</td><td align="center">0.0023</td></tr><tr><td align="left">EQ-5D VAS</td><td align="center">73(21)</td><td align="center">68(20)</td><td align="center">60(28)</td><td align="center">50(25)</td><td align="center">0.0007</td></tr><tr><td align="left">EQ-5D index</td><td align="center">0.84(0.15)</td><td align="center">0.74(0.21)</td><td align="center">0.72(0.28)</td><td align="center">0.63(0.25)</td><td align="center">0.0041</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>The severity grades affected the level of SGRQ Total scores as follows: stage 0: 25, stage I: 32, stage II: 34, and stage III: 45. There was a statistically significant difference in the SGRQ Total scores between the severity groups (p = 0.0023) (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref>, Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>).</p><p>The scores for EQ-5D VAS were 73 in stage 0 and 50 in stage III (p = 0.0007). The EQ-5D index scores were 0.84 and 0.63 in stages 0 and III, respectively (p = 0.0041) (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Influence of age, gender, smoking status and socio-economic group</title><p>The level of SF-36 PCS varied in the age groups from 44 ( &#x0003c; 45 years) to 36 ( &#x0003e; 79 years), with no statistical significance between the age groups. The level of SF-36 MCS was somewhat higher, 56 in the low age group and 51 in the high age group (not significant). The scores for SGRQ varied from 29 ( &#x0003c; 45 years) to 44 ( &#x0003e; 79 years) and they were statistically significant (p = 0.0047) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). The scores for EQ-5D VAS varied as follows: 86 ( &#x0003c; 45 years) to 81 ( &#x0003e; 79 years). No statistical difference in EQ-5D VAS and EQ-5D index between the age groups could be seen.</p><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>SGRQ, Total score (mean values) in the six age groups. </bold>p-values by test for trend.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1477-7525-3-56-2"/></fig><p>The gender comparison showed only a statistically significant difference in SF-36 PCS, with scores of 44 for the men and 35 for the women (p = 0.0005).</p><p>The mean scores for SGRQ Total were 26, 36 and 31 in the non-smoker, ex-smoker and smoker groups, respectively (not significant).</p><p>No significant differences were seen in the other two instruments. Socio-economic group showed no difference for any instrument.</p></sec><sec><title>HRQL in relation to FVC % predicted</title><p>The four stages of FVC % predicted ( &#x0003e; 95%, 95-81%, 80-66%, &#x0003c; 66%) had an impact on HRQL similar to the stages of FEV<sub>1 </sub>% predicted outlined from GOLD and BTS. SGRQ total score varied from 26 ( &#x0003e; 95%) to 43 ( &#x0003c; 66%) (p = 0.0002) (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">5</xref>). Using the GOLD stages, the number of patients was unequally distributed and the SGRQ Total scores were 26 ( &#x0003e; 80%, n = 81), 40 (79-50%, n = 68) and 46 (49-30%, n = 10) (p &#x0003c; 0.0001). No patient had a value less than 30% predicted.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Health-related quality of life scores, adjusted mean values (&#x000b1; SD) using FVC% predicted normal value</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="left"><bold>Scale</bold></td><td align="center" colspan="5"><bold>FVC % predicted</bold></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center"><bold> &#x0003e; 95% n = 35</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>95-81% n = 33</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>80-66% n = 40</bold></td><td align="center"><bold> &#x0003c; 66% n = 34</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>p-value (all stages)</bold></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">SF-36 PCS</td><td align="center">44(11)</td><td align="center">45(11)</td><td align="center">38(12)</td><td align="center">35(10)</td><td align="center">0.0008</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SF-36 MCS</td><td align="center">53(9)</td><td align="center">52(10)</td><td align="center">53(11)</td><td align="center">49(14)</td><td align="center">0.28</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SGRQ Total</td><td align="center">26(17)</td><td align="center">29(17)</td><td align="center">37(22)</td><td align="center">43(20)</td><td align="center">0.0002</td></tr><tr><td align="left">EQ-5D VAS</td><td align="center">71(19)</td><td align="center">69(24)</td><td align="center">63(25)</td><td align="center">49(25)</td><td align="center">0.0002</td></tr><tr><td align="left">EQ-5D index</td><td align="center">0.79(0.18)</td><td align="center">0.80(0.19)</td><td align="center">0.71(0.27)</td><td align="center">0.62(0.26)</td><td align="center">0.0017</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Correlations between the instruments</title><p>Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T6">6</xref> shows the Pearson correlation coefficients between the different instruments and FEV<sub>1 </sub>% and FVC % predicted. All the questionnaires were correlated with each other. The correlation coefficients between SGRQ and SF-36 PCS/MCS were -0.62 and -0.42, respectively. The lowest correlation was seen between SF-36 MCS and SF-36 PCS (r = 0.22). The correlations between SGRQ and either FEV<sub>1 </sub>% predicted or FVC % predicted were similar (-0.34 and -0.37, respectively).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T6"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Pearson's correlation coefficients (r)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td></td><td align="center"><bold>SF-36 PCS</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>SF-36 MCS</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>SGRQ Total</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>EQ-5D VAS</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>EQ-5D index</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>FEV<sub>1 </sub>% predicted</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>FVC % predicted</bold></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><bold>SF-36 PCS</bold></td><td align="center">1.0</td><td align="center">--</td><td align="center">--</td><td align="center">--</td><td align="center">--</td><td align="center">--</td><td align="center">--</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>SF-36 MCS</bold></td><td align="center">0.22</td><td align="center">1.0</td><td align="center">--</td><td align="center">--</td><td align="center">--</td><td align="center">--</td><td align="center">--</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>SGRQ Total</bold></td><td align="center">-0.62</td><td align="center">-0.42</td><td align="center">1.0</td><td align="center">--</td><td align="center">--</td><td align="center">--</td><td align="center">--</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>EQ-5D VAS</bold></td><td align="center">0.73</td><td align="center">0.49</td><td align="center">-0.63</td><td align="center">1.0</td><td align="center">--</td><td align="center">--</td><td align="center">--</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>EQ-5D index</bold></td><td align="center">0.64</td><td align="center">0.58</td><td align="center">-0.61</td><td align="center">0.68</td><td align="center">1.0</td><td align="center">--</td><td align="center">--</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>FEV<sub>1 </sub>% predicted</bold></td><td align="center">0.30</td><td align="center">0.10</td><td align="center">-0.34</td><td align="center">0.38</td><td align="center">0.26</td><td align="center">1.0</td><td align="center">--</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>FVC % predicted</bold></td><td align="center">0.32</td><td align="center">0.08</td><td align="center">-0.37</td><td align="center">0.36</td><td align="center">0.22</td><td align="center">0.81</td><td align="center">1.0</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>The present study confirms that disease severity (based on FEV<sub>1</sub>) and age influenced HRQL among subjects with COPD. HRQL was strongly related to impaired FEV<sub>1 </sub>in our study, which is in contrast to some previous studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>]. The relationship between disease severity using FEV<sub>1</sub>% predicted and HRQL was made obvious by staging the disease according to the GOLD and BTS guidelines. Once COPD has been diagnosed, neither gender, smoking status nor socio-economic group predicted the level of HRQL.</p><p>The relationship between disease severity and HRQL across different chronic conditions, such as ischemic stroke, Parkinson's disease and coronary heart disease, has been examined [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]. It was concluded that in Parkinson's disease the relationship between disease severity and HRQL is linear, whereas in other diseases, such as chronic coronary heart disease, a non-linear relationship was observed. One of the most important implications of a non-linear relationship is that similar changes in disease severity may have a different effect on measured HRQL. Comparing other studies with the present results, some results highlight the fact that physical functioning is one of the most important predictors of HRQL in older subjects. The present results add the clinical value of multidimensional and complex measures of HRQL as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>]. A moderate association between HRQL and COPD severity stage using FEV<sub>1 </sub>% predicted was seen in another study; however, a large variation in deterioration was observed within each stage of severity, indicating that both clinical and HRQL measures should be considered in the assessment of these patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>]. In a study by Mahler et al, the decline in lung function over time may predict various components of general HRQL [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>].</p><p>On the other hand, only a few studies have highlighted a relationship between disease severity and HRQL in COPD. A recent publication supports our findings by showing that GOLD stages of COPD severity differ significantly in SGRQ [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]. However, it was observed that the upper limit of stage IV marks a threshold for dramatic worsening of HRQL, whereas a change from stage 0 to II does not correspond to any meaningful difference in HRQL.</p><p>A moderate relationship between the disease stage of COPD and HRQL was found [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]. Our findings confirm these results as patients with COPD have significant decreases in HRQL, and the latter deteriorates in parallel with lung function impairment. An observational study was conducted to explore the relationship between various determinants of disease severity and HRQL [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>]. According to its results, lung function and HRQL express several different aspects of disease severity in COPD.</p><p>As was found in a study of asthma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>], no gender difference was seen in our study. However, this is not always the case, as women tend to be more sensitive to changes in HRQL [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>].</p><p>Smoking status did not affect the subjects' HRQL in the present study once COPD had been established. There are various results for the association between smoking status and HRQL. One study showed that COPD patients who continue smoking have a significantly lower HRQL than those who quit smoking [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>]. On the other hand, current smoking has been associated with a better HRQL in the study by Wijnhoven et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>]. The explanation given was that subjects who do not quit smoking might be those with a less severe stage of disease. One limitation with the present results might be the low number of subjects in the very severe stage group, however, the ANCOVA analysis compensate for the skew distribution.</p><p>The correlations between lung function and HRQL have been shown to be weak in a number of studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>]. In the present study the SGRQ Total score ranged from 23 in GOLD stage I to 56 in GOLD stage IV (according to BTS 23&#x02013;47). The correlation between FEV<sub>1 </sub>% predicted and the HRQL measurement varied between -0.34 and 0.10, with the highest correlation (-0.34) between FEV<sub>1 </sub>% predicted and SGRQ Total score. One reason for the difference in correlation between lung function and HRQL may be the influence of psychosocial variables on the HRQL outcome. The subjects in our study seemed to score their HRQL better compared to other subject groups with similar lung function. One study supported the view that the association between lung function and HRQL can be predicted by perceived self-efficacy for functional activities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>]. That study suggested that both biomedical and psychosocial influences should be taken into account in order to provide optimum assessment and treatment. The correlations in this study were stronger than previous seen and another reason might be that disease severity was considered as a category rather than a continuous variable.</p><p>Using FVC % predicted did not add any additional information; however, it supported the view that the level of lung function measured by volume has a similar but lower association with HRQL compared with FEV<sub>1 </sub>in subjects with COPD.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>In conclusion, the results show that the level of health-related quality of life of COPD subjects deteriorates considerably with increasing severity of disease and that the deterioration is linearly related to a decrease in FEV<sub>1 </sub>% predicted normal values. A higher age also affected the COPD subjects' HRQL, while gender, smoking status and socio-economic group did not, once COPD had been established.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>Elisabeth St&#x000e5;hl participated in the study design, evaluation of results and drafted the manuscript</p><p>Anne Lindberg, provided with subjects</p><p>Sven-Arne Jansson performed the interviews with the subjects</p><p>Eva R&#x000f6;nmark provided with subjects</p><p>Klas Svensson performed the statistical analysis</p><p>Fredrik Andersson participated in the study design</p><p>Claes-G&#x000f6;ran L&#x000f6;fdahl gave support with interpretation of the results</p><p>Bo Lundb&#x000e4;ck participated in the study design and responsible for the OLIN studies</p><p>All authors read and approved the final manuscript</p></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This study was funded by a grant from AstraZeneca.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vollmer</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Osborne</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Buist</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>20-year trends in the prevalence of asthma and chronic airflow obstruction in an HMO</article-title><source>American Journal of Respiratory &#x00026; Critical Care Medicine</source><year>1998</year><volume>157</volume><fpage>1079</fpage><lpage>1084</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9563722</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pauwels</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Buist</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Calverley</surname><given-names>PMA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hurd</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global strategy for the diagnosis, management, and prevention of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease: NHLBI and WHO Global Initiative for Chronic Obstructive Lung Disease (GOLD): executive summary.</article-title><source>Respiratory Care</source><year>2001</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>798</fpage><lpage>825</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11463370</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>BTS</collab></person-group><article-title>BTS guidelines for the management of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease. The COPD Guidelines Group of the Standards of Care Committee of the BTS</article-title><source>Thorax</source><year>1997</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>S1</fpage><lpage>28</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Abel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Selvaraj</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A 5-yr prospective epidemiological study of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease in rural south India</article-title><source>Indian Journal of Medical Research</source><year>1995</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>238</fpage><lpage>244</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7672833</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Renwick</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Connolly</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence and treatment of chronic airways obstruction in adults over the age of 45</article-title><source>Thorax</source><year>1996</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>164</fpage><lpage>168</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8711649</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mannino</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gagnon</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Petty</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lydick</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Obstructive lung disease and low lung function in adults in the United States - Data from the National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey, 1988-1994</article-title><source>Arch Intern Med</source><year>2000</year><volume>160</volume><fpage>1683</fpage><lpage>1689</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10847262</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archinte.160.11.1683</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sobradillo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Miravitlles</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jimenez</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gabriel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Viejo</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Masa</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernandez-Fau</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Villasante</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>[Epidemiological study of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease in Spain (IBERPOC): prevalence of chronic respiratory symptoms and airflow limitation]</article-title><source>Arch Bronconeumol</source><year>1999</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>159</fpage><lpage>166</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10330536</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lundback</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindstrom</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ronmark</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Jonsson</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Jonsson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Larsson</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sandstrom</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Larsson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Not 15 but 50% of smokers develop COPD? Report from the Obstructive Lung Disease in Northern Sweden Studies</article-title><source>Respiratory Medicine</source><year>2003</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>115</fpage><lpage>122</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12587960</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/rmed.2003.1446</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lindstrom</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jonsson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Larsson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lundback</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Underdiagnosis of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease in Northern Sweden</article-title><source>Int J Tuberc Lung Dis</source><year>2002</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>76</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11931405</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tirimanna</surname><given-names>PRS</given-names></name><name><surname>van Schayck</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>den Otter</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>van Weel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>van Herwaarden</surname><given-names>CLA</given-names></name><name><surname>van den Boom</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>van Grunsven</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>van den Bosch</surname><given-names>WJHM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of asthma and COPD in general practice in 1992: has it changed since 1977?</article-title><source>Br J Gen Pract</source><year>1996</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>277</fpage><lpage>281</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8762742</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soriano</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Vestbo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pride</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiri</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Maden</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Maier</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Survival in COPD patients after regular use of fluticasone propionate and salmeterol in general practice</article-title><source>Eur Respir J</source><year>2002</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>819</fpage><lpage>825</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12412670</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/09031936.02.00301302</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quality of life measurement for patients with diseases of the airways</article-title><source>Thorax</source><year>1991</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>676</fpage><lpage>682</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1835178</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ware</surname><given-names>JEJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sherbourne</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The MOS 36-item short-form health survey (SF-36). I. Conceptual framework and item selection</article-title><source>Med Care</source><year>1992</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>473</fpage><lpage>483</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1593914</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Quirk</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name><name><surname>Baveystock</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The St George's Respiratory Questionnaire</article-title><source>Respiratory Medicine</source><year>1991</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1759018</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kind</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Spilker B</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Chapter 22. The EuroQoL instrument: an index of health-related quality of life</article-title><source>Quality of Life and Pharmacoeconomics in Clinical Trials</source><year>1996</year><edition>Second</edition><publisher-name>Philadelphia, Lippincott-Raven Publishers</publisher-name><fpage>191</fpage><lpage>201</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jansson</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Borg</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ericsson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jonsson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Lundback</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Costs of COPD in Sweden According to Disease Severity</article-title><source>Chest</source><year>2002</year><volume>122</volume><fpage>1994</fpage><lpage>2002</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12475838</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1378/chest.122.6.1994</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Quirk</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name><name><surname>Baveystock</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Littlejohns</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A self-complete measure of health status for chronic airflow limitation. The St. George's Respiratory Questionnaire</article-title><source>American Review of Respiratory Disease</source><year>1992</year><volume>145</volume><fpage>1321</fpage><lpage>1327</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1595997</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Health status measurement in chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</article-title><source>Thorax</source><year>2001</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>880</fpage><lpage>887</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11641515</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/thorax.56.11.880</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interpreting thresholds for a clinically significant change in health status in asthma and COPD</article-title><source>European Respiratory Journal</source><year>2002</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>398</fpage><lpage>404</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11936514</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/09031936.02.00063702</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Brooks R, Rabin R and de Charro F</surname></name></person-group><article-title>The measurement and valuation of health status using EQ-5D: A European perspective</article-title><source>Evidence from the EuroQol BIO MED Research Programme</source><year>2003</year><publisher-name>Dordrecht, Kluwer Academic Publishers</publisher-name><fpage>303</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stahl</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Wadbo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bengtsson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Strom</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lofdahl</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Health-related quality of life, symptoms, exercise capacity and lung function during treatment for moderate to severe COPD</article-title><source>Journal of Outcomes Research</source><year>2001</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>24</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferrucci</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldasseroni</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bandinelli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>De Alfieri</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Cartei</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Calvani</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Masotti</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Marchionni</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Disease severity and health-related quality of life across different chronic conditions</article-title><source>J Am Geriatr Soc</source><year>2000</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>1490</fpage><lpage>1495</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11083330</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>IB</given-names></name><name><surname>Cleary</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Linking clinical variables with health-related quality of life. A conceptual model of patient outcomes</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>1995</year><volume>273</volume><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7996652</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.273.1.59</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferrer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Anto</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quality of life in COPD patients of different stages of the disease</article-title><source>Eur Respir J</source><year>1995</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>354s</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mahler</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomlinson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Olmstead</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tosteson</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Connor</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Changes in dyspnea, health status, and lung function in chronic airway disease</article-title><source>American Journal of Respiratory &#x00026; Critical Care Medicine</source><year>1995</year><volume>151</volume><fpage>61</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7812573</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Antonelli-Incalzi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Imperiale</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bellia</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Catalano</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Scichilone</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Pistelli</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Rengo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Do GOLD stages of COPD severity really correspond to differences in health status?</article-title><source>European Respiratory Journal</source><year>2003</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>444</fpage><lpage>449</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14516133</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/09031936.03.00101203</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferrer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Anto</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relationship between chronic obstructive pulmonary disease stage and health-related quality of life</article-title><source>Cardiology Review</source><year>1998</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>42</fpage><lpage>45</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000018585</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wijnhoven</surname><given-names>HAH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kriegsman</surname><given-names>DMW</given-names></name><name><surname>Hesselink</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Penninx</surname><given-names>BWJH</given-names></name><name><surname>de Haan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Determinants of different dimensions of disease severity in asthma and COPD - Pulmonary function and health-related quality of life</article-title><source>Chest</source><year>2001</year><volume>119</volume><fpage>1034</fpage><lpage>1042</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11296166</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1378/chest.119.4.1034</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Malo</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Boulet</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name><name><surname>Dewitte</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Cartier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>L'Archeveque</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cote</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bedard</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Boucher</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Champagne</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Tessier</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>Quality of life of subjects with occupational asthma</article-title><source>Journal of Allergy &#x00026; Clinical Immunology</source><year>1993</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>1121</fpage><lpage>1127</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8509574</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0091-6749(93)90313-5</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Juniper</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name><name><surname>Guyatt</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Epstein</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferrie</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaeschke</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiller</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of impairment of health related quality of life in asthma: development of a questionnaire for use in clinical trials</article-title><source>Thorax</source><year>1992</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>76</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1549827</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prigatano</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quality of life and its predictors in patients with mild hypoxemia and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</article-title><source>Arch Intern Med</source><year>1984</year><volume>144</volume><fpage>1613</fpage><lpage>1619</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6380440</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archinte.144.8.1613</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kohler</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Fish</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Greene</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The relationship of perceived self-efficacy to quality of life in chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</article-title><source>Health Psychology</source><year>2002</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>610</fpage><lpage>614</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12433014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037//0278-6133.21.6.610</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>



