<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Epidemiol Perspect Innov</journal-id><journal-title>Epidemiologic perspectives &#x00026; innovations : EP+I</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1742-5573</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">16033652</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1215500</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1742-5573-2-7</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1742-5573-2-7</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Methodology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Reporting incidence from a surveillance system with an operational case definition of unknown predictive value positive</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kegler</surname><given-names>Scott R</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>skegler@cdc.gov</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Office of Statistics and Programming, National Center for Injury Prevention and Control, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, 4770 Buford Highway NE, Mailstop K59, Atlanta GA 30341-3724, USA</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2005</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>7</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><volume>2</volume><fpage>7</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.epi-perspectives.com/content/2/1/7"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>2</day><month>5</month><year>2005</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>20</day><month>7</month><year>2005</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2005 Kegler; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2005</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Kegler; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>
               Kegler
               R
               Scott
               
               skegler@cdc.gov
            </dc:author><dc:title>
            Reporting incidence from a surveillance system with an operational case definition of unknown predictive value positive
         </dc:title><dc:date>2005</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>Epidemiologic Perspectives &#x00026; Innovations 2(1): 7-. (2005)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1742-5573(2005)2:1&#x0003c;7&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1742-5573</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><p>When reporting incidence rate estimates for relatively rare health conditions, associated case counts are often assumed to follow a Poisson distribution. Case counts obtained from large-scale electronic surveillance systems are often inflated by the presence of false positives, however, and adjusted case counts based on the results of a validation sample will have variances which are hyper-Poisson. This paper presents a simple method for constructing interval estimates for incidence rates based on case counts that are adjusted downward using an estimate of the predictive value positive of the surveillance case definition.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Large-scale surveillance for selected medical or health conditions often relies on electronic data sources which provide comprehensive coverage of a given population. For example, the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention conduct surveillance of brain injuries involving hospitalization or death, based on electronic hospital discharge and vital statistics data received from twelve to fifteen states each year [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. To identify cases, electronic records are scanned for specified diagnosis codes which collectively form the operational case definition. The resulting case counts are subsequently combined with population data to estimate incidence rates.</p><p>As with most surveillance methods, an operational case definition as described above may admit some records that do not represent true cases under a strict clinical definition ("false positives") and may also fail to capture some records representing true cases ("false negatives"). The customary terms reflecting these aspects of an operational case definition are predictive value positive (PVP) and sensitivity, defined in the present context as the conditional probabilities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]:</p><p>PVP = Pr{case meets clinical definition | case detected under operational definition};</p><p>sensitivity = Pr{case detected under operational definition | case meets clinical definition}.</p><p>Depending on the extent to which false positives and/or false negatives are believed to influence the surveillance process, it may be appropriate to use estimates of PVP and/or sensitivity to adjust incidence rate estimates accordingly. It is not generally possible to assess PVP or sensitivity using electronic surveillance data alone. The most direct approach to obtaining the additional data required for estimation of PVP involves manual review of medical records for a random sample of provisional cases identified via the operational case definition. Obtaining the additional data necessary for estimation of sensitivity may be more labor-intensive, particularly when considering an uncommon condition. Without additional "markers" (apart from the operational case definition) to narrow the scope of review, it may be necessary to select a very large sample of general medical records in order to identify enough true cases to support a stable estimate of sensitivity.</p><p>The methodology described in this paper is oriented to surveillance of relatively rare health conditions. Because validation data quantifying the influence of false positives will typically be easier to obtain than data quantifying the influence of false negatives in this setting, the development concentrates on incidence rate estimates reflecting adjustments for PVP. This emphasis is not intended to diminish the potential influence of false negatives; rather, it reflects the logistical difficulties associated with obtaining data on false negatives as part of ongoing surveillance. If there is sufficient doubt surrounding the sensitivity of case ascertainment for any particular surveillance process, the proposed methodology should be applied with due caution.</p></sec><sec><title>Analysis</title><p>For a given surveillance period, it is assumed that case confirmation data are available for a random sample (selected without replacement) of provisional cases. Data obtained through such validation efforts allow estimation of PVP as well as adjustments to case counts to eliminate the bias due to false positives. To illustrate, suppose that for a set period (e.g., one year) of observation:</p><p>N = size of the at-risk population covered by the surveillance system;</p><p>M = count of provisional cases detected under the operational case definition;</p><p>M<sub>T </sub>= count of true cases (unknown) among the provisional cases;</p><p>M<sub>F </sub>= count of false positive cases (unknown) among the provisional cases = M - M<sub>T</sub>;</p><p>S = number of provisional cases sampled for case confirmation;</p><p>C<sub>T </sub>= count of confirmed true cases among those sampled;</p><p>C<sub>F </sub>= count of cases determined to be false positives among those sampled = S - C<sub>T</sub>.</p><p>The usual estimate of PVP is given by [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]:</p><p><inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-5573-2-7-i1.gif"/> = C<sub>T</sub>/S = C<sub>T</sub>/(C<sub>T </sub>+ C<sub>F</sub>).</p><p>Noting that <inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-5573-2-7-i1.gif"/> is definable only when M &#x0003e; 0 (assuming also that S &#x0003e; 0) a reasonable estimate of the population of true cases which eliminates the false positive bias is:</p><p><inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-5573-2-7-i2.gif"/></p><p>Case counts obtained through comprehensive surveillance may be considered inherently variable even though they are essentially census-level quantities, in the sense that a case count can be viewed as representing one observation from a hypothetically repeatable process [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. For relatively rare conditions such case counts are often assumed to follow a Poisson distribution [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. For example, suppose that all M provisional cases were to be reviewed so that the count of true cases M<sub>T </sub>could be determined. When reporting the corresponding incidence rate R = M<sub>T</sub>/N one might also make use of the variance estimate <inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-5573-2-7-i3.gif"/>, based on the assumption that M<sub>T </sub>represents one observation from a Poisson process [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. Due to the estimation of PVP, however, the adjusted case count <inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-5573-2-7-i4.gif"/> cannot be treated in a similar fashion. Depending on the validation sample and the underlying PVP, for example, Var(<inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-5573-2-7-i4.gif"/>) can be well in excess of the variance that would be estimated under the assumption that <inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-5573-2-7-i4.gif"/> simply follows a Poisson distribution.</p><p>The remainder of this paper addresses three aspects of the problem outlined above: (i) a simple model for the true and false positive case counts within the defined framework, (ii) selected properties of <inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-5573-2-7-i4.gif"/> under a broadly applicable validation sample plan, and (iii) the relative frequency of coverage for interval estimates formulated using these properties.</p><sec><title>A Case Count Model</title><p>To evaluate the proposed estimator <inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-5573-2-7-i4.gif"/>, a working model characterizing the process underlying the case counts M, M<sub>T</sub>, and M<sub>F </sub>is needed. For a given at-risk population and surveillance period it will be assumed that the provisional case count M is generated according to a Poisson process with parameter &#x003bb;. Each provisional case, independent of other provisional cases, will be assumed to be a true case with probability equal to the underlying PVP. These assumptions are reflected in the following mixture model [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]:</p><p>M ~ POI(&#x003bb;);</p><p>M<sub>T</sub>|M ~ BIN(M, PVP)</p><p>where POI denotes the Poisson distribution and BIN denotes the binomial distribution. The count of false positive cases is implicitly given by M<sub>F </sub>= M - M<sub>T</sub>. It is well-established that under this type of decomposition M<sub>T </sub>and M<sub>F </sub>are independent Poisson random variables such that M<sub>T </sub>~ POI(&#x003c4;) and M<sub>F </sub>~ POI(&#x003c6;), where &#x003c4; = &#x003bb;&#x000b7;PVP and &#x003c6; = &#x003bb;&#x000b7;(1-PVP) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. In this model, the parameter &#x003bb; represents the average size of the recurring count of provisional cases and &#x003c4; represents the average size of the recurring count of true cases among the provisional cases. The quantity 1/PVP can be viewed as the factor by which the count of true cases is inflated (on average) under the operational case definition. Finally, the parameters &#x003bb;, &#x003c4; and &#x003c6; are implicitly dependent on the size of the at-risk population N; however, the functional form of this dependency is not important in the present development.</p></sec><sec><title>A Validation Sample Plan</title><p>This section examines several important properties of the estimator <inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-5573-2-7-i4.gif"/> when a fixed fraction of provisional cases are sampled for confirmation. The properties presented are derived in Appendix A. Letting 0 &#x0003c; f &#x0003c; 1 denote the fixed sampling fraction, assume that the sample size S = <inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-5573-2-7-i5.gif"/> where the quantity f&#x000b7;M is rounded up. Under this procedure:</p><p>E[<inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-5573-2-7-i4.gif"/>] = &#x003c4; &#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0; (2)</p><p>and when f&#x000b7;&#x003bb; is sufficiently large:</p><p><inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-5573-2-7-i6.gif"/></p><p>Equality (2) indicates that <inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-5573-2-7-i4.gif"/> is an unbiased estimator for the mean recurring count of true cases. The first component &#x003c4; on the right-hand side of (3) represents the variance of the true case count M<sub>T</sub>. The second component approximates the addition to variance that results from the case count adjustment based on <inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-5573-2-7-i1.gif"/>. Note that for any given PVP the variance inflation factor is essentially constant as a result of holding the sampling fraction fixed.</p><p>It is noted in passing that when case populations are typically small, it may be feasible to adopt the practice of confirming all provisional cases. Under this approach <inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-5573-2-7-i4.gif"/> will be equivalent to the true case count M<sub>T </sub>and it follows that <inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-5573-2-7-i4.gif"/> ~ POI(&#x003c4;). Based on familiar properties of the Poisson distribution [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>] it follows that E[<inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-5573-2-7-i4.gif"/>] = Var(<inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-5573-2-7-i4.gif"/>) = &#x003c4; and customary analysis methods are applicable.</p></sec><sec><title>Application</title><p>The remaining objective is the formulation of a simple method for constructing interval estimates for &#x003c4; and the corresponding incidence rate. From (2) it is already known that <inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-5573-2-7-i4.gif"/> is an unbiased estimator of &#x003c4;. In Appendix B it is shown that the following estimator is nearly unbiased for the right-hand side of (3):</p><p><inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-5573-2-7-i7.gif"/></p><p>Based on (4) an approximate (1-&#x003b1;)&#x000b7;100% confidence interval (adjusted for the false positive bias) for the recurring case count &#x003c4; is given by:</p><p><inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-5573-2-7-i8.gif"/></p><p>where z<sub>&#x003b1;/2 </sub>represents the appropriate quantile of the standard normal distribution. The corresponding interval estimate for the population-based incidence rate is:</p><p><inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-5573-2-7-i9.gif"/></p><p>where it will be recalled that N is the size of the at-risk population under surveillance. As an example, suppose that an interval estimate providing 95% relative frequency of coverage is desired for the population-based incidence rate. Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref> shows the relative frequency with which interval (5) covers the underlying incidence rate in repeated Monte Carlo simulations involving various underlying values of PVP, &#x003bb;, and f. For several cells f&#x000b7;&#x003bb; is small and the coverage is below the nominal (95%) level, providing an illustration of where the interval estimation procedure begins to break down. In the remaining table cells coverage is close to the nominal level.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Estimated Relative Coverage Frequencies of a Nominal 95% Interval with Variance Correction.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td></td><td align="center" colspan="3">PVP = 0.70</td><td align="center" colspan="3">PVP = 0.80</td><td align="center" colspan="3">PVP = 0.90</td></tr><tr><td align="center">f</td><td align="center">&#x003bb; = 100</td><td align="center">&#x003bb; = 500</td><td align="center">&#x003bb; = 1000</td><td align="center">&#x003bb; = 100</td><td align="center">&#x003bb; = 500</td><td align="center">&#x003bb; = 1000</td><td align="center">&#x003bb; = 100</td><td align="center">&#x003bb; = 500</td><td align="center">&#x003bb; = 1000</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center">0.10</td><td align="center">0.92</td><td align="center">0.94</td><td align="center">0.95</td><td align="center">0.92</td><td align="center">0.95</td><td align="center">0.95</td><td align="center">0.94</td><td align="center">0.95</td><td align="center">0.95</td></tr><tr><td align="center">0.25</td><td align="center">0.94</td><td align="center">0.95</td><td align="center">0.95</td><td align="center">0.95</td><td align="center">0.95</td><td align="center">0.95</td><td align="center">0.95</td><td align="center">0.95</td><td align="center">0.95</td></tr><tr><td align="center">0.50</td><td align="center">0.95</td><td align="center">0.95</td><td align="center">0.95</td><td align="center">0.95</td><td align="center">0.95</td><td align="center">0.95</td><td align="center">0.94</td><td align="center">0.95</td><td align="center">0.95</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>To illustrate the importance of the correction to the variance, Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref> shows the relative coverage frequencies (again based on repeated simulations) if the adjusted case counts are simply assumed to follow a Poisson distribution. It is apparent that for smaller sampling fractions, coverage is well below the nominal level even with the larger case populations.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Estimated Relative Coverage Frequencies of a Nominal 95% Interval w/o Variance Correction.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td></td><td align="center" colspan="3">PVP = 0.70</td><td align="center" colspan="3">PVP = 0.80</td><td align="center" colspan="3">PVP = 0.90</td></tr><tr><td align="center">f</td><td align="center">&#x003bb; = 100</td><td align="center">&#x003bb; = 500</td><td align="center">&#x003bb; = 1000</td><td align="center">&#x003bb; = 100</td><td align="center">&#x003bb; = 500</td><td align="center">&#x003bb; = 1000</td><td align="center">&#x003bb; = 100</td><td align="center">&#x003bb; = 500</td><td align="center">&#x003bb; = 1000</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center">0.10</td><td align="center">0.73</td><td align="center">0.70</td><td align="center">0.68</td><td align="center">0.78</td><td align="center">0.77</td><td align="center">0.76</td><td align="center">0.86</td><td align="center">0.84</td><td align="center">0.84</td></tr><tr><td align="center">0.25</td><td align="center">0.84</td><td align="center">0.85</td><td align="center">0.85</td><td align="center">0.87</td><td align="center">0.88</td><td align="center">0.88</td><td align="center">0.92</td><td align="center">0.91</td><td align="center">0.91</td></tr><tr><td align="center">0.50</td><td align="center">0.91</td><td align="center">0.92</td><td align="center">0.91</td><td align="center">0.92</td><td align="center">0.93</td><td align="center">0.93</td><td align="center">0.93</td><td align="center">0.94</td><td align="center">0.94</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Extensions to independent subgroups (e.g., age groups) and aggregates (e.g., age-adjusted rates) are straightforward. Provided that subgroup boundaries do not divide the surveillance population too finely, the error associated with the interval estimation method described above should remain minimal.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>This paper was motivated by considerations related to analysis of data from the brain injury surveillance system mentioned in the introduction. Beginning with surveillance year 2000, a number of participating states identified provisional cases which were subsequently determined to be false positives upon in-depth review. Preliminary estimates of PVP were observed to fall close to 0.9 for some states, suggesting the need for adjusted incidence rate estimates. This issue is also relevant in a broader context, as a wide range of PVP estimates have been reported for other surveillance systems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>].</p><p>Adjustments to incidence rate estimates to eliminate the false positive bias are straightforward. However, since the PVP estimates used to make such downward adjustments are subject to random variation, the adjusted rates have an additional source of variation beyond what is usually assumed. Interval estimates failing to account for this fact may have coverage frequencies well below the nominal level. This paper presents a simple method of interval estimation for rates that have been adjusted to remove the bias due to false positives, applicable in large-scale surveillance settings.</p><p>The methodology presented does not address the potential bias associated with false negatives. In situations where validation data also support estimation of sensitivity, surveillance case counts could be further adjusted to reduce or eliminate such bias. This in turn would introduce another source of variation in the adjusted case counts and associated rates. Other types of sampling plans might also be considered. For example, a fixed sample size s* might be preferred, in which case S = min(s*, M) and an alternate expression for Var(<inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-5573-2-7-i4.gif"/>) would result. Technical details aside, the essential point is that data available from validation samples can have a nontrivial influence on point and interval estimates, and should be factored into surveillance statistics whenever feasible.</p></sec><sec><title>Appendix A. Moments of the Estimator <inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-5573-2-7-i4.gif"/></title><p>In the sampling procedure considered, the size of the validation sample depends on the provisional case count M. To make the analysis generic, the sample size will be denoted by s(M) where s(&#x000b7;) depends on the particular sampling procedure but is assumed positive whenever M &#x0003e; 0. The PVP-adjusted case count (1) can then be defined more precisely as:</p><p><inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-5573-2-7-i10.gif"/></p><p>where implicitly <inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-5573-2-7-i1.gif"/> = C<sub>T</sub>/s(M). When M &#x0003e; 0 the distribution of C<sub>T </sub>conditional on M and M<sub>T </sub>is hypergeometric [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>], that is, C<sub>T</sub>|M, M<sub>T </sub>~ HYP(s(M), M<sub>T</sub>, M). It is not difficult to show that when M &#x0003e; 0 the distribution of C<sub>T </sub>conditional on M only is binomial, that is, C<sub>T</sub>|M ~ BIN(s(M), PVP). It follows that E[<inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-5573-2-7-i4.gif"/>|M] = M&#x000b7;PVP for M &#x02265; 0. Applying principles of conditional expectation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>] it is readily established that <inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-5573-2-7-i4.gif"/> is an unbiased estimator of &#x003c4; = &#x003bb;&#x000b7;PVP:</p><p>E[<inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-5573-2-7-i4.gif"/>] = E[E[<inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-5573-2-7-i4.gif"/>|M]] = E[M&#x000b7;PVP] = &#x003bb;&#x000b7;PVP.</p><p>To determine Var(<inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-5573-2-7-i4.gif"/>) it is convenient to employ the following variance decomposition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]:</p><p>Var(<inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-5573-2-7-i4.gif"/>) = E[Var(<inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-5573-2-7-i4.gif"/>|M)] + Var(E[<inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-5573-2-7-i4.gif"/>|M]).</p><p>Since E[<inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-5573-2-7-i4.gif"/>|M] = M&#x000b7;PVP it follows that Var(E[<inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-5573-2-7-i4.gif"/>|M]) = &#x003bb;&#x000b7;PVP<sup>2</sup>. Evaluation of the first component of variance is more complicated. Defining:</p><p><inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-5573-2-7-i11.gif"/></p><p>it follows from (A.1) and the fact that C<sub>T</sub>|M ~ BIN(s(M), PVP) when M &#x0003e; 0 that:</p><p>Var(<inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-5573-2-7-i4.gif"/>|M) = PVP&#x000b7;(1-PVP)&#x000b7;g(M).</p><p>The task is thus reduced to determining E[g(M)]. When s(M) = <inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-5573-2-7-i5.gif"/> it holds that g(M) &#x02264; M/f and hence that E[g(M)] &#x02264; E[M/f] = &#x003bb;/f. Given fixed f the upper bound is a good approximation provided that &#x003bb; is sufficiently large, so that E[g(M)] &#x0224c; &#x003bb;/f and E[Var(<inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-5573-2-7-i4.gif"/>|M)] &#x0224c; PVP&#x000b7;(1-PVP)&#x000b7;&#x003bb;/f. Combining variance components and simplifying results in:</p><p><inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-5573-2-7-i12.gif"/></p><p>Numerical calculation of Var(<inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-5573-2-7-i4.gif"/>) across a range of values for PVP, &#x003bb;, and f shows that for f &#x02265; 0.01 and f&#x000b7;&#x003bb; &#x02265; 50, the relative error of (A.2) is less than 0.01.</p></sec><sec><title>Appendix B. An Estimate of Var(<inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-5573-2-7-i4.gif"/>)</title><p>The following is proposed as an estimator of the right-hand side of (A.2):</p><p><inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-5573-2-7-i13.gif"/></p><p>Defining:</p><p><inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-5573-2-7-i14.gif"/></p><p>it follows from the treatment in Appendix A that the expected value of the variance estimator (B.1) conditioned on M is:</p><p><inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-5573-2-7-i15.gif"/></p><p>Then, since <inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-5573-2-7-i16.gif"/> it follows that:</p><p><inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-5573-2-7-i17.gif"/></p><p>When s(M) = <inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-5573-2-7-i5.gif"/> it holds that h(M) &#x02264; 1/f and hence that E[h(M)] &#x02264; 1/f. Given fixed f the upper bound is a good approximation provided that &#x003bb; is sufficiently large. Substituting 1/f in place of E[h(M)] results in:</p><p><inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-5573-2-7-i18.gif"/></p><p>Algebraic simplification results in:</p><p><inline-graphic xlink:href="1742-5573-2-7-i19.gif"/></p><p>As f&#x000b7;&#x003bb; becomes large, approximation (A.2) results.</p></sec><sec><title>Competing interests</title><p>The author(s) declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thurman</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sniezek</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenspan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><source>Guidelines for Surveillance of Central Nervous System Injury</source><year>1995</year><publisher-name>Atlanta: Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greenland</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Rothman KJ, Greenland S</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Basic methods for sensitivity analysis and external adjustment</article-title><source>Modern Epidemiology</source><year>1998</year><edition>2</edition><publisher-name>Philadelphia: Lippincott-Raven Publishers</publisher-name><fpage>343</fpage><lpage>357</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Romaguera</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>German</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Klaucke</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Teutsch SM, Churchill RE</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluating public health surveillance</article-title><source>Principles and Practice of Public Health Surveillance</source><year>2000</year><publisher-name>New York: Oxford University Press</publisher-name><fpage>176</fpage><lpage>193</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Keyfitz</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sampling variance of standardized mortality rates</article-title><source>Human Biology</source><year>1966</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>309</fpage><lpage>317</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brillinger</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The natural variability of vital rates and associated statistics</article-title><source>Biometrics</source><year>1986</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>693</fpage><lpage>734</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3814721</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greenland</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rothman</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Rothman KJ, Greenland S</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Introduction to categorical statistics</article-title><source>Modern Epidemiology</source><year>1998</year><edition>2</edition><publisher-name>Philadelphia: Lippincott-Raven Publishers</publisher-name><fpage>231</fpage><lpage>252</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Minino</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fingerhut</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Warner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Heinen</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><source>Deaths: Injuries, 2001 National Vital Statistics Reports</source><year>2004</year><volume>52</volume><publisher-name>Hyattsville MD: National Center for Health Statistics</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Casella</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group><source>Statistical Inference</source><year>1990</year><publisher-name>Belmont CA: Duxbury Press</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><source>Introduction to Probability Models</source><year>1989</year><edition>4</edition><publisher-name>San Diego: Academic Press</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Karlin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><source>An Introduction to Stochastic Modeling</source><year>1984</year><publisher-name>Orlando: Academic Press</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>German</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sensitivity and predictive value positive measurements for public health surveillance systems</article-title><source>Epidemiology</source><year>2000</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>720</fpage><lpage>727</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11055638</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00001648-200011000-00020</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cochran</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name></person-group><source>Sampling Techniques</source><year>1977</year><edition>3</edition><publisher-name>New York: Wiley</publisher-name></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>



