<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mol Pain</journal-id><journal-title>Molecular Pain</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1744-8069</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15813989</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1074353</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1744-8069-1-3</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1744-8069-1-3</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Sensitization of TRPV1 by EP<sub>1 </sub>and IP reveals peripheral nociceptive mechanism of prostaglandins</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" equal-contrib="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Moriyama</surname><given-names>Tomoko</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>tomokom@nips.ac.jp</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" equal-contrib="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Higashi</surname><given-names>Tomohiro</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>tomohiro@nips.ac.jp</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Togashi</surname><given-names>Kazuya</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>togashi@nips.ac.jp</email></contrib><contrib id="A4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Iida</surname><given-names>Tohko</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>iida@doc.medic.mie-u.ac.jp</email></contrib><contrib id="A5" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Segi</surname><given-names>Eri</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I4">4</xref><email>e-segi@mfour.med.kyoto-u.ac.jp</email></contrib><contrib id="A6" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sugimoto</surname><given-names>Yukihiko</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I5">5</xref><email>ysugimot@pharmsun.pharm.kyoto-u.ac.jp</email></contrib><contrib id="A7" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tominaga</surname><given-names>Tomoko</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>tomokoto@nips.ac.jp</email></contrib><contrib id="A8" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Narumiya</surname><given-names>Shuh</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I4">4</xref><email>snaru@mfour.med.kyoto-u.ac.jp</email></contrib><contrib id="A9" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tominaga</surname><given-names>Makoto</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>tominaga@nips.ac.jp</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Dept.of Cellular and Molecular Physiology, Mie University School of Medicine, Mie 514-8507, Japan</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Okazaki Institute for Integrative Bioscience, National Institutes of Natural Sciences, Okazaki 444-8787, Japan</aff><aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Department of Physiological Sciences, The Graduate University for Advanced Studies, Okazaki 444-8787, Japan</aff><aff id="I4"><label>4</label>Dept. ofPharmacology, Kyoto University Faculty of Medicine, Kyoto 606-8501, Japan</aff><aff id="I5"><label>5</label>Dept. of Physiological Chemistry, Graduated School of Pharmaceutical Sciences, Kyoto University, Kyoto 606-8501, Japan</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2005</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>17</day><month>1</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><volume>1</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>3</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.molecularpain.com/content/1/1/3"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>6</day><month>1</month><year>2005</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>17</day><month>1</month><year>2005</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2005 Moriyama et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2005</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Moriyama et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>
               Moriyama
               Tomoko
               
               
               tomokom@nips.ac.jp
            </dc:author><dc:title>
            Sensitization of TRPV1 by EP1 and IP reveals peripheral nociceptive mechanism of prostaglandins
         </dc:title><dc:date>2005</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>Molecular Pain 1(1): 3-. (2005)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1744-8069(2005)1:1&#x0003c;3&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1744-8069</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><p>Prostaglandin E<sub>2 </sub>(PGE<sub>2</sub>) and prostaglandin I<sub>2 </sub>(PGI<sub>2</sub>) are major inflammatory mediators that play important roles in pain sensation and hyperalgesia. The role of their receptors (EP and IP, respectively) in inflammation has been well documented, although the EP receptor subtypes involved in this process and the underlying cellular mechanisms remain to be elucidated. The capsaicin receptor TRPV1 is a nonselective cation channel expressed in sensory neurons and activated by various noxious stimuli. TRPV1 has been reported to be critical for inflammatory pain mediated through PKA- and PKC-dependent pathways. PGE<sub>2 </sub>or PGI<sub>2</sub>increased or sensitized TRPV1 responses through EP<sub>1 </sub>or IP receptors, respectively predominantly in a PKC-dependent manner in both HEK293 cells expressing TRPV1 and mouse DRG neurons. In the presence of PGE<sub>2 </sub>or PGI<sub>2</sub>, the temperature threshold for TRPV1 activation was reduced below 35&#x000b0;C, so that temperatures near body temperature are sufficient to activate TRPV1. A PKA-dependent pathway was also involved in the potentiation of TRPV1 through EP<sub>4 </sub>and IP receptors upon exposure to PGE<sub>2 </sub>and PGI<sub>2</sub>, respectively. Both PGE<sub>2</sub>-induced thermal hyperalgesia and inflammatory nociceptive responses were diminished in TRPV1-deficient mice and EP<sub>1</sub>-deficient mice. IP receptor involvement was also demonstrated using TRPV1-deficient mice and IP-deficient mice. Thus, the potentiation or sensitization of TRPV1 activity through EP<sub>1 </sub>or IP activation might be one important mechanism underlying the peripheral nociceptive actions of PGE<sub>2 </sub>or PGI<sub>2</sub>.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Tissue damage and inflammation produce an array of chemical mediators such as ATP, bradykinin, prostanoids, protons, cytokines and peptides including substance P that can excite or sensitize nociceptors to elicit pain at the site of injury. Among them prostanoids were shown to influence inflammation, and their administration was found to reproduce the major signs of inflammation including augmented pain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Prostaglandin E<sub>2 </sub>(PGE<sub>2</sub>) and prostaglandin I<sub>2 </sub>(PGI<sub>2</sub>) are the products of arachidonic acid metabolism through the cyclooxygenase pathway. In addition to numerous other physiological actions <italic>in vivo</italic>, previous studies have indicated important roles for PGE<sub>2 </sub>in nociception and inflammation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. PGE<sub>2 </sub>is generated in most cells in response to mechanical, thermal or chemical injury and inflammatory insult, resulting in sensitization or direct activation of nearby sensory nerve endings. Analgesic effects of non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) are attributed predominantly to inhibition of prostaglandin synthesis. Prostaglandins act upon a family of pharmacologically distinct prostanoid receptors including EP<sub>1</sub>, EP<sub>2</sub>, EP<sub>3</sub>, EP<sub>4 </sub>and IP that activate several different G protein-coupled signaling pathways [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. Primary sensory neurons in dorsal root ganglion (DRG) are known to express mRNAs encoding several prostanoid receptor subtypes, IP, EP<sub>1</sub>, EP<sub>3 </sub>and EP<sub>4 </sub>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. The role of IP in inflammation has been clearly shown by the analysis of IP-deficient mice, although the underlying cellular mechanisms still remain to be elucidated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. In contrast, the potential involvement of EP receptors other than IP in inflammation and pain generation has not been well studied, although some earlier studies have suggested that prostanoids contribute to the development of pain through EP receptors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>].</p><p>The capsaicin receptor TRPV1 is a non-selective cation channel expressed predominantly in unmyelinated C-fibers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. TRPV1 is activated not only by capsaicin, but also by protons or heat (with a threshold &#x0003e; ~43&#x000b0;C), both of which cause pain <italic>in vivo </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. A prominent role of TRPV1 in nociception has been demonstrated in studies of TRPV1-deficient mice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>].</p><p>Recently, we reported that inflammatory mediators such as ATP, bradykinin and trypsin or tryptase potentiate TRPV1 activity in a PKC-dependent manner [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>], and identified two target serine residues in TRPV1 as substrates for PKC-dependent phosphorylation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. On the other hand, there are several reports showing that a PKA signaling pathway mediates PGE<sub>2</sub>-induced potentiation of capsaicin-evoked responses in rat sensory neurons [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]. Therefore, we examined the effects of PGE<sub>2 </sub>and PGI<sub>2 </sub>on TRPV1 activity. Surprisingly, we found the functional interaction of TRPV1 with PGE<sub>2 </sub>or PGI<sub>2 </sub>occurs mainly through a PKC-dependent pathway at both cellular and behavioral levels.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>Functional interaction between TRPV1 and PGE<sub>2</sub></title><p>In order to examine the possibility that TRPV1 is involved in PGE<sub>2</sub>-induced hyperalgesia <italic>in vivo</italic>, we performed a behavioral analysis using wild type and TRPV1-deficient (TRPV1<sup>-/-</sup>) mice. PGE<sub>2 </sub>(500 pmol/20 &#x003bc;L) produced a significant reduction in paw withdrawal latency in response to radiant heat (thermal hyperalgesia) at 5 to 90 min following intraplantar injection in wild type mice (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>). On the other hand, the PGE<sub>2</sub>-induced thermal hyperalgesia was almost completely abolished in TRPV1<sup>-/- </sup>mice, suggesting a functional interaction between PGE<sub>2 </sub>and TRPV1 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>), consistent with a previous report that capsaicin-ablation of primary afferent neurons prevents PGE<sub>2</sub>-induced thermal hyperalgesia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>]. We next examined the interaction between PGE<sub>2 </sub>and TRPV1 in mouse DRG neurons using the patch-clamp technique. Capsaicin (100 nM) evoked small inward currents in DRG neurons. The capsaicin-evoked currents were significantly potentiated by 1.5 min pretreatment with PGE<sub>2 </sub>(1&#x003bc;M) in 19 of 23 cells as previously reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>] (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1C</xref>) (3.36 &#x000b1; 0.55 fold increase, n = 23 for PGE<sub>2 </sub>(+); 0.78 &#x000b1; 0.08 fold for PGE<sub>2 </sub>(-) (Cont.), n = 5, p &#x0003c; 0.05). Because it has been suggested that a PKA-dependent pathway is predominantly involved in the PGE<sub>2</sub>-induced potentiation of capsaicin-activated currents in rat DRG neurons [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>], we examined the potential involvement of such a mechanism both in mouse DRG neurons and human embryonic kidney-derived HEK293 cells expressing TRPV1. No potentiation of the capsaicin-activated current responses was observed in DRG neurons treated with a mixture of forskolin (FSK, 10 &#x003bc;M), 3-isobutyl-1-methylxanthine (IBMX, 1 mM) and dibutyryl-cAMP (dbcAMP, 3 mM) for the same time period (1.5 min) (1.15 &#x000b1; 0.20 fold increase, n = 9) although a significant increase in cAMP level was confirmed during such the treatment (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1C</xref>). When we treated cells longer (6.5 min), 7 out of 14 cells showed increase of capsaicin-activated currents (2.15 &#x000b1; 0.77 fold increase, n = 14, p = 0.28) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1C</xref>). In HEK293 cells, two different short (1.5 min) treatments to activate PKA produced no potentiation (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1D</xref>) (treatment with a mixture of FSK, IBMX and dbcAMP in cells expressing TRPV1, 1.20 &#x000b1; 0.19 fold increase, n = 11, and treatment with isoproterenol (Isop.) in cells expressing both TRPV1 and mouse &#x003b2;<sub>1</sub>-adrenergic receptors (&#x003b2;<sub>1</sub>-ADR), 0.83 &#x000b1; 0.12 fold increase, n = 4) although a significant increase in cAMP level was confirmed following both treatments in HEK293 cells (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref>). We also examined the effects of long treatment (6.5 min) with a mixture of FSK, IBMX and dbcAMP. This treatment caused significant potentiation of capsaicin-activated currents (2.39 &#x000b1; 0.60 fold increase, n = 7, p &#x0003c; 0.05) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1D</xref>). These results suggest that both PKA-dependent and -independent pathways are involved in the potentiation of the capsaicin-activated currents by PGE<sub>2</sub>, that it takes longer to cause potentiation of capsaicin-activated currents through a PKA-dependent pathway, and that the PKA-independent pathway is predominantly involved under the short treatment conditions. Indeed, it has been reported that capsaicin-activated currents were not increased upon FSK/IBMX or 8-bromo-cAMP (8-Br-cAMP)/IBMX treatment in <italic>Xenopus </italic>oocytes expressing TRPV1, or treatment with isoproterenol in oocytes expressing both TRPV1 and &#x003b2;<sub>1</sub>-ADR [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>].</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Physiological interaction of PGE<sub>2 </sub>with TRPV1 in mice. (<bold>A</bold>) PGE<sub>2</sub>-induced thermal hyperalgesia in TRPV1<sup>+/+ </sup>mice (&#x025cb;, n = 6) or TRPV1<sup>-/- </sup>mice (&#x025b2;, n = 6). Reduction of paw withdrawal latency (thermal hyperalgesia) by intraplantar PGE<sub>2 </sub>(500 pmol/ 20 &#x003bc;L) injection was significantly diminished in TRPV1<sup>-/- </sup>mice. * p &#x0003c; 0.05, ** p &#x0003c; 0.01 vs. TRPV1<sup>+/+ </sup>mice. (<bold>B</bold>) Intracellular cAMP levels in mouse DRG neurons or HEK293 cells treated with a mixture of forskolin (FSK, 10 &#x003bc;M), IBMX (1 mM) and dibutyryl cAMP (dbcAMP, 3 mM), or PGE<sub>2 </sub>(1 &#x003bc;M) or isoproterenol (Isop., 10 &#x003bc;M). *, # p &#x0003c; 0.05 vs. Cont., **, ## p &#x0003c; 0.01 vs. Cont. (<bold>C</bold>) Representative traces of potentiation of capsaicin (100 nM)-activated current by extracellular PGE<sub>2 </sub>(1 &#x003bc;M, 1.5 min) or a mixture of FSK(10 &#x003bc;M), IBMX (1 mM) and dbcAMP (3 mM) (6.5 min) in mouse DRG neurons. Currents were normalized to values induced by first capsaicin application in the absence of additives (bar graph). Capsaicin was reapplied 1.5 or 6.5 min after exposure to bath solution with additives. Numbers in parenthesis indicate cells tested. * p &#x0003c; 0.05 vs. Cont. Holding potential (V<sub>h</sub>): -60 mV. (<bold>D</bold>) Long (6.5 min) but not short (1.5 min) activation of PKA pathway has effect on TRPV1 responses in HEK293 cells. FSK (10 &#x003bc;M), IBMX (1 mM) and dbcAMP (3 mM) were applied to cells expressing rat TRPV1. Isop. (10 &#x003bc;M) was applied to cells expressing both rat TRPV1 and &#x003b2;<sub>1</sub>-adrenergic receptors (&#x003b2;<sub>1</sub>-ADR). Numbers in parenthesis indicate cells tested. V<sub>h</sub>: -60 mV. * p &#x0003c; 0.05 vs Cont.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1744-8069-1-3-1"/></fig></sec><sec><title>PGE<sub>2 </sub>increases TRPV1 activity through EP<sub>1 </sub>receptors</title><p>To explore the mechanism underlying the PKA-independent PGE<sub>2 </sub>(1.5 min)-induced potentiation of the capsaicin-evoked responses observed in DRG neurons, we first examine the effects of PGE<sub>2 </sub>on capsaicin-activated currents in HEK293 cells expressing TRPV1 and each EP receptor. PGE<sub>2 </sub>(1 &#x003bc;M, 1.5 min) caused a robust increase in the magnitude of low dose (20 nM) capsaicin-activated currents in HEK293 cells co-expressing TRPV1 with EP<sub>1 </sub>(0.90 &#x000b1; 0.04 fold increase, n = 9 for control (Cont.); 4.60 &#x000b1; 1.03 fold, n = 17 for PGE<sub>2</sub>, p &#x0003c; 0.05) (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2B</xref>). This increase lasted more than three minutes, as we previously reported for PAR-2 (proteinase activated receptor 2)-mediated potentiation of TRPV1 activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. In contrast, no such potentiation was detected in cells expressing TRPV1 with other EP receptor subtypes (0.91 &#x000b1; 0.09 fold increase, n = 7; 0.77 &#x000b1; 0.13, n = 9; 0.72 &#x000b1; 0.24, n = 5; 0.98 &#x000b1; 0.18, n = 7; 0.89 &#x000b1; 0.15, n = 9 for EP<sub>2</sub>, EP<sub>3&#x003b1;</sub>, EP<sub>3&#x003b2;</sub>, EP<sub>3&#x003b3; </sub>or EP<sub>4</sub>, respectively) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2B</xref>). Protracted (6.5 min) treatment with PGE<sub>2 </sub>caused a significant increase in capsaicin-activated currents in cells expressing TRPV1 and EP<sub>4</sub>, a phenomenon like that observed following treatment with a mixture of FSK, IBMX and dbcAMP (3.03 &#x000b1; 0.48 fold increase, n = 6, p &#x0003c; 0.05 vs. Cont.) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2B</xref>), suggesting that the EP<sub>4 </sub>receptor, known to be expressed in DRG and coupled to Gs protein, is the receptor that activates a PKA-dependent signaling pathway upon prostaglandin exposure. All cells exhibiting an increase of capsaicin-activated currents upon treatment with a mixture of FSK, IBMX and dbcAMP also showed an increase in current in the presence of PMA (data not shown), suggesting that both PKA- and PKC-dependent pathways work in the same cells. To examine how PGE<sub>2 </sub>changes TRPV1 responsiveness, we measured TRPV1 current in single cells by applying a range of concentrations of capsaicin in the absence or presence of PGE<sub>2</sub>. The currents were normalized to the maximal current produced by 1 &#x003bc;M capsaicin in each cell. Maximal current in the presence of PGE<sub>2 </sub>was almost the same as that in the absence of PGE<sub>2</sub>. The resultant dose-response curves clearly demonstrate that PGE<sub>2 </sub>enhances capsaicin action on TRPV1 by lowering EC<sub>50 </sub>values without altering maximal responses (EC<sub>50 </sub>from 81.0 nM to 27.6 nM) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2C</xref>). We next examined the effects of PGE<sub>2 </sub>on the thermal sensitivity of TRPV1. When temperature ramps were applied to HEK293 cells expressing both TRPV1 and EP<sub>1 </sub>in the absence of PGE<sub>2</sub>, heat-evoked currents developed at 40.7 &#x000b1; 0.3&#x000b0;C (n = 8) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2D</xref>). In contrast, the temperature threshold for TRPV1 activation was significantly reduced to 30.6 &#x000b1; 1.1&#x000b0;C in the presence of PGE<sub>2 </sub>(n = 8, p &#x0003c; 0.05) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2D</xref>) implying that under these conditions, TRPV1 could be activated at normal body temperature. A similar potentiating effect of PGE<sub>2 </sub>was observed for proton (pH 6.2)-evoked TRPV1 current responses (0.91 &#x000b1; 0.06 fold increase, n = 3 for control; 4.47 &#x000b1; 1.09 fold, n = 7 for PGE<sub>2</sub>, p &#x0003c; 0.01) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2E</xref>). These data clearly show that TRPV1 currents evoked by any of three different stimuli (capsaicin, proton, or heat) are potentiated or sensitized by PGE<sub>2 </sub>through EP<sub>1 </sub>receptor activation. On the other hand, the temperature threshold for TRPV1 activation was not changed upon treatment with a mixture of FSK, IBMX and dbcAMP in HEK293 cells expressing TRPV1 (40.8 &#x000b1; 0.8&#x000b0;C, n = 4), suggesting different actions on TRPV1 by PKA and PKC.</p><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>PGE<sub>2 </sub>increases TRPV1 activity through EP<sub>1 </sub>receptors in a PKC-dependent manner in HEK293 cells. (<bold>A</bold>) and (<bold>B</bold>) Treatment with PGE<sub>2 </sub>(1.5 min) potentiates capsaicin-evoked responses in cells expressing rat TRPV1 with mouse EP<sub>1 </sub>receptors, but not with other mouse EP receptors. Cells were pretreated with PGE<sub>2 </sub>(1 &#x003bc;M) for 1.5 or 6.5 min before second capsaicin (20 nM) application. V<sub>h</sub>: -60 mV. Currents were normalized as described in Figure 1. * p &#x0003c; 0.05 vs. control (Cont.). Numbers in parenthesis indicate cells tested. (<bold>C</bold>) Capsaicin dose-response curves for TRPV1 activation in the absence (&#x02022;) and presence (&#x025cb;) of extracellular 1 &#x003bc;M PGE<sub>2</sub>. Currents were normalized to the current maximally activated by 1 &#x003bc;M capsaicin in the absence of PGE<sub>2</sub>. Figure shows averaged data fitted with the Hill equation. EC<sub>50 </sub>= 81.0 nM and Hill coefficient = 1.33 in the absence of PGE<sub>2</sub>. EC<sub>50 </sub>= 27.6 nM and Hill coefficient = 1.01 in the presence of PGE<sub>2</sub>. Data were obtained from 54 different cells. (<bold>D</bold>) Temperature threshold for TRPV1 activation was reduced in the presence of extracellular PGE<sub>2 </sub>(1 &#x003bc;M). Representative temperature-response profiles in the absence (upper) and presence (lower) of PGE<sub>2 </sub>(left). Temperature threshold for TRPV1 activation in the presence of PGE<sub>2 </sub>(30.6 &#x000b1; 1.1&#x000b0;C) was significantly lower than that in the absence of PGE<sub>2 </sub>(40.7 &#x000b1; 0.3&#x000b0;C) (right). * p &#x0003c; 0.05 vs. PGE<sub>2 </sub>(-). Numbers in parenthesis indicate cells tested. (<bold>E</bold>) Proton-evoked TRPV1 responses were significantly potentiated by PGE<sub>2 </sub>(1 &#x003bc;M). * p &#x0003c; 0.01 vs. PGE<sub>2 </sub>(-). (<bold>F</bold>) PKC-dependent pathway is involved in the PGE<sub>2 </sub>(1 &#x003bc;M, 1.5 min)-induced potentiation of capsaicin-activated currents. In some experiments, calphostin C (Calp. C) (1 &#x003bc;M) or PKC&#x003b5; translocation inhibitor (PKC&#x003b5;-I) (200 &#x003bc;M) was included in the pipette solution. Currents were normalized as described in Figure 1. Numbers in parenthesis indicate cells tested. * p &#x0003c; 0.05 vs. Cont. V<sub>h</sub>: -60 mV.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1744-8069-1-3-2"/></fig><p>The signaling pathway downstream of EP<sub>1 </sub>remains to be clarified. We have reported that G<sub>q/11</sub>-coupled metabotropic receptor activation such as ATP (P2Y), bradykinin (B2) and proteinase-activated receptor 2 (PAR2) receptors causes potentiation or sensitization of TRPV1 through the PKC-dependent phosphorylation of TRPV1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. Therefore, we examined whether a similar signal transduction pathway is involved in the regulation of TRPV1 responses through EP<sub>1</sub>. When calphostin C (Calp.C), a specific PKC inhibitor, was added to the pipette solution, the effect of PGE<sub>2 </sub>was almost completely inhibited (0.92 &#x000b1; 0.15 fold increase, n = 10) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2F</xref>). Similarly, a PKC&#x003b5; translocation inhibitor (PKC&#x003b5;-I) abolished the potentiation of TRPV1 response by PGE<sub>2 </sub>(1.11 &#x000b1; 0.25 fold increase, n = 11) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2F</xref>). These data suggest that PGE<sub>2</sub>-induced potentiation of TRPV1 responsiveness develops through activation of PKC&#x003b5;. To further confirm the involvement of PKC-dependent phosphorylation, PGE<sub>2 </sub>effects were examined using cells expressing a TRPV1 mutant, S502A/S800A which is insensitive to PKC-dependent phosphorylation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. No potentiation of capsaicin-activated currents was observed upon PGE<sub>2</sub>treatment of cells expressing S502A/S800A (0.85 &#x000b1; 0.15 fold increase, n = 5) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2F</xref>), further indicating the involvement of PKC-dependent phosphorylation. Since S502 is a PKA-phosphorylation site as well [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>], we examined the effects of treatment with a mixture of FSK, IBMX and dbcAMP on the capsaicin-activated currents in cells expressing S502A/S800A. Such treatment failed to potentiate the capsaicin-activated currents (1.13 &#x000b1; 0.07 fold increase, n = 10), suggesting that S502 is a substrate for PKA-dependent phosphorylation of TRPV1 as well.</p></sec><sec><title>Sensitization of TRPV1 by EP<sub>1 </sub>receptors in mouse</title><p>To examine the involvement of EP<sub>1 </sub>in PGE<sub>2 </sub>(1.5 min)-induced potentiation of capsaicin-evoked response in native neurons, we used a specific EP<sub>1 </sub>agonist, ONO-DI-004 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>], and a specific EP<sub>1 </sub>antagonist, ONO-8713 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>], in mouse DRG neurons. ONO-DI-004 was found to significantly increase the capsaicin-activated currents to an extent similar to that observed with PGE<sub>2 </sub>(3.36 &#x000b1; 0.68 fold increase for PGE<sub>2</sub>, n = 23, p &#x0003c; 0.05 vs. control (Cont.); 3.30 &#x000b1; 0.68 fold for ONO-DI-004 (EP<sub>1 </sub>Agon.), n = 9, p &#x0003c; 0.05 vs. Cont.) (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref> left and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref>). Furthermore, potentiation of the capsaicin-activated currents by PGE<sub>2 </sub>was inhibited in the presence of ONO-8713 (EP<sub>1 </sub>Antg., 1.00 &#x000b1; 0.17 fold increase, n = 8) (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref> right and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref>). These results indicate that PGE<sub>2 </sub>(1.5 min)-induced potentiation of the capsaicin-activated current responses occurs through EP<sub>1 </sub>receptors in DRG neurons. To confirm the involvement of PKC-dependent events downstream of PGE<sub>2 </sub>effects in DRG neurons, we first examined the effects of a specific phospholipase C (PLC) inhibitor, U73122 (3 &#x003bc;M). PGE<sub>2</sub>-induced potentiation of capsaicin-activated current was significantly diminished in the presence of U73122 while control U73343 exhibited no such effects (0.73 &#x000b1; 0.11 fold increase, n = 8 for U73343; 3.40 &#x000b1; 1.11 fold, n = 8 for U73433, p &#x0003c; 0.05) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref>). Furthermore, PGE<sub>2 </sub>failed to potentiate the capsaicin-activated currents when PKC&#x003b5;-I was included in the pipette solution (0.86 &#x000b1; 0.09 fold increase, n = 12) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref>). A robust potentiating effect of phorbol 12-myristate 13-acetate (PMA, 100 nM) also supported the involvement of PKC-dependent events (16.36 &#x000b1; 3.68 fold increase, n = 11, p &#x0003c; 0.05) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref>). To further confirm the involvement of EP<sub>1 </sub>receptors, DRG neurons of EP<sub>1 </sub>deficient mice (EP<sub>1</sub><sup>-/-</sup>) were subjected to patch-clamp analysis. PGE<sub>2 </sub>failed to potentiate capsaicin-activated currents in the DRG neurons from EP<sub>1</sub><sup>-/- </sup>mice (1.45 &#x000b1; 0.70 fold increase, n = 10) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref>). Functional interaction of PKC&#x003b5; with TRPV1 prompted us to examine the expression of the two proteins in mouse DRG. Three hundred seventy eight out of 541 TRPV1 positive neurons (69.9 %) were stained with anti-PKC&#x003b5; antibody, supporting the TRPV1 activation pathway through PKC&#x003b5; (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3C</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>EP<sub>1 </sub>receptor involvement in PGE<sub>2 </sub>(1.5 min)-induced potentiation of capsaicin-activated currents in mouse DRG neurons. (<bold>A</bold>) Representative traces of potentiation of capsaicin-activated currents by a specific EP<sub>1 </sub>agonist, ONO-DI-004 (10 &#x003bc;M, 1.5 min), and reverse of the PGE<sub>2 </sub>(1.5 min)-induced potentiation by a specific EP<sub>1 </sub>antagonist, ONO-8713 (1 &#x003bc;M). V<sub>h</sub>: -60 mV. (<bold>B</bold>) Effects of PGE<sub>2 </sub>(1 &#x003bc;M), ONO-DI-004 (EP<sub>1 </sub>Agon., 10 &#x003bc;M), PGE<sub>2 </sub>plus ONO-8713 (EP<sub>1 </sub>Antg., 1 &#x003bc;M), PGE<sub>2 </sub>plus U73122 (3 &#x003bc;M), PGE<sub>2 </sub>plus U73343 (3 &#x003bc;M), phorbol 12-myristate 13-acetate (PMA, 100 nM) or PGE<sub>2 </sub>plus PKC&#x003b5;-I (200 &#x003bc;M) on capsaicin-activated currents in DRG neurons from wild type (EP<sub>1</sub><sup>+/+</sup>) mice, and effects of PGE<sub>2 </sub>on capsaicin-activated currents in DRG neurons from EP<sub>1</sub><sup>-/- </sup>mice. Currents are normalized as described in Fig. 1. * p &#x0003c; 0.05 vs. Cont., + p &#x0003c; 0.05 vs. U73343. Numbers in parenthesis indicate cells tested. (<bold>C</bold>) Co-expression of TRPV1 (green) and PKC&#x003b5; (blue) in mouse DRG. Arrowheads indicate neurons positive for TRPV1 but not for PKC&#x003b5;. Arrows indicate neurons positive for both TRPV1 and PKC&#x003b5; (light blue). Bar, 100 &#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1744-8069-1-3-3"/></fig><p>We next investigated the involvement of EP<sub>1 </sub>receptors in PGE<sub>2</sub>-induced thermal hyperalgesia at the behavioral level. PGE<sub>2</sub>-induced thermal hyperalgesia was significantly diminished at 15 to 45 min after injection in EP<sub>1</sub><sup>-/- </sup>mice (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4A</xref>), relative to that observed in wild type mice. The involvement of EP<sub>1 </sub>receptors in the PGE<sub>2</sub>-induced hypersensitivity was supported by another behavioral analysis in which PGE<sub>2 </sub>caused less reduction of paw withdrawal latency in wild type mice pretreated with a specific EP<sub>1 </sub>antagonist (500 pmol/ 20 &#x003bc;L) than in vehicle control (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4A</xref>). These results suggest that a PKC-dependent pathway downstream of EP<sub>1 </sub>activation is mainly involved in PGE<sub>2</sub>-induced thermal hyperalgesia. We have hypothesized that the potentiation of TRPV1 activity by several inflammatory mediators could represent one important mechanism underlying acute inflammatory pain sensation. To prove the accuracy of this hypothesis, we investigated the involvement of EP<sub>1 </sub>in inflammatory pain-related responses using mustard oil which is known to cause inflammation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>]. Topical application of mustard oil induced clear thermal hyperalgesia (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4B</xref>). The mustard oil-induced thermal hyperalgesia was significantly reduced both in TRPV1<sup>-/- </sup>mice and EP<sub>1</sub><sup>-/- </sup>mice. Thus, these data show that EP<sub>1 </sub>contributes to inflammatory nociception in mice and support the hypothesis.</p><fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Interaction between TRPV1 and EP<sub>1 </sub>receptors in a behavioral level. (<bold>A</bold>) PGE<sub>2</sub>-induced thermal hyperalgesia in wild type mice with (&#x025b4;, n = 6) or without (&#x025cb;, n = 6) pretreatment (ONO-8713, 500 pmol/ 20 &#x003bc;L), or in EP<sub>1</sub><sup>-/- </sup>mice (&#x02022;, n = 6). * p &#x0003c; 0.05 vs. wild type mice. (<bold>B) </bold>10% Mustard oil-induced thermal hyperalgesia in wild type mice (&#x025cb;, n = 12), TRPV1<sup>-/- </sup>mice (&#x025b2;, n = 6) or EP<sub>1</sub><sup>-/- </sup>mice (&#x02022;, n = 6). * p &#x0003c; 0.05, ** p &#x0003c; 0.01 vs. wild type mice.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1744-8069-1-3-4"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Sensitization of TRPV1 by IP receptors</title><p>In order to determine whether the observed responses are specific to PGE<sub>2</sub>, we extended our analysis to PGI<sub>2 </sub>whose receptor has been reported to be involved in nociception [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. We first examined the effects of PGI<sub>2 </sub>on capsaicin-activated currents in mouse DRG neurons. PGI<sub>2 </sub>pretreatment (1000 nM, 1.5 min) potentiated capsaicin (100 nM)-activated currents (3.23 &#x000b1; 0.55 fold increase, n = 14 or 0.78 &#x000b1; 0.08 fold, n = 5 with or without (Cont.) PGI<sub>2</sub>, respectively; p &#x0003c; 0.05) whereas at 100 nM, PGI<sub>2 </sub>(1.5 min) showed no such effects (1.24 &#x000b1; 0.22 fold, n = 11) (Figures. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>). On the other hand, long (6.5 min) treatment with PGI<sub>2 </sub>(100 nM) caused significant potentiation of capsaicin-activated currents as in the treatment with a mixture of FSK, IBMX and dbcAMP (2.06 &#x000b1; 0.54 fold increase, n = 11, p &#x0003c; 0.05 vs. Cont.) (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>). The potentiation effects of PGI<sub>2 </sub>appear to occur through IP receptors because a specific IP agonist, ONO-54918-07 (100 nM) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>] caused similar potentiation of capsaicin-activated currents (Agon., 3.71 &#x000b1; 0.81 fold increase, n = 9, p &#x0003c; 0.05 vs. Cont.) (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>) although PGI<sub>2 </sub>is known to cross react with some EP receptors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. The fact that a specific EP<sub>1 </sub>antagonist, ONO-8713 failed to prevent the PGI<sub>2</sub>-induced potentiation (+EP<sub>1 </sub>Antg., 3.55 &#x000b1; 1.17 fold increase, n = 6) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>) further suggests the involvement of IP receptors in the potentiation process. The involvement of IP receptors in the PGI<sub>2</sub>-induced potentiation of capsaicin-activated currents was further supported by the ineffectiveness of PGI<sub>2 </sub>on DRG neurons from IP-deficient mice (IP<sup>-/-</sup>) (1.25 &#x000b1; 0.16 fold increase, n = 9, p &#x0003c; 0.01 vs. 1000 nM of PGI<sub>2</sub>) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>). It has been reported that low concentrations of PGI<sub>2 </sub>stimulate Gs protein coupled to IP receptors whereas high concentrations of PGI<sub>2 </sub>stimulate not only Gs but also Gq [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>]. This property might explain the dose-dependent effects of PGI<sub>2 </sub>on capsaicin-activated currents: PKC-dependent sensitization of TRPV1 occurs downstream of Gq-coupled IP receptor activation at high concentrations (1000 nM) of PGI<sub>2 </sub>(1.5 min) while long (6.5 min) treatment with low concentrations (100 nM) of PGI<sub>2 </sub>causes potentiation of TRPV1 activity through Gs activation. To test this hypothesis, PGI<sub>2 </sub>(1.5 min)-induced potentiation of capsaicin-activated currents was examined in the presence of U73122. When U73122 was included in the pipette solution, PGI<sub>2 </sub>(1.5 min) failed to potentiate the currents whereas U73343 exhibited no such effects, indicating the involvement of PLC activation in the potentiating process (0.97 &#x000b1; 0.40 fold increase, n = 9 for U73122, 2.58 &#x000b1; 0.66 fold, n = 5 for U73343, p &#x0003c; 0.05) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>). Furthermore, PKC&#x003b5;-I included in the pipette solution almost completely blocked the PGI<sub>2 </sub>(1000 nM)-induced potentiation (1.49 &#x000b1; 0.60 fold increase, n = 14), suggesting the involvement of PKC&#x003b5;-dependent regulation mechanism (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>PGI<sub>2 </sub>causes potentiation or sensitization of TRPV1 through mainly through PKC activation. (<bold>A</bold>) Representative traces of potentiation of capsaicin-activated currents by PGI<sub>2 </sub>(1000 nM, 1.5 min), a specific IP agonist, ONO-54918-07 (1.5 min) or PGI<sub>2 </sub>(100 nM, 6.5 min), but not by PGI<sub>2 </sub>(100 nM, 1.5 min) in mouse DRG neurons. V<sub>h</sub>: -60 mV. (<bold>B</bold>) Effects of treatments (1.5 or 6.5 min) with PGI<sub>2 </sub>(100 or 1000 nM), ONO-54918-07 (IP Agon., 100 nM), PGI<sub>2 </sub>(1000 nM) plus ONO-8713 (EP<sub>1 </sub>Antg., 1 &#x003bc;M), PGI<sub>2 </sub>(1000 nM) plus U73122 (3 &#x003bc;M), PGI<sub>2 </sub>(1000 nM) plus U73343 (3 &#x003bc;M) or PGI<sub>2 </sub>(1000 nM) plus PKC&#x003b5;-I (200 &#x003bc;M) on capsaicin-activated currents in DRG neurons from wild type (IP<sup>+/+</sup>) mice, and effects of PGI<sub>2 </sub>on capsaicin-activated currents in DRG neurons from IP-deficient (IP<sup>-/-</sup>) mice. Currents are normalized as described in Figure 1. * p &#x0003c; 0.05 vs. Cont. ++ p &#x0003c; 0.01 vs. U73343, # p &#x0003c; 0.05, ## p &#x0003c; 0.01 vs. PGI<sub>2 </sub>(1000 nM, 1.5 min) in DRG neurons from IP<sup>+/+ </sup>mice. Numbers in parenthesis indicate cells tested. (<bold>C</bold>) A representative trace of potentiation of capsaicin-activated currents by PGI<sub>2 </sub>(1000 nM, 1.5 min) in HEK293 cells expressing both TRPV1 and IP. V<sub>h</sub>: -60 mV. (<bold>D</bold>) Effects of treatments (1.5 or 6.5 min) with PGI<sub>2 </sub>(100 or 1000 nM) or PGI<sub>2 </sub>(1000 nM) plus calphostin C (Calp. C, 1 &#x003bc;M) on capsaicin-activated currents in HEK293 cells expressing rat wild type TRPV1 or S502A/S800A mutant with IP. Currents are normalized as described in Figure 1. * p &#x0003c; 0.05 vs. Cont. (<bold>E</bold>) Temperature threshold for TRPV1 activation in the presence of PGI<sub>2 </sub>(32.2 &#x000b1; 1.2&#x000b0;C) was significantly lower than that in the absence of PGI<sub>2 </sub>(38.2 &#x000b1; 0.5&#x000b0;C) in HEK293 cells expressing rat TRPV1 and IP. * p &#x0003c; 0.01 vs. PGI<sub>2 </sub>(-).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1744-8069-1-3-5"/></fig><p>Dose-dependent PGI<sub>2 </sub>(1.5 min)-induced potentiation of capsaicin-activated currents was also observed in HEK293 cells expressing TRPV1 and IP receptors (0.90 &#x000b1; 0.04 fold increase, n = 9 without PGI<sub>2 </sub>(Cont.); 0.68 &#x000b1; 0.08 fold, n = 12 with 100 nM of PGI<sub>2</sub>; 0.75 &#x000b1; 0.07 fold, n = 6 with 300 nM PGI<sub>2</sub>, 4.96 &#x000b1; 1.36 fold, n = 8 with 1000 nM of PGI<sub>2</sub>, p &#x0003c; 0.01 vs. Cont.) (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5C</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5D</xref>, and data not shown). Calp. C blocked PGI<sub>2</sub>-induced potentiation of TRPV1 currents (0.75 &#x000b1; 0.15 fold increase, n = 6) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5D</xref>). Furthermore, PGI<sub>2 </sub>(1000 nM) failed to potentiate capsaicin-activated currents in HEK293 cells expressing the S502/S800 mutant (0.80 &#x000b1; 0.05 fold, n = 6) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5D</xref>). Long (6.5 min) treatment with PGI<sub>2 </sub>(100 nM) caused an increase in capsaicin-activated currents in 4 out of 6 cells, as did long treatment with a mixture of FSK, IBMX and dbcAMP in HEK293 cells expressing TRPV1 (3.19 &#x000b1; 1.45 fold increase, n = 6, p = 0.16). These results suggest that a mechanism involving PKC is predominantly involved in the regulation of TRPV1 activity during short treatment with PGI<sub>2 </sub>although both PKA-dependent and PKC-dependent pathways may contribute. The temperature threshold for TRPV1 activation was significantly reduced (from 38.2 &#x000b1; 0.5&#x000b0;C, n = 5 to 32.2 &#x000b1; 1.2&#x000b0;C, n = 5) in the presence of PGI<sub>2</sub>, suggesting the possibility that IP receptor activation can cause nociception at body temperature (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5E</xref>). Finally, PGI<sub>2</sub>-induced thermal hyperalgesia observed in wild type mice disappeared almost completely in both TRPV1-deficient (TRPV1<sup>-/-</sup>) mice and IP-deficient (IP<sup>-/-</sup>) mice, suggesting that the functional interaction of TRPV1 with IP causes thermal hyperalgesia at the behavioral level (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Interaction between TRPV1 and IP receptors at a behavioral level. PGI<sub>2</sub>-induced thermal hyperalgesia in wild type mice (&#x025cb;, n = 6), TRPV1<sup>-/- </sup>mice (&#x025b2;, n = 6) or IP<sup>-/- </sup>mice (&#x02022;, n = 6). Thermal hyperalgesia by intraplantar PGI<sub>2 </sub>(500 pmol/ 20 &#x003bc;L) injection was significantly diminished in TRPV1<sup>-/- </sup>mice and IP<sup>-/- </sup>mice. * p &#x0003c; 0.05, ** p &#x0003c; 0.01 vs. wild type mice.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1744-8069-1-3-6"/></fig></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>The data presented herein demonstrate that TRPV1 is essential for the development of thermal hyperalgesia <italic>in vivo </italic>induced by two major inflammation-associated prostaglandins, PGE<sub>2 </sub>and PGI<sub>2</sub>, and that TRPV1 and EP<sub>1 </sub>or IP receptors can functionally interact, mainly through a PKC-dependent pathway. The temperature threshold for TRPV1 activation is reduced below 35&#x000b0;C in the presence of prostaglandins, so that TRPV1 can be activated at normal body temperature, possibly leading to spontaneous pain sensation. This interaction might be one important underlying mechanism for the well-recognized peripheral nociceptive actions of PGE<sub>2 </sub>or PGI<sub>2 </sub>in the context of inflammation. In the present study, 1 &#x003bc;M PGE<sub>2 </sub>or PGI<sub>2 </sub>was found to potentiate or sensitize TRPV1 activity. It is not well known how much PGE<sub>2 </sub>or PGI<sub>2 </sub>is released locally at the site of inflammation. However, more than micromolar-order concentrations of PGE<sub>2 </sub>and PGI<sub>2 </sub>have been reported to be synthesized by macrophages upon lipopolysacharide (LPS) stimulation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>], suggesting that 1 &#x003bc;M is an attainable concentration in the context of inflammation. It has been previously reported that EP<sub>1 </sub>is coupled to intracellular Ca<sup>2+ </sup>mobilization in CHO cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>]. However, the transduction events downstream of EP<sub>1 </sub>signaling have been unclear. Together with a report suggesting the possible coupling of EP<sub>1 </sub>with G<sub>q/11</sub>-protein [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>], our data indicate that EP<sub>1 </sub>receptors activate a PKC-dependent signal transduction pathway.</p><p>There has been extensive work demonstrating the activation of a PKA-dependent pathway by PGE<sub>2 </sub>that influences capsaicin- or heat-mediated actions in rat sensory neurons [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>] as well as interactions between cloned TRPV1 and PKA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>]. These results suggest that PKA plays a pivotal role in the development of hyperalgesia and inflammation by prostaglandins. In our experiments using mouse DRG neurons and HEK293 cells expressing TRPV1, a PKC-dependent pathway was found to be predominantly involved in both PGE<sub>2 </sub>(1.5 min)- and PGI<sub>2 </sub>(1.5 min)-induced responses. The reason that there has been no study describing the involvement of a PKC-dependent pathway in the regulation of TRPV1 following prostaglandin receptor activation is not clear. In the present study, it was found that both PKA- and PKC-dependent pathways are involved downstream of prostaglandin actions on TRPV1 although the PKC-dependent one appears to predominate. A PKA-dependent pathway took a relatively long time to exert its potentiating effects on TRPV1 activity, suggesting some difference between PKA- and PKC-dependent phosphorylation of TRPV1. Indeed, Bhave et al. treated cells with 8-Br-cAMP for 30 min to inhibit TRPV1 desensitization through phosphorylation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>], and significant potentiation of capsaicin-activated currents in rat DRG neurons was observed upon prolonged (greater than 10 min) exposure to PGE<sub>2 </sub>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>]. Furthermore, there is a report describing the ineffectiveness of PKA stimulation on TRPV1 currents in <italic>Xenopus </italic>oocytes treated with 8-Br-cAMP and IBMX for relatively short periods [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>]. Both PKA-dependent and PKC-dependent pathways might work in concert in native cells. Patch-clamp recordings in the previous studies were performed in the Ca<sup>2+</sup>-containing solutions, whereas we did all of our experiments under Ca<sup>2+</sup>-free conditions, to avoid Ca<sup>2+</sup>-dependent TRPV1 desensitization [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>]. Potentiation of capsaicin-activated currents by PGE<sub>2 </sub>was observed in embryonic rat DRG neurons [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>] while we used adult mouse DRG neurons. Furthermore, potentiation of heat-activated currents [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>], inhibition of desensitization of capsaicin-activated currents [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>] or anandamide-induced cytosolic Ca<sup>2+ </sup>increase [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>] but not potentiation of capsaicin-activated current response were examined in the previous studies investigating the involvement of PKA-dependent pathway in TRPV1 activity. Thus, difference in experimental conditions or readout might also account for the different outcomes. The physiological relevance of the two different pathways downstream of prostaglandin exposure remains to be elucidated. The fact that only PKC activation leads to the reduction of temperature threshold for TRPV1 activation might be pertinent to this issue. Disruption of interaction between phosphatidylinositol-4, 5-bisphosphate (PIP<sub>2</sub>) and TRPV1 has also been reported to be involved in the sensitization of TRPV1 downstream of PLC activation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>]. In our study, however, both PGE<sub>2</sub>- and PGI<sub>2</sub>-induced potentiation of TRPV1 activity was completely inhibited by treatments with two kinds of PKC inhibitors. Thus, we believe that a PKC-dependent pathway is predominantly involved in the PGE<sub>2</sub>- and PGI<sub>2</sub>-induced potentiation or sensitization of TRPV1 activity in mice.</p><p>The inhibition of PGE<sub>2</sub>-induced thermal hyperalgesia observed in EP<sub>1</sub><sup>-/- </sup>mice, while significant, was not very robust, compared with that in TRPV1<sup>-/- </sup>mice (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). Other pathways, most likely including one involving PKA, might account for the residual component. Further, inhibition of mustard oil-induced thermal hyperalgesia observed in TRPV1<sup>-/- </sup>or EP<sub>1</sub><sup>-/- </sup>mice might seem not to be robust or dramatic (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). Since many inflammatory factors activating PLC-coupled receptors are involved in the inflammatory response [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>]. In such a complicated environment, thermal hyperalgesia was significantly diminished in TRPV1<sup>-/- </sup>mice or EP<sub>1</sub><sup>-/- </sup>mice albeit at a few time points, suggesting the importance of the two molecules in the context of inflammatory pain sensation. Given the fact that one of the final targets of both PGE<sub>2 </sub>and PGI<sub>2 </sub>is TRPV1 as shown in our study, compounds acting on EP<sub>1</sub>, IP or TRPV1, or interfering with their interaction could prove useful in the treatment of pain and inflammation.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Potentiation or sensitization of TRPV1 activity through EP<sub>1 </sub>or IP activation, mainly through PKC- and PKA-dependent mechanisms, might be important mechanism underlying the peripheral nociceptive actions of PGE<sub>2 </sub>or PGI<sub>2</sub>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Animals</title><p>Male C57BL/6-strain mice (4 weeks, SLC, Shizuoka, Japan), EP<sub>1</sub>-deficient mice (4 weeks, from Dr. Narumiya), IP-deficient mice (4 weeks, from Dr. Narumiya) or TRPV1-deficient mice (4 weeks, from Dr. Julius, UCSF) were used. They were housed in a controlled environment (12 h light/dark cycle, room temperature 22&#x02013;24&#x000b0;C, 50&#x02013;60% relative humidity) with free access to food and water. All procedures involving the care and use of mice were carried out in accordance with institutional (Mie University) guidelines and the National Institute of Health guide for the care and use of laboratory animals.</p></sec><sec><title>Behavioral study</title><p>Thermal nociceptive threshold was assessed using the paw withdrawal test. Mice were placed in a transparent Perspex box on a thin glass platform (Plantar test, Ugo Basile, Italy). They were injected intraplantarly with PGE<sub>2 </sub>(500 pmol/ 20 &#x003bc;L, Sigma) with or without ONO-8713 (500 pmol/ 20 &#x003bc;L), or with PGI<sub>2 </sub>(500 pmol/ 20 &#x003bc;L, Sigma), or applied topically to the plantar surface of right hind paw with 10% mustard oil (Sigma) (diluted with mineral oil), and the paw withdrawal latency to radiant heat applied to the plantar surface of hind paw was measured as the time from onset of the radiant heat to the withdrawal of the mouse hind paw.</p></sec><sec><title>Cell culture</title><p>Human embryonic kidney-derived (HEK293) cells were maintained in Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium (Invitrogen; supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum, penicillin, streptomycin and L-glutamine) and transfected with 0.5 &#x003bc;g of rat TRPV1 cDNA and 0.5 &#x003bc;g of mouse EP or IP receptor cDNAs (EP<sub>1</sub>, EP<sub>2</sub>, EP<sub>3&#x003b1;</sub>, EP<sub>3&#x003b2;</sub>, EP<sub>3&#x003b3;</sub>, EP<sub>4 </sub>or IP) using Lipofectamine Plus Reagent (Invitrogen). Primary cultures prepared from adult C57BL/6-strain mice, EP<sub>1</sub>-deficient mice or IP-deficient mice dorsal root ganglion (DRG) neurons were incubated in medium containing nerve growth factor (Sigma, 100 ng/ml).</p></sec><sec><title>Electrophysiology</title><p>Whole-cell patch-clamp recordings were performed 1 day after transfection to HEK293 cells or dissociation of the DRG neurons. Standard bath solution contained 140 mM NaCl, 5 mM KCl, 2 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 5 mM EGTA, 10 mM HEPES, 10 mM glucose, pH7.4 (adjusted with NaOH). Pipette solution contained 140 mM KCl, 5 mM EGTA, 10 mM HEPES, pH7.4 (adjusted with KOH). All patch-clamp experiments were performed at room temperature (22&#x000b0;C). Thermal stimulation was applied by increasing the bath temperature at a rate of 1.0&#x000b0;C/sec with a preheated solution. When the heat-activated currents started to inactivate, the preheated solution was changed to a 22&#x000b0;C one. Chamber temperature was monitored with a thermocouple placed within 100 &#x003bc;m of the patch-clamped cell. For this analysis, heat-evoked current responses were compared between different cells, rather than within the same cell, because repetitive heat-evoked currents show significant desensitization even in the absence of extracellular Ca<sup>2+ </sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>] and because the thermal sensitivity of TRPV1 increases with repeated heat application [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>]. Threshold temperature for activation was defined as the intersection where two lines approximating the stable baseline current and the clearly increasing temperature-dependent current cross in the temperature-response profile. The sensitivity of DRG neurons to capsaicin is slightly lower than that of TRPV1-transfected HEK293 cells as previously reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>]. Therefore, we applied capsaicin at 100 nM to DRG neurons and at 20 nM to HEK293 cells.</p></sec><sec><title>cAMP measurement</title><p>Intracellular cAMP level was examined using 'cAMP Biotrak Enzymeimmunoassay System' according to the manufacture's direction (Amersham Biosciences). In brief, intracellular cAMP released upon membrane hydrolysis of treated cells (10,000 cells/ well) after stimulation (90 sec) was measured based on competition between unlabelled cAMP and a fix quantity of Peroxidase-labeled cAMP for a limited number of the binding sites on a cAMP specific antibody.</p></sec><sec><title>Immunostaining</title><p>DRG was removed from male C57BL/6-strain mice and frozen in liquid nitrogen, and the frozen tissue was cut on a cryostat at a 10 &#x003bc;m thickness. The sections were incubated with the rabbit anti-rat TRPV1 polyclonal antibody (1: 500; Oncogene) and anti-rat PKC&#x003b5; monoclonal antibody (1: 250; Transduction lab) at 4&#x000b0;C for 2 days. Slides with the section were washed with PBS, followed by incubation with Alexa 488-conjugated goat anti-rabbit IgG (1: 700, Molecular Probes), Alexa 350-conjugated anti-mouse IgG (1: 500, Molecular Probes) and Texas Red-phalloidin (1: 500, Molecular Probes). Images were obtained using an Olympus fluorescent microscope with a cooled-CCD camera (ORCA-ER, Hamamatsu Photonics) and IP-Lab Image software (Scanalytics Inc.).</p></sec><sec><title>Chemicals</title><p>ONO-DI-004, ONO-8713 and ONO-54918-07 were obtained from Ono Pharmaceutical Co., Ltd (Osaka, Japan). Calphostin C, phorbol 12-myristate 13-acetate, forskolin, 3-isobutyl-1-methylxanthine, dibutyryl-cAMP, isoproterenol, U73122 and U73343 were from Sigma, and PKC&#x003b5; translocation inhibitor was from Calbiochem.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistics</title><p>Values are shown as the mean &#x000b1; S.E. and data are analyzed using an unpaired <italic>t </italic>test. P values of &#x0003c; 0.05 were considered significant.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Competing interests</title><p>The author(s) declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>TM and TH carried out most of the experiments in this study. KT carried out the immunostaining experiments. TI carried out some electrophysiological experiments. ES made and maintained EP<sub>1</sub>- and IP-deficient mice, and participated in the interpretation of data. YS and SN participated in experimental design and discussion. TT carried out some biochemical experiments. MT contributed to all aspects of the study and wrote the manuscript.</p></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank D. Julius (University of California, San Francisco) for giving us TRPV1-deficient mice, and M.J. Caterina (Johns Hopkins University), N. Saito (Kobe University) and M. Numazaki (University of Tsukuba) for their critical reading of the manuscript, and N. Suzuki and H. Tsumura (Mie University) for their support for maintaining mice. This work was supported by grants from the Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology in Japan, Japan Brain Foundation, Yamanouchi Foundation for Research on Metabolic Disorders, Uehara Memorial Foundation, AstraZeneca Research Foundation and ONO Medical Research Foundation to M.T.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tilley</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Coffman</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Koller</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mixed messages: modulation of inflammation and immune responses by prostaglandins and thromboxanes</article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><year>2001</year><volume>108</volume><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11435451</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI200113416</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Narumiya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugimoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ushikubi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prostanoid receptors: structures, properties, and functions</article-title><source>Physiol Rev</source><year>1999</year><volume>79</volume><fpage>1193</fpage><lpage>1226</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10508233</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Samad</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sapirstein</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Woolf</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prostanoids and pain: unraveling mechanisms and revealing therapeutic targets</article-title><source>Trends Mol Med</source><year>2002</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>390</fpage><lpage>396</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12127725</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1471-4914(02)02383-3</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Breyer</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bagdassarian</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Breyer</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prostanoid receptors: subtypes and signaling</article-title><source>Annu Rev Pharmacol Toxicol</source><year>2001</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>661</fpage><lpage>690</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11264472</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.pharmtox.41.1.661</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Narumiya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>FitzGerald</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic and pharmacological analysis of prostanoid receptor function</article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><year>2001</year><volume>108</volume><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11435452</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI200113455</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oida</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Namba</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugimoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ushikubi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohishi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ichikawa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Narumiya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In situ hybridization studies of prostacyclin receptor mRNA expression in various mouse organs</article-title><source>Br J Pharmacol</source><year>1995</year><volume>116</volume><fpage>2828</fpage><lpage>2837</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8680713</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sugimoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shigemoto</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Namba</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Negishi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mizuno</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Narumiya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ichikawa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distribution of the messenger RNA for the prostaglandin E receptor subtype EP3 in the mouse nervous system</article-title><source>Neuroscience</source><year>1994</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>919</fpage><lpage>928</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7870313</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0306-4522(94)90483-9</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murata</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ushikubi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuoka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirata</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamasaki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugimoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ichikawa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Aze</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueno</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Oh-ishi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Narumiya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Altered pain perception and inflammatory response in mice lacking prostacyclin receptor</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1997</year><volume>388</volume><fpage>678</fpage><lpage>682</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9262402</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/41780</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Minami</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakano</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugimoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ushikubi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ichikawa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Narumiya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of EP receptor subtypes responsible for prostaglandin E2-induced pain responses by use of EP1 and EP3 receptor knockout mice</article-title><source>Br J Pharmacol</source><year>2001</year><volume>133</volume><fpage>438</fpage><lpage>444</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11375261</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.bjp.0704092</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stock</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinjo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Burkhardt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Roach</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Taniguchi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishikawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Flannery</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Coffman</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>McNeish</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Audoly</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The prostaglandin E2 EP1 receptor mediates pain perception and regulates blood pressure</article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><year>2001</year><volume>107</volume><fpage>325</fpage><lpage>331</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11160156</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caterina</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Julius</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The vanilloid receptor: a molecular gateway to the pain pathway</article-title><source>Annu Rev Neurosci</source><year>2001</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>487</fpage><lpage>517</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11283319</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.neuro.24.1.487</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caterina</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schumacher</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Tominaga</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosen</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Julius</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The capsaicin receptor: a heat-activated ion channel in the pain pathway</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1997</year><volume>389</volume><fpage>816</fpage><lpage>824</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9349813</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/39807</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tominaga</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Caterina</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Malmberg</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosen</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilbert</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Skinner</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Raumann</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name><surname>Basbaum</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name><name><surname>Julius</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The cloned capsaicin receptor integrates multiple pain-producing stimuli</article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>1998</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>531</fpage><lpage>543</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9768840</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0896-6273(00)80564-4</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caterina</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Leffler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Malmberg</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Trafton</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Petersen-Zeitz</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Koltzenburg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Basbaum</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name><name><surname>Julius</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impaired nociception and pain sensation in mice lacking the capsaicin receptor</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2000</year><volume>288</volume><fpage>306</fpage><lpage>313</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10764638</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.288.5464.306</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gunthorpe</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hatcher</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Davey</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name><surname>Overend</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Harries</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Latcham</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Clapham</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Atkinson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rance</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Grau</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Harper</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pugh</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Bingham</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Randall</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheardown</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vanilloid receptor-1 is essential for inflammatory thermal hyperalgesia</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2000</year><volume>405</volume><fpage>183</fpage><lpage>187</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10821274</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35012076</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Moriyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Higashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Togashi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamanaka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tominaga</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Noguchi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Proteinase-activated receptor 2-mediated potentiation of transient receptor potential vanilloid subfamily 1 activity reveals a mechanism for proteinase-induced inflammatory pain</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2004</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>4293</fpage><lpage>4299</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15128843</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.0454-04.2004</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sugiura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tominaga</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Katsuya</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Mizumura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bradykinin lowers the threshold temperature for heat activation of vanilloid receptor 1</article-title><source>J Neurophysiol</source><year>2002</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>544</fpage><lpage>548</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12091579</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tominaga</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wada</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Masu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Potentiation of capsaicin receptor activity by metabotropic ATP receptors as a possible mechanism for ATP-evoked pain and hyperalgesia</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2001</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>6951</fpage><lpage>6956</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11371611</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.111025298</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Numazaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tominaga</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Toyooka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tominaga</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Direct phosphorylation of capsaicin receptor VR1 by protein kinase Cepsilon and identification of two target serine residues</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2002</year><volume>277</volume><fpage>13375</fpage><lpage>13378</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11884385</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.C200104200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwong</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ca2+ transient evoked by chemical stimulation is enhanced by PGE2 in vagal sensory neurons: role of cAMP/PKA signaling pathway</article-title><source>J Neurophysiol</source><year>2003</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>1985</fpage><lpage>1993</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12612039</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lopshire</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicol</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The cAMP transduction cascade mediates the prostaglandin E2 enhancement of the capsaicin-elicited current in rat sensory neurons: whole-cell and single-channel studies</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>1998</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>6081</fpage><lpage>6092</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9698303</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Burgess</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prostaglandin E2-induced sensitization of bradykinin-evoked responses in rat dorsal root ganglion neurons is mediated by cAMP-dependent protein kinase A</article-title><source>Eur J Neurosci</source><year>2000</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>3250</fpage><lpage>3258</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10998108</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1460-9568.2000.00218.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schuligoi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Donnerer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Amann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bradykinin-induced sensitization of afferent neurons in the rat paw</article-title><source>Neuroscience</source><year>1994</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>211</fpage><lpage>215</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8190269</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0306-4522(94)90111-2</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaang</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The cAMP-dependent kinase pathway does not sensitize the cloned vanilloid receptor type 1 expressed in xenopus oocytes or Aplysia neurons</article-title><source>Neurosci Lett</source><year>2000</year><volume>288</volume><fpage>57</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10869815</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0304-3940(00)01208-8</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moriyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Iida</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Higashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukuoka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsumura</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Leon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Gachet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Noguchi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tominaga</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Possible involvement of P2Y2 metabotropic receptors in ATP-induced transient receptor potential vanilloid receptor 1-mediated thermal hypersensitivity</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2003</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>6058</fpage><lpage>6062</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12853424</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rathee</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Distler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Obreja</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Neuhuber</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Nau</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kress</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PKA/AKAP/VR-1 module: A common link of Gs-mediated signaling to thermal hyperalgesia</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2002</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>4740</fpage><lpage>4745</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12040081</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shibuya</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Setiadji</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Harayama</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Maruyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueta</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamashita</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Involvement of postsynaptic EP4 and presynaptic EP3 receptors in actions of prostaglandin E2 in rat supraoptic neurones</article-title><source>J Neuroendocrinol</source><year>2002</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>64</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11903814</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2826.2002.00741.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawamori</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakatsugi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohta</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohuchida</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Maruyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kondo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Narumiya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugimura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Wakabayashi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibitory effect of a prostaglandin E receptor subtype EP(1) selective antagonist, ONO-8713, on development of azoxymethane-induced aberrant crypt foci in mice</article-title><source>Cancer Lett</source><year>2000</year><volume>156</volume><fpage>57</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10840160</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0304-3835(00)00440-7</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Woolf</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wall</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relative effectiveness of C primary afferent fibers of different origins in evoking a prolonged facilitation of the flexor reflex in the rat</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>1986</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1433</fpage><lpage>1442</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3711988</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reeh</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kocher</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Does neurogenic inflammation alter the sensitivity of unmyelinated nociceptors in the rat?</article-title><source>Brain Res</source><year>1986</year><volume>384</volume><fpage>42</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3790998</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0006-8993(86)91217-5</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rashid</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawashima</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Maeda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kishioka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueda</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The algogenic-induced nociceptive flexion test in mice: studies on sensitivity of the test and stress on animals</article-title><source>Brain Res Bull</source><year>2003</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>275</fpage><lpage>281</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12754089</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0361-9230(03)00045-5</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Namba</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Oida</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugimoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kakizuka</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Negishi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ichikawa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Narumiya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>cDNA cloning of a mouse prostacyclin receptor. Multiple signaling pathways and expression in thymic medulla</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1994</year><volume>269</volume><fpage>9986</fpage><lpage>9992</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7511597</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Pietro</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Increased TNF-alpha and PGI(2), but not NO release from macrophages in 18-month-old rats</article-title><source>Mech Ageing Dev</source><year>2000</year><volume>114</volume><fpage>79</fpage><lpage>88</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10799706</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0047-6374(00)00090-7</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ikegami</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugimoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Segi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Katsuyama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Karahashi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Amano</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Maruyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamane</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsuchiya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ichikawa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The expression of prostaglandin E receptors EP2 and EP4 and their different regulation by lipopolysaccharide in C3H/HeN peritoneal macrophages</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>2001</year><volume>166</volume><fpage>4689</fpage><lpage>4696</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11254729</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Watabe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugimoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Honda</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Irie</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Namba</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Negishi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Narumiya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ichikawa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cloning and expression of cDNA for a mouse EP1 subtype of prostaglandin E receptor</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1993</year><volume>268</volume><fpage>20175</fpage><lpage>20178</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7690750</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tabata</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugimoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaneko</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ichikawa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Possible coupling of prostaglandin E receptor EP(1) to TRP5 expressed in Xenopus laevis oocytes</article-title><source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><year>2002</year><volume>298</volume><fpage>398</fpage><lpage>402</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12413954</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0006-291X(02)02455-5</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pitchford</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prostaglandins sensitize nociceptors in cell culture</article-title><source>Neurosci Lett</source><year>1991</year><volume>132</volume><fpage>105</fpage><lpage>108</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1724065</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0304-3940(91)90444-X</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Distler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Rathee</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Lips</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Obreja</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Neuhuber</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Kress</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fast Ca2+-induced potentiation of heat-activated ionic currents requires cAMP/PKA signaling and functional AKAP anchoring</article-title><source>J Neurophysiol</source><year>2003</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>2499</fpage><lpage>2505</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12740405</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B39"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhave</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Brasier</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Oxford</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name><surname>Gereau</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>cAMP-dependent protein kinase regulates desensitization of the capsaicin receptor (VR1) by direct phosphorylation</article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>2002</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>721</fpage><lpage>731</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12194871</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0896-6273(02)00802-4</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B40"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Petrocellis</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bisogno</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tognetto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Brandi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>Creminon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Geppetti</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Marzo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The vanilloid receptor (VR1)-mediated effects of anandamide are potently enhanced by the cAMP-dependent protein kinase</article-title><source>J Neurochem</source><year>2001</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>1660</fpage><lpage>1663</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11413249</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1471-4159.2001.00406.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B41"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhave</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Gereau</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prostaglandin and protein kinase A-dependent modulation of vanilloid receptor function by metabotropic glutamate receptor 5: potential mechanism for thermal hyperalgesia</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2002</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>7444</fpage><lpage>7452</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12196566</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B42"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sugiuar</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Bielefeldt</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Gebhart</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TRPV1 function in mouse colon sensory neurons is enhanced by metabotropic 5-hydroxytryptamine receptor activation</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2004</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>9521</fpage><lpage>9530</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15509739</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.2639-04.2004</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B43"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Numazaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tominaga</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeuchi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Murayama</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Toyooka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tominaga</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structural determinant of TRPV1 desensitization interacts with calmodulin</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2003</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>8002</fpage><lpage>8006</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12808128</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1337252100</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B44"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mohapatra</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Nau</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Desensitization of capsaicin-activated currents in the vanilloid receptor TRPV1 is decreased by the cyclic AMP-dependent protein kinase pathway</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2003</year><volume>278</volume><fpage>50080</fpage><lpage>50090</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14506258</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M306619200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B45"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chuang</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name><surname>Prescott</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Shields</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jordt</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Basbaum</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name><name><surname>Chao</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>Julius</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bradykinin and nerve growth factor release the capsaicin receptor from PtdIns(4,5)P2-mediated inhibition</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2001</year><volume>411</volume><fpage>957</fpage><lpage>962</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11418861</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35082088</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B46"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prescott</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><name><surname>Julius</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A modular PIP2 binding site as a determinant of capsaicin receptor sensitivity</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2003</year><volume>300</volume><fpage>1284</fpage><lpage>1288</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12764195</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1083646</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B47"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Julius</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Basbaum</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular mechanisms of nociception</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2001</year><volume>413</volume><fpage>203</fpage><lpage>210</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11557989</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35093019</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B48"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scholz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Woolf</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Can we conquer pain?</article-title><source>Nat Neurosci</source><year>2002</year><volume>5 Suppl</volume><fpage>1062</fpage><lpage>1067</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12403987</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn942</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B49"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caterina</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosen</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Tominaga</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Brake</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Julius</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A capsaicin-receptor homologue with a high threshold for noxious heat</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1999</year><volume>398</volume><fpage>436</fpage><lpage>441</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10201375</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/18906</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B50"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differences in sensitivity of vanilloid receptor 1 transfected to human embryonic kidney cells and capsaicin-activated channels in cultured rat dorsal root ganglion neurons to capsaicin receptor agonists</article-title><source>Neurosci Lett</source><year>2001</year><volume>299</volume><fpage>135</fpage><lpage>139</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11166956</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0304-3940(00)01777-8</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>



