<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="letter"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Environ Health Perspect</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Environ. Health Perspect</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Environmental Health Perspectives</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0091-6765</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1552-9924</issn><publisher><publisher-name>National Institute of Environmental Health Sciences</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">16203221</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1281316</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ehp0113-a0652a</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Perspectives</subject><subj-group><subject>Correspondence</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Missing Link?: Alachlor and Semen Quality</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gustafson</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ehp0113-a0652a"/></contrib><aff id="af1-ehp0113-a0652a">Monsanto Company, St. Louis, Missouri, E-mail:
<email>david.i.gustafson@monsanto.com</email></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn><p>The author is employed by Monsanto, a manufacturer of alachlor.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>10</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><volume>113</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage seq="a">A652</fpage><lpage>A652</lpage><permissions><copyright-year>2005</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/" license-type="public-domain"><license-p>Publication of EHP lies in the public domain and is therefore without copyright. All text from EHP may be reprinted freely. Use of materials published in EHP should be acknowledged (for example, ?Reproduced with permission from Environmental Health Perspectives?); pertinent reference information should be provided for the article from which the material was reproduced. Articles from EHP, especially the News section, may contain photographs or illustrations copyrighted by other commercial organizations or individuals that may not be used without obtaining prior approval from the holder of the copyright. </license-p></license></permissions><related-article id="d35e63" related-article-type="commentary-article" xlink:href="12948887" ext-link-type="pubmed" vol="111" page="1478"/></article-meta></front><body><p>The article by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7-ehp0113-a0652a">Swan et al. (2003)</xref> suggested that alachlor exposure was linked to reduced sperm quality in fertile men; after publication of the article, Monsanto (St. Louis, MO) began a detailed examination of the issue because the findings were entirely unexpected and inconsistent with both our information and the extensive published literature on alachlor. Most surprisingly, alachlor mercapturate (AM) was reportedly found in the urine of 92% of study participants in Columbia, Missouri. Because this metabolite arises exclusively from exposure to the parent compound, few, if any, detects would be expected based on declining alachlor use (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5-ehp0113-a0652a">National Agricultural Statistics Service 2005</xref>) and our detailed understanding of its biological and environmental properties (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2-ehp0113-a0652a">Feng et al. 1994</xref>). Also, extensive water monitoring studies submitted to the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) have shown that parent alachlor occurs very infrequently in both potable wells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4-ehp0113-a0652a">Holden et al. 1992</xref>) and drinking water from surface water sources (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3-ehp0113-a0652a">Hackett et al. 2005</xref>), thereby calling into question the plausibility of such widespread exposure.</p><p>We met with Swan and colleagues at the University of Missouri in Columbia (UMC), and with the personnel at the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) who conducted the analyses, to discuss our surprise at the findings. Our concern about the reported frequent detections of alachlor in urine was heightened when we learned that the liquid chromatography/mass spectrometry&#x02013;mass spectrometry method employed by the CDC (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6-ehp0113-a0652a">Olsson et al. 2004</xref>) included no confirmatory ions, a standard technique for avoiding false positives in the analysis of urine (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1-ehp0113-a0652a">Department of Health and Human Services 1998</xref>). An 18-month collaboration ensued, which included numerous discussions and a round-robin study conducted between Monsanto and the CDC, with involvement by UMC researchers, to assess the performance and transferability of the methods used by each laboratory.</p><p>After successful completion of the round-robin study, several frozen urine samples retained from the original study were sent to Monsanto. In results that we intend to submit for publication, we found no detectable level of AM (limit of detection &#x0003c; 0.10 ppb) in samples that the CDC reported to contain up to 3 ppb (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7-ehp0113-a0652a">Swan et al. 2003</xref>). Sample degradation does not explain this difference, because we have data demonstrating AM stability under such conditions. Our analyses followed Good Laboratory Practice standards [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8-ehp0113-a0652a">U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) 1989</xref>] and included confirmatory ions. We also analyzed urine samples of 52 volunteers from agricultural areas across North America, none of which actually contained detectable AM, but 11 of which showed false positives when confirmatory ions were not used.</p><p>The CDC has now modified its method to include confirmatory ions for alachlor. We are confident that little or no AM would have been detected had they included confirmatory ions in the original analysis. The CDC previously declined Monsanto's request that they analyze the original samples using a modified method with confirmatory ions. However, after receiving an earlier version of this letter, the CDC quickly performed new analyses of 14 retained frozen samples and informed us that analysis with confirmatory ions validated their original findings. Unfortunately, the CDC has not provided us with sufficient data to confirm the validity of the new method and results. Monsanto continues to believe the detections are spurious. From our perspective, the only possible resolution of the matter at this time would be for the retained samples to be sent to an independent third-party laboratory for confirmatory analysis.</p><p>We understand Swan et al. are now having urine samples from other similar agricultural areas analyzed using a confirmatory method, and that AM is no longer being routinely detected. This would affirm that alachlor exposure is rare and the alleged link to semen quality is implausible. It would be very informative to identify the apparent interferent using high-resolution mass spectrometry methodology, but our collaboration has clearly shown that it was not AM. The evidence presented by our analyses of the samples provided by Swan, supported by our successful performance in the round-robin analysis of fortified samples, demonstrates that the reported detections of alachlor were most likely attributable to an interferent. The data refute any link between alachlor exposure and reduced sperm quality in fertile men.</p></body><back><fn-group><fn><p>Editor&#x02019;s note: Swan et al. chose not to respond because the criticism was aimed at the CDC; see Barr&#x02019;s response below.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="b1-ehp0113-a0652a"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>Department of Health and Human Services</collab><year>1998</year><article-title>Federal workplace drug testing programs; mandatory guidelines</article-title><source>Fed Reg</source><volume>63</volume><fpage>63483</fpage><lpage>63484</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b2-ehp0113-a0652a"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>PCC</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharp</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Horton</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><year>1994</year><article-title>Quantitation of alachlor residues in monkey urine by ELISA</article-title><source>J Agric Food Chem</source><volume>42</volume><fpage>316</fpage><lpage>319</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b3-ehp0113-a0652a"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Hackett</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Gustafson</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name><name><surname>Moran</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hendley</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>van Wesenbeeck</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Simmons</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>The Acetochlor Registration Partnership Surface Water Monitoring Program for four corn herbicides</article-title><source>J Environ Qual</source><volume>34</volume><fpage>877</fpage><lpage>889</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15843651</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b4-ehp0113-a0652a"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Holden</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitmore</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pratt</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Liddle</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1992</year><article-title>Results of the National Alachlor Well Water Survey</article-title><source>Environ Sci Technol</source><volume>26</volume><fpage>935</fpage><lpage>943</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b5-ehp0113-a0652a"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>National Agricultural Statistics Service</collab> 2005. NASS Database: Agricultural Chemical Statistics Search&#x02014;By Year. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pestmanagement.info/nass/app_statcs1_year.cfm">http://www.pestmanagement.info/nass/app_statcs1_year.cfm</ext-link> [accessed 5 April 2005].</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b6-ehp0113-a0652a"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Olsson</surname><given-names>AO</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name><surname>Romanoff</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Udunka</surname><given-names>SO</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>A liquid chromatography-tandem mass spectrometry multiresidue method for quantification of specific metabolites of organophosphorous pesticides, synthetic pyrethroids, selected herbicides, and DEET in human urine</article-title><source>Anal Chem</source><volume>76</volume><fpage>2453</fpage><lpage>2461</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15117183</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b7-ehp0113-a0652a"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Swan</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kruse</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Barr</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Drobnis</surname><given-names>EZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Redmon</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Semen quality in relation to biomarkers of pesticide exposure</article-title><source>Environ Health Perspect</source><volume>111</volume><fpage>1478</fpage><lpage>1484</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12948887</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b8-ehp0113-a0652a"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>U.S. EPA (U.S. Environmental Protection Agency)</collab><year>1989</year><article-title>Good laboratory practices</article-title><source>Fed Reg</source><volume>54</volume><fpage>34052</fpage><lpage>34074</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
