<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Infect Dis</journal-id><journal-title>BMC Infectious Diseases</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2334</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">16001978</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1183208</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1471-2334-5-56</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2334-5-56</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Seroprevalence of hepatitis A infection in a low endemicity country: a systematic review</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" equal-contrib="yes" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pham</surname><given-names>Ba'</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>ba.z.pham@gsk.com</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" equal-contrib="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Duval</surname><given-names>Bernard</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>bernard.duval@ssss.gouv.qc.ca</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" equal-contrib="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>De Serres</surname><given-names>Gaston</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>gaston.deserres@ssss.gouv.qc.ca</email></contrib><contrib id="A4" equal-contrib="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gilca</surname><given-names>Vladimir</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I4">4</xref><email>vladimir.gilca@ssss.gouv.qc.ca</email></contrib><contrib id="A5" equal-contrib="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tricco</surname><given-names>Andrea C</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>andrea.tricco@utoronto.ca</email></contrib><contrib id="A6" equal-contrib="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ochnio</surname><given-names>Jan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I5">5</xref><email>jochnio@interchange.ubc.ca</email></contrib><contrib id="A7" equal-contrib="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Scheifele</surname><given-names>David W</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I5">5</xref><email>dscheifele@cw.bc.ca</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>BioMedical Data Sciences, GlaxoSmithKline, Ontario, Canada</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Chalmers Research Group, Children's Hospital of Eastern Ontario Research Institute, Ontario, Canada</aff><aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Centre De Recherche du CHUQ, Institut Nationale Sante Publique du Quebec, Quebec, Canada</aff><aff id="I4"><label>4</label>Centre de Recherche du CHUQ, Quebec, Canada</aff><aff id="I5"><label>5</label>Vaccine Evaluation Centre, University of British Columbia, British Columbia, Canada</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2005</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>7</day><month>7</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><fpage>56</fpage><lpage>56</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2334/5/56"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>5</month><year>2005</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>7</day><month>7</month><year>2005</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2005 Pham et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2005</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Pham et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>
               Pham
               Ba'
               
               
               ba.z.pham@gsk.com
            </dc:author><dc:title>
            Seroprevalence of hepatitis A infection in a low endemicity country: a systematic review
         </dc:title><dc:date>2005</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>BMC Infectious Diseases 5(1): 56-. (2005)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1471-2334(2005)5:1&#x0003c;56&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1471-2334</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>In Canada &#x02013; a low endemicity country, vaccines for hepatitis A virus (HAV) are currently recommended to individuals at increased risk for infection or its complications. Applying these recommendations is difficult because the epidemiology of HAV infection is poorly defined, complex, and changing. This systematic review aimed to 1) estimate age-specific prevalence of HAV antibody in Canada and 2) evaluate infection-associated risk factors.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><p>MEDLINE (1966&#x02013;2005) and EMBASE (1980&#x02013;2005) were searched to identify relevant studies for the systematic review. Archives for the Canada Diseases Weekly Report (1975&#x02013;1991) and Canada Communicable Disease Report (1992&#x02013;2005) were searched for relevant public health reports. Data were abstracted for study and participants' characteristics, age-specific prevalence, and risk factors.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>A total of 36 reports describing 34 unique studies were included.</p><p>The seroprevalence in Canadian-born children was approximately 1% in ages 8&#x02013;13, 1&#x02013;6% in 20&#x02013;24, 10% in 25&#x02013;29, 17% in 30&#x02013;39, and increased subsequently. In age groups below 20 and 20&#x02013;29, age-specific seroprevalence generally remained constant for studies conducted across geographic areas and over time.</p><p>Compared to Canadian-born individuals, subjects born outside Canada were approximately 6 times more likely to be seropositive (relative risk: 5.7 [95% CI 3.6, 9.0]). Travel to high risk areas in individuals aged 20&#x02013;39 was associated with a significant increase in anti-HAV seropositivity (RR 2.8 [1.4, 5.5]). Compared to heterosexuals, men having sex with men were only at a marginally higher risk (adjusted odds ratio 2.4 [0.9, 6.1]). High risk for seropositivity was also observed for Canadian First Nations and Inuit populations.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Results from the current systematic review show that in this low endemicity country, disease acquisition occurs in adulthood rather than childhood. The burden of disease is high; approximately 1 in 10 Canadians had been infected by ages 24&#x02013;29. The increase in prevalence in young adults coincides with disease importation and increasing frequency of risk factors, most likely behavioral-related ones.</p><p>Gaps in seroprevalence data were identified rendering the application of current immunization recommendations difficult. A nationwide prevalence survey for all Canadians is needed. This is essential to quantify the effectiveness of current recommendations and conduct cost-effectiveness evaluations of alternative immunization programs, if necessary.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Hepatitis A virus (HAV) is prominent in many areas of the world [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. In North America, infection rates have declined with better hygiene practice and public sanitation but remain heterogeneous across geographic and socioeconomic strata [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. Further decline is possible with HAV vaccines which provide consistent, long-lasting protection and have been available since the mid-1990s [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. In the United States, universal vaccination of children and youth has been in place for about 6 years in high endemicity areas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>], leading to historically low rates nationally in recent years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. In Canada, the current national immunization guide recommends HAV vaccines for individuals at increased risk of infection or its complications. The guide also states that a universal immunization program should be considered, but further discussion is needed nationally [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>].</p><p>Applying the Canadian recommendations is difficult because the epidemiology of HAV infection in Canada is poorly defined, complex, and changing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. Reported rates differ substantially by province, gender, and age [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. The rates show repeated peaks and troughs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>] and the last peak occurred in mid-1990 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. It was during the subsequent period of decline that vaccines were used as a tool to enhance HAV control [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>].</p><p>Evaluating the impact of the current recommendations is also difficult. Data are needed to distinguish between a cyclical decline and a further decline associated with the recommendations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. Such assessment is important to inform future immunization policies. A combination of timely case-notification data, prevalence data, and risk factor data is required for both the application and evaluation of the recommendations.</p><p>Case-notification data is of limited use due to under-detection of sub-clinical infection and under-reporting of confirmed cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. A useful means that circumvent these limitations is to measure the prevalence of HAV antibody [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. Following an acute infection, antibody to HAV develops in virtually every instance, remaining detectable for decades, and providing a reliable marker of past infection. In the United States, countrywide seroprevalence surveys and sentinel surveillance have been conducted to provide insight into HA epidemiology, and to rationalize and evaluate immunization programs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. In Canada, similar surveys exist but are limited in scope and comprehensiveness [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. Consequently, risk factor data are also limited and fragmented [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. The current systematic review aimed to 1) estimate age-specific prevalence of hepatitis A antibody in Canada and 2) evaluate infection-associated risk factors.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><p>MEDLINE (Jan. 1966 &#x02013; Mar. 2005) and EMBASE (Jan.1980 &#x02013; Mar. 2005) were searched to identify citations of potentially relevant studies for the systematic review (MeSH terms: "hepatitis" exploded AND "Canada" exploded). A study report was included if it contained prevalence data of HAV-antibody (detected through sera or saliva samples, hereafter referred to as seroprevalence) for a Canadian population. Reasons for exclusion were categorized and reported. Citations were screened independently by two reviewers. Full-text study reports from citations deemed relevant by one reviewer were obtained. Archives for the Canada Diseases Weekly Report (Jan. 1975 &#x02013; Dec. 1991, the last year of reporting) and Canada Communicable Disease Report (Jan. 1992 &#x02013; Mar. 2005) were also searched for potentially relevant public health reports [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>]. Two reviewers independently reviewed both published and public health reports. Discrepancies were resolved through discussion. Back referencing and author searches of all included studies were conducted. Other potentially relevant reports were obtained by contacting HA experts and related public health units.</p><p>From the included reports, data were independently abstracted for study and participants' characteristics. Age-specific prevalence of HAV antibody data were extracted for Canadian-born participants, all Canadians including individuals born outside the country, and participants with known risk factors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. Seroprevalence estimates and 95% confidence intervals (CI) were derived assuming a binomial distribution for the number of seropositive individuals from the total numbers of tested individuals. Participants who reported receiving the HA vaccine were excluded from the prevalence estimates as they were likely to have vaccine-induced antibody.</p><p>If available, adjusted odds ratios (AOR) for seropositivity of both demographics and risk factors were extracted, together with the baseline risk of HAV seropositivity (i.e., population, location and timing of the survey). When the AOR of a variable was not reported, HAV antibody data stratified by the variable were obtained to derive the unadjusted relative risk for seropositivity (URR). Relative risk was used as it is a better risk estimate than the odds-ratio in the range of seroprevalence observed in this systematic review [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>]. If appropriate, a random effects model was used to combine URRs across studies, together with an assessment for heterogeneity (i.e., chi-squared test).</p><p>Information related to the risk of seropositivity was summarized for the following risk categories [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]: 1) travelers to high endemicity areas; 2) groups with high risk activities such as men who have sex with men (MSM), illicit drug users, and street people; 3) First Nations and Inuit populations; and 4) others (e.g., individuals with chronic hepatitis, household contacts, infected food handlers, etc.).</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>Literature search</title><p>A total of 36 reports describing 34 unique studies were included in the systematic review (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">55</xref>]. These were obtained from screening 413 potentially relevant citations and reviewing 66 full-text study reports and 25 public health reports (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). Common reasons for exclusion at the screening stage included studies of hepatitis B virus (n = 95), hepatitis C virus (n = 64), commentaries (n = 24), and others (n = 121; Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). Common reasons for exclusion at the full-text review stage included general review of HAV (n = 9), no seroprevalence data (n = 17), and other viral hepatitis (n = 16; Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Study and participant characteristics</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="left"><bold>Study</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>Study Design</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>Study Year</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>n</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>Population</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>Location</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>Age in years</bold></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><bold>PUBLISHED LITERATURE</bold></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="left"><bold>Mean &#x000b1; SD or (range)</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="7"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Ochnio 2005* [22]</td><td align="left">P</td><td align="left">2000&#x02013;1</td><td align="left">811</td><td align="left">Grade 9 students</td><td align="left">British Columbia</td><td align="left">(14&#x02013;15)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Muecke 2004* [23]</td><td align="left">CC</td><td align="left">2001</td><td align="left">492</td><td align="left">Day-care educators</td><td align="left">Montreal</td><td align="left">37</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Minuk 2003 [24]</td><td align="left">P</td><td align="left">1999</td><td align="left">315</td><td align="left">First Nations</td><td align="left">Manitoba</td><td align="left">34 &#x000b1; 15</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Ochnio 2001 [25]</td><td align="left">P</td><td align="left">1998</td><td align="left">494</td><td align="left">Street youth, IDU, MSM</td><td align="left">Vancouver</td><td align="left">19, 35, 34</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Smieja 2001 [26]</td><td align="left">CC</td><td align="left">1997&#x02013;8</td><td align="left">179</td><td align="left">IHD patients</td><td align="left">Hamilton</td><td align="left">61 (38&#x02013;81)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Kiefer 2000 [27]</td><td align="left">R</td><td align="left">1997</td><td align="left">343</td><td align="left">Hepatitis C patients</td><td align="left">Edmonton</td><td align="left">40 (0&#x02013;95)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Allard 2001 [28]</td><td align="left">P</td><td align="left">1995&#x02013;97</td><td align="left">353</td><td align="left">Gay men</td><td align="left">Montreal</td><td align="left">37</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Moses 2002 [29]</td><td align="left">P</td><td align="left">1995&#x02013;6</td><td align="left">533</td><td align="left">Street people</td><td align="left">Winnipeg</td><td align="left">26 (11&#x02013;65)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Roy 2002 [30]</td><td align="left">R</td><td align="left">1995&#x02013;6</td><td align="left">427</td><td align="left">Street youth</td><td align="left">Montreal</td><td align="left">(14&#x02013;25)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Ochnio 1997 [31]</td><td align="left">P</td><td align="left">1995&#x02013;6</td><td align="left">224</td><td align="left">Grade 6 students</td><td align="left">Vancouver</td><td align="left">(10&#x02013;12)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">De Serres 1997 [32]</td><td align="left">P</td><td align="left">1995</td><td align="left">85</td><td align="left">Sewer workers</td><td align="left">Quebec</td><td align="left">36 &#x000b1; 7</td></tr><tr><td align="left">De Serres 1995 [33]</td><td align="left">CC</td><td align="left">1995</td><td align="left">228</td><td align="left">Sewer workers</td><td align="left">Quebec</td><td align="left">41 (28&#x02013;64)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Smieja 2003 [34]</td><td align="left">R</td><td align="left">1993&#x02013;5</td><td align="left">3127</td><td align="left">CV or high risk diabetes</td><td align="left">Canada</td><td align="left">65</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Payment 1991 [18]</td><td align="left">P</td><td align="left">1988&#x02013;9</td><td align="left">617</td><td align="left">French-Canadian</td><td align="left">Montreal</td><td align="left">(9&#x02013;79)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Embil 1989 [35]</td><td align="left">P</td><td align="left">1981&#x02013;3</td><td align="left">2036<break/>1922</td><td align="left">1/CF recruits<break/>2/CF males</td><td align="left">Nova Scotia, Quebec, Posted abroad</td><td align="left">1/(15&#x02013;25)<break/>2/26 (17&#x02013;53)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Nicolle 1986 [36], Minuk 1985 [37]</td><td align="left">P</td><td align="left">1982</td><td align="left">172</td><td align="left">Chesterfield Inlet</td><td align="left">Northwest Territories</td><td align="left">0 &#x02013; 78</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Crewe 1983 [38]</td><td align="left">P</td><td align="left">1981&#x02013;2</td><td align="left">304</td><td align="left">Children attending outpatient clinic</td><td align="left">Halifax</td><td align="left">(0.5&#x02013;16)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Minuk 1982 [39]<break/>Minuk 1982 [40]</td><td align="left">P</td><td align="left">1980</td><td align="left">720</td><td align="left">Inuit</td><td align="left">Northwest Territories</td><td align="left">(0.3&#x02013;86)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">McFarlane 1980 [41]</td><td align="left">P, R</td><td align="left">1980</td><td align="left">243<break/>152<break/>293 &#x00026; 282</td><td align="left">1/STD clinic patients<break/>2/Student nurses<break/>3/2 groups of blood donors</td><td align="left">Nova Scotia</td><td align="left">1/(16&#x02013;26)<break/>2/(18&#x02013;24)<break/>3/(16&#x02013;26) &#x00026; (51&#x02013;65)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Buchner 1980 [42]</td><td align="left">R</td><td align="left">1980</td><td align="left">5097</td><td align="left">Blood donors</td><td align="left">Toronto</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;21, &#x0003e;60</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Richer 1982 [55]</td><td align="left">R</td><td align="left">1970&#x02013;79</td><td align="left">447</td><td align="left">Samples of acute viral hepatitis</td><td align="left">Montreal</td><td align="left">Not reported</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Minuk 1994 [43]</td><td align="left">P</td><td align="left">1974&#x02013;8</td><td align="left">42</td><td align="left">Household transmission</td><td align="left">Winnipeg</td><td align="left">27 &#x000b1; 12</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Minuk 2003 [44]</td><td align="left">SR</td><td align="left">1980&#x02013;2000</td><td align="left">1706</td><td align="left">Inuit and First Nations</td><td align="left">Various locations</td><td align="left">0&#x02013;60+</td></tr><tr><td align="left">McFarlane 1982 [45]</td><td align="left">P</td><td align="left">NR</td><td align="left">154</td><td align="left">Institutions</td><td align="left">Nova Scotia</td><td align="left">(13&#x02013;28)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">McFarlane 1981 [46]</td><td align="left">P</td><td align="left">NR</td><td align="left">130</td><td align="left">Patients with hematological malignancy</td><td align="left">Nova Scotia</td><td align="left">(4&#x02013;76)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>GREY LITERATURE</bold></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="7"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Duval 2005* [48]</td><td align="left">P</td><td align="left">2003</td><td align="left">1057</td><td align="left">Canadian aged 8&#x02013;13</td><td align="left">Canada</td><td align="left">(8&#x02013;13)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Wu 2005 [47]</td><td align="left">R</td><td align="left">1992&#x02013;9</td><td align="left">NR</td><td align="left">Subjects tested for HAV infection</td><td align="left">Manitoba</td><td align="left">Not reported</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Ochnio 2004 [49]</td><td align="left">P</td><td align="left">2003</td><td align="left">585</td><td align="left">Young adults</td><td align="left">Vancouver</td><td align="left">(20&#x02013;39)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Cook 2000 [19]</td><td align="left">R</td><td align="left">2000</td><td align="left">1206</td><td align="left">Women of child-bearing age</td><td align="left">British Columbia</td><td align="left">(15&#x02013;44)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Harb 2000 [50]</td><td align="left">P</td><td align="left">1999</td><td align="left">172</td><td align="left">First Nations</td><td align="left">British Columbia</td><td align="left">(0&#x02013;40+)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Levy 2001 [51]</td><td align="left">P</td><td align="left">1997</td><td align="left">1000</td><td align="left">University students</td><td align="left">Toronto</td><td align="left">25 &#x000b1; 5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Ford-Jones 1995 [52]</td><td align="left">P</td><td align="left">1993</td><td align="left">122</td><td align="left">Day-care providers</td><td align="left">Toronto</td><td align="left">Not reported</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Ochnio 1995 [53]</td><td align="left">P</td><td align="left">1994&#x02013;5</td><td align="left">1019</td><td align="left">Clients to travel clinic</td><td align="left">Vancouver</td><td align="left">(2&#x02013;69+)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Kocuipchyk 1995 [54]</td><td align="left">P</td><td align="left">1991&#x02013;2</td><td align="left">505</td><td align="left">Individuals attending travel clinic</td><td align="left">Edmonton</td><td align="left">(16&#x02013;60+)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><bold>Notes</bold>:*Study reported seroprevalence data for individuals with or without HAV vaccination.</p><p><bold>Abbreviations: </bold>Study design: P prospective data acquisition, R retrospective data acquisition, CC case control, SR systematic review. Population: IDU injection drug users, MSM men who have sex with men, IHD ischemic heart disease, CV cardiovascular, CF Canadian Forces, STD sexually transmitted disease.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Results of the literature search.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2334-5-56-1"/></fig><p>Overall, 74% (n = 25) of the included studies were reported in peer-reviewed journals while 26% (n = 9) were grey literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>], including 9% (n = 3) public health reports, 14% (n = 5) abstracts, and 3% (n = 1) unpublished study (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). HAV antibody was detected using serum samples in 28 studies and saliva samples in 6. The median sample size was 427 and 793 for the published and grey literature studies, respectively. Only 21% (7/34) of all studies reported prevalence among Canadian-born participants and 29% (10/34) reported prevalence data of all participants including foreign-born individuals. The majority of these studies (27/34) reported prevalence data of participants with known risk factors.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Study characteristics</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td></td><td align="left"><bold>Published Literature (n = 25)</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>Grey Literature (n = 9)</bold></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td></td><td align="left"><bold>Peer-reviewed study report (n = 25)</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>Public health report (n = 3)</bold><break/><bold>Abstract (n = 5)</bold><break/><bold>Unpublished report (n = 1)</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="3"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Study Design</bold></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Case-control</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Prospective (P) data acquisition</td><td align="left">16</td><td align="left">7</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Retrospective (R) data acquisition</td><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;P &#x00026; R data acquisition</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Systematic review</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Sample Size</bold></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x0003e;1000</td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;&#x02003;100 &#x02013; 1000</td><td align="left">19</td><td align="left">6</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x0003c;100</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Median [1<sup>st</sup>, 3<sup>rd </sup>Quartile]</td><td align="left">427 [224, 720]</td><td align="left">793 [422, 1029]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Mean (Min, Max)</td><td align="left">877 (42, 5097)</td><td align="left">708 (122, 1206)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Timing of data collection</bold></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;2000 &#x02013; 2004</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;1990 &#x02013; 1999</td><td align="left">12</td><td align="left">6</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;1980 &#x02013; 1989</td><td align="left">7</td><td align="left">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;1970 &#x02013; 1979</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Not reported</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">0</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Populations with prevalence data</bold></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Canadian born subjects</td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;All Canadians&#x000b6;</td><td align="left">6</td><td align="left">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Participants with known risk factors</td><td align="left">21</td><td align="left">7</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Seropositivity test</bold></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Serum samples</td><td align="left">22</td><td align="left">6</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Saliva samples</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">3</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><bold>Notes</bold>: &#x000b6;including subjects born outside of Canada</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Age-specific seroprevalence</title><p>The seroprevalence in Canadian-born children aged 8&#x02013;13 was 1% [95% CI: 0.5&#x02013;2%] according to a national survey conducted in 2003 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>]. The seroprevalence was 1&#x02013;6% in ages 20&#x02013;24, approximately 10% in 25&#x02013;29, 17% in 30&#x02013;39, and increased subsequently (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). In age groups below 20 and 20&#x02013;29, age-specific seroprevalence generally remained constant for studies conducted across geographic areas in 1980, 1988, 1997, and 2003. This remained so despite differences in study methodology.</p><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Seropositivity rate (95% confidence interval) among Canadian-born study participants.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2334-5-56-2"/></fig><p>There was no association between seropositivity and gender based on 9 population comparisons from 5 studies (n = 4158, URR: 1.0 [95% CI: 0.9, 1.1]) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">54</xref>], which was consistent with results of 3 other studies reporting adjusted risk estimates (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>]. Two studies in the early 1980's suggested that individuals living in urban areas were 30% more likely to have HAV antibody compared to those in rural areas (n = 647, URR: 1.3 [1.2, 1.5]) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>].</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Assessment of risk factors</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="left"><bold>Risk factor</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>n</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>Risk Measure</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>Risk Estimate (95% CI)</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>Population, Location, Timing of Data Acquisition</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>Age in years</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>Study</bold></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><bold>DEMOGRAPHICS</bold></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="left"><bold>Mean &#x000b1; SD or (range)</bold></td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="7"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Female versus Male</td><td align="left">1003</td><td align="left">AOR</td><td align="left">2.2 (0.8, 6.25)</td><td align="left">School-aged children, Canada, 2003</td><td align="left">(8&#x02013;13)</td><td align="left">[48]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Female versus Male</td><td align="left">3128</td><td align="left">AOR</td><td align="left">0.8 (0.6, 0.96)</td><td align="left">CV or high risk diabetes, Canada, 1993&#x02013;5</td><td align="left">65</td><td align="left">[34]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Female versus Male</td><td align="left">494</td><td align="left">AOR</td><td align="left">1.3 (0.8, 2.3)</td><td align="left">SY, MSM, IDU, Vancouver, 1998</td><td align="left">32 &#x000b1; 11</td><td align="left">[25]</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Female versus Male</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>4158</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>URR</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>1.0 (0.9. 1.1) [p = 0.30]*</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>9 population comparisons from 5 studies</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>(8&#x02013;65+)</bold></td><td align="left">[31,35,41,49,54]</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Urban versus Rural</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>647</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>URR</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>1.3 (1.2, 1.5) [p = 0.59]*</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>3 population comparisons from 2 studies</bold></td><td align="left">(16&#x02013;76)</td><td align="left">[41,46]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Born in high risk country versus born in Canada</td><td align="left">494</td><td align="left">AOR</td><td align="left">2.9 (1.1, 7.6)</td><td align="left">SY, MSM, IDU, Vancouver, 1998</td><td align="left">32 &#x000b1; 11</td><td align="left">[25]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Born in endemic country versus born in Canada</td><td align="left">1003</td><td align="left">AOR</td><td align="left">22.3 (6.6, 75.0)</td><td align="left">School-aged children, Canada, 2003</td><td align="left">(8&#x02013;13)</td><td align="left">[48]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Foreign-born versus Canadian-born</td><td align="left">353</td><td align="left">AOR</td><td align="left">6.2 (2.6, 15.0)</td><td align="left">Gay men, Montreal, 1995&#x02013;97</td><td align="left">36</td><td align="left">[28]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Born in a high-income country versus moderate to low&#x02020;</td><td align="left">492</td><td align="left">AOR</td><td align="left">20.8 (9.4, 46.0)</td><td align="left">Day-care educators, Montreal, 2001</td><td align="left">37</td><td align="left">[23]</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Foreign-born versus Canadian-born</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>3008</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>URR</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>5.7 (3.6, 9.0) [p &#x0003c; 0.01]*</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>5 population comparisons from 5 studies</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>(2&#x02013;69+)</bold></td><td align="left">[30,31,49,51,53]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>TRAVEL TO HIGH RISK AREA</bold></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="7"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Travel to high risk area versus otherwise</td><td align="left">1003</td><td align="left">AOR</td><td align="left">1.4 (0.4, 4.8)</td><td align="left">School-aged children, Canada, 2003</td><td align="left">(8&#x02013;13)</td><td align="left">[48]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Travel to high risk areas versus otherwise</td><td align="left">407</td><td align="left">URR</td><td align="left">2.8 (1.4, 5.5)</td><td align="left">Canadian-born adults, Vancouver, 2003</td><td align="left">(20&#x02013;39)</td><td align="left">[49]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Ever travelled to a developing country&#x02021;</td><td align="left">492</td><td align="left">AOR</td><td align="left">2.4 (1.3, 4.2)</td><td align="left">Day-care educators, Montreal, 2001</td><td align="left">37</td><td align="left">[23]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>HIGH RISK ACTIVITIES</bold></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="7"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left">MSM versus heterosexuals</td><td align="left">494</td><td align="left">AOR</td><td align="left">2.4 (0.9, 6.1)</td><td align="left">SY, MSM, IDU, Vancouver, 1998</td><td align="left">(25&#x02013;34)</td><td align="left">[25]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Sexual partners with VH history versus otherwise</td><td align="left">420</td><td align="left">AOR</td><td align="left">13.8 (4.2, 45.2)</td><td align="left">Street youths, Montreal, 1995&#x02013;6</td><td align="left">(14&#x02013;25)</td><td align="left">[30]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Insertive anal penetration versus otherwise</td><td align="left">420</td><td align="left">AOR</td><td align="left">5.1 (1.6, 16.7)</td><td align="left">Street youths, Montreal, 1995&#x02013;6</td><td align="left">(14&#x02013;25)</td><td align="left">[30]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">History of STD versus no history</td><td align="left">500</td><td align="left">AOR</td><td align="left">2.0 (1.2, 3.3)</td><td align="left">Street people, Winnipeg, 1995&#x02013;6</td><td align="left">26 (11&#x02013;65)</td><td align="left">[29]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">History of IDU versus no history</td><td align="left">494</td><td align="left">AOR</td><td align="left">6.5 (1.6, 26.3)</td><td align="left">SY, MSM, IDU, Vancouver, 1998</td><td align="left">(25&#x02013;34)</td><td align="left">[25]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">History of IDU versus no history</td><td align="left">500</td><td align="left">AOR</td><td align="left">1.6 (0.99, 2.7)</td><td align="left">Street people, Winnipeg, 1995&#x02013;6</td><td align="left">26 (11&#x02013;65)</td><td align="left">[29]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>FIRST NATIONS AND INUIT</bold></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="7"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Native versus Non-native</td><td align="left">1003</td><td align="left">AOR</td><td align="left">5.2 (1.0, 26.0)</td><td align="left">School-aged children, Canada, 2003</td><td align="left">(8&#x02013;13)</td><td align="left">[48]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Aboriginal versus Non-aboriginal</td><td align="left">500</td><td align="left">AOR</td><td align="left">6.6 (3.8, 11.5)</td><td align="left">Street people, Winnipeg, 1995&#x02013;6</td><td align="left">26 (11&#x02013;65)</td><td align="left">[29]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Inuit versus white in NWT</td><td align="left">708</td><td align="left">URR</td><td align="left">4.5 (2.4, 8.5)</td><td align="left">Inuits, Baker Lake, NWT, 1980</td><td align="left">(0.3&#x02013;86)</td><td align="left">[39,40]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">4+ versus 1&#x02013;3 household occupants</td><td align="left">635</td><td align="left">URR</td><td align="left">1.1 (0.98, 1.3)</td><td align="left">Canadian Inuit, Baker Lake, 1980</td><td align="left">(0.3&#x02013;86)</td><td align="left">[39,40]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>OTHERS</bold></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="7"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Years working in day-care, 5-year groups&#x000a7;</td><td align="left">339</td><td align="left">AOR</td><td align="left">1.3 (1.0, 1.8)</td><td align="left">Canadian-born day-care educators, Montreal, 2001</td><td align="left">34</td><td align="left">[23]</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>History of daycare versus no history</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>1278</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>URR</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>1.2 [0.7, 2.2] [p = 0.30]*</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>2 population comparisons from 2 studies</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>8&#x02013;13</bold></td><td align="left">[31,48]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Sewer workers versus controls||</td><td align="left">228</td><td align="left">URR</td><td align="left">1.1 (0.8, 1.4)</td><td align="left">Sewer workers, Quebec City, 1993</td><td align="left">41 (28&#x02013;64)</td><td align="left">[33]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">3+ versus 0&#x02013;3 siblings</td><td align="left">502</td><td align="left">URR</td><td align="left">2.0 (1.7, 2.5)</td><td align="left">Travel clinic, Edmonton, 1991&#x02013;2</td><td align="left">(16&#x02013;60+)</td><td align="left">[54]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Current household income &#x0003c;20,000/yr&#x000b6;</td><td align="left">153</td><td align="left">AOR</td><td align="left">5.3 (1.2, 24.2)</td><td align="left">Foreign-born day-care educators, Montreal, 2001</td><td align="left">39.7</td><td align="left">[23]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Annual family income &#x0003c;30,000 vs &#x02265;30,000</td><td align="left">1057</td><td align="left">URR</td><td align="left">0.7 (0.3, 2.0)</td><td align="left">School-aged children, Canada, 2003</td><td align="left">(8&#x02013;13)</td><td align="left">[48]</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><bold>Abbreviations: </bold>AOR adjusted odds ratio. CV cardiovascular. SY street youth. MSM men who have sex with men. IDU injectable drug user. URR unadjusted relative risk. STD sexually transmitted disease. NWT North West Territory. G6 grade 6. yr year</p><p><bold>Notes</bold>: *Meta-analytical estimates (95% CI) [p-value from a test of homogeneity] from random-effects models. &#x02020; The day-care educator study included 492 participants, including 339 Canadian-born individuals and 153 foreign-born. The odds-ratio for "born in a high-income country versus moderate to low" was 20.8 (95% CI 9.4, 46.0) for all 492 participants, not reported for Canadian-born, and 4.6 (1.7, 12.2) for foreign-born. &#x02021; The odds-ratio for "ever traveled to a developing country" in the day-care educators study was 2.4 (1.3, 4.2) for all 492 participants, not significant for Canadian-born (estimated OR not available), and 8.1 (2.3, 29.0) for foreign-born. &#x000a7; The odds-ratio for "years working in day-care, 5-year groups" was not significant for all 492 participants (estimated OR not available), 1.3 (1.0, 1.8) for Canadian-born, and not significant (estimated OR not available) for foreign-born. || Control subjects were outpatients undergoing lipid testing,. &#x000b6; The odds-ratio for "current household income &#x0003c;20,000/yr" in the day-care educators study was not significant (estimated OR not available) for all 492 participants and Canadian-born and was 5.3 (1.2, 24.2) for foreign-born.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Compared to Canadian-born individuals, subjects born outside Canada were approximately 6 times more likely to be seropositive (n = 3008, URR: 5.7 [3.6, 9.0], Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">53</xref>], which most likely occurred in their birth country. However, the possibility that infection occurred in Canada could not be ruled out. Age-specific seroprevalence estimates including these individuals varied substantially and could only be used to infer the level of immunity in the population. For example, seroprevalence among all Canadians aged &#x0003c;20 ranged from 2&#x02013;16% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>] for which 3&#x02013;25% of the sampled populations were individuals born outside the country [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">53</xref>]. This contrasted the 1% seropositivity for Canadian-born participants reported above.</p></sec><sec><title>Risk factors</title><p>Travel-related data were available in 6 studies (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">53</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">54</xref>]. HAV antibody prevalence for Canadian-born individuals visiting a travel clinic was 2.3% in ages 20&#x02013;25 and 4.3% in ages 25&#x02013;28 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">53</xref>]. The prevalence of seropositivity in these individuals was comparable to that reported above for Canadian-born individuals. The risk related to travel among Canadian-born was also not significant in a study of day-care educators [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>]. Two population-based surveys reported travel-related risk [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>]. In one study, travel to high risk areas by Canadian-born individuals aged 20&#x02013;39 (approximately 12% of study participants) was associated with a significant increase in seropositivity (n = 407, URR: 2.8 [1.4, 5.5]) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>]. In a national survey of children aged 8&#x02013;13, the prevalence was 1.9% in Canadian-born non-vaccinated travelers and 1.3% in non-travelers; the association was again not significant (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>].</p><p>Two studies evaluated HAV infection among MSM in two different cities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>]. MSM participants on average had 3 sexual partners over the preceding 6 months, according to one study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>]. Also, 18% of these individuals were food handlers. Compared to heterosexuals, MSM were only at a marginally higher risk for seropositivity (n = 494, AOR 2.4 [0.9, 6.1]), according to the second study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. However, the study sample was highly heterogeneous and included MSM, injection drug users (IDU), and street youth.</p><p>Data on street-involved populations were available in three studies (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>]. Seropositivity was approximately 5% in street youth aged 14&#x02013;25 in Vancouver and Montreal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>]. In the Montreal study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>], the outbreak in MSM (n = 376 cases from December 1994 to February 1998 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>]) seemed to have little effect on the prevalence of anti-HAV among street youth, measured during the same period. Significant behavioral risk factors for seropositivity were reported for street-involved individuals. These included IDU, history of sexually-transmitted disease, and high HAV-risk sexual activities (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>).</p><p>Seroprevalence in Canadian First Nations and Inuit populations were reported in four studies and summarized in a systematic review [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>]. The prevalence ranged from 75&#x02013;95% and was approximately three times that of non-Aboriginal Canadians residing in the same communities across all ages [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>]. For example, Minuk and colleagues reported on a seroprevalence survey of 720 inhabitants of an Inuit community (n = 850). Approximately 27% of this community were aged 0&#x02013;9, 30% aged 10&#x02013;19, 32% aged 20&#x02013;49, and 11% aged 50 or above [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>].</p><p>Among Canadian-born day-care educators, there was a borderline significant association between risk of HAV positivity and years of employment (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>]. A history of daycare attendance among grade 6 students was not associated with seropositivity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>]. Also, the seropositivity was 1.3&#x02013;1.6 times higher in children aged 8&#x02013;13 who attended day-care, but no statistical difference was evident in all participants, non-vaccinated participants, or those without known risk factors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>].</p><p>Other potential risk factors were also examined. From a sample of 343 individuals who tested positive for hepatitis C, 30% of those aged 20&#x02013;29 were seropositive for HAV [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]. One prospective cohort followed 62 household contacts and 20 index cases over 6 months; the risk of infection was 52% among other susceptible household members [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>]. Working in a sewage plant was not associated with seropositivity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>The seroprevalence data consolidated in this systematic review had many limitations. Except for one national survey in ages 8&#x02013;13 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>], other studies were generally not representative of the general population. Substantial variation across studies was observed with respect to study population, timing, sample size, and location. Reporting of data was inconsistent with respect to age stratification and definition of risk factors. Some studies conducted after the introduction of the vaccine around 1997 did not take vaccine-induced HAV antibody into account. This was, however, rectified in more recent studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>]. For example, the seroprevalence in a national survey of children aged 8&#x02013;13 was 2.7% overall and 2.0% after the exclusion of self-reported vaccinees [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>]. The corresponding figures in a survey of young adults aged 20&#x02013;39 were 22% and 16%, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>]. Given these limitations, improvements in the reporting of future HAV prevalence studies are required. Most importantly, prevalence data should be stratified by participants' birthplace and account for vaccine-induced antibody.</p><p>Results from the current systematic review show that disease acquisition occurs in adulthood rather than childhood [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. In Canada, the increase in prevalence in young adults coincides with disease importation and increasing frequency of behavioral risk factors, such as risk activities among MSM and street-involved populations. Even in this low endemicity country, approximately 1 in 10 Canadians had been infected by ages 24&#x02013;29.</p><p>A low level of HAV immunity in Canada is evident from this systematic review. Over 90% of Canadian-born individuals aged 20&#x02013;29, and over 80% of those aged 30&#x02013;39 remained unprotected. Canadians born outside the country generally have a higher prevalence of HAV antibody, yet including these individuals did not significantly improve the percentage of protected Canadians. This low level of immunity and persistent risk of exposure to HAV suggest that outbreaks are possible in the future [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>]. For example, unprotected clients exposed to an infected food handler led to mass immunizations in the early 2000's (Toronto 2002 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>], n = 19,208; London 2002 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">57</xref>], n = 16,320; Vancouver 2002 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">58</xref>] n = 6,000).</p><p>Clarifications are required to better understand the epidemiology of HAV in Canada, especially the inter-relation between timely case-notification data, seroprevalence data, and risk factor data. In a study examining national case-notification data from 1990&#x02013;1999, estimated incidence of reported cases decreased while the average age of exposure and subsequent infection increased [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. Given the low seroprevalence in Canadian youth, the current results suggest that the average age of HA exposure is above 24 and is increasing. While infection in children is often sub-clinical or mild, infected adults often experience more severe symptoms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">59</xref>].</p><p>Results of the current systematic review are consistent with low HAV endemicity patterns in developed countries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60">60</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B62">62</xref>]. A substantial burden of infection was observed in young Canadians and this did not decrease among successive generations over the past 20 years. Similar observations were reported elsewhere [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">63</xref>]. In these low endemicity countries, outbreaks are common [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B64">64</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B65">65</xref>]. Sources of outbreaks that are common in these countries include infected food handlers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">57</xref>], contaminated food importation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B66">66</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B67">67</xref>], and unprotected immigrants who visit friends and relatives in their original countries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B68">68</xref>].</p><p>In order to apply the current immunization recommendations, substantial information pertaining to groups at increased risk of HA infection or its complications is required. Results from this systematic review suggest that the risk of HA infection in these target groups was not well documented. With the exception of a few population-based surveys [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>], most studies enrolled participants with known risk factors and failed to include a control group. In addition, some used residual sera obtained for other tests with virtually no risk factor data.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Results from the current systematic review show that in this low endemicity country, disease acquisition occurs in adulthood rather than childhood. The burden of disease is high; approximately 1 in 10 Canadians had been infected by ages 24&#x02013;29. The increase in prevalence in young adults coincides with disease importation and increasing frequency of risk factors, most likely behavioral-related ones.</p><p>Gaps in seroprevalence data were also identified in this systematic review, rendering the application of current recommendations difficult. A nationwide prevalence survey for all Canadians is needed. This is essential to quantify the effectiveness of current recommendations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>] and conduct cost-effectiveness evaluations of alternative immunization programs, if necessary [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B69">69</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Abbreviations</title><p>G6 students grade 6 students</p></sec><sec><title>Competing interests</title><p>Funding for this systematic review was provided by GlaxoSmithKline Canada. BP and ACT are employed by GlaxoSmithKline. BD, GDS, VG, JO, and DS have received research funding from GlaxoSmithKline.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>BP contributed to the development of the research question and methodology, project management, systematic review, data management and data analysis, derivation of charts and tables, and interpretation of the results. BD, GDS, DS contributed to the development of the research question and methodology, acquisition of unpublished data, and interpretation of the results. JO and VG contributed to the development of the research methodology, acquisition of unpublished data, derivation of charts and tables and interpretation of the results. ACT contributed to the development of the research methodology, project management, systematic review, derivation charts and tables and interpretation of the results. All of us contributed to the manuscript writing and approved the final version of the manuscript.</p></sec><sec><title>Pre-publication history</title><p>The pre-publication history for this paper can be accessed here:</p><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2334/5/56/prepub"/></p></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We would like to thank Perica Sever for her continued support. We would like to also thank Dr. Jun Wu for his guidance on how hepatitis A cases were reported as a notifiable disease in Canada. Additionally, we would also like to thank Richard Foty for compiling the data and Yang Liu for her technical assistance.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cuthbert</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hepatitis A: old and new</article-title><source>Clin Microbiol Rev</source><year>2001</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>38</fpage><lpage>58</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11148002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/CMR.14.1.38-58.2001</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gust</surname><given-names>ID</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epidemiological patterns of hepatitis A in different parts of the world</article-title><source>Vaccine</source><year>1992</year><volume>10 Suppl 1</volume><fpage>S56</fpage><lpage>S58</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1335660</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0264-410X(92)90544-T</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tapia-Conyer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><name><surname>Cavalcanti</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Urdaneta</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Rivera</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Manterola</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Potin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruttiman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hepatitis A in Latin America: a changing epidemiologic pattern</article-title><source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source><year>1999</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>825</fpage><lpage>829</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10586919</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><name><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name><surname>Alter</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Moyer</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Judson</surname><given-names>FN</given-names></name><name><surname>Mottram</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Fleenor</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryder</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Margolis</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The diverse patterns of hepatitis A epidemiology in the United States-implications for vaccination strategies</article-title><source>J Infect Dis</source><year>1998</year><volume>178</volume><fpage>1579</fpage><lpage>1584</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9815207</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/314518</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><article-title>Notifiable disease annual summary 1997</article-title><source>Can Commun Dis Rep</source><year>1999</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>119</fpage><lpage>121</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>British Columbia Center for Disease Control</collab></person-group><article-title>BC reportable communicable diseases, annual summary 1998</article-title><year>1999</year><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>25</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Furesz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheifele</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Palkonyay</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Safety and effectiveness of the new inactivated hepatitis A virus vaccine</article-title><source>CMAJ</source><year>1995</year><volume>152</volume><fpage>343</fpage><lpage>348</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7828098</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scheifele</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Ochnio</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hepatitis A vaccine: is it being used to best advantage?</article-title><source>CMAJ</source><year>2002</year><volume>167</volume><fpage>44</fpage><lpage>45</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12137079</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Practices</surname><given-names>ACI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevention of hepatitis A through active or passive immunization</article-title><source>MMWR Morb Mort Wkly Rep</source><year>1999</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>37</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Samandari</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantifying the impact of hepatitis A immunization in the United States, 1995-2001</article-title><source>Vaccine</source><year>2004</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>4342</fpage><lpage>4350</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15474727</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vaccine.2004.04.014</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Immunization</surname><given-names>NAC</given-names></name></person-group><source>Canadian Immunization Guide</source><year>2002</year><edition>6</edition><publisher-name>Ottawa, Canadian Medical Association</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Giulivi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Current hepatitis A status in Canada</article-title><source>Can J Infect Dis Med Microbiol</source><year>2001</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>341</fpage><lpage>344</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Population and Public Health Branch</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Notifiable disease incidence for years 1987-1999</article-title><year>2004</year></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scheifele</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hepatitis A vaccines: the growing case for universal immunisation of children</article-title><source>Expert Opin Pharmacother</source><year>2005</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>157</fpage><lpage>164</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15757414</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1517/14656566.6.2.157</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koff</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Seroepidemiology of hepatitis A in the United States</article-title><source>J Infect Dis</source><year>1995</year><volume>171 Suppl 1</volume><fpage>S19</fpage><lpage>S23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7876642</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hepatitis A virus infections in the United States: model-based estimates and implications for childhood immunization</article-title><source>Pediatrics</source><year>2002</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>839</fpage><lpage>845</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11986444</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.109.5.839</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>elSaadany</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gully</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Giulivi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hepatitis A, B, and C in Canada. Results from the National Sentinel Health Unit Surveillance System, 1993-1995</article-title><source>Can J Public Health</source><year>2002</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>435</fpage><lpage>438</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12448866</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Payment</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antibody Levels to Selected Enteric Viruses in a French-Canadian Population in the Province of Quebec</article-title><source>Immunol Infect Dis</source><year>1991</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>317</fpage><lpage>322</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilton</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>D</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Krajden</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of antibodies to hepatitis A virus in a cohort of women of child-bearing age</article-title><source>68th Canadian Association for Clinical Microbiology and Infectious Disease, Nov 5-8, 2000 - Ottawa</source><year>2000</year></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McAuley</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Pham</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Tugwell</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Moher</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Does the inclusion of grey literature influence estimates of intervention effectiveness reported in meta-analyses?</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2000</year><volume>356</volume><fpage>1228</fpage><lpage>1231</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11072941</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(00)02786-0</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deeks</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Issues in the selection of a summary statistic for meta-analysis of clinical trials with binary outcomes</article-title><source>Stat Med</source><year>2002</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>1575</fpage><lpage>1600</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12111921</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/sim.1188</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ochnio</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheifele</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Fyfe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bigham</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowering</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Martiquet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Talling</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The prevalence of hepatitis A in children in British Columbia.</article-title><source>Can J Infect Dis Med Microbiol</source><year>2005</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>175</fpage><lpage>179</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muecke</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Beliveau</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahme</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Soto</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Gyorkos</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hepatitis A seroprevalence and risk factors among day-care educators</article-title><source>Clin Invest Med</source><year>2004</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>259</fpage><lpage>264</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15559862</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Minuk</surname><given-names>GY</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Uhanova</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernstein</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Dawood</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Vardy</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Giulvi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Viral hepatitis in a Canadian First Nations community</article-title><source>Can J Gastroenterol</source><year>2003</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>593</fpage><lpage>596</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14571297</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ochnio</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Patrick</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Talling</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name><name><surname>Dobson</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Past infection with hepatitis A virus among Vancouver street youth, injection drug users and men who have sex with men: implications for vaccination programs</article-title><source>CMAJ</source><year>2001</year><volume>165</volume><fpage>293</fpage><lpage>297</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11517645</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smieja</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cronin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldsmith</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Yusuf</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahony</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Previous exposure to Chlamydia pneumoniae, Helicobacter pylori and other infections in Canadian patients with ischemic heart disease</article-title><source>Can J Cardiol</source><year>2001</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>270</fpage><lpage>276</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11264559</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kiefer</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Honish</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Predy</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Talbot</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The seroprevalence of hepatitis A and B in people testing positive for hepatitis C</article-title><source>CMAJ</source><year>2000</year><volume>162</volume><fpage>207</fpage><lpage>208</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10674054</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Allard</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Beauchemin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bedard</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Dion</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Tremblay</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Carsley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hepatitis A vaccination during an outbreak among gay men in Montreal, Canada, 1995-1997</article-title><source>J Epidemiol Community Health</source><year>2001</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>251</fpage><lpage>256</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11238580</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/jech.55.4.251</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moses</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mestery</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaita</surname><given-names>KDE</given-names></name><name><surname>Minuk</surname><given-names>GY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Viral hepatitis in a Canadian street-involved population</article-title><source>Can J Public Health</source><year>2002</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>128</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11963516</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Haley</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Leclerc</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Cedras</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bedard</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Allard</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Seroprevalence and risk factors for hepatitis A among Montreal street youth</article-title><source>Can J Public Health</source><year>2002</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>52</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11925701</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ochnio</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheifele</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hepatitis A virus infections in urban children--are preventive opportunities being missed?</article-title><source>J Infect Dis</source><year>1997</year><volume>176</volume><fpage>1610</fpage><lpage>1613</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9395375</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Serres</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Laliberte</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hepatitis A among workers from a waste water treatment plant during a small community outbreak</article-title><source>Occup Environ Med</source><year>1997</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>60</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9072036</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Serres</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Levesque</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Major</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Laliberte</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Boulianne</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Duval</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Need for vaccination of sewer workers against leptospirosis and hepatitis A</article-title><source>Occup Environ Med</source><year>1995</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>505</fpage><lpage>507</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7663634</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smieja</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gnarpe</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lonn</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Gnarpe</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Olsson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Dzavik</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>McQueen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yusuf</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multiple infections and subsequent cardiovascular events in the Heart Outcomes Prevention Evaluation (HOPE) Study</article-title><source>Circulation</source><year>2003</year><volume>107</volume><fpage>251</fpage><lpage>257</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12538424</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.CIR.0000044940.65226.1F</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Embil</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Manley</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hepatitis A: a serological study in the Canadian Armed Forces</article-title><source>Mil Med</source><year>1989</year><volume>154</volume><fpage>461</fpage><lpage>465</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2552354</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nicolle</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Minuk</surname><given-names>GY</given-names></name><name><surname>Postl</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Madden</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoofnagle</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cross-sectional seroepidemiologic study of the prevalence of cytomegalovirus and herpes simplex virus infection in a Canadian Inuit (Eskimo) community</article-title><source>Scand J Infect Dis</source><year>1986</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3008308</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Minuk</surname><given-names>GY</given-names></name><name><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Postl</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Waggoner</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicolle</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoofnagle</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The changing epidemiology of hepatitis B virus infection in the Canadian north</article-title><source>Am J Epidemiol</source><year>1985</year><volume>121</volume><fpage>598</fpage><lpage>604</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4014149</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crewe</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Embil</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Garner</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of antibodies to hepatitis A virus in Nova Scotia children</article-title><source>Can Med Assoc J</source><year>1983</year><volume>128</volume><fpage>1195</fpage><lpage>1197</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6301669</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B39"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Minuk</surname><given-names>GY</given-names></name><name><surname>Waggoner</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Jernigan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicolle</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Postl</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoofnagle</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of antibody to hepatitis A virus in a Canadian Inuit community</article-title><source>Can Med Assoc J</source><year>1982</year><volume>127</volume><fpage>850</fpage><lpage>852</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7139503</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B40"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Minuk</surname><given-names>GY</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicolle</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Postl</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Waggoner</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoofnagle</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hepatitis virus infection in an isolated Canadian Inuit (Eskimo) population</article-title><source>J Med Virol</source><year>1982</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>255</fpage><lpage>264</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7161596</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B41"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McFarlane</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Embil</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Manuel</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorelick</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of antibodies to hepatitis A antigen in patients attending a clinic for treatment of sexually transmitted diseases</article-title><source>Sex Transm Dis</source><year>1980</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>87</fpage><lpage>89</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6893088</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B42"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buchner</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><name><surname>Staszak</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Duravetz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hepatitis markers detected in a Canadian blood donor population</article-title><source>Acta Haematol Pol</source><year>1980</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6252746</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B43"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Minuk</surname><given-names>GY</given-names></name><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>LX</given-names></name><name><surname>Hannon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sekla</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The risks of transmission of acute hepatitis A and B virus infection in an urban centre</article-title><source>J Hepatol</source><year>1994</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>118</fpage><lpage>121</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7963411</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0168-8278(94)80147-9</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B44"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Minuk</surname><given-names>GY</given-names></name><name><surname>Uhanova</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Viral hepatitis in the Canadian Inuit and First Nations populations</article-title><source>Can J Gastroenterol</source><year>2003</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>707</fpage><lpage>712</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14679425</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B45"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McFarlane</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Embil</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antibody to hepatitis A virus in young inmates</article-title><source>J Infect Dis</source><year>1982</year><volume>146</volume><fpage>442</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7108284</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B46"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McFarlane</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Embil</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of antibodies to Hepatitis A antigen in sera from patients with haematological malignancies</article-title><source>J Med Virol</source><year>1981</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6271921</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B47"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaniewski</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dawood</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Smart</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Geodhuis</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Giulivi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Changes in the epidemiology of hepatitis A infection in Manitoba 1992-2003: Implications for vaccination strategies</article-title><source>Can J Infect Dis Med Microbiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>356 (Abstract P25)</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="B48"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duval</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>De Serres</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilca</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Ochnio</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheifele</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nationwide Canadian study of hepatitis A antibody prevalence among children eight to thirteen years old</article-title><source>Pediatr Infect Dis J</source><year>2005</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>514</fpage><lpage>519</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15933561</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/01.inf.0000164705.74498.86</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B49"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ochnio</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheifele</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Marion</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bigham</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hepatitis A virus (HAV) infections in young adults in British Columbia: feasibility of a novel mail-based approach to population sampling</article-title><source>Proceedings of the 7th Annual Conference on Vaccine Research Arlington, VA, USA</source><year>2004</year><volume>Abstract P4</volume></citation></ref><ref id="B50"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harb</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hepatitis A in the Northern Interior of British Columbia: An Outbreak Among Members of a First Nations Community</article-title><source>Can Commun Dis Rep</source><year>2000</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>157</fpage><lpage>161</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11057007</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B51"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Krajden</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hepatitis A virus seroprevalence in 1,000 university students in Toronto.</article-title><source>Can Commun Dis Rep</source><year>2001</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11416942</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B52"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>EL</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>I</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>M</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>M</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>R</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>N</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>R</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Seroprevalence of hepatitis A (HAV), hepatitis B (HBV), human parvovirus B19 (HPV B19) and toxoplasmosis (Toxo) in Toronto infant-toddler day care providers</article-title><source>35th Interscience Conference on Antimicrobial Agents and Chemotherapy, Sept 17-20, 1995</source><year>1995</year><volume>San Francisco, CA. Washington: American Society for Microbiology, 1995 (Abstract K154)</volume></citation></ref><ref id="B53"><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ochnio</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Traveler Seroprevalence Data in Vancouver</article-title><year>1995</year></citation></ref><ref id="B54"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kocuipchyk</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Seroprevalence of hepatitis A antibodies in travellers at the Edmonton Travellers' Health Clinic--Alberta</article-title><source>Can Commun Dis Rep</source><year>1995</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7787817</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B55"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Richer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name><name><surname>Huet</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Incidence of hepatitis non-A, non-B compared with types A and B in hospital patients</article-title><source>Can Med Assoc J</source><year>1982</year><volume>127</volume><fpage>384</fpage><lpage>386</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6809306</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B56"><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Basrur</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Toronto Staff Report: Hepatitis A at a Toronto grocery store</article-title><source>Toronto Public Health</source><year>2002</year></citation></ref><ref id="B57"><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pollett</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Middlesex-London Health Unit Report No. 128-02: Hepatitis A in a foodhandler</article-title><year>2002</year></citation></ref><ref id="B58"><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Authority</surname><given-names>VCH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hepatitis A in a Capers grocery store in Vancouver</article-title><source>Infectious Diseases News Brief</source><year>2002</year></citation></ref><ref id="B59"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jacobsen</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Koopman</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Declining hepatitis A seroprevalence: a global review and analysis</article-title><source>Epidemiol Infect</source><year>2004</year><volume>132</volume><fpage>1005</fpage><lpage>1022</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15635957</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0950268804002857</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B60"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beutels</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Damme</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Vranckx</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Meheus</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The shift in prevalence of hepatitis A immunity in Flanders, Belgium</article-title><source>Acta Gastroenterol Belg</source><year>1998</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>4</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9629763</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B61"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morris-Cunnington</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Edmunds</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A population-based seroprevalence study of hepatitis A virus using oral fluid in England and Wales</article-title><source>Am J Epidemiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>159</volume><fpage>786</fpage><lpage>794</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15051588</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aje/kwh107</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B62"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prodinger</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Larcher</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Solder</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Geissler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Dierich</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hepatitis A in Western Austria--the epidemiological situation before the introduction of active immunisation</article-title><source>Infection</source><year>1994</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8181844</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF01780769</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B63"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bottiger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Christenson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Grillner</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hepatitis A immunity in the Swedish population. A study of the prevalence of markers in the Swedish population</article-title><source>Scand J Infect Dis</source><year>1997</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9181642</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B64"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Hollinger FB LSMMHS</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Global impact of hepatitis A virus infection: changing patterns</article-title><source>Viral Hepatitis and Liver Disease</source><year>2005</year><publisher-name>Baltimore, Williams and Wilkins</publisher-name><fpage>14</fpage><lpage>20</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B65"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hadler</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>cala de</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bensabath</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Schatz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Fields</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epidemiology of hepatitis delta virus infection in less developed countries</article-title><source>Prog Clin Biol Res</source><year>1991</year><volume>364</volume><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2020698</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B66"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hutin</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pool</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Cramer</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name><surname>Nainan</surname><given-names>OV</given-names></name><name><surname>Weth</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>IT</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name><surname>Gensheimer</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><name><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name><surname>Alter</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Margolis</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A multistate, foodborne outbreak of hepatitis A. National Hepatitis A Investigation Team</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>1999</year><volume>340</volume><fpage>595</fpage><lpage>602</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10029643</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJM199902253400802</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B67"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosenblum</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Mirkin</surname><given-names>IR</given-names></name><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Safford</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hadler</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A multifocal outbreak of hepatitis A traced to commercially distributed lettuce</article-title><source>Am J Public Health</source><year>1990</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>1075</fpage><lpage>1079</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2382744</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B68"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fulford</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Keystone</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Health Risks Associated with Visiting Friends and Relatives in Developing Countries</article-title><source>Curr Infect Dis Rep</source><year>2005</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>48</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15610671</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B69"><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krahn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Remis</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hogg</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimian</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Universal hepatitis A vaccination for adolescents and children in Canada: a cost effectiveness analysis</article-title><year>2005</year></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>



