<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Immun Ageing</journal-id><journal-title>Immunity &#x00026; ageing : I &#x00026; A</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1742-4933</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">16271147</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1298323</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1742-4933-2-15</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1742-4933-2-15</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Constitutive degradation of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; in human T lymphocytes is mediated by calpain</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ponnappan</surname><given-names>Subramaniam</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>sponnappan@uams.edu</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cullen</surname><given-names>Sarah J</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>scullen@uams.edu</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ponnappan</surname><given-names>Usha</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>uponnappan@uams.edu</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Geriatrics, University of Arkansas for Medical Sciences, Little Rock, AR, USA</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Department of Microbiology and Immunology, University of Arkansas for Medical Sciences, Little Rock, AR, USA</aff><aff id="I3"><label>3</label>VA Medical Research, Central Arkansas Veterans Health care system, Little Rock, AR, USA</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2005</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>4</day><month>11</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><volume>2</volume><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.immunityageing.com/content/2/1/15"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>8</month><year>2005</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>4</day><month>11</month><year>2005</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2005 Ponnappan et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2005</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Ponnappan et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>
               Ponnappan
               Subramaniam
               
               
               sponnappan@uams.edu
            </dc:author><dc:title>
            Constitutive degradation of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; in human T lymphocytes is mediated by calpain
         </dc:title><dc:date>2005</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>Immunity &#x00026; Ageing 2(1): 15-. (2005)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1742-4933(2005)2:1&#x0003c;15&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1742-4933</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Activation-induced induction of transcription factor NF&#x003ba;B in T lymphocytes is regulated by its inhibitor I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1;. NF&#x003ba;B activation has been demonstrated to occur either by phosphorylation on serine residues 32 and 36 of the inhibitor, I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1;, followed by ubiquitination and degradation of the inhibitor by the 26S proteasome, or by a proteasome-independent mechanism involving tyrosine phosphorylation, but not degradation. However, the mechanism underlying constitutive regulation of the levels of the inhibitor, I&#x003ba;B, in primary human T lymphocytes, remains to be fully delineated.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>We demonstrate here, the involvement of a proteasome-independent pathway for constitutive regulation of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; levels in primary human T lymphocytes. Pretreatment with a cell permeable calpain inhibitor, E64D, but not with a proteasome specific inhibitor, lactacystin, blocks stimulus-independent I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; degradation in primary human T cells. However, E64D pre-treatment fails to impact on I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; levels following stimulation with either TNF&#x003b1; or pervanadate. Other isoforms of the inhibitor, I&#x003ba;B&#x003b2;, and I&#x003ba;B&#x003b3;, appear not to be subject to a similar ligand-independent regulation. Unlike the previously reported decline in ligand-induced degradation of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; in T cells from the elderly, constitutive degradation does not exhibit an age-associated decline, demonstrating proteasome-independent regulation of the activity.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Our studies support a role for an E64D sensitive protease in regulating constitutive levels of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; in T cells, independent of the involvement of the 26S proteasome, and suggests a biological role for constitutive degradation of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; in T cells.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Transcription factor NF&#x003ba;B exists as homo-or-hetero-dimeric complexes, consisting of the Rel family of proteins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. These dimers operate as transcriptional regulators essential for a variety of cellular processes ranging from cell cycle progression to immune response gene induction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. In human T lymphocytes, like most other cells, NF&#x003ba;B exists in the cytoplasm coupled to its inhibitor I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; or I&#x003ba;B&#x003b2;, predominant members of I&#x003ba;B family of proteins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. A high affinity for RelA and c-Rel molecules enables these inhibitory proteins to associate with and thus restrict nuclear localization of the NF&#x003ba;B molecules. Most stimuli responsible for NF&#x003ba;B induction have been demonstrated to either invoke serine phosphorylation of the inhibitory proteins followed by ubiquitination and degradation via the 26S proteasome pathway, or involve the activation of tyrosine phosphorylation, as in the case of oxidative stress mediated stimuli, which is independent of proteasomal degradation mechanism [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. While stimulation-induced modification of I&#x003ba;B has been studied extensively, little is known about the constitutive regulation of I&#x003ba;B protein in T cells under resting conditions.</p><p>Recent studies in B cell lines have demonstrated that I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1;, but not I&#x003ba;B&#x003b2;, is constitutively degraded and is important for the induction of constitutive NF&#x003ba;B activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. These studies indicate that constitutive degradation of I&#x003ba;B is mediated by a proteasome independent pathway. Studies also suggest that a calcium-dependent protease, calpain, may be important in regulating levels of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. These studies prompted us to investigate whether a similar regulation of "constitutive" i.e., stimulus-independent levels of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; occurs in primary T lymphocytes. Unlike B cells, NF&#x003ba;B induction and I&#x003ba;B regulation reported in T cells is clearly mediated by exogenous activating stimuli, with little or no constitutive nuclear NF&#x003ba;B present under basal condition.</p><p>Further, as NF&#x003ba;B regulation is significantly altered during aging in human T cells, we examined whether abnormal constitutive regulation may underlie lowered activation-mediated induction. Employing primary T cells obtained from human donors, we evaluated whether aging affects the regulation of constitutive levels of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1;. We hypothesized that, as constitutive levels of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; were relatively unaffected by age in primary T cells, this may reflect minimal effect of age on calpain activity in T cells. We now report that E64D sensitive protease, calpain, is indeed responsible for regulating constitutive levels of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1;, but not I&#x003ba;B&#x003b2; or I&#x003ba;B&#x003b3;, in human T cells. Further, calcium-ionophore mediated increase in calpain activity induced in T cells from young donors showed consistently higher activity at early time points after activation, when compared to the elderly. However, total calpain activity measured at the end of 60 minutes demonstrated no significant modulation based on the age of the donor. Thus, while the kinetics of calpain activation appears to be altered in T cells from the elderly, cumulative activity over a period of time remains unaffected. Additionally, we demonstrate that aging does not significantly affect stimulus-independent degradation of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; mediated by calpain, demonstrating proteasome-independent regulation. Thus, the calpain system is involved in the constitutive regulation of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1;, and hence the NF&#x003ba;B signaling pathway, under resting conditions, in primary human T lymphocytes.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>Treatment with a cell permeable cysteine protease inhibitor, E64D, inhibits constitutive degradation of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; but not I&#x003ba;B&#x003b2; or I&#x003ba;B&#x003b3; in T lymphocytes from young and elderly donors</title><p>We examined the effect of a cell permeable cysteine protease inhibitor, E64D, on the basal levels of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1;, I&#x003ba;B&#x003b2; and I&#x003ba;B&#x003b3;, inhibitors of the ubiquitous transcription factor NF&#x003ba;B. Employing primary T cells and western blotting using antibody specific to the inhibitor isoforms, we now demonstrate that constitutive levels of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1;, but not I&#x003ba;B&#x003b2; or I&#x003ba;B&#x003b3; are modulated by pretreatment with E64D. Results presented in fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>, demonstrate that pretreatment with E64D significantly inhibits constitutive degradation of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; with little or no effect on either I&#x003ba;B&#x003b2; (fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>) or I&#x003ba;B&#x003b3; (fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). Levels of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; before treatment with E64D are significantly lower, than that observed following treatment, indicating inhibition of degradation.</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Effect of treatment with E64D on constitutive levels of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; in T cells from young and elderly donors. </bold>T cells obtained from young and elderly donors were either treated with E64D (+), 50 &#x003bc;M, or left untreated (-) for 45 minutes. At the end of incubation, cells were washed and cell lysates prepared. Lysates, equalized for protein, were resolved using SDS-PAGE, followed by electroblotting. Resolved proteins were detected using specific antibody to I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; and ECL. Representative data from one donor pair are presented (A). Values obtained from a minimum of 4 donor pairs following densitometric scanning, are presented as mean integrated density units &#x000b1; S.D.(B); ** indicates statistical difference from untreated controls.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1742-4933-2-15-1"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>Effect of age on constitutive degradation of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b2;. </bold>T cells obtained from young and elderly donors were either treated with E64D (+), 50 &#x003bc;M, or left untreated (-) for 45 minutes. At the end of incubation, cells were washed and cell lysates prepared. Lysates, equalized for protein, were resolved using SDS-PAGE, followed by electroblotting. Resolved proteins were detected using specific antibody to I&#x003ba;B&#x003b2; and ECL. Representative data from one donor pair are presented (A). Values obtained from a minimum of 4 donor pairs following densitometric scanning, are presented as mean integrated density units &#x000b1; S.D.(B).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1742-4933-2-15-2"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>Effect of age on constitutive degradation of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b3;. </bold>T cells obtained from young and elderly donors were either treated with E64D (+), 50 &#x003bc;M, or left untreated (-) for 45 minutes. At the end of incubation, cells were washed and cell lysates prepared. Lysates, equalized for protein, were resolved using SDS-PAGE, followed by electroblotting. Resolved proteins were detected using specific antibody to I&#x003ba;B&#x003b3; and ECL. Representative data from one donor pair are presented (A). Values obtained from a minimum of 4 donor pairs following densitometric scanning, are presented as mean integrated density units &#x000b1; S.D.(B).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1742-4933-2-15-3"/></fig><p>As I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; degradation induced by exogenous signals has been reported to be differentially regulated during aging [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>], we next assessed the effect of treatment with E64D on I&#x003ba;B-&#x003b1; in T cells obtained from young and elderly donors. Results presented in fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>, demonstrate that, irrespective of the age of the T cell donor, E64D pretreatment significantly protected I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; levels from constitutive degradation, and had little impact on isoforms, I&#x003ba;B&#x003b2; (fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>) and I&#x003ba;B&#x003b3; (fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). Thus, aging does not influence cysteine protease-sensitive constitutive degradation of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; in T cells.</p></sec><sec><title>Inhibition of cysteine protease activity by E64D does not affect TNF&#x003b1;-induced degradation of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; in T cells</title><p>Treatment of T cells by activating stimuli such as, anti-CD3 or TNF&#x003b1;, have been demonstrated to induce transcription factor NF&#x003ba;B activation by a signal-induced, proteasome-mediated degradation of the inhibitor I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1;. To determine whether such signal-induced degradation of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; was subjected to regulation by cysteine proteases, we next examined the role of E64D on activation-induced levels of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1;. Results depicted in fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref>, clearly demonstrate that activation of T cells with TNF&#x003b1; induces degradation of I&#x003ba;B-&#x003b1;, irrespective of treatment with E64D. This indicates that E64D sensitive protease does not modulate or impact on activation-induced, proteasome-dependent degradation of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1;. It should be noted that a slower mobility I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; band appears at later time-points (20 and 30 min.) in TNF activated cells from the elderly. We believe that this represents modified I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1;. Future experiments will determine the precise nature of this modification. As proteasome dependent degradation of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; is clearly differentially regulated in T cells from young and elderly donors, we next examined, whether E64D mediated inhibition of constitutive levels impact differentially on the induced degradation of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; in T cells from the elderly. Results presented in fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref>, demonstrate that pre-treatment with E64D failed to influence activation-induced degradation of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1;. Thus, irrespective of the age of the donor, treatment with E64D failed to modulate activation-induced degradation of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1;.</p><fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><bold>Effect of E64D on stimulus-dependent modification of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; (Western Blots). </bold>T cells obtained from young and elderly donors were either left untreated or treated with E64D (50 &#x003bc;M) for 45 min. At the end of incubation cells were stimulated with 100 &#x003bc;M pervanadate or TNF&#x003b1; (10 ng/ml) for 10, 20 or 30 min. Cell lysates were prepared and resolved by SDS-PAGE, using equal amounts of protein (30 &#x003bc;g / lane). Resolved proteins were transferred to nitrocellulose membrane and Western blotted with antibody to I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; and detected using ECL. Representative results obtained from one donor pair are presented. Arrows represent I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; specific bands detected and used in the analyses.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1742-4933-2-15-4"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><bold>Effect of E64D on stimulus-dependent modification of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; (Integrated Densities). </bold>T cells obtained from young and elderly donors were either left untreated or treated with E64D (50 &#x003bc;M) for 45 min. At the end of incubation cells were stimulated with 100 &#x003bc;M pervanadate or TNF&#x003b1; (10 ng/ml) for 10, 20 or 30 min. Cell lysates were prepared and resolved by SDS-PAGE, using equal amounts of protein (30 &#x003bc;g / lane). Resolved proteins were transferred to nitrocellulose membrane and Western blotted with antibody to I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; and detected using ECL. Mean integrated densities of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; specific bands obtained from a minimum of 4 donor pairs were used to determine <underline>fold change</underline> when compared to their respective controls and are presented as Mean (fold-change) &#x000b1; S.D. [TNF-&#x003b1; (A); Pervanadate (B)].</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1742-4933-2-15-5"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Pretreatment with E64D does not interfere with activation-induced modification mediated by pervanadate treatment in T cells</title><p>As a next step in the analyses, we examined the effect of pretreatment with E64D on modes of activation that does not involve signal-induced degradation of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1;, such as those mediated by pervanadate. Similar to the observation with TNF&#x003b1;, pretreatment with E64D failed to impact on activation-induced I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; modification in cells pre-treated with pervanadate, irrespective of the age of the donor (fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>). It is important to note that I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; in cells treated with pervanadate clearly demonstrate a slower mobility band representing tyrosine-phosphorylated I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1;. Thus, irrespective of the activation stimuli (TNFa or Pervanadate), E64D appeared not to impact on the activation-induced modulation of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1;. NF&#x003ba;B dependent luciferase activity was also assayed following pervanadate treatment, in the presence or absence of E64D. In keeping with the data obtained with I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1;, E64D pretreatment, failed to impact on NF&#x003ba;B dependent luciferase activity, (data not shown).</p></sec><sec><title>Treatment of T cells with proteasome inhibitor, Lactacystin, does not influence constitutive I&#x003ba;B-&#x003b1; levels, unlike that mediated by E64D</title><p>As I&#x003ba;B-&#x003b1; is constitutively degraded by E64D sensitive cysteine protease, we next assessed whether treatment with a proteasome inhibitor also interfered with this basal degradation. Results presented in fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6A</xref>, clearly demonstrate that pretreatment with lactacystin, a proteasome specific inhibitor, failed to influence basal levels of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1;. Thus suggesting that basal or constitutive regulation of I&#x003ba;B-&#x003b1; is not dependent on the proteasome. To ensure that lactacystin did inhibit proteasome at the dose employed, i.e. positive control, T cells from young and elderly donors were either pretreated with lactacystin or left untreated. These cells were then subjected to treatment with TNFa. As seen in fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6B</xref>, TNFa treatment in the young induced degradation of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1;, when compared to untreated controls. Pretreatment with lactacystin and then TNF&#x003b1; (L+T), inhibited TNFa mediated degradation. As reported previously, lactacystin is only minimally effective in T cells from the elderly.</p><fig position="float" id="F6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><bold>Treatment with proteasome inhibitor, Lactacystin, fails to affect constitutive levels of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; in human T cells. </bold>T cells obtained from young and elderly donors were either left untreated (-) or treated with lactacystin (5 &#x003bc;M) for 2 h to inhibit the proteasome. At the end of incubation cells were washed and lysates were prepared as described. Equal amounts of protein from cell lysates were resolved using SDS-PAGE and electroblotted. Resolved I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; was detected using antibody to I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; and ECL. To ensure equal protein loading, blots were stripped and reprobed with &#x003b2;-actin. Representative data from one donor pair are presented (A). As a positive control for lactacystin, T cells from young and elderly donors were either pretreated with Lactacystin (5 &#x003bc;M, 2 h) and then activated with TNF&#x003b1; for 10 min (L+T) or activated with TNF&#x003b1; without lactacystin pretreatment (T). US represent untreated T cells. Cell lysates were resolved using SDS-PAGE and I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; detected as indicated above (B).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1742-4933-2-15-6"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Treatment of T cell lysates with purified calpain, mimics constitutive degradation of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1;</title><p>As E64D pretreatment specifically inhibited basal degradation of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1;, implicating a role for cysteine proteases such as calpain in regulating the constitutive levels of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1;, we tested for a direct role for calpain by treating cytosolic lysates obtained from T cells with a purified preparation of calpain in an <italic>in vitro </italic>assay. T cell lysates equalized for protein from young donors were pooled and subjected to lysis in the presence of purified calpain, as indicated. Degradation of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; was determined by measuring the detectable levels of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; by SDS-PAGE and western blotting using antibody to I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1;. Results presented in fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>, show that upon exposure to 0.01 U of calpain, lysates from T cells demonstrate lowered levels of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1;, indicating calpain-mediated degradation, which is inhibited by pretreatment with E64D.</p><fig position="float" id="F7"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p><bold>Pretreatment with E64D inhibits calpain-mediated degradation of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; in T cell lysates. </bold>T cell lysates obtained from young donors were pooled and 50 &#x003bc;g protein was incubated with 0.01 U purified calpain. The mixture was incubated at 37&#x000b0;C for 15 min. At the end of incubation samples were denatured and resolved using SDS-PAGE. I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; was detected usingspecific antibody and ECL (A). Values obtained from a minimum of 4 donor pairs following densitometric scanning, are presented as mean integrated density units &#x000b1; S.D. (B). * indicates significant degradation (p &#x0003c; 0.05).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1742-4933-2-15-7"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Kinetics of induction of calpain activity following calcium ionophore treatment, is modulated by age, but has no impact on overall effective calpain activity in T cells</title><p>To assess the effect of age on calpain activity, we obtained T cells from young and elderly healthy volunteers and examined them for endogenous calpain activity. As demonstrated in fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>, calpain specific protease hydrolyzing activity appeared to be slightly higher at time 0 in T cells from young donors; however, calcium ionophore induced increase in calpain activity was not significantly different between T cells from young and elderly donors. In fact, total hydrolyzing activity measured at the end of 60 minutes was not statistically different between cells obtained from the two age groups. Therefore, effective calpain activity remained unaffected by age of the T cell donor.</p><fig position="float" id="F8"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p><bold>Basal Calpain activity in T cells obtained from young and elderly donors. </bold>T cells obtained from young and elderly donors were adjusted to 2.5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5 </sup>cells /ml. Calpain activity was measured using a fluorogenic substrate Boc-Met-AMC at 380 nm <sub>exc </sub>and 460 nm <sub>emm </sub>using a fluorometer. Specific activity was determined in the presence of calpain inhibitor E64D. Values represent calpain specific activity and represent Mean fluorescence intensity &#x000b1; S.D of data obtained from 4 independent experiments.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1742-4933-2-15-8"/></fig></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>Calpain system has been demonstrated to be the main protease involved in constitutive degradation of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. Delineation of the exact region of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; necessary for degradation by calpain resulted in the identification of the C-terminal 39 amino acid sequence containing the PEST sequence to be critical for degradation in vitro by Shumway and Miyamoto [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. However, their studies, demonstrated that calpain was not responsible for the degradation of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; in primary B cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. Unlike B cells, that express constitutive nuclear NF&#x003ba;B, significant nuclear expression of NF&#x003ba;B in T cells occurs predominantly following stimulus-induced activation. Few studies, to date, have delved into constitutive regulation of NF&#x003ba;B in resting T cells. In our current studies, employing E64D, we demonstrate specificity of constitutive degradation of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; mediated by calpain in human primary T lymphocytes. The inhibition of this degradation in the presence of E64D, a cell permeable, cysteine protease inhibitor, supports the potential involvement of calpain activity in this process. Given the central role of NF&#x003ba;B in cell survival and signaling [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>], constitutive degradation of the inhibitor I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; is vital in understanding steady state kinetics of T cell regulation in the context of immune activation.</p><p>Our studies also demonstrate that degradation of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; under resting condition is refractory to proteasome inhibitor, Lactacystin, but not to calpain inhibitor, E64D. Therefore, unlike that reported for activation-induced degradation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>], constitutive levels of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; appear not to be subject to proteosomal regulation. This is particularly important given that our previous findings clearly showed that inducible degradation of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; is subject to an "age-effect" due to the inhibitory action of aging on proteasome- associated proteolytic activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>].</p><p>Calpain-dependent degradation of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; has been demonstrated to occur in other cell types, which are refractory to proteasome activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. Thus, it appears, that the degradation of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; can occur through two mutually exclusive pathways, dependent on the state of the cells, i.e., resting versus activated. Calpain system plays a role in constitutive, but not induced I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; degradation, while proteasome degradation dictates induced levels in T cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. Calpain activity has been demonstrated to be involved in the degradation of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; under certain conditions of viral infection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. It is therefore likely that this ability of constitutive degradation may be exploited by certain pathogens.</p><p>Unlike the most predominant inhibitor I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1;; I&#x003ba;B&#x003b2; and I&#x003ba;B&#x003b3; isoforms, appear not to be susceptible to this calpain-mediated degradation. Recent elegant experiments by Miyamoto et al implicate similar degradation kinetics for I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; isoform in B cell lines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. Drawing upon the significance of such degradation events in the constitutive induction of NF&#x003ba;B in B cells, the role for constitutive regulation of NF&#x003ba;B by the calpain pathway in primary T cells was examined here. Results from these experiments clearly provide a biological basis for stimulus-independent degradation and its importance in the maintenance of NF&#x003ba;B in cell survival, which is not evident, unless challenged by stimuli capable of inducing apoptosis (data not shown).</p><p>Our studies on the effect of advancing age on constitutive degradation of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1;, clearly implicate absence of any effect of donor age on the maintenance of E64D protease sensitive/calpain activity responsible for this degradation. Experiments conducted to determine the impact of aging on calpain activity clearly indicate that the effective activity is unaltered during aging. This is also reflected in the levels of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; in resting T cells from young and elderly donors, which are unaffected by age. Thus, despite loss in proteasome activity accompanying aging, calpain-mediated degradation of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; remains unaltered, demonstrating little or no role for the proteasomal regulation in calpain-mediated pathway that regulates I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; levels. This observation is in keeping with earlier reports from our laboratory that demonstrated minimal effect of age on overall cellular proteolytic activity, especially, T cell chymotryptic activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. It is also interesting to note that reports on calpain activity as a function of advancing age have been conflicting, with some demonstrating increased activity, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>] and others, decreased activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>], however, these studies either used other cell types, employed exogenous substrates or cell lysates for the evaluation of the activity. Using a fluorogenic model substrate that is cell permeable, we now demonstrate that, ionomycin-inducible specific calpain activity, inhibitable by E64D, is unaffected; however, proteolytic activity observed in T cell lysates appeared to follow different kinetics in cells from the young than those observed in the elderly. Importantly, while 90% of the activity in cells from the young was clearly inhibitable by treatment with E64D, only 50% of the activity was inhibitable in cells from the elderly (data not shown).</p><p>While constitutive degradation of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; is clearly regulated by E64D sensitive calpain in T cells, activation-induced degradation, appears unaffected by pretreatment with E64D. Similarly, while activation-induced degradation of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; is sensitive to proteasome inhibition, constitutive degradation is unaffected by pretreatment with lactacystin, a proteasome inhibitor. Clearly, susceptibility of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; to degradation is not only dependent on the state of activation but also on the specificity of the protease. The physiologic significance of the degradation of the inhibitor clearly dictates induction of NF&#x003ba;B levels, and thus anti-apoptotic or survival ability, under uninduced conditions. Thus, regulation of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; levels in basal state of a cell is crucial and sets the stage for activation-induced survival signals. These results also indicate that the calpain pathway works independently of phosphorylation, since neither TNF nor pervanadate that induce serine and tyrosine phosphorylation, respectively, were affected by the inhibitor. Further, while proteasome dependent activation-induced degradation pathway, as well as proteasome pathway has been demonstrated to be compromised in T cells during aging, calpain activity clearly appears to be still functional, and is minimally affected by advancing age.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>In summary, we have demonstrated that basal levels of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1;, but not I&#x003ba;B&#x003b2; or I&#x003ba;B&#x003b3; are subject to regulation by E64D sensitive protease, and can be mimicked by pretreatment with calpain. The regulation of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; levels by cysteine protease appears to have no effect on activation-induced I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; or on other isoforms of I&#x003ba;B, irrespective of the stimuli employed. Additionally, it appears that interference with this decrease in basal degradation of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; does not impact on cell survival under resting conditions.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec sec-type="materials"><title>Materials</title><p>Fluorochrome labeled anti-CD3, and FITC- and PE-labeled isotype controls were obtained from Sigma Chemical Co. (St. Louis, MO). Anti IgG coupled to horseradish peroxidase was obtained from BD-Transduction Laboratories (Lexington, KY). All other antibodies were from Santa Cruz Biotech (Carlsbad,CA). Enhanced Chemi-luminescence reagents were from Amersham (Arlington Heights, IL). All fine chemicals unless otherwise mentioned were obtained from Sigma Chemical Company, (St. Louis, MO.), Electrophoresis supplies and Molecular weight standards were from BioRad (Richmond, CA.). E64D and lactacystin were from Calbiochem (CA). Substrate for Calpain was from Molecular probes, (Eugene, OR).</p></sec><sec><title>Human subjects</title><p>Blood was obtained from healthy individuals living in the community. Young donors were between 21 and 30 years and old donors were between 65 and 85 years of age. A minimum of at least four donor pairs were used in each experiment. Both young and elderly donors were in good physical and mental health, had no apparent illness as suggested by an elaborate screening history and were not on any medication directly impacting the immune system during the course of this study.</p></sec><sec><title>T Lymphocyte Isolation</title><p>Peripheral blood was obtained and T cells were purified and maintained in RPMI 1640 culture medium as previously described (20). Magnetic sorting by negative selection was used to isolate CD3<sup>+ </sup>T cells. Purity of the isolated T cells was determined by flow cytometry using anti-CD3 conjugated to FITC. Populations were 90&#x02013;95% pure. Treatment of T cells (20 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup>cells/ml) with pervanadate (100 &#x003bc;M, freshly prepared before use) was carried out for indicated times at 37&#x000b0;C, before cell lysates were prepared. For experiments involving the use of inhibitor, cells were treated with E64D at 50 &#x003bc;M for 45 minutes.</p></sec><sec><title>Western blotting</title><p>Cytosolic extracts for Western blotting were prepared by homogenization of cells in lysis buffer (1 mM Hepes, 10 mM KCl, 1.5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, and 1 mM sodium orthovanadate, and 0.5% NP-40) (20). The following reagents were added to all buffers prior to their use: 0.5 mM dithiothreitol (DTT), 0.5 mM phenylmethylsulfonyl fluoride (PMSF), and 10 &#x003bc;g/ml each of aprotinin, leupeptin, and soybean trypsin inhibitor. Protein content of cytosolic extracts was determined using BioRad protein assay. Cell lysates equalized for protein (40 &#x003bc;g) were resolved by SDS-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (PAGE), transferred to nitrocellulose, immuno-blotted with specific antibody/s, and detected using anti-IgG coupled to horseradish peroxidase followed by Enhanced Chemi-luminescence (ECL). Where possible samples from young and elderly donors were resolved on the same gel, but in experiments where different treatments were analyzed, samples from young and the elderly were resolved on different gels, but were run simultaneously, to avoid inter and intra experimental variability. Resolution of samples on different gels did not influence the outcome of the results.</p><sec><title>Calpain activity assays</title><p>Using a cell permeable fluorescent substrate Boc-Met-AMC, calpain activity within live cells was measured using a spectrofluorometer. Fluorescence was measured in cell suspension (2.5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup>cells/ml) following the addition of fluorophore, using the LS-50 model, Perkin-Elmer Spectrofluorometer. The fluorometer was equipped with a magnetic stirrer and warmed with recirculating water at 37&#x000b0;C using a pump. Fluorescence was measured using excitation and emission wavelengths of 380 and 460 nm, respectively. Values were obtained using a time drive mode, for up to 60 minutes.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analyses</title><p>Data were analyzed using student's t-test. Differences were considered significant, if p &#x0003c; 0.05.</p></sec></sec></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This work was supported by Grants provided by NIH RO1 AG13081, MO1RR1288 and in part by the use of facilities at the VA Medical Center, Little Rock, Arkansas. We gratefully acknowledge the technical assistance of Mrs. Virginia Fitzhugh and assistance provided by the General Clinical Research Center, in sample collection.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hayden</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Signaling to NF-kappaB</article-title><source>Gene Dev</source><year>2004</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>2195</fpage><lpage>2224</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15371334</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.1228704</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Levchenko</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Baltimore</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The IkappaB-NF-kappaB signaling module: temporal control and selective gene activation</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2002</year><volume>298</volume><fpage>1241</fpage><lpage>1245</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12424381</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1071914</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Israel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The IKK complex: an integrator of all signals that activate NF-kappaB?</article-title><source>Trends Cell Biol</source><year>2000</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>129</fpage><lpage>133</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10740266</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0962-8924(00)01729-3</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Imbert</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Rupec</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Livolsi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pahl</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Traenckner</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name><surname>Mueller-Dieckmann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Farahifar</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Auberger</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Baeuerle</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Peyron</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tyrosine phosphorylation of I kappa B-alpha activates NF-kappa B without proteolytic degradation of I kappa B-alpha</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1996</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>787</fpage><lpage>798</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8797825</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(00)80153-1</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Glickman</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ciechanover</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The ubiquitin-proteasome proteolytic pathway: destruction for the sake of construction</article-title><source>Physiol Rev</source><year>2002</year><volume>82</volume><fpage>373</fpage><lpage>428</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11917093</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shumway</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyamoto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A mechanistic insight into a proteasome-independent constitutive inhibitor kappaBalpha (IkappaBalpha) degradation and nuclear factor kappaB (NF-kappaB) activation pathway in WEHI-231 B-cells</article-title><source>Biochem J</source><year>2004</year><volume>380</volume><fpage>173</fpage><lpage>180</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14763901</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/BJ20031796</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name><name><surname>Kudo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyamoto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A nuclear export signal in the N-terminal regulatory domain of IkappaBalpha controls cytoplasmic localization of inactive NF-kappaB/IkappaBalpha complexes</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2000</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>1014</fpage><lpage>1019</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10655476</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.97.3.1014</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Waris</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Livolsi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Imbert</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Peyron</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Siddiqui</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hepatitis C virus NS5A and subgenomic replicon activate NF-kappaB via tyrosine phosphorylation of IkappaBalpha and its degradation by calpain protease</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2003</year><volume>278</volume><fpage>40778</fpage><lpage>40787</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12909638</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M303248200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schaecher</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Goust</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Banik</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effects of calpain inhibition on IkB alpha degradation after activation of PBMCs: identification of the calpain cleavage sites</article-title><source>Neurochem Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>1443</fpage><lpage>1451</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15202778</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/B:NERE.0000026410.56000.dd</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Weinman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Boldogh</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Brasier</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tumor necrosis factor-alpha-inducible IkappaBalpha proteolysis mediated by cytosolic m-calpain. A mechanism parallel to the ubiquitin-proteasome pathway for nuclear factor-kappab activation</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1999</year><volume>274</volume><fpage>787</fpage><lpage>794</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9873017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.274.2.787</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Poulaki</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitsiades</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Joussen</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lappas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirchhof</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitsiades</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Constitutive nuclear factor-kappaB activity is crucial for human retinoblastoma cell viability</article-title><source>Am J Pathol</source><year>2002</year><volume>161</volume><fpage>2229</fpage><lpage>2240</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12466137</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alkalay</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Yaron</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hatzubai</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Orian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ciechanover</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ben-Neriah</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stimulation-dependent I kappa B alpha phosphorylation marks the NF-kappa B inhibitor for degradation via the ubiquitin-proteasome pathway</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>1995</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>10599</fpage><lpage>10603</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7479848</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trebilcock</surname><given-names>GU</given-names></name><name><surname>Ponnappan</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence for lowered induction of nuclear factor kappa B in activated human T lymphocytes during aging</article-title><source>Gerontology</source><year>1996</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>137</fpage><lpage>146</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8796372</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trebilcock</surname><given-names>GU</given-names></name><name><surname>Ponnappan</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nuclear factor-kappaB induction in CD45RO+ and CD45RA+ T cell subsets during aging</article-title><source>Mech Ageing Dev</source><year>1998</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>163</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9720648</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0047-6374(97)00160-7</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ponnappan</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ubiquitin-proteasome pathway is compromised in CD45RO+ and CD45RA+ T lymphocyte subsets during aging</article-title><source>Exp Gerontol</source><year>2002</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>359</fpage><lpage>367</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11772523</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0531-5565(01)00203-0</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hinman</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Duce</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Siman</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hollander</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Abraham</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Activation of calpain-1 in myelin and microglia in the white matter of the aged rhesus monkey</article-title><source>J Neurochem</source><year>2004</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>430</fpage><lpage>441</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15056286</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Averna</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>De Tullio</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Salamino</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Minafra</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pontremoli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Melloni</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Age-dependent degradation of calpastatin in kidney of hypertensive rats</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2001</year><volume>276</volume><fpage>38426</fpage><lpage>38432</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11485997</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M101936200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guttmann</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>GV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oxidative stress inhibits calpain activity in situ</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1998</year><volume>273</volume><fpage>13331</fpage><lpage>13338</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9582380</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.273.21.13331</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Witkowski</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bryl</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Paradoxical age-related cell cycle quickening of human CD4 (+) lymphocytes: a role for cyclin D1 and calpain</article-title><source>Exp Gerontol</source><year>2004</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>577</fpage><lpage>585</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15050293</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.exger.2003.10.028</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ponnappan</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Trebilcock</surname><given-names>GU</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>MZ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Studies into the effect of tyrosine phosphatase inhibitor phenylarsine oxide on NFkappaB activation in T lymphocytes during aging: evidence for altered IkappaB-alpha phosphorylation and degradation</article-title><source>Exp Gerontol</source><year>1999</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>107</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10197731</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0531-5565(98)00059-X</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>



