<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" dtd-version="1.3" article-type="review-article" xml:lang="en"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Saline Syst</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Saline Syst</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Saline Systems</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1746-1448</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">16176593</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1224875</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1746-1448-1-2</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1746-1448-1-2</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Review</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A hundred years of <italic>Dunaliella </italic>research: 1905&#x02013;2005</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A1"><name><surname>Oren</surname><given-names>Aharon</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>orena@shum.cc.huji.ac.il</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>The Institute of Life Sciences, The Hebrew University of Jerusalem, 91904 Jerusalem, Israel</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>the Moshe Shilo Minerva Center for Marine Biogeochemistry, The Hebrew University of Jerusalem, 91904 Jerusalem, Israel</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2005</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>4</day><month>7</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><volume>1</volume><fpage>2</fpage><lpage>2</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>3</day><month>4</month><year>2005</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>4</day><month>7</month><year>2005</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2005 Oren; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2005</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Oren; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.salinesystems.org/content/1/1/2"/><abstract><p>A hundred years have passed since the description of the genus <italic>Dunaliella</italic>, the unicellular green alga which is responsible for most of the primary production in hypersaline environments worldwide. The present paper provides an historical survey of research on <italic>Dunaliella</italic>, from the early work in the 19<sup>th </sup>century to the thorough taxonomic studies by Teodoresco, Hamburger, Lerche and others from the beginnig of the 20<sup>th </sup>century onwards. It attempts to trace the origin of some of the most important breakthroughs that have contributed to our present understanding of this alga that plays such a key role in many hypersaline environments.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>1. Introduction</title><p>A hundred years have passed since the description of the genus <italic>Dunaliella</italic>, the unicellular green alga which is responsible for most of the primary production in hypersaline environments worldwide. First sighted in 1838 in saltern evaporation ponds in the south of France by Michel Felix Dunal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>], it was named after its discoverer by Teodoresco in 1905 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>].</p><p>In the century that has elapsed since its formal description, <italic>Dunaliella </italic>has become a convenient model organism for the study of salt adaptation in algae. The establishment of the concept of organic compatible solutes to provide osmotic balance was largely based on the study of <italic>Dunaliella </italic>species. Moreover, the massive accumulation of <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-carotene by some strains under suitable growth conditions has led to interesting biotechnological applications.</p><p>The present paper provides an historical survey of research on <italic>Dunaliella</italic>, from the early work in the 19<sup>th </sup>century to the thorough taxonomic studies by Teodoresco, Hamburger, Lerche and others from the beginning of the 20<sup>th </sup>century onwards. It attempts to trace &#x02013; often through quotations from the original articles &#x02013; the origin of some of the most important breakthroughs that have contributed to our present understanding of this alga that plays such a key role in many hypersaline environments.</p><p>Extensive additional information on the alga can be found in a review by Ginzburg [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>], in the multi-author review edited by Avron and Ben-Amotz [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>], and in my monograph on halophilic microorganisms and their environments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>2. Reports on <italic>Dunaliella </italic>Prior to 1905</title><p>The first description of a unicellular biflagellate red-colored alga living in concentrated brines (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>) was given in 1838 by Dunal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>], who reported occurrence of the organism we know today as <italic>Dunaliella salina </italic>in the salterns of Montpellier, on the Mediterranean coast of France. He named the organisms observed <italic>Haematococcus salinus </italic>and <italic>Protococcus</italic>. The discovery of these algae was made in the framework of an investigation, invited by the Acad&#x000e9;mie des Sciences, Paris, of the cause of the red coloration of saltern brines. At the time it was widely assumed that chemical and physical parameters are responsible for the coloration of these brines. Dunal refuted an earlier claim that the color is due to the brine shrimp <italic>Artemia salina</italic>. The Acad&#x000e9;mie then appointed a committee to reexamine the matter, and this committee confirmed Dunal's finding [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]; see also [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. Another idea brought forward during that period was that <italic>Artemia </italic>contributes to the color due to the partially digested and decaying red flagellates ("<italic>Monas Dunalii</italic>") present in its intestine [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. Nowadays it is clear that, although <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-carotene-rich <italic>Dunaliella </italic>salina are indeed present in the saltern ponds, most of the coloration of the crystallizer brine is caused not by the algae but by red halophilic Archaea instead [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>].</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><italic>Dunaliella salina </italic>cells from the crystallizer brine of the salterns in Eilat, at the Red Sea coast of Israel.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1746-1448-1-2-1"/></fig><p>In the course of the 19<sup>th </sup>century, Dunal's red flagellate algae has been observed by other biologists as well in salt lakes and other hypersaline sites in Crimea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>], Algeria [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>], Lorraine, France [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>] and Romania [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. Different names were attached to the organism by each investigator [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>] (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Names attached to the red-colored unicellular flagellate algae observed in hypersaline brines, 1838&#x02013;1906.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Name</th><th align="left">Author</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><italic>Haematococcus salinus</italic></td><td align="left">Dunal [1]</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Protococcus salinus</italic></td><td align="left">Dunal [1]; Geleznow [11]</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Monas Dunalii</italic></td><td align="left">Joly [8]; Blanchard [16]; Butschinsky [12]</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Diselmis Dunalii</italic></td><td align="left">Dujardin [17]</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Chlamydomonas Dunalii</italic></td><td align="left">Cohn [18]; Blanchard [13]; Bujor [15]</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Sphaerella lacustris </italic>var. <italic>Dunalii</italic></td><td align="left">Hansgirg [19]</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Dunaliella salina</italic></td><td align="left">Teodoresco [2,20]</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>3. The Description of the Genus <italic>Dunaliella</italic></title><p>The year 1905 saw the publication of two papers presenting in-depth descriptions of <italic>Dunaliella </italic>as a new genus, one by E.C. Teodoresco from Bucharest [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>] and the second written by Clara Hamburger from Heidelberg [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. Teodoresco's publication preceded that by Hamburger, who only learned about the Teodoresco paper when finalizing the writing of her own article [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]:</p><p>"Anfang M&#x000e4;rz wollte ich an die Ausarbeitung meiner Notizen gehen, als ich am 10. M&#x000e4;rz von Herrn Prof. Lauterborn eine Arbeit von Teodoresco mit dem Titel: "Organisation et d&#x000e9;veloppement du <italic>Dunaliella</italic>, nouveau genre de Volvocaceae &#x02013; Polyblepharid&#x000e9;e erhielt, welche as Separatdruck aus dem botanischen Centralblatt soeben versendet war. <italic>Dunaliella </italic>ist der von mir untersuchte Organismus, den ich schon als Vertreter einer neuen Gattung erkannt hatte. Unsere Resultaten stimmten in vielen Punkten &#x000fc;berein, in anderen m&#x000fc;ssen meiner Ansicht nach erst weitere Untersuchungen die entg&#x000fc;ltige Entscheidung bringen. Da jedoch meine Studien, besonders bez&#x000fc;glich des innern Baues eingehender sind (Teodoresco hat nur lebendes Material untersucht) und ich auch einige noch bestehende L&#x000fc;cken ausf&#x000fc;llen kann; da ferner alle meine Resultate unbeinflu&#x000df;t von denen Teodoresco's erhalten wurden, so m&#x000f6;chte ich sie dennoch ver&#x000f6;ffentlichen."</p><p>[In the beginning of March [1905] I wanted to start to work out my notes, when on March 10 I received from Prof. Lauterborn a paper by Teodoresco entitled: "Organization and development of <italic>Dunaliella</italic>, a new genus of the Volvocida &#x02013; Polyblepharidae", which was just sent as offprint from the Botanisches Centralblatt. <italic>Dunaliella </italic>is the organism that I had been investigating, and that I had already recognized as representative of a new genus. Our results corresponded in many respects, while in other respects I am of the opinion that further investigations will have to decide. However, because my studies, especially with respect to the internal structure, are more thorough (Teodoresco had studied only live material) and I also can fill in certain still existing gaps in the knowledge, and also because my results were obtained independently of those of Teodoresco, I still would like to publish them.]</p><p>Teodoresco studied material collected from a Romanian salt lake, while Hamburger worked with samples sent to her from the salterns of Cagliari, Sardinia. Both authors presented detailed drawings of the organisms (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>) and provided extensive information on its morphology, cell structure, reproduction, behavior and ecology. A formal description of the genus <italic>Dunaliella</italic>, named in honor of Dunal who had first seen these organisms in salterns in France almost seventy years earlier, and of the first two species within the genus, <italic>D. salina </italic>and <italic>D. viridis</italic>, was published in 1906 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>].</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Drawings by Hamburger (1905) of red cells (<italic>Dunaliella salina</italic>) (1&#x02013;4) and green cells (<italic>D. viridis</italic>) (5&#x02013;8), diverse shapes observed in a drop that becomes more concentrated by evaporation (9&#x02013;29), spherical forms obtained upon dilution (30&#x02013;31), and initiation of cell division (32&#x02013;34). From [2].</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1746-1448-1-2-2"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><italic>Dunaliella salina </italic>(1&#x02013;17) preserved with different fixation techniques; (3), pigment crystals; (8), granules (starch?); (10&#x02013;13), division stages; (14,15), aplanospores; (16&#x02013;17), and green cells (<italic>D. viridis</italic>?), as drawn by Hamburger (1905) [7].</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1746-1448-1-2-3"/></fig><p>The papers by Teodoresco and Hamburger were soon followed by others. Noteworthy studies in the early years of <italic>Dunaliella </italic>research are articles by Cavara [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>], who extended the study of the organism in the Cagliari, Sardinia salterns, a study of the algae in the Salton Sea, California [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>], a series of ecological papers by Labb&#x000e9; based on observations made in the salterns of Le Croisic on the Atlantic coast of France [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>], articles by Baas Becking and coworkers, who collected specimens from all over the world [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>], and the taxonomic studies by Hamel [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>] and Lerche [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>4. The Taxonomy of the Genus <italic>Dunaliella</italic></title><p><italic>Dunaliella </italic>is a genus of unicellar algae belonging to the family Polyblepharidaceae. Its cells lack a rigid cell wall, and they reproduce by longitudinal division of the motile cell or by fusion of two motile cells to form a zygote.</p><p>Teodoresco [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>] described two species: <italic>D. salina </italic>and <italic>D. viridis</italic>. <italic>D. salina </italic>has somewhat larger cells, and under suitable conditions it synthesizes massive amounts of carotenoid pigments, coloring the cells brightly red. <italic>D. viridis </italic>never produces such red cells. It is interesting to note that in the early years there have been extensive discussions whether indeed two species are present or whether the red and the green cells represent different forms of the same species. For example, Blanchard [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>] and Hamburger [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>] considered the green cells as juvenile stages of the red ones. Labb&#x000e9; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>] was of the opinion that differences in salt concentration of the environment are responsible for the different colors of the cells. Upon transferring of saltern brine samples to a lower salinity he grew a form of <italic>Dunaliella </italic>adapted to fresh water and lacking the brown-red pigment. His statements that:</p><p>"En ce qui concerne les facteurs de la transformation, l'hypoth&#x000e8;se simpliste de Teodoresco ne peut &#x000ea;tre conserv&#x000e9;e et it ne s'agit pas l&#x000e0; de deux esp&#x000e8;ces distinctes (<italic>D. salina </italic>et <italic>D. viridis</italic>). Il s'agit d'une alternance de formes due aux changements de milieu."</p><p>[Concerning the factors of the transformation, the simplistic hypothesis of Teodoresco cannot be maintained, and we do not have here two distinct species (<italic>D. salina </italic>and <italic>D. viridis</italic>). We deal with an alternation of forms due to environmental changes.]</p><p>and:</p><p>"L'organisme qui colore en rouge les marais salants et &#x000e0; qui nous pouvons conserver le nom de <italic>Dunaliella salina </italic>n'est que la phase ultime de l'&#x000e9;volution d'un flagell&#x000e9; chlorophyllien voisin de Volvocin&#x000e9;es, tr&#x000e8;s eurihyalin, qui en eau sursal&#x000e9;e donne les formes st&#x000e9;nohyalines non r&#x000e9;versibles aux formes chlorophylliennes, et color&#x000e9;es par un h&#x000e9;matochrome."</p><p>[The organism which colors the salterns red and for which we can conserve the name <italic>Dunaliella salina </italic>is nothing but the final phase in the development of a very euryhyaline chlorophyll-containing flagellate related to the Volvocinae, which in hypersaline water produces stenohyaline foms that cannot revert to chlorophyll-containing forms, and are colored by a hematochrome.]</p><p>have not withstood the test of time. We now know that not all <italic>Dunaliella </italic>species produce massive amounts of carotene, and those that can, do so only under suitable conditions (exposure to high light intensities, nutrient limitation, etc., see also section 6 below). Lerche [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>] thus saw that under suitable conditions all red clones became green, but after several weeks they turned olive to yellow-green and after several months they were red again.</p><p>Additional species were later added to the genus, especially thanks to the in-depth studies by Lerche [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>] and Butcher [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>] (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). Lerche investigated material collected from salt lakes in Romania and in California, as well as the above-mentioned Cagliari salterns. She concluded that the former species <italic>D. viridis </italic>is heterogeneous and should be split into several new species. Thus the species <italic>D. media</italic>, <italic>D. euchlora</italic>, <italic>D. minuta</italic>, and <italic>D. parva </italic>were created. It must be stressed here that not all species mentioned tolerate the extremely high salt concentrations in which <italic>D. salina </italic>and <italic>D. viridis </italic>are found in nature. Some are typically marine organisms that were never reported to occur in hypersaline environments.</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Selected <italic>Dunaliella </italic>species</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Name</th><th align="left">Author, year</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><italic>D. salina</italic></td><td align="left">Teodoresco, 1905, 1906 [2,20]</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>D. viridis</italic></td><td align="left">&#x0201e;</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>D. peircei</italic></td><td align="left">Nicolai and Baas Becking, 1935 [28]</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>D. parva</italic></td><td align="left">Lerche, 1937 [30]</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>D. media</italic></td><td align="left">&#x0201e;</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>D. euchlora</italic></td><td align="left">&#x0201e;</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>D. minuta</italic></td><td align="left">&#x0201e;</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>D. tertiolecta</italic></td><td align="left">Butcher, 1959 [31]</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>D. primolecta</italic></td><td align="left">&#x0201e;</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>D. quartolecta</italic></td><td align="left">&#x0201e;</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>D. polymorpha</italic></td><td align="left">&#x0201e;</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>An in-depth taxonomic treatment of the genus was given in Massyuk's 1973 monograph [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>]. She divided the genus into two subgenera, <italic>Dunaliella </italic>(23 species) and <italic>Pascheria </italic>(5 species), the latter consisting of freshwater species only. Some of the species recognized by Massyuk may eventually be found to be polymorphic forms of a single taxon [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>].</p><p>A species of considerable interest is <italic>Dunaliella acidophila</italic>, isolated from acidic waters and soils in the Czech Republic and in Italy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>]. This is not a true halophile but an acidophilic alga that grows optimally at pH values between 0.5 and 2. In recent years it has become a popular research object for the study of adaptation of life to low pH environments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>]. Its taxonomic/phylogenetic affiliation with the halophilic <italic>Dunaliella </italic>species has to my knowledge never been verified.</p><p>Molecular phylogeny techniques have been applied to the taxonomic study of <italic>Dunaliella </italic>from 1999 onwards. These studies have encompassed the 18S rRNA genes and the internal transcribed spacer regions, and have been based on gene sequence comparisons as well as on restriction fragment length polymorphism studies. Little correlation was found between the molecular data and the morphological-physiological attributes used in older studies to delineate species within the genus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>]. On the basis of 18S rRNA gene sequences, Olmos et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>] could differentiate between <italic>D. salina</italic>, <italic>D. parva </italic>and <italic>D. bardawil </italic>as species containing one, two and three introns, respectively, within the 18S rRNA gene. The molecular studies have made it clear that many culture collection strains are probably misnamed, and that some unnecessary species names may have been proposed in the past.</p></sec><sec><title>5. Life Stages and Sexual Reproduction in <italic>Dunaliella</italic></title><p><italic>Dunaliella salina </italic>and some of the other species undergo complex life cycles that encompass, in addition to division of motile vegetative cells, the possibility of sexual reproduction. Fusion of two equally sized gametes to form a zygote was documented in many of the early studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>]. We thank a most detailed study of sexual reproduction in <italic>Dunaliella </italic>to Lerche [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>], who reported sexual zygote formation in five of the six species studied (<italic>D. salina</italic>, <italic>D. parva</italic>, <italic>D. peircei</italic>, <italic>D. euchlora</italic>, and <italic>D. minuta</italic>). She reported zygote formation in <italic>D. salina </italic>to be induced by a reduction in salt concentration from 10 to 3%. In the process first the flagella touch, and then the gametes form a cytoplasmic bridge and fuse. The zygote has a thick outer layer. It can withstand exposure to freshwater and also survive prolonged periods of dryness. These zygotes germinate with the release of up to 32 haploid daughter cells through a tear in the cell envelope [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>]. It is well possible that the cyst-like structures observed by Oren et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>] at the end of a bloom of green <italic>Dunaliella </italic>cells in the Dead Sea in 1992 were actually such zygotes. In this case, however, the formation of these rounded, thick-walled cells took place at a time of an increase in water salinity. Lerche [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>] performed a series of elegant experiments in which carotenoid-rich red cells were crossed with green cells, enabling the investigator to follow the fusion of the two parent cells to form a zygote. A few of her drawings to illustrate the process are reproduced in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>. The possibility of formation of asexual resting cysts by <italic>D. salina </italic>was indicated by Hamburger [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>], a finding that was disputed by Lerche. However, more recently, Loeblich [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>] has reported formation of such cysts in media of reduced salinity (for a discussion see also [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>]).</p><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Aggregation of the red and the green form of <italic>Dunaliella salina </italic>(upper part) and zygote formation of <italic>D. salina </italic>(green and red form) (lower part). From [30].</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1746-1448-1-2-4"/></fig><p>Some <italic>Dunaliella </italic>species can also develop a vegetative palmelloid stage consisting of round non-motile cells. Lerche [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>] has documented this phenomenon in <italic>D. salina </italic>cultures at lowered salinities, and Brock [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>] observed such palmelloid forms of <italic>Dunaliella </italic>in benthic algal mats of Great Salt Lake, Utah.</p></sec><sec><title>6. Carotenoid Pigments of <italic>Dunaliella</italic></title><p>The pigment responsible for the brightly red coloration displayed by <italic>D. salina</italic>, often designated in the older literature as "hematochrome", was recognized already very early as a carotenoid. As such it was identified by Blanchard [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>], and Teodoresco [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>], Lerche [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>] and Ruinen [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>] confirm this identification based on the solubility of the pigment in alcohol and in ether and on the blue color formed in the presence of concentrated sulfuric acid.</p><p>Before the modern electron microscope showed the <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-carotene as granules between the thylakoids of the cell's single chloroplast, considerable differences of opinion existed regarding the intracellular location of this red carotenoid pigment. Thus, both Teodoresco [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>] and Labb&#x000e9; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>] stated that the red pigment was distributed all over the cells' cytoplasm. Relating to a different claim by Hamburger [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>], Teodoresco [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>] wrote:</p><p>"je n'h&#x000e9;site pas &#x000e0; croire que ce pigment impr&#x000e8;gne tout le corps des zoospores, except&#x000e9;, bien entendu, l'extr&#x000e9;mit&#x000e9; ant&#x000e9;rieure, &#x000e0; l'endroit de l'insertion des flagellums."</p><p>[I don't hesitate to believe that the pigment impregnates the whole body of the zoospores, except, of course, the extreme anterior part, on the place where the flagella are inserted.]</p><p>Likewise, Hamel [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>] claimed that at elevated salt concentrations, <italic>D. salina </italic>forms "hematochrome" that penetrates not only the "chromophore" (= chloroplast) but the entire cytoplasm as well. On the other hand, Hamburger believed the red pigment to be located as small droplets (which is true, see e.g. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>]), but she was mistaken about the location of the pigment:</p><p>"Er tritt in Form kleiner Tr&#x000f6;pfchen auf, und ist, wie mir sicher scheint, nur der &#x000e4;u&#x000df;eren Alveolarschicht des Plasmas eingelagert, w&#x000e4;hrend das Chromatophor Tr&#x000e4;ger des gr&#x000fc;nen Farbstoffes ist. Die Bemerkung Teodoresco's "h&#x000e9;matochrome impr&#x000e9;gnant non seulement le chromatophore, mais encore tout le corps des individus &#x000e2;g&#x000e9;s", stimmt mit meinen Beobachtungen nicht &#x000fc;berein."</p><p>[It occurs in the form of small droplets, and is, as seems sure to me, only deposited in the outer alveolar layer of the plasma, while the chromatophore is the bearer of the green pigment. The remark by Teodoresco that "the hematochrome that impregnates not only the chromatophore, but also the whole body of adult individuals" does not correspond with my observations.]</p><p>Baas Becking [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>] correctly located the red-orange pigment in the chloroplast, and Leche [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>] realized that the carotene masks the chlorophyll, so that the chloroplast can assume all shades from orange-red to yellow-green, olive and green:</p><p>"Der rote Farbstoff ist in Form &#x000f6;liger Tr&#x000f6;pfchen zwischen den Wabe des Chloroplasten eingelagert und nicht wie Hamburger (1905) annimmt, in der &#x000e4;u&#x000df;eren Alveolarschicht des Protoplasmas."</p><p>[The red pigment is located in the form of oily droplets between the honeycomb structure of the chloroplast and not, as Hamburger (1905) assumes, in the outer cytoplasmic layer of the protoplast.]</p><p><italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-Carotene, the major carotenoid accumulated by <italic>D. salina </italic>and <italic>D. bardawil</italic>, is a valuable chemical, in high demand as a natural food coloring agent, as pro-vitamin A (retinol), as additive to cosmetics, and as a health food [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>]. Some <italic>Dunaliella </italic>strains can accumulate very large amounts of this carotenoid. Thus, as much as 13.8% of the total dry organic matter in the <italic>D. salina </italic>community in Pink Lake, Victoria, Australia, was estimated to be <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-carotene [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>]. Also in culture some strains may contain up to 10% and more of <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-carotene in their dry weight, including a large percentage of the 9-<italic>cis </italic>isomer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>]. Therefore the biotechnological potential of <italic>Dunaliella </italic>as a source of <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-carotene was investigated already relatively early. The first pilot plant for <italic>Dunaliella </italic>cultivation for <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-carotene production was established in the USSR in 1966 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>]. The commercial cultivation of <italic>Dunaliella </italic>for the production of <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-carotene throughout the world is now one of the success stories of halophile biotechnology [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">53</xref>]. Different technologies are used, from low-tech extensive cultivation in lagoons to intensive cultivation at high cell densities under carefully controlled conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">54</xref>].</p><p>One of the methods used in such biotechnological operations to induce massive carotenoid accumulation is reduction of the growth rate by deprivation of nutrients. That a high carotenoid content of the cells may be caused by nutrient limitation as well as by high light intensities was already reported by Lerche [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>]:</p><p>"Da die Rotf&#x000e4;rbung besonders in alten Kulturen auftrat, lag die Annahme nahe, sie in Zusammenhang mit den Ern&#x000e4;hrungsbedingungen und speziell mit dem Fehlen eines oder mehrerer Stoffe zu bringen. Da Phosphor und Stickstoff bei der pflanzlichen Ern&#x000e4;hrung h&#x000e4;ufig die Stoffe sind, die im Minimum vorhanden sind, wurde das Augenmerk zun&#x000e4;chst auf diese Stoffe gerichtet."</p><p>[As the red coloration occurred especially in old cultures, it was reasonable to assume a correlation with the nutritional conditions and in particular with the lack of one or more compounds. As phosphorus and nitrogen are in plant nutrition often the substances present in limiting amounts, we directed our attention first of all to these substances.]</p></sec><sec><title>7. Population Dynamics of <italic>Dunaliella </italic>in Salt Lakes and Salterns</title><p>Only few studies have been devoted to the quantitative evaluation of <italic>Dunaliella </italic>populations in salt lakes and salterns, the dynamics of their appearance and decline, and their contribution to the primary production in their habitats. Stephens and Gillespie (1976) reported measurements of the primary production in the south arm of Great Salt Lake, Utah, performed in 1973 (salinity around 135 g/l). Post [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>] reported that in the cold season, round cyst-like cells of <italic>D. salina </italic>increased in numbers in the Great Salt Lake, especially on the lake's bottom. In the Dead Sea, green <italic>Dunaliella </italic>cells have been reported since the 1940s [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">57</xref>]. The first quantitative estimates of the <italic>Dunaliella </italic>population in the lake were made in 1964, and showed very high numbers: up to 4 &#x000d7; 10<sup>4 </sup>cells per ml of surface water (sampling season not specified) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">58</xref>]. Systematic monitoring of the population density at different seasons and depths in the Dead Sea from 1980 onwards have yielded a clear picture of the factors that determine development of the alga in this unusual environment. High concentrations of magnesium and calcium ions are known to be inhibitory to <italic>Dunaliella </italic>since Baas-Becking's earlier studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]. <italic>Dunaliella </italic>blooms therefore occur in the Dead Sea only when during unusually wet winters the upper water layers of the lake become sufficiently diluted to enable growth, and when phosphate, the limiting nutrient, is available. Such events have been observed in 1980 and again in 1992 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">59</xref>].</p><p>Surprisingly, very little is known about the factors that determine the dynamics of <italic>Dunaliella </italic>in saltern pond systems. It is therefore interesting to note that some of the most in-depth studies on this topic were performed in the early 1920s in the salterns of Le Croisic on the Atlantic coast of France, where salt making is a seasonal operation. Labb&#x000e9; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>] showed changes in the algal community structure and related these to changes in salinity ("osmotic pressure; viscosity") of the brine, but he also recognized the role of the light intensity and the water temperature, as well as that of the pH. Based on the faulty assumption that the smaller green and the larger red <italic>Dunaliella </italic>cells are stages in the development of a single organism (see section 4 above), he described an annual cycle in which in the beginning of the winter few red motile cells ("&#x000e9;rythrospores") and smaller green motile cells ("chlorospores") are present [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>]. Dilution of the water by winter rains triggers the formation of red cysts ("&#x000e9;rythrocystes"), but the "chlorospores" develop rapidly, conjugate, and form "chlorocystes". When the salt concentration increases in the summer season, red motile cells start to appear, always accompanied by green cells:</p><p>"Peu &#x000e0; peu, les &#x000e9;rythrospores provenant de chlorospores prolif&#x000e8;rent, et leur dominance est fonction de la concentration saline."</p><p>[Gradually the "erythrospores" that are formed from "chlorospores" proliferate, and their dominance is a function of the salt concentration.]</p></sec><sec><title>8. Cultivation and Salt Tolerance of <italic>Dunaliella</italic></title><p>The first controlled experiments to evaluate the effect of salinity on the growth rate of different <italic>Dunaliella </italic>isolates were reported in the 1930s. Baas-Becking [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>] observed that <italic>D. viridis </italic>thrives equally well over the whole range of 1&#x02013;4 M (6&#x02013;23%) NaCl and over the pH range 6&#x02013;9. He found calcium and magnesium ions in high concentrations to be inhibitory. More detailed and well-documented experiments, using a variety of species and isolates, were reported by Lerche [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>]. She found most isolates to grow optimally between 2 and 8% salt, with very slow growth, if at all, at salt concentrations above 15% (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>). Between 0.47 and 1.22 divisions per day were recorded under optimal conditions.</p><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Division rate ("Teilungsrate") (as number of divisions per day) of different <italic>Dunaliella </italic>isolates belonging to several species, as a function of the NaCl concentration of the medium. From [30].</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1746-1448-1-2-5"/></fig><p>The nutritional requirements of different <italic>Dunaliella </italic>strains were investigated in-depth by Gibor [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60">60</xref>], Johnson et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">61</xref>], Van Auken and McNulty [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B62">62</xref>], and others, enabling the optimization of media to grow the alga. Optimal salt concentrations for cultivation varies according to the strain, with values reported for <italic>D. viridis </italic>around 6%, for <italic>D. salina </italic>around 12% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>], while different Great Salt Lake isolates had optima of 10&#x02013;15% or even 19% salt [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B62">62</xref>]. A general trend, observed in all these studies, is that the actual salinity of the environments from which the strains had been isolated was always much higher than the salt concentration found to be optimal in laboratory experiments. This may well reflect the fact that growth of an organism occurs in a certain environment not necessarily means that that environment is optimal for its development, but rather that the organism performs there better than all its competitors.</p></sec><sec><title>9. Osmotic Behavior of <italic>Dunaliella </italic>Cells</title><p><italic>Dunaliella </italic>cells lack a rigid cell wall, and the cell is enclosed solely by a thin elastic plasma membrane. As a result, the cells' morphology is strongly influenced by osmotic changes. This was documented already in the early days. The descriptions by Teodoresco [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>] are very exact here, and they deserve to be cited unabridged:</p><p>"Ces zoospores sont d&#x000e9;pourvues de membrane cellulosique; celle-ci est repr&#x000e9;sent&#x000e9;e par une enveloppe qui poss&#x000e8;de une certaine souplesse et une certaine extensibilit&#x000e9;, qui permet au corps de prendre les formes assez vari&#x000e9;es, suivant la concentration de l'eau. A ce point de vue, le genre <italic>Dunaliella </italic>diff&#x000e8;re totalement de toutes les esp&#x000e8;ces de <italic>Chlamydomonas </italic>..."</p><p>[These zoospores are devoid of a cellulose cell wall; instead there is a cell envelope that possesses a certain flexibility and a certain elasticity, which allows the body to take quite different forms, in accordance with the [salt] concentration of the water. In this respect the genus <italic>Dunaliella </italic>differs completely from all species of <italic>Chlamydomonas </italic>...]</p><p>and:</p><p>"Ainsi, si nous pla&#x000e7;ons une goutte d'eau sal&#x000e9;e, contenant des zoospores, sur le porte-objet, on constate, au microscope, qu'elles se pr&#x000e9;sentent sous la forme mention&#x000e9;e plus haut. Mais si nous laissons la goutte s'&#x000e9;vaporer un peu, on observe que le corps commence &#x000e0; s'allonger et &#x000e0; se difformer ... ; si alors nous ajoutons &#x000e0; la pr&#x000e9;paration une goutte d'eau douce, les zoospores s'arrondissent brusquement .... Cette exp&#x000e9;rience, que j'ai r&#x000e9;p&#x000e9;t&#x000e9;e un tr&#x000e9;s grand nombre de fois, m'a toujours donn&#x000e9; les m&#x000ea;mes r&#x000e9;sultats."</p><p>[Thus, when we place a drop of salt water that contains zoospores [= motile vegetative cells] on a microscope slide, one detects in the microscope that these present themselves in the above-described form. However, when we let the drop evaporate a little, one observes that the body starts to elongate and to lose its shape. ... ; when we then add to the preparation a drop of fresh water, the zoospores suddenly round up. .... This experiment, which I have repeated a great number of times, has always given me the same results.]</p><p>The phenomena described above are illustrated in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>, drawings 9&#x02013;29 and 30&#x02013;31, respectively. Teodoresco further writes:</p><p>"Si &#x000e0; une goutte d'eau sal&#x000e9;e on ajoute une goutte plus grande d'eau douce, ce qui am&#x000e8;ne une abaissement brusque de la concentration, les zoospores non seulement s'arrondissent, mais encore cessent leurs mouvements; le volume du corps augmente et devient parfois deux fois plus grand et &#x000e0; la fin la zoospore &#x000e9;clate. La cause de cet &#x000e9;clatement n'est pas difficile &#x000e0; comprendre: c'est l'action m&#x000e9;chanique de la pression osmotique trop &#x000e9;lev&#x000e9;e par rapport &#x000e0; la densit&#x000e9; diminu&#x000e9;e du milieu ambiant."</p><p>[If to a drop of salt water one adds a larger drop of fresh water, which leads to a sudden drop in concentration, the zoospores not only round up, but in addition cease their movements; the volume of the body increases and sometimes becomes twice as large, and finally the zoospore bursts. The cause of this burst is not difficult to understand: it is the mechanical action of the too high osmotic pressure in comparison to the decreased density of the ambient medium.]</p><p>Lerche [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>] likewise observed the osmotic changes that occur when the salt concentration is changed. She noted that when a drop of <italic>D. salina </italic>cells suspended in 20% salt is flooded with distilled water, a large fraction of the cells burst, but some cells survived the treatment.</p></sec><sec><title>10. Intracellular Salt and Solute Concentrations of <italic>Dunaliella</italic></title><p>Marr&#x000e8; and Servetta ([<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">63</xref>], as cited in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">61</xref>]) described measurements of the freezing point of the cytoplasmic fluid of <italic>D. salina </italic>to obtain information on the intracellular salt concentration. The results indicated an apparent "salt" concentration that exceeded the 3.9 M salt in which the cells were grown. At the time it was postulated that NaCl is taken up through the allegedly very permeable cell membrane during salt upshock, followed by free water flux to equalize intracellular and extracellular osmotic pressures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">63</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B65">65</xref>].</p><p>That the salt concentrations within <italic>Dunaliella </italic>cells cannot be that high, was convincingly shown by the enzymological studies by Johnson et al. (1968), who demonstrated that some of the key enzymes of the algal metabolism such as pentose phosphate isomerase, ribulose bisphosphate carboxylase, glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase and phosphohexose isomerase, are strongly inhibited by NaCl. We now know that the intracellular ionic concentrations of <italic>Dunaliella </italic>are very low indeed. Using lithium ions as a marker for the extracellular water space to estimate the intracellular volume, the intracellular Na<sup>+ </sup>concentrations, both in cells grown in 0.5 M and in 4 M NaCl, was found not to exceed 100 mM [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B66">66</xref>]. Such low intracellular Na<sup>+ </sup>levels are achieved by the activity of a Na<sup>+</sup>/H<sup>+ </sup>antiporter in the cytoplasmic membrane [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B67">67</xref>], as well as by direct electron transport-coupled Na<sup>+ </sup>extrusion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B68">68</xref>].</p><p>The enigma of the apparent incompatibility between the low intracellular ionic concentrations and the need for osmotic equilibrium of the cells' contents with the external medium was solved with the discovery that the cells accumulate photosynthetically produced glycerol as osmotic, "compatible" solute. It is interesting to note that the first experiments in which the effects of glycerol on <italic>Dunaliella </italic>were tested had already been performed by Teodoresco [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>], almost hundred years ago. He examined the effect of glycerol and other non-ionic compounds that normally cause plasmolysis. He observed that <italic>D. salina </italic>cells temporarily lose their motility when suspended in 50% glycerol, but that motility is rapidly restored when the glycerol concentration is then slightly lowered in a humid environment. With 75% glycerol results were largely similar, except that a large fraction of cells died, and in 100% glycerol only few cells survived.</p><p>The first indications that glycerol is accumulated by <italic>Dunaliella </italic>to provide osmotic balance can be found in a short paper published in 1964 by Craigie and McLachlan [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B69">69</xref>]. They incubated <italic>D. tertiolecta </italic>with <sup>14</sup>CO<sub>2</sub>, then extracted the cells with ethanol, separated the neutral fraction containing soluble carbohydrates and related compounds using ion exchange procedures, and characterized the compounds by two-dimensional paper chromatography and autoradiography. When the salinity of the medium was increased 100-fold from 0.025 to 2.5 M, 94-fold more radioactivity was found in the neutral fraction. Glycerol amounted to 56, 76, and 81% of the radioactivity of the neutral fraction extracted from cells incubated in 0.025, 0.5, and 2.5 M NaCl, respectively, most of the remainder probably consisting of soluble polysaccharides. In a subsequent study, Wegmann [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B70">70</xref>] confirmed that the proportion of the radiolabel from <sup>14</sup>C-bicarbonate that ends up as glycerol increases with increasing salt concentration up to 2.8 M. He postulated that "The glycerol formation is considered to be a protective mechanism for the survival of <italic>Dunaliella </italic>in its natural habitat".</p><p>The role that glycerol plays in the salt adaptation of <italic>Dunaliella </italic>was firmly established by the studies of Ben-Amotz and Avron [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B71">71</xref>] and Borowitzka and Brown [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B72">72</xref>]. The concept of "compatible solutes", a term coined by Duncan Brown to indicate solutes that not only contribute to the osmotic status of the cell but also maintain enzyme activity under conditions of low water activity, was largely based on the study of the function of glycerol in <italic>Dunaliella</italic>.</p><p>Intracellular glycerol concentrations in <italic>Dunaliella </italic>can be very high indeed: cells grown in 4 M NaCl were reported to contain approximately 7.8 M glycerol inside, equivalent to a solution of 718 g l<sup>-1 </sup>glycerol in water [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B73">73</xref>]. Maintenance of such a high concentration requires special properties of the cell membrane in view of the fact that most biological membranes are relatively permeable to glycerol. It has been established that <italic>Dunaliella </italic>possesses a membrane with an unusually low permeability for glycerol [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B74">74</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B75">75</xref>], and this enables the cells to keep the glycerol inside the cell. The causes of the low glycerol permeability of the <italic>Dunaliella </italic>membrane are still not fully understood.</p><p>Attempts have been made to exploit the high concentrations of glycerol accumulated by <italic>Dunaliella </italic>as the basis for the commercial production of this compound. Although technically the production of glycerol from <italic>Dunaliella </italic>was shown to be possible [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B76">76</xref>] economic feasibility is low, and to my knowledge no biotechnological operation presently exists that exploits the alga for glycerol production.</p></sec><sec><title>11. Proteomics Approaches to the Understanding of Salt Tolerance in <italic>Dunaliella</italic></title><p>A versatile organism such as <italic>Dunaliella </italic>that can adapt to a wide variety of salt concentrations can be used as a convenient model to study the formation of specific proteins as a function of changes in medium salinity. Such proteomic approaches have led to some interesting observations in recent years.</p><p>A number of such studies were directed to the detection of changes in the protein content of the cytoplasmic membrane, whose outer side is exposed to the medium salinity, when the cells are shifted from low to high salinity. Two membrane proteins were strongly induced by salt upshock, one with an apparent molecular mass of 60 kDa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B77">77</xref>] and one of 150 kDa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B78">78</xref>]. These proteins have been purified and characterized. The 60 kDa protein is a carbonic anhydrase that apparently helps the cell to take up carbon dioxide in concentrated brines in which the solubility of gases is decreased [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B79">79</xref>]. The 150 kDa protein is an unusual transferrin-like protein, involved in the transport of iron into the cell [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B80">80</xref>].</p><p>With a study published in 2004 by Liska et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B81">81</xref>], <italic>Dunaliella </italic>research has entered the era of modern proteomics. Comparison of protein patterns of low-and of high-salt-grown cells were compared on two-dimensional gels led to the identification of 76 salt-induced proteins. Among the proteins up-regulated following salinity stress were key enzymes in the Calvin cycle, enzymes involved in starch mobilization and in redox energy production, regulatory factors in protein biosynthesis and degradation, and a homolog of bacterial Na<sup>+</sup>-redox transporters. The results indicate that <italic>Dunaliella </italic>responds to transfer to a high salinity by enhancement of photosynthetic CO<sub>2 </sub>assimilation and by diversion of carbon and energy resources for synthesis of glycerol. This beautiful study is a worthy conclusion of the first century of <italic>Dunaliella </italic>research, and provides us with a preview of the kind of information that may be expected to be obtained in the coming years, using approaches of genomics, proteomics and systems biology.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dunal</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><article-title>Extrait d'un m&#x000e9;moire sur les algues qui colorent en rouge certains eaux des marais salants m&#x000e9;diterran&#x000e9;ens</article-title><source>Ann Sc Nat Bot 2 S&#x000e9;r</source><year>1838</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>172</fpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Teodoresco</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><article-title>Organisation et d&#x000e9;veloppement du <italic>Dunaliella</italic>, nouveau genre de Volvocac&#x000e9;e-Polyblepharid&#x000e9;e</article-title><source>Beih z Bot Centralbl</source><year>1905</year><volume>Bd. XVIII</volume><fpage>215</fpage><lpage>232</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ginzburg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title><italic>Dunaliella </italic>: a green alga adapted to salt</article-title><source>Adv Bot Res</source><year>1987</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>183</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Avron</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ben-Amotz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><collab>Ed</collab><source>Dunaliella: Physiology, Biochemistry, and Biotechnology</source><year>1992</year><publisher-name>Boca Raton: CRC Press</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Oren</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><source>Halophilic Microorganisms and their Environments</source><year>2002</year><publisher-name>Dordrecht: Kluwer Academic Publishers</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><name><surname>Turpin</surname><given-names>PJF</given-names></name><article-title>Quelques observations nouvelles sur les <italic>Protococcus</italic>, qui colorent en rouge les eaux des marais salants</article-title><source>Comp Rend Acad Sci</source><year>1839</year></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hamburger</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><article-title>Zur Kenntnis der <italic>Dunaliella salina </italic>und einer Am&#x000f6;be aus Salinenwasser von Cagliari</article-title><source>Arch f Protistenkd</source><year>1905</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>131</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Joly</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><article-title>Histoire d'un petit crustac&#x000e9; (<italic>Artemia salina</italic>) auquel on a faussement attribu&#x000e9; la coloration en rouge des marais salants m&#x000e9;diterran&#x000e9;ens, suivie de recherches sur la cause r&#x000e9;elle de cette coloration</article-title><source>Ann Sc Nat Zool Ser 2</source><year>1840</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>225</fpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Oren</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Stambler</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubinsky</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><article-title>On the red coloration of saltern crystallizer ponds</article-title><source>Int J Salt Lake Res</source><year>1992</year><volume>1</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>89</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Oren</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubinsky</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><article-title>On the red coloration of saltern crystallizer ponds. II. Additional evidence for the contribution of halobacterial pigments</article-title><source>Int J Salt Lake Res</source><year>1994</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF01990638</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Geleznow</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><article-title>&#x000dc;ber die Ursache der F&#x000e4;rbung des Salzwassers im See Sak in der Krim</article-title><source>Bull de l'Acad&#x000e9;mie Imp des Sciences de St Petersburg</source><year>1872</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>557</fpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><name><surname>Butschinsky</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><article-title>Die Protozoenfauna der Salzseelimane bei Odessa</article-title><source>Zool Anz</source><year>1897</year><fpage>20</fpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><name><surname>Blanchard</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><article-title>R&#x000e9;sultats d'une excursion zoologique en Alg&#x000e9;rie</article-title><source>M&#x000e9;m de la Soc Zool de France</source><year>1891</year><fpage>IV</fpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Florentin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><source>Faune des Mares Sal&#x000e9;es de Lorraine</source><year>1899</year><publisher-name>Nancy</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><name><surname>Bujor</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><article-title>Contributions &#x000e0; la faune des lacs sal&#x000e9;es de Roumanie</article-title><source>Ann Sci de l'Universit&#x000e9; de Jassy</source><year>1900</year><fpage>1</fpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Blanchard</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><article-title>Note pr&#x000e9;liminaire sur <italic>Monas Dunalii</italic>, flagell&#x000e9;, qui cause la rub&#x000e9;faction des marais salants</article-title><source>Bull de la Soc Zool de France</source><year>1888</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>153</fpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Dujardin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><source>Histoire Naturelle des Zoophytes (Infusoires)</source><year>1841</year><publisher-name>Paris</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cohn</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><article-title><italic>Chlamydomonas marina </italic>Cohn</article-title><source>Hedwigia</source><year>1865</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>97</fpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><name><surname>Hansgirg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>Prodromus d. Algenflora von B&#x000f6;hmen</article-title><year>1866</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>106</fpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Teodoresco</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><article-title>Observations morphologiques et biologiques sur le genre <italic>Dunaliella</italic></article-title><source>Rev G&#x000e9;n Bot</source><year>1906</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>353</fpage><lpage>371</lpage><comment><bold>18: </bold>409&#x02013;427</comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cavara</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><article-title>Alcune osservazione sulla <italic>Dunaliella salina </italic>(Dun.) Teod. delle saline di Cagliari</article-title><source>Rend della R Acad delle Sc Fis e Matemat. di Napoli Ser. 3</source><year>1906</year><volume>12</volume></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Peirce</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><article-title>The behavior of certain micro-organisms in brine. The Salton Sea</article-title><source>Carnegie Inst Washington Publ</source><year>1914</year><volume>193</volume><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>70</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Labb&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>Sur les modifications adaptives de <italic>Dunaliella salina </italic>Dunal</article-title><source>C R Acad Sci</source><year>1921</year><volume>172</volume><fpage>1074</fpage><lpage>1076</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Labb&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>Le cycle &#x000e9;volutif de <italic>Dunaliella salina</italic></article-title><source>C R Acad Sci</source><year>1921</year><volume>172</volume><fpage>1689</fpage><lpage>1690</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Labb&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>Les variations de la concentration en ions hydrog&#x000e8;ne dans les marais salants, comme facteur biologique</article-title><source>C R Acad Sci</source><year>1922</year><volume>175</volume><fpage>843</fpage><lpage>845</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Baas Becking</surname><given-names>LGM</given-names></name><article-title>On organisms living in concentrated brine</article-title><source>Tijdschr Ned Dierk Ver Ser III</source><year>1928</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>6</fpage><lpage>9</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Baas-Becking</surname><given-names>LGM</given-names></name><article-title>Salt effects on swarmers of <italic>Dunaliella viridis </italic>Teod</article-title><source>J Gen Physiol</source><year>1931</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>765</fpage><lpage>779</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1085/jgp.14.6.765</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19872621</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nicolai</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name><name><surname>Baas Becking</surname><given-names>LGM</given-names></name><article-title>Einige Notizen &#x000fc;ber Salzflagellaten</article-title><source>Arch f Protistenkd</source><year>1935</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>319</fpage><lpage>328</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hamel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><article-title>Chlorophyc&#x000e9;es des c&#x000f4;tes fran&#x000e7;aises</article-title><source>Extr Rev Algol</source><year>1931</year><volume>I-V</volume><fpage>4</fpage><lpage>6</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lerche</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><article-title>Untersuchungen &#x000fc;ber Entwicklung und Fortpflanzung in der Gattung <italic>Dunaliella</italic></article-title><source>Arch f Protistenkd</source><year>1937</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>236</fpage><lpage>268</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Butcher</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><source>An Introductory Account of the Smaller Algae of British Coastal Waters. Part I: Introduction and Chlorophyceae</source><year>1959</year><publisher-name>London: Ministry for Agriculture, Fisheries and Food, Fishery Investigations, Series IV. Her Majesty's Stationery Office</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Massyuk</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><source>Morphology, Taxonomy, Ecology and Geographic Distribution of the Genus Dunaliella Teod. and Prospects for its Potential Utilization</source><year>1973</year><publisher-name>Kiev: Naukova Dumka</publisher-name><comment>(in Russian)</comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Preisig</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><person-group person-group-type="editor">Ben-Amotz A, Avron M</person-group><article-title>Morphology and taxonomy</article-title><source>Dunaliella: Physiology, Biochemistry and Biotechnology</source><year>1992</year><publisher-name>Boca Raton: CRC Press</publisher-name><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>15</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kalina</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><article-title>Zur Morphologie und Taxonomie der Gattung <italic>Spermatozopsis </italic>Korschikow (Volvocales). <italic>Spermatozopsis acidophila </italic>sp. nov</article-title><source>Preslia</source><year>1965</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>12</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Albertano</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinto</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Santisi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Taddei</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><article-title><italic>Spermatozopsis acidophila </italic>Kalina (Chlorophyta, Volvocales), a little known alga from highly acidic environments</article-title><source>Giorn Bot Ital</source><year>1981</year><volume>115</volume><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>76</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Gimmler</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Weis</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><person-group person-group-type="editor">Ben-Amotz A, Avron M</person-group><article-title><italic>Dunaliella acidophila </italic>&#x02013; life at pH 1.0</article-title><source>Dunaliella: Physiology, Biochemistry and Biotechnology</source><year>1992</year><publisher-name>Boca Raton: CRC Press</publisher-name><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>133</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x000f3;mez</surname><given-names>PI</given-names></name><name><surname>Montoya</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><article-title>Comparison of PCR-RFLP analysis of the ITS region with morphological criteria of various strains of <italic>Dunaliella</italic></article-title><source>J Appl Phycol</source><year>1999</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>573</fpage><lpage>580</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1008035422784</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x000f3;mez</surname><given-names>PI</given-names></name><name><surname>Montoya</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><article-title>Phylogenetic relationship among various strains of <italic>Dunaliella </italic>(Chlorophyceae) based on nuclear ITS rDNA sequences</article-title><source>J Phycol</source><year>2001</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>604</fpage><lpage>611</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1529-8817.2001.037004604.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Olmos</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Paniagua</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Contreras</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><article-title>Molecular identification of <italic>Dunaliella </italic>sp. utilizing the 18S rDNA gene</article-title><source>Lett Appl Microbiol</source><year>2000</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>80</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1472-765x.2000.00672.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10728567</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Oren</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gurevich</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Anati</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Barkan</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Luz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><article-title>A bloom of <italic>Dunaliella parva </italic>in the Dead Sea in 1992: biological and biogeochemical aspects</article-title><source>Hydrobiologia</source><year>1995</year><volume>297</volume><fpage>173</fpage><lpage>185</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00019283</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><name><surname>Loeblich</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><article-title>Aplanospores of <italic>Dunaliella salina </italic>(Chlorophyta)</article-title><source>J Protozool</source><year>1969</year><issue>Suppl 16</issue><fpage>22</fpage><lpage>23</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Borowitzka</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><article-title>The microflora. Adaptations to life in extremely saline lakes</article-title><source>Hydrobiologia</source><year>1981</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>46</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00048704</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Brock</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><article-title>Salinity and the ecology of <italic>Dunaliella </italic>from Great Salt Lake</article-title><source>J Gen Microbiol</source><year>1975</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>285</fpage><lpage>292</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ruinen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>Notizen &#x000fc;ber Salzflagellaten. II. &#x000dc;ber die Verbreitung der Salzflagellaten</article-title><source>Arch Protistenkd</source><year>1938</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>210</fpage><lpage>258</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ben-Amotz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Avron</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Accumulation of <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-carotene in halotolerant algae: purification and characterization of <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-carotene-rich globules from <italic>Dunaliella bardawil </italic>(Chlorophyceae)</article-title><source>J Phycol</source><year>1982</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>529</fpage><lpage>537</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.0022-3646.1982.00529.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ben-Amotz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lers</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Avron</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Stereoisomers of <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-carotene and phytoene in the alga <italic>Dunaliella bardawil</italic></article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>1988</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>1286</fpage><lpage>1291</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16666068</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Borowitzka</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><article-title>Micro-algae as sources of fine chemicals</article-title><source>Microbiol Sci</source><year>1986</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>372</fpage><lpage>375</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3153571</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Aasen</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Eimhjellen</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Liaaen-Jensen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><article-title>An extreme source of <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-carotene</article-title><source>Acta Chem Scand</source><year>1969</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>2544</fpage><lpage>2545</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5368546</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Massyuk</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><article-title>Mass culture of the carotene bearing alga <italic>Dunaliella salina</italic></article-title><source>Ukr Bot Zh</source><year>1968</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>12</fpage><lpage>19</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Drokova</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name><article-title>The alga <italic>Dunaliella salina </italic>as a source of <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-carotene</article-title><source>Ukr Bot Zh</source><year>1961</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>110</fpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Ben-Amotz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><person-group person-group-type="editor">Shelef G, Soeder CJ</person-group><article-title>Glycerol, <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-carotene and dry algal meal production by commercial cultivation of <italic>Dunaliella</italic></article-title><source>Algae Biomass</source><year>1980</year><publisher-name>Amsterdam: Elsevier</publisher-name><fpage>603</fpage><lpage>610</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ben-Amotz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Avron</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Accumulation of metabolites by halotolerant algae and its industrial potential</article-title><source>Ann Rev Microbiol</source><year>1983</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>119</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.mi.37.100183.000523</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6416147</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Borowitzka</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Borowitzka</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Moulton</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><article-title>The mass culture of <italic>Dunaliella </italic>for fine chemicals: from laboratory to pilot plant</article-title><source>Hydrobiologia</source><year>1984</year><volume>116/117</volume><fpage>115</fpage><lpage>121</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00027649</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Ben-Amotz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Avron</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><person-group person-group-type="editor">Cresswell RC, Rees TAV, Shah, N</person-group><article-title>The biotechnology of mass culturing <italic>Dunaliella </italic>for products of commercial interest</article-title><source>Algal and Cyanobacterial Biotechnology</source><year>1989</year><publisher-name>Harlow: Longman Scientific and Technical Press</publisher-name><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>114</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Stephens</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Gillespie</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><article-title>Phytoplankton production in the Great Salt Lake, Utah, and a laboratory study of algal response to enrichment</article-title><source>Limnol Oceanogr</source><year>1976</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>74</fpage><lpage>87</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Post</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><article-title>The microbial ecology of the Great Salt Lake</article-title><source>Microb Ecol</source><year>1977</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>143</fpage><lpage>165</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24233467</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Volcani</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><article-title>The microorganisms of the Dead Sea</article-title><source>Papers Collected to Commemorate the 70th Anniversary of Dr. Chaim Weizmann. Collective volume</source><year>1944</year><publisher-name>Rehovoth: Daniel Sieff Research Institute</publisher-name><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>85</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>IR</given-names></name><name><surname>Friedmann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>Biological productivity in the Dead Sea. Part I. Microorganisms in the water column</article-title><source>Israel J Chem</source><year>1970</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>513</fpage><lpage>528</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Oren</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Shilo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Population dynamics of <italic>Dunaliella parva </italic>in the Dead Sea</article-title><source>Limnol Oceanogr</source><year>1982</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>201</fpage><lpage>211</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gibor</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>The culture of brine algae</article-title><source>Biol Bull</source><year>1956</year><volume>111</volume><fpage>223</fpage><lpage>229</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B61"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>MacElroy</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Speer</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruff</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><article-title>Effects of salts on the halophilic alga <italic>Dunaliella viridis</italic></article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>1968</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>1461</fpage><lpage>1468</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5646631</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B62"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Van Auken</surname><given-names>OW</given-names></name><name><surname>McNulty</surname><given-names>IB</given-names></name><article-title>The effect of environmental factors on the growth of a halophylic species of algae</article-title><source>Biol Bull</source><year>1973</year><volume>145</volume><fpage>210</fpage><lpage>222</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4732535</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B63"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Marr&#x000e8;</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Servettaz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>Sul meccanismo di adattemento a condizioni osmotiche estreme in <italic>Dunaliella salina</italic>. II. Rapporto fra concentrazioni del mezzo esterno e composizione del succo cellulare</article-title><source>Atti Accad Naz Lincei Cl Sci Fis Mat Nat Rend Ser 8</source><year>1959</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>272</fpage><lpage>278</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B64"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Trezzi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Galli</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Bellini</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><article-title>L'osomo-resistenza di <italic>Dunaliella salina</italic>. Ricerche ultrastructurali</article-title><source>Giorn Bot Ital</source><year>1965</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>255</fpage><lpage>263</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B65"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ginzburg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>The unusual membrane permeability of two halophilic unicellular organisms</article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><year>1969</year><volume>173</volume><fpage>370</fpage><lpage>376</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5769637</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B66"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Avron</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Determination of intracellular osmotic volume and sodium concentration in <italic>Dunaliella</italic></article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>1985</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>817</fpage><lpage>820</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16664332</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B67"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pick</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Avron</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Characterization and reconstitution of the Na<sup>+</sup>/H<sup>+ </sup>antiporter from the plasma membrane of the halophilic alga <italic>Dunaliella</italic></article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><year>1989</year><volume>983</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2758043</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B68"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pick</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><article-title>Plasma membrane electron transport coupled to Na<sup>+ </sup>extrusion in the halotolerant alga <italic>Dunaliella</italic></article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><year>2001</year><volume>1504</volume><fpage>423</fpage><lpage>431</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11245805</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B69"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Craigie</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>McLachlan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>Glycerol as a photosynthetic product in <italic>Dunaliella tertiolecta </italic>Butcher</article-title><source>Can J Bot</source><year>1964</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>777</fpage><lpage>778</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B70"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wegmann</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><article-title>Osmotic regulation of photosynthetic glycerol production in <italic>Dunaliella</italic></article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><year>1971</year><volume>234</volume><fpage>317</fpage><lpage>323</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5117572</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B71"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ben-Amotz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Avron</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>The role of glycerol in the osmotic regulation of the halophilic alga <italic>Dunaliella parva</italic></article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>1973</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>875</fpage><lpage>878</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16658431</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B72"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Borowitzka</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><article-title>The salt relations of marine and halophilic species of the unicellular green alga, <italic>Dunaliella</italic>. The role of glycerol as a compatible solute</article-title><source>Arch Microbiol</source><year>1974</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00590161</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B73"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><source>Microbial Water Stress Physiology. Principles and Perspectives</source><year>1990</year><publisher-name>Chichester: John Wiley &#x00026; Sons</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B74"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>FF</given-names></name><name><surname>Sussman</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Avron</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Degani</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><article-title>NMR studies of glycerol permeability in lipid vesicles, erythrocytes and the alga <italic>Dunaliella</italic></article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><year>1982</year><volume>690</volume><fpage>165</fpage><lpage>173</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7126572</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B75"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gimmler</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartung</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><article-title>Low permeability of the plasma membrane of <italic>Dunaliella parva </italic>for solutes</article-title><source>J Plant Physiol</source><year>1988</year><volume>133</volume><fpage>165</fpage><lpage>172</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B76"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chi</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><article-title>Process development and evaluation for algal glycerol production</article-title><source>Biotechnol Bioengin</source><year>1981</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>1267</fpage><lpage>1287</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bit.260230608</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B77"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sadka</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Himmelhoch</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zamir</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>A 150 kilodalton cell surface protein is induced by salt in the halotolerant green alga <italic>Dunaliella salina</italic></article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>1991</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>822</fpage><lpage>831</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16668060</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B78"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pick</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Zamir</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>A salt-induced 60-kilodalton plasma membrane protein plays a potential role in the extreme halotolerance of the alga <italic>Dunaliella</italic></article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>1994</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>1359</fpage><lpage>1365</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12232413</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B79"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gokhman</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Pick</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Zamir</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>A salt-resistant plasma membrane carbonic anhydrase is induced by salt in <italic>Dunaliella salina</italic></article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1996</year><volume>271</volume><fpage>17718</fpage><lpage>17723</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.271.30.17718</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8663366</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B80"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gokhman</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Pick</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Zamir</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>A structurally novel transferrin-like protein accumulates in the plasma membrane of the unicellular green alga <italic>Dunaliella salina </italic>grown in high salinities</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1997</year><volume>272</volume><fpage>1565</fpage><lpage>1570</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.272.3.1565</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8999829</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B81"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Liska</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Shevhenko</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pick</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>Enhanced photosynthesis and redox energy production contribute to salinity tolerance in <italic>Dunaliella </italic>as revealed by homology-based proteomics</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>136</volume><fpage>2806</fpage><lpage>2817</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.104.039438</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15333751</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
