<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="news"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Environ Health Perspect</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Environ. Health Perspect</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Environmental Health Perspectives</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0091-6765</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1552-9924</issn><publisher><publisher-name>National Institute of Environmental Health Sciences</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1278519</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ehp0113-a0236b</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Environews</subject><subj-group><subject>NIEHS News</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Toxicogenomics Data on Acetaminophen Now Available</article-title></title-group><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>4</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><volume>113</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage seq="b">A236</fpage><lpage>A237</lpage><permissions><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/" license-type="public-domain"><license-p>Publication of EHP lies in the public domain and is therefore without copyright. All text from EHP may be reprinted freely. Use of materials published in EHP should be acknowledged (for example, ?Reproduced with permission from Environmental Health Perspectives?); pertinent reference information should be provided for the article from which the material was reproduced. Articles from EHP, especially the News section, may contain photographs or illustrations copyrighted by other commercial organizations or individuals that may not be used without obtaining prior approval from the holder of the copyright. </license-p></license></permissions></article-meta></front><body><p>The National Toxicology Program (NTP), under the leadership of director Kenneth Olden and deputy director Christopher Portier, recently completed a study of hepatic transcript levels following exposure to the model hepatotoxicant acetaminophen. The study was conducted under the Principles of Good Laboratory Practice, and the pathology diagnoses were reviewed and approved following standard NTP guidelines.</p><p>The study involved 240 male F344/N rats, half of which were dosed at night. Exposure was a single oral gavage of doses varying from nontoxic to toxic, with collection of the left lobe of the liver for transcript measurements at 6, 18, 24, and 48 hours after dosing. The RNA from time-matched controls served as the reference sample, and 4 individual rats at each dose and time were hybridized against the controls using Agilent&#x02019;s 60 mer rat oligo microarray chip with 20,000 features. With fluor reversals this resulted in 256 hybridizations. Hybridizations were done under a National Center for Toxicogenomics (NCT) contract. Details of the study were published in volume 33, issue 1 (2005) of <italic>Toxicologic Pathology</italic>.</p><p>Toxicogenomics offers the promise of the availability of large data sets that other investigators can compare against their own studies. Therefore, the NTP is making available the microarray results, individual animal pathology diagnoses, clinical chemistry, hepatic glutathione levels, and individual animal data such as body weights. These data are available at the NTP website (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ntp.niehs.nih.gov/a/apap.html">http://ntp.niehs.nih.gov/a/apap.html</ext-link>). The data will also be available in the NCT Chemical Effects in Biological Systems database, currently under development.</p></body><floats-group><fig id="f1-ehp0113-a0236b" position="float"><caption><title><bold>Knowledge for all.</bold> A broad array of toxicogenomics data on acetaminophen, a liver toxicant, is now available to any researcher.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="ehp0113-a0236bf1"/></fig></floats-group></article>
