<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="letter"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Environ Health Perspect</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Environ. Health Perspect</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Environmental Health Perspectives</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0091-6765</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1552-9924</issn><publisher><publisher-name>National Institute of Environmental Health Science</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15579399</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1253685</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ehp0112-a0978b</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Perspectives</subject><subj-group><subject>Correspondence</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>U.S. PBDE Levels: Effects in Mice</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cleet</surname><given-names>Christopher</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>American Chemistry Council, Arlington, Virginia, E-mail:
<email>christopher_cleet@americanchemistry.com</email></aff><author-notes><fn><p>The author is the manager of the American Chemistry Council&#x02019;s (ACC) Brominated Flame Retardants Industry Panel (BFRIP). ACC is a trade association representing the leading companies in the business of chemistry. BFRIP is composed of the manufacturers of brominated flame retardants. The members of BFRIP are Albemarle Corporation; Ameribrom, Inc.; Bromine Counpounds, Ltd.; and the Great Lakes Chemical Corporation.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>12</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><volume>112</volume><issue>17</issue><fpage seq="b">A978</fpage><lpage>A979</lpage><permissions><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/" license-type="public-domain"><license-p>Publication of EHP lies in the public domain and is therefore without copyright. All text from EHP may be reprinted freely. Use of materials published in EHP should be acknowledged (for example, ?Reproduced with permission from Environmental Health Perspectives?); pertinent reference information should be provided for the article from which the material was reproduced. Articles from EHP, especially the News section, may contain photographs or illustrations copyrighted by other commercial organizations or individuals that may not be used without obtaining prior approval from the holder of the copyright. </license-p></license></permissions><related-article id="d35e57" related-article-type="commentary-article" xlink:href="15121506" ext-link-type="pubmed" vol="112" page="654"/></article-meta></front><body><p>I am pleased to submit this letter as a representative of the American Chemistry Council Brominated Flame Retardants Industry Panel (BFRIP). The BFRIP is composed of producers of brominated flame retardants; member companies include Albemarle Corporation, Ameribrom Inc., and Great Lakes Chemical Corporation.</p><p>In a recent study, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5-ehp0112-a0978b">Sj&#x000f6;din et al. (2004)</xref> investigated polybrominated diphenyl ethers (PBDEs) in human sera collected in the United States between 1988 and 2002. The authors concluded that such levels were increasing over time and were higher than those reported in Europe. Several points regarding these conclusions require clarification and are addressed below.</p><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5-ehp0112-a0978b">Sj&#x000f6;din et al. (2004)</xref> used the term &#x0201c;PBDEs&#x0201d;; however, the PBDEs analyzed in sera were only the tetra to hepta congeners. These congeners are commonly found in the commercial pentaBDE product, which is used in flexible polyurethane foam in upholstery applications. The sole U.S. manufacturer of the pentaBDE product (Great Lakes Chemical Corporation, West Lafayette, IN) will voluntarily discontinue production by the end of 2004. However, approximately 80% of the global production of PBDEs is composed of the decabromodiphenyl ether/oxide (DBDPO) commercial product, which is used primarily in electrical and electronic components (typically television cabinet backs, connectors, and wire and cable insulation) and to a minor extent in upholstery textiles. DBDPO was not included in the set of congeners analyzed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5-ehp0112-a0978b">Sj&#x000f6;din et al. (2004)</xref>. Thus, the comments with respect to time trends, if valid, apply only to tetra- to heptaPBDE congeners and not the major PBDE product in production and use, DBDPO.</p><p>Second, the results indicate that the PBDEs, and BDE-47 in particular, for the last two time intervals (1995&#x02013;1999 and 2000&#x02013;2002) appeared to level off. Of the six isomers analyzed, only BDE-153 appeared to increase between 1995&#x02013;1999 and 2000&#x02013;2002. Thus, the most recent data suggest that, in general, U.S. PBDE serum levels for the lower congeners are not continually increasing but have reached a plateau.</p><p>Third, the authors state that BDE-47 concentrations collected in similar time frames and reported by other studies in milk (83 or 130 ng/g lipid) and sera (0.63 ng/g lipid, 1988) compare &#x0201c;favorably&#x0201d; with their present sera results of 46 (1995&#x02013;1999), 34 (2000&#x02013;2002), and 5.4 (1985&#x02013;1988) ng/g lipid. These values appear dissimilar from one another and appear to point out highly variable, rather than similar, results.</p><p>Finally, we question the validity of a comparison of U.S. to European PBDE levels. As indicated by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5-ehp0112-a0978b">Sj&#x000f6;din et al. (2004)</xref>, the analyzed sera were not collected in such a way as to be representative of the general U.S. population. The same is likely true with respect to the blood and milk samples collected in Sweden; these samples are unlikely to be representative of the general European population. Thus, based on this collection process, one cannot reach reliable conclusions regarding U.S. versus European levels.</p><p>I would also like to correct information reported regarding manufacture of polybrominated biphenyls (PBBs). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5-ehp0112-a0978b">Sj&#x000f6;din et al. (2004)</xref> stated that the hexaBB product continued to be produced in Europe after the Michigan incident in the 1970s in which it was accidentally included in cattle feed. After that incident, production of only the decabromobiphenyl (decaBB) product, not the hexaBB product, continued in Europe, and that production ceased several years ago. The decaBB product did not exhibit the same toxicologic properties as the hexaBB product.</p><p>Finally, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5-ehp0112-a0978b">Sj&#x000f6;din et al. (2004)</xref> stated that &#x0201c;PBDEs cause neurodevelopmental effects in mice &#x02026;,&#x0201d; citing <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1-ehp0112-a0978b">Eriksson et al. (2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2-ehp0112-a0978b">2002)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8-ehp0112-a0978b">Viberg et al. (2002)</xref>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6-ehp0112-a0978b">Taylor et al. (2002)</xref> were unable to reproduce these effects in rats, whereas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9-ehp0112-a0978b">Viberg et al. (2004)</xref> reported similar results in rats and mice. Perhaps these diverging results are related to the small sample size and statistical design used by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1-ehp0112-a0978b">Eriksson et al. (2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2-ehp0112-a0978b">2002)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9-ehp0112-a0978b">Viberg et al. (2004)</xref> that grossly inflates the type 1 (i.e., false positive) error rate. Eriksson et al. and Viberg et al. both used mouse pups as the experimental unit, whereas the litter is the more appropriate measure [U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) 2004; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4-ehp0112-a0978b">Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD) 2003</xref>]. Litter effects are substantial, and using more than one pup from a few litters, as reported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1-ehp0112-a0978b">Eriksson et al. (2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2-ehp0112-a0978b">2002)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9-ehp0112-a0978b">Viberg et al. (2004)</xref>, will confound treatment effects with litter effects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3-ehp0112-a0978b">Holson and Pearce 1992</xref>). Holson and Pearce also stated that &#x0201c;within-litter variance would likely become substantially lower with age than that between litters.&#x0201d; This would further increase the already sizeable effects of litter and may account for the conclusions of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1-ehp0112-a0978b">Eriksson et al. (2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2-ehp0112-a0978b">2002)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9-ehp0112-a0978b">Viberg et al. (2004)</xref> that neurodevelopmental effects increase with age.</p></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="b1-ehp0112-a0978b"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Eriksson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Jakobsson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Fredriksson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Brominated flame retardants: a novel class of developmental neurotoxicants in our environment?</article-title><source>Environ Health Perspect</source><volume>109</volume><fpage>903</fpage><lpage>908</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11673118</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b2-ehp0112-a0978b"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Eriksson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Viberg</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Jakobsson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Orn</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Fredridsson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>A brominated flame retardant, 2,2&#x02032;,4,4&#x02032;,5&#x02032;-pentabromodiphenyl ether: uptake, retention, and induction of neurobehavioral alterations in mice during a critical phase of neonatal brain development</article-title><source>Toxicol Sci</source><volume>67</volume><fpage>98</fpage><lpage>103</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11961221</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b3-ehp0112-a0978b"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Holson</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Pearce</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year>1992</year><article-title>Principles and pitfalls in the analysis of prenatal treatment effects in multiparous species</article-title><source>Neurotoxicol Teratol</source><volume>14</volume><fpage>221</fpage><lpage>228</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1635542</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b4-ehp0112-a0978b"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>OECD</collab> 2003. OECD Guideline for the Testing of Chemicals: Proposal for a New Guideline 426. Developmental Neurotoxicity Study (Draft Document). Paris:Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.oecd.org/dataoecd/14/12/15487898.pdf">http://www.oecd.org/dataoecd/14/12/15487898.pdf</ext-link> [accessed 27 May 2004].</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b5-ehp0112-a0978b"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Sj&#x000f6;din</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Focant</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Lapeza</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>McGahee</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Retrospective time-trend study of polybrominated diphenyl ether and polybrominated and polychlorinated biphenyl levels in human serum from the United States</article-title><source>Environ Health Perspect</source><volume>112</volume><fpage>654</fpage><lpage>658</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15121506</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b6-ehp0112-a0978b"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hedge</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>DeVito</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Crofton</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Perinatal exposure to a polybrominated diphenyl ether mixture (DE-71) disrupts thyroid hormones but not neurobehavioral development [Abstract]</article-title><source>Toxicologist</source><volume>66</volume><issue>1-S</issue><fpage>Abstract 642</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b7-ehp0112-a0978b"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>U.S. EPA</collab> 1998. Health Effects Test Guidelines OPPTS 870.6300 Developmental Neurotoxicity Study. Washington, DC:U.S. Environmental Protection Agency. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.epa.gov/opptsfrs/OPPTS_Harmonized/870_Health_Effects_Test_Guidelines/Series/870-6300.pdf">http://www.epa.gov/opptsfrs/OPPTS_Harmonized/870_Health_Effects_Test_Guidelines/Series/870-6300.pdf</ext-link> [accessed 27 May 2004].</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b8-ehp0112-a0978b"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Viberg</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Fredriksson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Eriksson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Neonatal exposure to the brominated flame retardant 2,2&#x02032;,4,4&#x02032;,5-pentabromodiphenyl ether causes altered susceptibility in the cholinergic transmitter system in the adult mouse</article-title><source>Toxicol Sci</source><volume>67</volume><fpage>104</fpage><lpage>107</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11961222</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b9-ehp0112-a0978b"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Viberg</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Fredriksson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Eriksson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Comparative developmental neurotoxicity of PBDE 99 in two different mouse strains and rat [Abstract]</article-title><source>Toxicologist</source><volume>78</volume><issue>1-S</issue><fpage>Abstract 1907</fpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
