<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="letter"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Environ Health Perspect</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Environ. Health Perspect</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Environmental Health Perspectives</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0091-6765</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1552-9924</issn><publisher><publisher-name>National Institute of Environmental Health Sciences</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15687042</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC1277886</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ehp0113-a0087b</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Perspectives</subject><subj-group><subject>Correspondence</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Inappropriate Influence by Industry on <italic>EHP</italic> News Article</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sass</surname><given-names>Jennifer</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ehp0113-a0087b"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af1-ehp0113-a0087b">Natural Resources Defense Council Washington, DC, E-mail:
<email>jsass@nrdc.org</email></aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Solomon</surname><given-names>Gina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-ehp0113-a0087b"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af2-ehp0113-a0087b">Natural Resources Defense Council San Francisco, CA</aff><author-notes><fn><p>The authors declare they have no competing financial interests.</p></fn><fn><p>Editor&#x02019;s note: Science Selections articles are summaries of peer-reviewed research articles published in the concurrent issue of EHP. They are not investigative pieces, and thus differ from other EHP news articles in several substantive ways. They are not meant to analyze, critique, or comment upon the research methodology, findings, or integrity. Contextual information in the news article is generally confined to context provided by the authors of the research paper in the paper&#x02019;s introduction and conclusion. For this reason, corresponding authors of the research papers have been involved in the review process of Science Selections to ensure accurate presentation of their research.</p></fn><fn><p>We now recognize that this process is vulnerable to at least the appearance of conflicts of interest and regret this incident. To avoid this, Science Selections articles will now be reviewed by outside experts the same as all other EHP news articles. EHP is also contemplating convening an international meeting to address complex questions associated with ethics in publishing in the fields of environmental and public health.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>2</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><volume>113</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage seq="b">A87</fpage><lpage>A88</lpage><permissions><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/" license-type="public-domain"><license-p>Publication of EHP lies in the public domain and is therefore without copyright. All text from EHP may be reprinted freely. Use of materials published in EHP should be acknowledged (for example, ?Reproduced with permission from Environmental Health Perspectives?); pertinent reference information should be provided for the article from which the material was reproduced. Articles from EHP, especially the News section, may contain photographs or illustrations copyrighted by other commercial organizations or individuals that may not be used without obtaining prior approval from the holder of the copyright. </license-p></license></permissions><related-article related-article-type="commentary-article" id="d35e80" vol="110" page="A532" ext-link-type="pmc"/></article-meta></front><body><p>We are disturbed at the recent revelation that, before its publication, an <italic>EHP</italic> Science Selection article on the toxic rocket fuel additive perchlorate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8-ehp0113-a0087b">Renner 2002</xref>) was substantially revised by a paid consultant to the perchlorate industry to downplay adverse health effects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2-ehp0113-a0087b">Danelski 2004</xref>). <italic>EHP</italic> contracted freelance journalist Rebecca Renner to write the Science Selection piece to accompany publication of a research article by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4-ehp0113-a0087b">Greer et al. (2002)</xref>. The Greer study was partially funded by the Perchlorate Study Group (PSG), a self-described alliance of perchlorate users and manufacturers, including the military contractors Boeing, Lockheed Martin, Aerojet, and Kerr-McGee. It seems apparent that the PSG had a significant financial interest in continued perchlorate use. The study included two authors affiliated with Intertox, Inc., a consulting firm contracted by the PSG. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4-ehp0113-a0087b">Greer et al. (2002)</xref> reported on the effects of perchlorate ingestion by 37 healthy adults over a 2-week period, concluding that</p><disp-quote><p>Assuming that the drinking water supply is the only significant source of exposure &#x02026;, a perchlorate concentration of 180&#x02013;220 ppb (and possibly much higher) should be of no health concern in iodine-sufficient populations.</p></disp-quote><p>The original article by Renner reported that the Greer study results disagreed with a draft toxicologic review released by the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) just a few months earlier, recommending no more than 1 ppb perchlorate in drinking water, on the basis of reduced thyroid hormone levels, abnormal brain morphology, and thyroid cancers in young rat pups exposed <italic>in utero</italic> and perinatally to perchlorate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11-ehp0113-a0087b">U.S. EPA 2002</xref>).</p><p>Prior to publication, the <italic>EHP</italic> editors sent Renner&#x02019;s article to one of the authors of the Greer study, Gay Goodman, of Intertox, Inc., to check the characterization of her study for accuracy. According to an invoice from Intertox to PSG (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7-ehp0113-a0087b">Pleus 2002</xref>), Goodman was paid by the industry for her time spent &#x0201c;editing the <italic>EHP</italic> news article (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8-ehp0113-a0087b">Renner 2002</xref>).&#x0201d; Intertox explained in the invoice that Renner&#x02019;s article, as originally written, &#x0201c;was potentially very damaging to PSG&#x0201d; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7-ehp0113-a0087b">Pleus 2002</xref>). The invoice described Intertox&#x02019;s work: &#x0201c;Dr. Goodman gained the trust of the editor and, through a cooperative process entailing five or more drafts, provided substantial and critical improvements to the article&#x0201d; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7-ehp0113-a0087b">Pleus 2002</xref>). Renner was never provided an opportunity to review the revised version, yet practically every sentence of her article had been altered (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2-ehp0113-a0087b">Danelski 2004</xref>). In particular, all references to the inconsistency between the drinking water &#x0201c;safe&#x0201d; level recommended by the Greer study and that of the U.S. EPA were scrubbed from the published version, as was the disclosure of the major funding source of the Greer study.</p><p>Although the Intertox rewrite of Renner&#x02019;s news story was titled &#x0201c;Reprieve for Perchlorate: Effects Not a Significant Concern&#x0201d; and the revised story was written to imply that the Greer study proved perchlorate to be less toxic than previously believed, these conclusions are unfounded and misleading. More recent reviews of the Greer study by state agencies, the U.S. EPA, and independent scientists have noted that the low-dose group in the study was too small to have the statistical power to detect a relevant effect (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6-ehp0113-a0087b">Massachusetts Department of Environmental Protection 2004</xref>). Furthermore, the results could not be extrapolated to longer-term exposures, iodine-deficient populations (including 15% of women in the United States), or to the fetus and infant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5-ehp0113-a0087b">Hollowell et al. 1998</xref>).</p><p>The Department of Defense and its military contractors have waged a coordinated assault on the U.S. EPA regulatory recommendation of no more than 1 ppb perchlorate in drinking water (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1-ehp0113-a0087b">Beeman and Danelski 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10-ehp0113-a0087b">Sass 2004</xref>). It now appears that <italic>EHP</italic> unwittingly became part of that campaign to manipulate the public perception of perchlorate and avoid strict regulatory standards. In other efforts, the Department of Defense and PSG pushed for the National Academies to provide a review of the U.S. EPA recommendations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9-ehp0113-a0087b">Renner 2003</xref>), with the report expected in late January 2005. A paid consultant to Lockheed Martin was initially appointed to the Academies&#x02019; scientific committee, but was later asked to resign when previously undisclosed evidence of financial conflicts emerged (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12-ehp0113-a0087b">Waldman 2004</xref>).</p><p>We applaud <italic>EHP</italic>&#x02019;s excellent reputation for scientific quality and integrity. However, in this case we believe the evidence shows that <italic>EHP</italic> was unwittingly used as part of a deliberate campaign to undermine a health policy position taken by a sister agency. We request that the <italic>EHP</italic> editors implement policies to ensure that any alterations made to a manuscript be clearly marked and reviewed by the author before going to press. <italic>EHP</italic> has indicated that it may add another layer of editing by outside scientists to the Science Selection editing process in response to this situation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1-ehp0113-a0087b">Beeman and Danelski 2004</xref>). We strongly discourage the use of outside reviewers for news stories and suggest instead that <italic>EHP</italic> rely on the expertise of its editorial staff and news reporters, with limited use of outside reviewers for accuracy checks only. We applaud the recent <italic>EHP</italic> policy to ban from publishing for 3 years any author who fails to disclose financial conflicts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3-ehp0113-a0087b">EHP 2004</xref>). If <italic>EHP</italic> applied such a requirement to news articles, it would bring needed transparency to efforts like those of Intertox consultant Gay Goodman, who effectively ghost authored the Renner article (with permission of <italic>EHP</italic> editors) without disclosure to the <italic>EHP</italic> readership.</p></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="b1-ehp0113-a0087b"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group><name><surname>Beeman</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Danelski</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> 2004. Cost, risks fuel debate over safety: impact on health weighed against billions for cleanup. Riverside (California) Press-Enterprise. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pe.com/digitalextra/environment/perchlorate/vt_stories/PE_News_Local_perch19.5838f.html">http://www.pe.com/digitalextra/environment/perchlorate/vt_stories/PE_News_Local_perch19.5838f.html</ext-link> [accessed 19 December 2004].</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b2-ehp0113-a0087b"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group><name><surname>Danelski</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> 2004. Controversy cut from news story. Riverside (California) Press-Enterprise. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pe.com/localnews/inland/stories/PE_News_Local_edited19.5824b.html">http://www.pe.com/localnews/inland/stories/PE_News_Local_edited19.5824b.html</ext-link> [accessed 19 December 2004].</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b3-ehp0113-a0087b"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>EHP</collab> 2004. Instructions to Authors. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ehp.niehs.nih.gov/docs/admin/edpolicy.html">http://ehp.niehs.nih.gov/docs/admin/edpolicy.html</ext-link> [accessed 4 January 2005].</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b4-ehp0113-a0087b"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Greer</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Pleus</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Greer</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Health effects assessment for environmental perchlorate contamination: the dose response for inhibition of thyroidal radioiodine uptake in humans</article-title><source>Environ Health Perspect</source><volume>110</volume><fpage>927</fpage><lpage>937</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12204829</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b5-ehp0113-a0087b"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Hollowell</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Staehling</surname><given-names>NW</given-names></name><name><surname>Hannon</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Flanders</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Gunter</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name><name><surname>Maberly</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Iodine nutrition in the United States. Trends and public health implications: iodine excretion data from National Health and Nutrition Examination Surveys I and III (1971-1974 and 1988-1994)</article-title><source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source><volume>83</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>3401</fpage><lpage>3408</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9768638</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b6-ehp0113-a0087b"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Massachusetts Department of Environmental Protection</collab> 2004. Interpretative Differences between Massachusetts&#x02019; and California&#x02019;s Perchlorate Health Assessments. Boston:Office of Research and Standards.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b7-ehp0113-a0087b"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group><name><surname>Pleus</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> 2002. Letter from Rick Pleus, Intertox, Inc., to Dan Guth, The Boeing Company, Seattle, WA Re: Invoices 98802, 98803, 98812&#x02013;98815. 12 September.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b8-ehp0113-a0087b"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Renner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Reprieve for perchlorate: effects not a significant concern</article-title><source>Environ Health Perspect</source><volume>110</volume><fpage>A532</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b9-ehp0113-a0087b"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Renner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Environmental health. Academy to mediate debate over rocket-fuel contaminants</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>299</volume><issue>5614</issue><fpage>1829</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12649455</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b10-ehp0113-a0087b"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Sass</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>U.S. Department of Defense and White House working together to avoid cleanup and liability for perchlorate pollution</article-title><source>Int J Occup Environ Health</source><volume>10</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>330</fpage><lpage>334</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15473090</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b11-ehp0113-a0087b"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>U.S. EPA</collab> 2002. Perchlorate Environmental Contamination: Toxicological Review and Risk Characterization (2002 External Review Draft). U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, Office of Research and Development, National Center for Environmental Assessment, Washington, DC, NCEA-1-0503, 2002.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b12-ehp0113-a0087b"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group><name><surname>Waldman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> 2004. Perchlorate-panel member resigns. Wall St Journal 11 June: A3.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
